<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MITS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Mechatronics and Intelligent Transportation Systems</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Mechatron. Intell Transp. Syst.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">MITS</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2958-0218</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-020X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-fy6unzgPe3gLTN_dY_G14xrn06H32nVy</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/mits030302</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Exploring the Dynamics of Maglev Trains on Curved Bridges: A Case Study from the Fenghuang Maglev Sightseeing Express</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-4660-0828</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiao</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>Liangxiao1014@outlook.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2,3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1285-1553</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Sumei</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>may.sm.wang@polyu.edu.hk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2,3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5811-4113</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Shengyuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>syliu229@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2,3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1527-7777</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ni</surname>
            <given-names>Yiqing</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>ceyqni@polyu.edu.hk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3108-7271</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>Gaofeng</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>gao-feng.jiang@connect.polyu.hk</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Hunan Rail Transit Holding Group Co., Ltd., 410011 Changsha, China</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">National Rail Transit Electrification and Automation Engineering Technology Research Center (Hong Kong Branch), 999077 Hong Kong SAR., China</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, 999077 Hong Kong SAR., China</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>07</month>
        <year>2024</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>156</fpage>
      <lpage>168</lpage>
      <page-range>156-168</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>05</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>07</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2024 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Magnetic levitation (maglev) transportation represents an advanced rail technology that utilizes magnetic forces to lift and propel trains, eliminating direct contact with tracks. This system offers numerous advantages over conventional railways, including higher operational speeds, reduced maintenance requirements, enhanced energy efficiency, and reduced environmental impact. However, the dynamic interaction between maglev trains and railway bridges, particularly curved bridges, presents challenges in terms of potential instability during operation. To better understand the dynamic behavior of maglev trains on curved bridges, an experimental study was conducted on the Fenghuang Maglev Sightseeing Express Line (FMSEL), the world’s first “Maglev + Culture + Tourism” route. The FMSEL employs a unique ‘U’-shaped girder design, marking its first application in such a setting. Field test data were collected to analyze the dynamic characteristics of the vehicle, suspension bogie, curved rail, and ‘U’-shaped bridge across a range of train speeds. The responses of both the train and bridge were examined in both time and frequency domains, revealing that response amplitudes increased with train speed. Notably, the ride quality of the vehicle remained excellent, as indicated by Sperling index values consistently below 2.5. Furthermore, lateral acceleration of the train was observed to be lower than vertical acceleration, while for the track, vertical acceleration was consistently lower than lateral acceleration. These findings offer insights into the dynamic performance of maglev trains on curved infrastructure, highlighting key factors that must be considered to ensure operational stability and passenger comfort.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Maglev train</kwd>
        <kwd>Curved bridge</kwd>
        <kwd>Dynamic interaction</kwd>
        <kwd>Field test</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="5"/>
        <fig-count count="20"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <ref-count count="20"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>As populations gather and metropolitan areas expand, the requirements for more speedy, safe, comfortable, and environmentally friendly public transport are increasing. Maglev systems stand out as one of the best solutions due to their advantages over traditional transportation, including no risk of derailment, contactless operation, low noise, small turning radius, and high climbing capability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]. Considerable global attention has been garnered in low- and medium-speed maglev trains in recent years. Magnetic suspension technology has been used in many intercity and regional lines in the US, Germany, Japan, South Korea, and China. Examples include Japan's Nagoya Linimo Maglev Line, South Korea's Incheon Airport Maglev Line, China's Changsha Airport Maglev Express, and Beijing S1 Line. Electromagnetic suspension (EMS) maglev systems are inherently unstable, as the square of the air gap is inversely proportional to the constant current derived electromagnetic force. Therefore, a controller along the track is active to adjust the air gap to maintain the stability of EMS maglev trains. The dynamic performance of EMS maglev systems and their operational safety and comfort depend not only on the interaction between vehicles and guideways but also on the effectiveness of the suspension control system, resulting in a highly coupled, nonlinear, and inherently unstable system. Years of operation have shown that the coupled vibration between the vehicle, track, and bridge is a key issue impacting the safety and stability of maglev systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. Thus, studying the dynamic interactions between these three subsystems is crucial for guaranteeing maglev trains’ safe and stable operation.</p><p>There is a significant coupling interaction between the maglev bridges, track, and train, creating a time-varying system problem because of the coupling interaction between the three subsystems. This interaction leads to the modal damping ratio and natural frequency of the guideway changing temporally since the vibration of the guideway is easily affected by inherent mass or additional damping. The guideway's flexibility, performing an external force to excite the train, can induce unacceptable vibrations and dynamic instability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>]. When the train's natural frequency aligns with that from external exciting sources, the dynamic response of the vehicle increases sharply, resulting in resonance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>]. Both maglev trains on experimental and commercial lines have observed that the air gap is unstable by resonance, leading to suspension control failure. Since the 1970s and 1980s, numerous scholars have undertaken extensive research into the dynamic analysis of maglev vehicle-track-bridge systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>] analyze how the track structure influences the vertical dynamic interactions within the low- and medium-speed maglev train-track-bridge system by developing vertical dynamic interaction models. Liu and Chen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>] explored the impact of the excitation current, air gap, lateral offset, and other various structural parameters on levitation force by using analytical methods, and 2D and 3D finite element methods. Li et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>] investigated the vertical vibration characteristics of maglev trains and steel railway bridges. In addition, Chen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>] analyzed the different stiffness conditions for the vehicle-track-bridge system's dynamic response.</p><p>Most studies were focused on the dynamic features of a maglev train moving on ‘T’-shaped girders or box girders in a straight line by using numerical simulation. In this study, an experimental study was conducted to study the dynamic features of maglev trains moving on ‘U’-shaped girders, which were first used in the FMSEL. Meanwhile, a dynamic test selects a curved section to study the vehicle-track-bridge system's performance. The test results can be used to provide basic data for subsequent projects, such as numerical model validation and engineering design.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Field test of the maglev system</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Background of fmsel</title>
          
          <p>FMSEL connects the Fenghuang High-speed Rail Station and the Fenghuang Ancient Town in Hunan Province. The line has a designed speed of 100 km/h and passes through six stations. The entire route is 9.121 km in total length, comprising straight sections, slope sections, tunnels, turnouts, and small-radius curves. This paper analyzes the dynamic performance of the maglev train as it traverses a curved bridge (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>) with a curve radius of 300 m.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>A curved railway bridge on FMSEL</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_m1I-sTn7GNFD8b5w.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>The cross section of the bridge</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_WPSyisvUREC2Nl48.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The curved bridge, which is a 25-meter length span simply supported girder, has a ‘U’-shaped cross-section measuring 1.7 m in height and 5.05 m in width. As depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>, the F-type rail is embedded in the center of the ‘U’-shaped girder, with the bridge’s cross-sectional details illustrated.</p><p>The test vehicle consists of three carriages, each of which is supported by five levitation bogies. There are two levitation modules in each levitation bogie with functions of levitation, guidance, and traction. An anti-rolling beam is adopted to connect the two modules. There is one longitudinal beam, two support arms, one polar plate, four levitation electromagnets, and one short-primary linear induction motor (SLIM). The levitation and guidance functions of the levitation module are realized with the F-type rail and the electromagnet, and the SLIM is adopted for traction. The levitation bogies are connected to the carriages by air springs. The test vehicle and its structural components are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>The test vehicle and structural components: (a) Test vehicle; (b) Levitation bogie; (c) Air spring; (d) Rocker arm</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_pPeRopTSu6rwW8H9.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Arrangement of field test</title>
          
          <p>Several accelerometers were installed on various places, including the vehicle body, levitation bogies, concrete bridge, and tracks, to analyze the dynamic response of the vehicle-track-bridge system as the vehicle moves over the curved bridge. The acceleration data was collected using Dewesoft software, with a sampling frequency of 5000 Hz. The tests were conducted at train speeds ranging from 20 to 60 km/h.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Individual levitation bogie measurement point</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_MQsjKuCZmLyKBlXN.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The measurement points of the carriage were placed on the floor of the head vehicle. A three-dimensional accelerometer (measuring vertical, longitudinal, and lateral directions) was installed on the front left floor, an accelerometer (measuring the vertical direction) was positioned on the middle floor, and a two-dimensional accelerometer (measuring lateral and vertical directions) was placed at the rear. For the bogie measurements, accelerometers were distributed on the 1#, 2#, and 3# bogie of the head vehicle. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> shows four locations of the accelerometers on one levitation bogie. The detailed sensor arrangements are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Levitation bogie sensors layout</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Number of Bogies</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Location</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Test Direction</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>1# bogie</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Left front</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Left rear</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Right front</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Right rear</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>2# bogie</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Left front</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Left rear</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lateral, longitudinal and vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Right front</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Right rear</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lateral and vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>3# bogie</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Left front</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lateral and vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Left rear</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Right front</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Right rear</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>The curved bridge includes the F-type rail and a concrete bridge. Several accelerometers were mounted on the F-type rail, sleepers, and bridge to measure the vibration of curved bridges. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> show the deployment of these accelerometers on the bridge.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_5">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Test point arrangement of track-bridge system</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_6KWinV66RtdqUXpj.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Track-bridge system sensors layout</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Test Point</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Location</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Test Direction</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Concrete beam</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mid-span</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lateral and vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1/4 span</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Track</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mid-span of right F-type rail</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Type 1 joint</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lateral and vertical</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Type 2 joint</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lateral and vertical</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Dynamic response of the carriage</title>
          
          <p>To analyze the dynamic response of the vehicle as it moves along the curved guideway section, data was collected from the previously installed accelerometers when the train was traveling at a speed of 20 km/h. The time series data at the left front and rear measurement points of the vehicle body are given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>. The peak vertical accelerations recorded at the left front and rear of the vehicle body were 0.4232 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mkam16847b">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and 0.3105 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mu1m4hjcte">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, respectively, while the peak lateral accelerations were 0.0883 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mk35i0f5v5">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and 0.1376 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mfftsb7mcq">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> at the same points. It was found that the lateral acceleration was significantly minor to the vertical acceleration, which can be attributed to the suspension force in the lateral direction being less than in the vertical direction. </p>
          
            <fig id="fig_6">
              <label>Figure 6</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Temporal change of the carriage’s acceleration: (a) The left front of the carriage; (b) The rear of the carriage</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_F6qIXXI8w0bSghUP.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref> illustrates the vertical accelerations at various speeds to investigate the impact of train speed on the dynamic vibration of the vehicle body. The results show that the accelerations at the left and rear measurement points are greater than those at the middle point, which is due to the combined pitching and left-rear vibrations of the vehicle body. By comparing the vertical accelerations at different train speeds, it was found that the vehicle body's vibration accelerations did not significantly increase with higher speeds. The vertical accelerations at the left front, middle, and rear points are about 0.4232 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m05q5chthv">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, 0.2341 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mpbnnd462q">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and 0.3105 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="maa0mgmiv8">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> at 20 km/h. These values are well within the ride quality assessment requirements for passenger vehicles, where the maximum allowable acceleration is no more than 2.5 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mlro1e22iq">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>].</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_7">
              <label>Figure 7</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Peak vertical acceleration of the carriage</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_NcNjJ9eC-aEVzSJi.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Dynamic response of bogies</title>
          
          <p>When the train moves on the curved bridge at 20 km/h, the acceleration of the levitation bogies is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>. The vertical accelerations at the left front of the #2 bogie, the right rear of the #2 bogie, and the left front of the #3 suspension were 2.0051 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mbugh2kii6">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, 1.6095 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mr8r7lzeua">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and 1.7182 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="muq0ukgvmc">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, respectively.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_8">
              <label>Figure 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Temporal change of the bogies’ acceleration: (a) The left rear of 2# bogie; (b) The right rear of 2# bogie; (c) The left front of 3# bogie</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_zHGIRcuUttnKauTA.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Meanwhile, the corresponding lateral accelerations at these points were 1.7367 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7z6qtfnin">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, 1.3169 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mqerz8wvzb">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and 0.7374 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mvbhn5o5pc">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. These results demonstrate that the lateral vibration is less significant than the vertical vibration for the levitation bogie. Moreover, compared with the vehicle body, the acceleration experienced by the levitation bogie was much higher, highlighting the superb vibration isolation provided by the air spring components between the levitation bogies and the vehicle body.</p><p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref> shows the maximum accelerations of the bogies at various train speeds in both vertical and lateral directions. The maximum lateral acceleration increases slightly as the train speed rises, while the vertical acceleration significantly increases. For a bogie, this indicates that there is more sensitivity for the vertical vibration compared to the lateral when changing the train speed.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_9">
              <label>Figure 9</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Comparison on the maxmium accelerations of the bogies: (a) vertical; (b) lateral</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_IiuiVBifC8oUz3RK.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.5. Vehicle comfort analysis</title>
          
          <p>Vehicle comfort is an important indicator for determining the overall performance of a train. Sperling indexes of the carriage under different speed conditions are used to determine the ride quality. Sperling index is defined in Eq. (1).</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <mml:math id="mw7tkuehz3">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:msup>
                  <mml:mn>7.08</mml:mn>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mn>10</mml:mn>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msup>
                <mml:msqrt>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msqrt>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p> where <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mhb8an6uk9">
    <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the frequency correction coefficient, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myv5ysl80z">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is acceleration in m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mx87peynp6">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m98c5ggyyj">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the frequency in Hz. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> shows their values.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Frequency correction coefficient</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th colspan="2">Vertical Vibration</th><th colspan="2">Lateral Vibration</th></tr><tr><td >0.5-5.9 Hz</td><td ><mml:math id="mqklxbdhdk">
  <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mn>0.325</mml:mn>
</mml:math></td><td >0.5-5.4 Hz</td><td ><mml:math id="maqarehlwk">
  <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mn>0.8</mml:mn>
</mml:math></td></tr><tr><td >5.9-20 Hz</td><td ><mml:math id="mh8v08l23j">
  <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mn>400</mml:mn>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></td><td >5.4-26 Hz</td><td ><mml:math id="mplvkfmxbk">
  <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mn>650</mml:mn>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></td></tr><tr><td >$&gt;$20 Hz</td><td ><mml:math id="mavy8868pt">
  <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:math></td><td >$&gt;$26 Hz</td><td ><mml:math id="my2arbms7p">
  <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:math></td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>For various speeds of the vehicle body, the Sperling indexes are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_10">Figure 10</xref>, where the indexes obtained by using the data at different test points are almost the same. Similar to the vehicle body's vibration response, the Sperling indexes do not significantly increase with rising train speeds. The maximum Sperling index recorded for the vehicle body is 1.79, which is less than 2.5, which indicates an “excellent” level for the train's ride quality.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_10">
              <label>Figure 10</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Comparison on the carriage's Sperling indexes</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_93Tzsi8FGe_y3Xuy.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.6. Dynamic response of the track-bridge system</title>
          
          <p>When the vehicle passed by at 60 km/h, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_11">Figure 11</xref> illustrates the temporal change of acceleration at the curved bridge's mid-span, whose maximum accelerations were 0.2223 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mlawl1dqje">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and 0.1082 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="moe9d4txqz">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> in vertical and lateral directions, respectively. The bridge's lateral vibration is lower than the vertical, similar to the vehicle body's vibration characteristics. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_12">Figure 12</xref> shows the mid-span peak accelerations at different train speeds to explore the train speed effect on the bridge. It is evident that bridge acceleration increases with higher train speeds.</p><p>For an analysis of the track's vibration characteristics on the curved section, the accelerations were measured in lateral and vertical directions at a train speed of 60 km/h. As depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_13">Figure 13</xref>, the maximum accelerations of the curved track were 0.4814 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mey3qzw49z">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and 0.612 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mma71mvvg0">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> for vertical and lateral, respectively. In contrast to the vehicle and bridge, the track's lateral acceleration was greater than its vertical acceleration. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_14">Figure 14</xref> shows the maximum accelerations of the curved track at different train speeds, confirming that the lateral accelerations are consistently higher than the vertical ones, with both increasing as the train speed rises.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_11">
              <label>Figure 11</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Temporal change of the bridge mid-span's acceleration</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_VwJvO6Cszg8HgTG6.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_12">
              <label>Figure 12</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Comparison on the maximum acceleration of the bridge</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_NZHAZ3vf0SIPAutA.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_13">
              <label>Figure 13</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Temporal change of the F-type rail's acceleration on the curved section</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_CJcO-bBPS7QSWpWj.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_14">
              <label>Figure 14</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Peak vertical acceleration of the track</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_5ZO8qFHey3xpeXpJ.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_15">Figure 15</xref> presents the F-type rail's accelerations on the straight section at 60 km/h to compare the vibration characteristics between the curved and straight track sections. The F-type rail's accelerations on the straight section were the maximum of 0.5331 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m66948ygfp">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and 0.2068 m/s<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mc4m2dy3oi">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> for vertical and lateral, respectively. By comparing the corresponding accelerations in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_13">Figure 13</xref>, it can be obtained that the vertical accelerations on both the curved and straight sections are similar. However, the lateral acceleration on the curved section is much higher than that on the straight section.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_15">
              <label>Figure 15</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Temporal change of the F-type rail's acceleration on the straight section</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_RdnDTLPSikvqbfKo.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Frequency domain analysis</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. The vehicle body</title>
          
          <p>A frequency-domain analysis is conducted by analyzing the collected data to investigate the vehicle's vibration characteristics. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_16">Figure 16</xref> displays the Fourier transform results for the vehicle body's vertical accelerations. The analysis revealed that the peak frequency obtained from the rear point is about 2.4 Hz, whereas the dominant frequencies obtained from the left front point are concentrated at 16.5 Hz and 30 Hz.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_16">
              <label>Figure 16</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Vibration acceleration spectrum of the carriage</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_hOB9SxP_ebP8AWLW.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. The bogies</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_17">Figure 17</xref> presents the Fourier transform results for both accelerations of the bogies vertically and laterally. For the lateral vibrations of the bogies, the frequency distributions at different measurement points are similar, with the dominant frequencies focused on 15 Hz and 30 Hz. Regarding vertical vibrations, the fundamental frequency for all measurement points was 4.3 Hz. In addition, the peak frequency for the 3# bogie is 23.8 Hz, while the dominant frequencies for the 2# bogie are 15 Hz and 30 Hz.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_17">
              <label>Figure 17</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Frequency spectrum of the bogies: (a) vertical; (b) lateral</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_5rgcUDpZ477oaxqS.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. The track-bridge system</title>
          
          <p>A key indicator for assessing the bridge's vibration characteristics is the fundamental frequency. To determine its 1st-order frequency and perform the frequency domain analysis, the data were selected under the free vibration phase, which occurs after the vehicle leaves the bridge. For the free vibration condition, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_18">Figure 18</xref> plots the Fourier transform results and illustrates that the bridge's 1st-order frequencies are 5.7 Hz for vertical vibration and 1.03 Hz for lateral vibration, respectively. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_19">Figure 19</xref> shows the Fourier transform results when the train crosses the curved section. The results show that the peak vertical frequency is 5.7 Hz, confirming it as the bridge’s fundamental frequency. In terms of lateral vibration, a frequency range of 95-103 Hz is dominant.</p><p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_20">Figure 20</xref> displays the Fourier transform results for the F-type rail, showing that both lateral and vertical dominant frequencies are 97.7 Hz. The lateral vibrations have a greater amplitude below 30 Hz when comparing the spectrograms measured from the different directions of the track. While the vertical accelerations are concentrated between 90 Hz and 150 Hz. This indicates that the track is more sensitive to the lateral vibrations at low frequencies when the vehicle moves over the curved section, whereas the vertical vibrations are mainly influenced by high frequencies.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_18">
              <label>Figure 18</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Frequency spectrum of the bridge</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_DR0OnIT_nLcyZtVS.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_19">
              <label>Figure 19</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Frequency spectrum of the bridge</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_aYkVsvUL8_0U7L2W.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_20">
              <label>Figure 20</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Frequency spectrum of the track</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/9/img_xsy9RY_cuS6RBg_O.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Conclusion</title>
      <p>The ‘U’-shaped girder from FMSEL was the first attempt of design implemented on a maglev line. A dynamic test is conducted in this line to analyze the vehicle-track-bridge system’s vibration characteristics in both time and frequency domains. The key findings are as follows:</p><p>1) Vibration acceleration: The vertical direction bears higher accelerations for both the vehicle and the bridge, while the track experiences a greater lateral acceleration than the vertical.</p><p>2) Effect of speed: Vehicle speed significantly influences acceleration amplitude. As train speed increases, the accelerations of the vehicle, bridge, and track increase substantially, whereas the carriage acceleration shows only a slight increase.</p><p>3) Ride quality: The Sperling indexes for the carriage, in both lateral and vertical directions, remain below 2.5 across different speed conditions, indicating excellent ride quality.</p><p>4) Natural frequencies: 1.03 Hz and 5.7 Hz for the 1st-order lateral and vertical of the ‘U’-shaped girder, respectively.</p><p>5) Dominant frequencies: Concentrated around 15 Hz and 30 Hz for the peak frequencies of the vehicle, while 97.7 Hz for the dominant frequency of the track-bridge system.</p><p>These results provide valuable insights for future simulations and tests. In subsequent work, the results of this test will also be compared with other operating conditions in preparation for a full-scale model.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>The paper was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No.: 52302481), in part by Wuyi University’s Hong Kong and Macao Joint Research and Development Fund (Grants No.: 2021WGALH15), and in part by the Innovation and Technology Commission of Hong Kong SAR Government, China (Grant No.: K-BBY1).</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The author declares no conflicts of interest regarding this work.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>42</volume>
          <page-range>1917-1925</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2006</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>H. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>K. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMAG.2006.875842</pub-id>
          <article-title>Review of maglev train technologies</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Trans. Magn.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>209-226</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhai</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3969/j.issn.0258-2724.2016.02.001</pub-id>
          <article-title>Frontiers and challenges of sciences and technologies in modern railway engineering</article-title>
          <source>J. Southwest Jiaotong Univ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>66</volume>
          <page-range>8589-8599</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qiang</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TIE.2019.2891409</pub-id>
          <article-title>Adaptive neural-fuzzy robust position control scheme for maglev train systems with experimental verification</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>10-20</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hansen</surname>
              <given-names>C. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20855/ijav.2010.15.1255</pub-id>
          <article-title>Review of coupled vibration problems in EMS maglev vehicles</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Acoust. Vib.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>93-96</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1999</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Long</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Guideway resonance vibration and levitation control system design of an EMS maglev vehicle</article-title>
          <source>J. Natl. Univ. Def. Technol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>47</volume>
          <page-range>309-324</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>H. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yim</surname>
              <given-names>B. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>N. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hur</surname>
              <given-names>Y. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00423110802054342</pub-id>
          <article-title>Effects of the guideway's vibrational characteristics on the dynamics of a maglev vehicle</article-title>
          <source>Veh. Syst. Dyn.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>1366-1377</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>D. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>P. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11771-015-2654-z</pub-id>
          <article-title>Modeling and simulation of CMS04 maglev train with active controller</article-title>
          <source>J. Cent. South Univ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>337</volume>
          <page-range>135-149</page-range>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yau</surname>
              <given-names>J. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsv.2014.10.024</pub-id>
          <article-title>Vertical and pitching resonance of train cars moving over a series of simple beams</article-title>
          <source>J. Sound Vib.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2016</volume>
          <page-range>8071938</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fang</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ni</surname>
              <given-names>Q.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/8071938</pub-id>
          <article-title>A practical control strategy for the maglev self‐excited resonance suppression</article-title>
          <source>Math. Probl. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <page-range>567–574</page-range>
          <year>2004</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhai</surname>
              <given-names>W. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>C. F. Zhao</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>C. B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dynamic simulation of the EMS maglev vehicle-guideway-controller coupling system</article-title>
          <source>Proc. of the 18th Int. Conf. on Magnetically Levitated Systems and Linear Drives, Shanghai, China</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>195-199</page-range>
          <issue>2-3</issue>
          <year>1975</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Popp</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schiehlen</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00423117508968491</pub-id>
          <article-title>Dynamics of magnetically levitated vehicles on flexible guideways</article-title>
          <source>Veh. Syst. Dyn.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>175</volume>
          <page-range>625-646</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>1994</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rote</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coffey</surname>
              <given-names>H. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jsvi.1994.1350</pub-id>
          <article-title>Vehicle/guideway interaction for high speed vehicles on a flexible guideway</article-title>
          <source>J. Sound Vib.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>118</volume>
          <page-range>526-530</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>1996</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rote</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coffey</surname>
              <given-names>H. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1115/1.2801176</pub-id>
          <article-title>Vehicle/guideway dynamic interaction in maglev systems</article-title>
          <source>J. Dyn. Sys., Meas., Control</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>83-111</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1998</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsunashima</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abe</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00423119808969368</pub-id>
          <article-title>Static and dynamic performance of permanent magnet suspension for maglev transport vehicle</article-title>
          <source>Veh. Syst. Dyn.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>328</volume>
          <page-range>301-317</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwon</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>M. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeo</surname>
              <given-names>I. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsv.2009.08.010</pub-id>
          <article-title>A parametric study on the dynamics of urban transit maglev vehicle running on flexible guideway bridges</article-title>
          <source>J. Sound Vib.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>874-878</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>1976</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamamura</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMAG.1976.1059125</pub-id>
          <article-title>Magnetic levitation technology of tracked vehicles present status and prospects</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Trans. Magn.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>2937-2950</page-range>
          <issue>14</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qiu</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1369433219854550</pub-id>
          <article-title>Influence of the track structure on the vertical dynamic interaction analysis of the low-to-medium-speed maglev train-bridge system</article-title>
          <source>Adv. Struct. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>20</volume>
          <page-range>93-97</page-range>
          <year>2012</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03325784</pub-id>
          <article-title>Levitation force analysis of medium and low speed maglev vehicles</article-title>
          <source>J. Mod. Transport.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>236</volume>
          <page-range>609-622</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lei</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gong</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/09544097211032460</pub-id>
          <article-title>Experimental study on vertical vibration characteristics of medium-low speed maglev vehicle when standing still on steel beams</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Inst. Mech. Eng., Part F: J. Rail Rapid Transit</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>4129-4142</page-range>
          <issue>17-18</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ji</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/10775463221112621</pub-id>
          <article-title>Experimental study on vertical vehicle-rail-bridge coupling of medium and low speed maglev train based on track beam with different stiffness</article-title>
          <source>J. Vib. Control</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>