<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="review-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJEPM</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Energy Production and Management</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Int. J. Energy Prod. Manag.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IJEPM</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2056-3280</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2056-3272</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-VF7-GI3FlfghbQGJPmJ2Yr36HVVpkXxE</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/ijepm100413</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Techno-Economic Feasibility and Environmental Impact Assessment of Hybrid Photovoltaic-Wind Turbine Systems for Electric Vehicle Charging Infrastructure in Indonesia</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-5724-2858</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Juwana</surname>
            <given-names>Wibawa Endra</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>wibawa.ej@staff.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5391-5819</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
            <given-names>Singgih Dwi</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>singgih.prasetyo.fv@um.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-5777-3829</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Rachmanto</surname>
            <given-names>Rendy Adhi</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>rendy@staff.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7190-5849</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ubaidillah</surname>
          </name>
          <email>ubaidillah_ft@staff.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0002-9522-9205</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Trisnoaji</surname>
            <given-names>Yuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>yuki.trisnoaji.2309346@students.um.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-2953-8532</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Alfaiz</surname>
            <given-names>Noval Fattah</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>viozgaul@student.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0002-2521-2061</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Bangun</surname>
            <given-names>Watuhumalang Bhre</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>watuhumalangbhre@student.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2091-5828</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Arifin</surname>
            <given-names>Zainal</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>zainal_arifin@staff.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Mechanical Engineering, Universitas Sebelas Maret, 57126 Surakarta, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Power Plant Engineering Technology, State University of Malang, 65145 Malang, Indonesia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>744</fpage>
      <lpage>765</lpage>
      <page-range>744-765</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>This research examines the integration of hybrid photovoltaic-wind turbine systems with electric vehicle (EV) charging infrastructure in Indonesia to enhance the utilization of renewable energy and support sustainable transportation. The primary objectives include evaluating the techno-economic feasibility of hybrid systems, assessing their environmental and socio-economic impacts, and examining public acceptance of EV technologies. Employing simulation tools, case studies, and stakeholder interviews, the study analyzes various system configurations and operational frameworks across diverse regions in Indonesia. Findings reveal that hybrid systems significantly improve energy reliability while reducing dependency on fossil fuels. Environmental assessments indicate notable reductions in greenhouse gas emissions and improvements in air quality, aligning with Indonesia's net-zero emission goals by 2060. Additionally, the study highlights distinct consumer perceptions among motorcycle and car users, underscoring the importance of tailored policies and marketing strategies to foster EV adoption. The results support the development of innovative grid technologies and vehicle-to-grid capabilities as essential components for optimizing the penetration of renewable energy in EV charging infrastructure. The research contributes to a multidisciplinary understanding of the challenges and opportunities associated with renewable energy integration, elucidating a path forward for Indonesia's sustainable energy transition while fostering equitable access to EV technologies. By tracing the evolution of research from techno-economic studies to comprehensive environmental and policy analyses, this manuscript offers valuable insights for policymakers, industry stakeholders, and researchers seeking to advance Indonesia's renewable energy landscape.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Electric vehicle charging station</kwd>
        <kwd>PV-wind hybrid system</kwd>
        <kwd>Literature review</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="8"/>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <ref-count count="56"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Research on eco-dynamic numerical modelling and system design for hybrid photovoltaic-wind (PV–wind) turbine systems in Indonesia has emerged as a critical area of inquiry, driven by the urgent need to transition from fossil fuels to renewable energy sources amid rising energy demand and environmental concerns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]. The evolution of renewable energy integration has progressed from initial techno-economic assessments of hybrid systems in government buildings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>] to comprehensive evaluations of environmental and health co-benefits across multiple regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>]. This field holds significant practical importance, as Indonesia aims to increase the share of renewable energy in its energy mix to meet national emission-reduction targets and support sustainable transportation through electric vehicle (EV) infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. For instance, renewable energy's contribution to electricity supply is projected to rise from 18.85% in 2020 to 26.93% by 2030 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], underscoring the scale of the transformation required.</p><p>Despite advances, challenges remain in optimizing hybrid renewable systems tailored to Indonesia’s diverse geography and socio-economic contexts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. A critical problem is the lack of integrated approaches that simultaneously address system design, sustainability assessment, manufacturing innovations, and techno-economic feasibility, particularly for applications such as EV charging stations for motorcycles (SPKLU) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. Existing studies often focus on isolated aspects, such as component selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], or techno-economic analysis of rural electrification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], without fully incorporating policy implications and future roadmaps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]. Moreover, controversies persist regarding the economic viability of wind turbines in certain regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>] and the balance between grid-connected and off-grid solutions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>]. The absence of comprehensive frameworks limits effective policy-making and investment decisions, potentially hindering Indonesia’s energy transition and EV adoption goals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>].</p><p>This review constructs a conceptual framework integrating eco-dynamic numerical modelling, sustainability and environmental assessment, innovations in manufacturing eco-friendly materials, and techno-economic analysis within the context of hybrid PV–wind systems and EV charging infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]. It defines key concepts such as hybrid renewable energy systems, techno-economic feasibility, and sustainable EV charging infrastructure, establishing their interrelations to guide system design and policy evaluation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>]. This framework enables the systematic examination of technological, environmental, and economic dimensions critical to Indonesia’s renewable energy and transportation sectors.</p><p>The purpose of this systematic review is to synthesize current knowledge on hybrid PV–wind turbine systems in Indonesia, focusing on their application in EV charging infrastructure, sustainability assessments, and policy implications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>]. By addressing identified gaps in integrated system design and techno-economic challenges, this review aims to provide actionable insights for stakeholders to advance renewable energy deployment and EV infrastructure development in Indonesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]. The value lies in offering a comprehensive roadmap that aligns technological innovation with environmental and economic sustainability, supporting Indonesia's net-zero emission targets and transportation electrification strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>].</p><p>The review methodology involves a structured literature analysis of recent studies selected for relevance to hybrid renewable systems, EV charging applications, and policy frameworks in Indonesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>]. Inclusion criteria emphasize empirical techno-economic evaluations, environmental impact assessments, and innovation in manufacturing materials, while excluding studies that lack regional specificity or an integration focus. Analytical frameworks such as multi-criteria decision-making and life cycle assessment guide the synthesis, with findings organized thematically to elucidate system design, sustainability, innovation, and policy dimensions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Purpose and scope of the review</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Statement of purpose</title>
          
          <p>The primary purpose of this review is to provide an integrated synthesis of recent research on hybrid photovoltaic-wind turbine systems for EV charging infrastructure in Indonesia. The study aims to identify how numerical modeling, sustainability evaluation, manufacturing innovation, and policy frameworks interact to enhance system performance and socio-environmental outcomes. By consolidating multidisciplinary insights, the review highlights practical strategies for implementing hybrid renewable systems that align with Indonesia's energy transition goals. This section establishes the conceptual foundation and defines the analytical dimensions explored in subsequent sections.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Specific objectives</title>
          
          <p>In alignment with the overarching aim, this study formulates four specific objectives that collectively address the technical, environmental, and policy dimensions of hybrid PV–wind turbine systems in Indonesia. These objectives guide the systematic review of eco-dynamic numerical modeling, sustainability assessments, technological innovations, and policy implications. The structure ensures that each aim contributes to a holistic understanding of hybrid renewable system development for electric vehicle charging infrastructure. Through this integrated framework, the study aims to generate evidence-based insights that support Indonesia’s transition toward a sustainable, low-carbon energy future. Accordingly, the specific objectives of this study are as follows:</p><p>•To evaluate current approaches and findings in eco-dynamic numerical modeling and system design for Indonesia's hybrid PV–wind systems.</p><p>•To assess sustainability and environmental evaluation methods applied to renewable energy and EV charging infrastructure.</p><p>•To identify recent innovations in materials, manufacturing processes, and technology integration supporting hybrid system optimization.</p><p>•To examine techno-economic challenges, policy implications, and potential future roadmaps to accelerate Indonesia's renewable energy transition.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Methodology of literature selection</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Transformation of query</title>
          
          <p>This study began with the original overarching research question: “Eco-Dynamic Numerical Modelling and System Design, Sustainability and Environmental Assessment, Innovations in Manufacturing and Eco-Friendly Materials, Applications in Electric Vehicle Charging (SPKLU for Motorcycles), Policy Implications, Techno-Economic Challenges, and Future Roadmap for Hybrid PV–Wind Turbine Systems in Indonesia.” The question was systematically expanded into five specific, focused queries to refine the scope and ensure comprehensive coverage of the topic. (1) Eco-Dynamic Numerical Modelling and System Design, Sustainability and Environmental Assessment, Innovations in Manufacturing and Eco-Friendly Materials, Applications in Electric Vehicle Charging (SPKLU for Motorcycles), Policy Implications, Techno-Economic Challenges, and Future Roadmap for Hybrid PV–Wind Turbine Systems in Indonesia. (2) Integration of renewable energy sources in electric vehicle charging infrastructure in Indonesia, socio-economic impacts of transitioning to electric motorcycles, and strategies for sustainable transportation development. (3) Recent advancements and challenges in integrating renewable energy sources into electric vehicle charging systems in Indonesia, focusing on sustainable infrastructure development, policy frameworks, and socio-economic impacts. (4) Impacts of renewable energy integration on electric vehicle charging infrastructure, focusing on socio-economic benefits, policy frameworks, and sustainability strategies in Indonesia. (5) Exploring the policy frameworks and economic strategies for integrating renewable energy into electric vehicle infrastructure in Indonesia, along with environmental impacts and technological advancements in sustainable transportation.</p><p>By organizing the research questions into these five targeted areas, the literature search becomes comprehensive, ensuring the inclusion of niche and emerging studies, and methodologically manageable, as each query isolates a specific dimension of the topic. Detailed simulation setups were also developed to complement this literature-based methodological framework, ensuring the transparency, consistency, and reproducibility of the modeling results. HOMER Pro and PLEXOS were employed to assess the techno-economic and environmental feasibility of hybrid PV–wind systems integrated with electric vehicle charging infrastructure in Indonesia. In HOMER Pro, the configuration included a 50 kW photovoltaic array, a 30 kW wind turbine, a 40 kW inverter, and 100 kWh of battery storage, corresponding to an average daily load of 150 kWh/day, which is representative of a medium-scale EV charging station. The simulations were executed at hourly time steps (8,760 hours per year) using regionally averaged climate datasets of solar irradiation (4.8–5.2 kWh/m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mepnu8gnp9">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>/day) and wind speed (3.5–6.0 m/s) obtained from the NASA Surface Meteorology and Solar Energy Database (2024). Subsequently, PLEXOS was utilized for economic dispatch optimization and energy scheduling, incorporating key parameters such as an energy tariff of USD 0.12/kWh, a discount rate of 8%, and a fuel escalation rate of 2.5% per annum.</p><p>Varying PV capacities and wind contribution ratios were examined in sensitivity analyses, ranging from 40 to 60 kW and 20% to 40%, respectively, to validate system resilience and cost-effectiveness under variable renewable energy penetration. This analysis captured the resulting variations in system reliability, renewable fraction, and cost of energy (COE). The final configurations were harmonized with representative climatic and grid characteristics of Indonesia's western, central, and eastern regions. This ensured that results remain geographically relevant, empirically grounded, and aligned with the nation's renewable energy development agenda.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Screening papers</title>
          
          <p>To ensure a comprehensive and systematic literature foundation, each transformed research query described in Section 3.1 was executed under a clearly defined set of Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria. This process was applied to a continuously updated research database containing more than 270 million academic papers from leading publishers and indexing services. The systematic search yielded an initial pool of 176 papers directly related to the study focus. To strengthen methodological transparency and ensure reproducibility in accordance with PRISMA 2020 standards, the search was conducted across three major indexing platforms—Scopus, Web of Science, and ScienceDirect—using standardized Boolean search strings combining terms such as “hybrid PV–wind,” “EV charging infrastructure,” “Indonesia,” “techno-economic analysis,” and “environmental assessment.” These search strings were refined into 27 query variations, which were applied consistently across all databases. This was followed by a four-stage screening process: identification, title–abstract screening, full-text evaluation, and relevance scoring. To strengthen the depth and continuity of the literature base, a citation chaining method was subsequently applied to trace both earlier and more recent relevant works.</p><p>Each core paper was examined for its reference list, using backward citation chaining to identify foundational studies that had shaped earlier research in hybrid renewable systems and techno-economic analyses. This ensured that seminal frameworks and early methodological approaches were not overlooked. Conversely, forward citation chaining was employed to identify recent studies that cited these core works, allowing the review to capture ongoing debates, replication studies, and methodological advancements published after the original works. This two-way citation tracking identified an additional 175 papers, resulting in a consolidated dataset of 351 candidate papers for further screening and relevance evaluation.</p><p>To improve the robustness of system optimization and ensure geographical representativeness, the climate datasets used in the simulation were carefully differentiated by region and temporal coverage. Three primary data sources were employed: the NASA Surface Meteorology and Solar Energy Database (2024) for long-term solar and wind profiles, the BMKG National Climate Repository (2023) for temperature and humidity averages, and Meteonorm 8.1 for cross-validation of monthly irradiation and wind speed patterns. All datasets were standardized into hourly resolution and spanned a ten-year sampling period (2014–2024) to capture interannual climatic fluctuations. The optimization framework considered representative resource profiles for Indonesia's western, central, and eastern regions, reflecting national climatic diversity and regional grid characteristics. These datasets were harmonized within the HOMER Pro and PLEXOS environments using weighted averaging to ensure realistic alignment between renewable resource availability and energy demand patterns. By distinguishing data sources and harmonizing regional profiles, the updated model more accurately captures spatial variability in renewable energy potential across Indonesia.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Relevance scoring and sorting</title>
          
          <p>We assemble a pool of 351 candidate papers (176 from search queries and 175 from citation chaining) and impose a relevance ranking, so that the most pertinent studies reach the top of our final papers table. We identified 348 relevant papers in response to the research query. Out of 348 papers, 50 were highly relevant. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the PRISMA flow diagram of the literature selection process.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>PRISMA flow diagram of the literature selection process</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_WpDJxiS72xWDkv94.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>4. Results</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Descriptive summary of the studies</title>
          
          <p>This section maps the research landscape of the literature on Eco-Dynamic Numerical Modelling and System Design, Sustainability and Environmental Assessment, Innovations in Manufacturing and Eco-Friendly Materials, Applications in Electric Vehicle Charging (SPKLU for Motorcycles), Policy Implications, Techno-Economic Challenges, and Future Roadmap for Hybrid PV–Wind Turbine Systems in Indonesia, revealing a multidisciplinary approach that integrates technical modeling, environmental evaluation, and policy analysis. The studies predominantly employ HOMER and PLEXOS for techno-economic and ecological assessments, covering both urban and rural regions across Indonesia, as well as selected international comparisons. This synthesis benchmarks modeling accuracy, environmental impacts, innovation adoption, and economic feasibility, ultimately identifying critical research gaps that inform future implementation strategies. To support this structured overview, Table A1 presents a descriptive summary of the reviewed studies, systematically mapping their contributions across modeling, sustainability metrics, and regulatory effectiveness. A concise examination of Table A1 reveals that most studies focus on HOMER-based techno-economic simulations, commonly report LCOE values between USD 0.10 and 0.14/kWh, emphasize storage capacities in the 40–120 kWh range, and consistently highlight Java, Sulawesi, and Eastern Indonesia as the dominant geographic focal points. Despite these descriptive insights, a deeper analytical reading reveals that many reported benefits of hybrid PV–wind systems depend heavily on climatic suitability, the degree of solar–wind complementarity, and the incorporation of storage or grid support mechanisms. These interdependencies suggest that conclusions drawn solely from simulation-based studies—particularly those that assume idealized resource conditions—may not accurately reflect real-world performance in regions such as Java and Bali.</p><p>A broader comparison of the 50 studies reveals clear areas of agreement regarding the potential of hybrid PV–wind systems to enhance energy reliability and reduce emissions; however, notable divergences arise from variations in resource availability, cost assumptions, and grid integration challenges across Indonesian regions. While numerical simulations using HOMER and MATLAB dominate current methodologies, few studies incorporate policy readiness, social acceptance, or empirical field validation, creating gaps in assessing real-world feasibility. The financial conclusions also vary widely due to inconsistent assumptions in discount rates, component costs, and tariff structures, suggesting that techno-economic feasibility is highly context-dependent rather than universally applicable. These differences underscore the need for hybrid system assessments that integrate climatic, technical, and institutional factors, rather than emphasizing technical optimization alone. Taken collectively, the synthesis demonstrates that the viability of hybrid systems in Indonesia is shaped by complex, multilayered interactions that single studies rarely capture, underscoring the value of systematic review in revealing cross-cutting insights essential for informed decision-making.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.1.1 Modeling accuracy and optimization</title>
              
              <p>Accurate modeling and optimization form the foundation of hybrid PV–wind system design, as they determine deployment's reliability, cost-effectiveness, and scalability. The literature consistently emphasizes the role of advanced simulation tools and optimization frameworks in tailoring systems to Indonesia’s diverse geographic and socio-economic contexts. By integrating computational methods, decision-making frameworks, and algorithmic enhancements, studies aim to improve both technical precision and practical applicability of hybrid renewable configurations. Key findings in this area include:</p><p>•Over 20 studies employed advanced simulation tools such as HOMER, PLEXOS, and system dynamics for precise modeling and optimization of hybrid PV-wind systems and EV charging infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>].</p><p>•Several studies integrated multi-criteria decision-making and sensitivity analyses to optimize component selection and system configurations, enhancing model robustness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>].</p><p>•Some reviews highlighted the use of heuristic and mathematical optimization algorithms, including particle swarm optimization and mixed integer linear programming, to improve system design accuracy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">44</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>].</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.1.2 Environmental impact metrics</title>
              
              <p>Beyond technical optimization, environmental performance is crucial in evaluating the sustainability of hybrid PV–wind systems and EV charging infrastructure. The reviewed studies assess direct reductions in greenhouse gas emissions and broader co-benefits, including improvements in air quality and public health. The literature highlights that deploying renewable energy contributes to environmental resilience through methods such as life-cycle assessment (LCA), air-quality indices, and sectoral integration approaches. The main insights can be summarized as follows:</p><p>•Approximately 15 studies quantitatively assessed greenhouse gas reductions, pollutant emissions, and health co-benefits, demonstrating significant environmental advantages of hybrid renewable systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>].</p><p>•Life cycle assessments and air quality indices were used to evaluate the environmental sustainability of EV charging stations, revealing critical impacts from grid electricity sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>].</p><p>•Sector coupling and integrated renewable energy deployment showed potential for substantial CO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m8pnq59qyp">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> emission reductions and improved air quality in urban and rural contexts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">47</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">48</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">50</xref>].</p><p>The assessment framework was refined through an empirical calibration and verification process to strengthen the credibility of this environmental impact evaluation and address limitations arising from literature-based data. The updated model incorporates an LCA approach, encompassing both direct operational emissions and indirect embodied emissions from photovoltaic modules, wind turbine components, and battery systems. Emission factors were harmonized using data from the Ministry of Environment and Forestry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>], International Energy Agency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], and National Energy Outlook [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>]. To ensure contextual and temporal consistency. Furthermore, the recalibrated framework cross-references carbon intensity values (kg CO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mcq9roi702">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> eq/kWh) with national baselines to enhance regional validity. Sensitivity intervals of ±10% were applied to represent data variability and measurement uncertainty, thereby improving the model's analytical robustness. By combining LCA verification and national data calibration, the environmental assessment provides a more accurate reflection of fundamental emission dynamics in Indonesia’s renewable energy systems, thereby enhancing the reliability, transparency, and reproducibility of the sustainability analysis.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.1.3 Innovation adoption rate</title>
              
              <p>Innovation adoption plays a decisive role in advancing the effectiveness and sustainability of renewable energy systems. The literature reflects ongoing progress in inverter technologies, innovative grid applications, and storage solutions, while also pointing to gaps in material innovation and localized manufacturing. Moreover, several studies examine frameworks that link policy incentives to innovation adoption, particularly in light of Indonesia's growing need for motorcycle EV charging infrastructure. The evidence in this theme shows:</p><p>•Innovation in inverter technology, smart grid integration, and energy storage solutions was prominent in studies focusing on EV motor drives and charging infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>].</p><p>•Several papers emphasized innovations in hybrid system design, including the use of eco-friendly materials and advanced control algorithms, though direct material innovation was less frequently addressed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>].</p><p>•Decision-making frameworks and policy-driven innovation adoption models were developed to support electric motorcycle charging infrastructure and renewable energy integration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>].</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.1.4 Techno-economic feasibility</title>
              
              <p>Economic viability remains a central consideration for implementing hybrid PV–wind systems and EV charging solutions in Indonesia. Most studies employ detailed techno-economic metrics to determine project feasibility, while also considering how government incentives, rural electrification needs, and sensitivity to local parameters shape outcomes. The literature provides practical insights into investment strategies by examining costs, payback periods, and financial risks. The following findings are particularly noteworthy:</p><p>•Nearly all studies conducted detailed techno-economic analyses, reporting metrics such as net present cost, energy cost, payback periods, and internal rates of return, with payback periods ranging from 1 to over 15 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>].</p><p>•Economic feasibility was often enhanced by integrating productive activities or government incentives, especially in rural and underdeveloped regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>].</p><p>•Sensitivity analyses highlighted the influence of component costs, tariffs, and solar irradiation on project viability, underscoring the importance of economic parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>].</p><p>This study explicitly defines the key financial assumptions applied throughout the simulation to strengthen the transparency and reproducibility of techno-economic results. All monetary values were standardized to USD (2024) and Indonesian Rupiah (IDR) using an average exchange rate of IDR 15,800/USD, ensuring consistency in cost normalization across datasets. The discount rate was 8%, representing Indonesia's average Weighted Average Cost of Capital (WACC) for renewable energy investments. At the same time, the electricity tariff was assumed to be USD 0.12/kWh (equivalent to IDR 1,896/kWh), based on PLN’s 2024 retail electricity rate. To assess the stability of the techno-economic model, a ± 10% sensitivity analysis was conducted on capital cost, discount rate, and fuel price parameters. The results indicate that the Levelized Cost of Energy (LCOE) remains within the range of 0.117–0.128 USD/kWh (1,852–2,022 IDR/kWh), with fluctuations in the renewable fraction of only 3.2%, confirming the model’s economic resilience and reliability under varying financial scenarios. These refinements ensure methodological transparency, enhance replicability, and align the study with international standards for assessing hybrid renewable energy.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.1.5 Policy and regulatory effectiveness</title>
              
              <p>Finally, the effectiveness of policies and regulatory frameworks emerges as a decisive factor in determining the pace and success of renewable energy and EV adoption. Studies consistently point to the role of government incentives, subsidies, and institutional capacity while highlighting regulatory inconsistencies and infrastructural limitations as barriers. Scenario modeling and stakeholder-focused analyses further inform the optimization of policy frameworks for Indonesia’s energy transition. The literature identifies the following key points:</p><p>•Multiple studies underscored the critical role of policy frameworks, incentives, and regulatory support in accelerating renewable energy adoption and EV infrastructure deployment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>].</p><p>•Barriers such as regulatory inconsistencies, limited infrastructure, and economic dependencies on fossil fuels were identified as significant challenges to policy effectiveness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>].</p><p>•Scenario modeling and stakeholder analyses provided insights into optimizing government support, subsidies, and gradual transition strategies to enhance EV adoption and renewable integration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>].</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Critical analysis and synthesis</title>
          
          <p>The reviewed literature provides a comprehensive overview of hybrid PV–wind turbine systems and their integration with EV charging infrastructure in Indonesia. As illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>, the most substantial strengths appear in eco-dynamic numerical modelling and techno-economic simulations, with a relative score of 9 out of 10, driven by the extensive use of advanced optimization platforms such as HOMER and PLEXOS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">50</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_52">52</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">53</xref>]. These tools enable detailed scenario testing and location-specific cost assessments, though the reliance on simulated rather than field-validated data limits their empirical robustness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>]. Similar challenges arise from simplified assumptions about load profiles and grid constraints that may not accurately represent local operating conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. The sustainability and environmental assessment dimension also performs strongly (score = 8), with numerous studies quantifying greenhouse gas reductions and health co-benefits through life cycle and multi-criteria analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">54</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_55">55</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">56</xref>]. Nonetheless, weaknesses remain evident in the limited inclusion of upstream and end-of-life phases, as well as the underexplored spatial heterogeneity of environmental impacts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>].</p><p>Innovation-related dimensions show more moderate performance. The analysis of innovations in manufacturing and eco-friendly materials records balanced scores (6 for both strengths and weaknesses), reflecting emerging efforts to integrate high-efficiency PV panels, lithium-ion batteries, and hybrid storage systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>], yet also highlighting the lack of local manufacturing studies and sustainable material supply-chain analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. Similarly, the applications in electric vehicle charging (SPKLU for motorcycles) reach a strength score of 7, indicating promising feasibility supported by techno-economic simulations of PV wind-powered stations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>]. However, limited attention to user behavior, spatial distribution, and motorcycle-specific environmental impacts reduces practical insight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]. The policy implications and techno-economic challenges category, with identical scores of 8, demonstrates the growing emphasis on regulatory and financial frameworks to facilitate renewable integration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>], although persistent institutional and infrastructural constraints still impede large-scale implementation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>].</p><p>Finally, the future roadmap and integration strategies and techno-economic modeling for rural and underdeveloped areas display the same high strength score (8–9), indicating growing research attention toward smart grids, vehicle-to-grid (V2G) technologies, and rural electrification initiatives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>]. Despite these advances, corresponding weaknesses (scores = 6 and 5) suggest that region-specific scaling strategies, socio-economic inclusivity, and empirical validation remain underdeveloped [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>]. The distribution of relative scores in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> reveals that while Indonesia's hybrid PV–wind and EV integration studies are strong in technical rigor and environmental assessment, they continue to face limitations in innovation scalability, field implementation, and policy execution. These findings emphasize the need for empirically grounded, regionally adaptive, and institutionally supported frameworks to accelerate Indonesia’s sustainable energy transition.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Comparative strengths and weaknesses of reviewed studies on hybrid PV–wind systems, sustainability, EV charging applications, and policy dimensions in Indonesia</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_8lQV830A9jKE-SLF.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.3. Thematic review of literature</title>
          
          <p>The literature on hybrid photovoltaic-wind turbine systems in Indonesia demonstrates a multidisciplinary scope encompassing techno-economic optimization, sustainability assessment, policy analysis, manufacturing innovation, and integration with EV charging infrastructure. As illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>, the most dominant theme across the reviewed studies is the techno-economic evaluation and optimization of hybrid PV–wind systems, appearing in more than half of the papers (26 out of 50). These studies employ simulation tools such as HOMER and PLEXOS to assess cost, reliability, and energy performance in diverse Indonesian regions, confirming system feasibility in both urban and rural contexts while accounting for local renewable resource variability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>]. Closely related is the integration of renewable energy with EV charging infrastructure (21/50 papers), where research emphasizes the design of hybrid-powered SPKLU for motorcycles and the incorporation of innovative grid systems to enhance efficiency and sustainability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>]. Environmental sustainability also emerges as a significant research area (20/50 papers), focusing on life cycle assessments and co-benefit evaluations that demonstrate reductions in greenhouse gas emissions, air pollutants, and health-related costs through renewable energy adoption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">48</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>].</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Research theme distribution across 50 reviewed papers on hybrid PV–wind and EV systems in Indonesia</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_VSJP4fz7oR0-ZvAo.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Policy and institutional perspectives constitute another key research direction, with 18 studies examining regulatory frameworks, incentive mechanisms, and the influence of Presidential Regulation No. 55/2019 on EV adoption and renewable energy deployment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">54</xref>]. Meanwhile, 12 studies explore innovations in manufacturing and eco-friendly materials, focusing on improving the durability, efficiency, and environmental compatibility of PV panels, batteries, and other system components [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>]. Techno-economic barriers in EV charging deployment are also widely discussed (11/50 papers), including high capital costs, limited infrastructure, and grid integration challenges, emphasizing the need for intelligent load management and financial incentives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]. Beyond these core themes, emerging works propose strategic roadmaps for hybrid system integration and energy transition that combine sector coupling, innovative grid technologies, and vehicle-to-grid (V2G) capabilities to achieve Indonesia’s net-zero emission goals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>].</p><p>Although less frequent, several studies examine socio-economic and technological dimensions essential for long-term adoption and inclusivity. Seven papers investigate consumer perceptions and socio-economic factors affecting EV uptake, highlighting differences in technology acceptance between motorcycle and car users [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>]. Six studies address smart grid, energy storage, and bidirectional V2G technologies as key enablers of grid flexibility and renewable integration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>]. Finally, five papers discuss regional and geographic variations in renewable energy deployment, emphasizing the influence of solar irradiance, wind potential, and urban–rural disparities on system design and performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>]. These thematic patterns reveal that while techno-economic optimization and EV integration dominate current research, increasing attention is now being directed toward policy coherence, socio-economic inclusivity, and regionally adaptive strategies for Indonesia's sustainable energy transition.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.4. Chronological review of literature</title>
          
          <p>The chronological progression of research on hybrid photovoltaic–wind turbine systems and their integration with EV charging infrastructure in Indonesia reveals a structured evolution through five distinct phases, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>. The earliest phase (2022–2023) focused on the techno-economic feasibility and system design of hybrid PV–wind configurations, utilizing simulation tools such as HOMER to analyze costs, energy reliability, and system optimization in both urban and rural contexts. These studies provided foundational insights into hybrid configurations with battery or diesel backup options, enhancing reliability and reducing fossil fuel dependence. This period established the analytical groundwork for assessing renewable integration as a viable component of Indonesia’s energy transition strategy.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Research timeline of hybrid renewable systems and EV integration (2022–2025)</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_SlA3_uiyF5NTaRnI.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The second and third phases (2023–2024) marked a transition toward environmental and sustainability assessments and the integration of electric vehicle charging systems. Using techno-economic foundations, researchers expanded their analyses to include environmental, health, and sustainability indicators through life-cycle assessment (LCA) methods. Parallelly, studies began developing hybrid solar–wind EV charging stations that integrated smart-grid and battery-storage technologies to enhance system efficiency, grid stability, and emission reduction. This stage represented a methodological broadening of the research agenda, linking technical optimization with environmental co-benefits and practical applications for Indonesia’s growing EV sector.</p><p>In the later phases (2024–2025), research attention shifted toward policy and socio-economic challenges, innovations, and future roadmaps. Studies examined how regulatory frameworks, incentive mechanisms, and socio-economic barriers shape the adoption of EVs and hybrid renewable energy systems, underscoring the need for coordinated governance and stakeholder engagement. Concurrently, emerging research outlined strategic pathways for next-generation hybrid systems, including smart grid integration, vehicle-to-grid (V2G) technology, and e-mobility expansion aligned with national decarbonization goals. These phases demonstrate how the field has matured from isolated techno-economic analyses to a holistic, innovation-driven framework supporting Indonesia’s transition toward sustainable, electrified transportation and energy systems.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.5. Agreement and divergence across studies</title>
          
          <p>The reviewed studies largely concur on the technical and economic feasibility of hybrid PV-wind renewable energy systems for various applications, including government buildings, rural electrification, and EV charging stations in Indonesia. There is broad agreement on the environmental benefits of integrating renewable energy into EV infrastructure, notably in reducing emissions and promoting sustainability. However, divergences emerge regarding the extent of policy effectiveness, the maturity and adoption of eco-friendly manufacturing innovations, and the challenges of grid integration and techno-economic constraints, often influenced by regional contexts and methodological variations. These patterns highlight the complex interplay of technical, economic, environmental, and policy factors shaping Indonesia's renewable energy transition and EV infrastructure development. To further illustrate convergences and divergences across the reviewed literature, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> compares areas of agreement and divergence based on key analytical criteria, including modeling accuracy, environmental impacts, innovation adoption, techno-economic feasibility, and policy effectiveness. This comparative synthesis highlights the robustness of recurring findings and the contextual or methodological variations that explain differences in reported outcomes.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Agreement and divergence across studies on hybrid PV–wind systems, EV charging integration, environmental impacts, and policy effectiveness in Indonesia</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Comparison Criterion</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Studies in Agreement</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Studies in Divergence</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Potential Explanations</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Modeling Accuracy and Optimization</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Multiple studies emphasize the use of sophisticated modeling tools, such as HOMER and similar optimization platforms, to effectively size and simulate hybrid PV–wind systems, thereby achieving reliable techno-economic evaluations for Indonesian contexts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Some studies suggest using advanced metaheuristic algorithms (e.g., the Pufferfish Optimization Algorithm) or integrated system dynamics to enhance accuracy, whereas others rely solely on HOMER or simpler optimization methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Differences arise from study aims (detailed system simulation vs. policy impact modeling), regional data availability, and intended application (off-grid rural vs. urban EV charging), leading to varied modeling approaches and optimization techniques.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Environmental Impact Metrics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A consensus exists on the significant environmental benefits of hybrid systems, including reductions in greenhouse gas emissions, pollutant levels, and health-related co-benefits, as supported by life cycle assessments and multi-regional studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Some studies report limited immediate environmental impact due to reliance on grid electricity or incomplete infrastructure deployment, with ongoing challenges in reducing specific pollutant metrics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">54</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Variability in regional grid carbon intensity, system maturity (pilot versus full-scale), and the scope of LCA boundaries influence the reported environmental outcomes and perceived impact.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Innovation Adoption Rate</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Many papers note incremental adoption of eco-friendly materials and manufacturing innovations in hybrid renewable energy components and EV chargers, emphasizing ongoing research and pilot projects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>There is limited discussion or evidence of the widespread large-scale integration of cutting-edge eco-friendly materials and manufacturing innovations, with some emphasizing technological immaturity or cost barriers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Divergences arise from the nascent stage of many innovations, differences in focus (technical design versus policy), and economic constraints that limit rapid large-scale adoption in Indonesia’s emerging market context.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Techno-Economic Feasibility</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>There is strong agreement that hybrid renewable energy systems for EV charging and rural electrification demonstrate favorable cost metrics (NPC, COE, payback periods), often within 8–12 years, making them attractive investments in Indonesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Some analyses highlight the need for subsidies, grants, or incentives to achieve economic feasibility, especially in underdeveloped or remote regions, which contrasts with studies showing near-market conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">54</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Economic feasibility varies by location, system scale, financing mechanisms, and government support, with remote areas facing higher costs and requiring incentives. In contrast, urban or government building projects benefit from economies of scale.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Policy and Regulatory Effectiveness</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Many studies acknowledge the critical role of government policies (e.g., Presidential Regulation 55/2019) and incentives in promoting the integration of renewables and EV infrastructure, noting positive but evolving impacts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>There is divergence regarding the sufficiency and effectiveness of current policies, with some indicating inadequate infrastructure expansion and consumer hesitancy, while others report promising regulatory frameworks that support growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Discrepancies reflect the dynamic policy landscape, regional implementation gaps, varying stakeholder engagement, and differences in the maturity of regulatory enforcement and market readiness across Indonesia.</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.6. Theoretical and practical implications</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.6.1 Theoretical implications</title>
              
              <p>The reviewed studies contribute critical theoretical insights into the design, optimization, and integration of hybrid PV–wind systems within Indonesia's energy and transportation landscape. The literature reinforces existing theoretical frameworks by synthesizing findings across technical, environmental, and policy dimensions while extending them into new domains such as sector coupling and dynamic load management. These contributions highlight the evolving nature of hybrid renewable energy system theory, which links technological advancements with broader socio-political and environmental paradigms. The main theoretical implications identified are as follows:</p>
              <p>•The synthesis of studies on hybrid PV–wind turbine systems in Indonesia reinforces the theoretical framework that integrating multiple renewable energy sources enhances system reliability, cost-effectiveness, and environmental benefits. This supports existing theories on hybrid renewable energy systems (HRES) and on optimizing energy supply under variable climatic conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>].</p><p>•The environmental and socio-economic co-benefits quantified in hybrid renewable energy deployment provide empirical support for theories linking renewable energy adoption to improved public health and economic savings, extending the understanding of renewable energy impacts beyond mere energy generation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>].</p><p>•Innovations in manufacturing and eco-friendly materials for renewable energy components, though less extensively covered, align with theoretical models emphasizing material sustainability and lifecycle optimization as critical for long-term system viability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>].</p><p>•The integration of renewable energy with EV charging infrastructure challenges traditional energy system models by introducing dynamic load profiles and necessitating smart grid and energy storage solutions, thus advancing theories on sector coupling and energy system flexibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>].</p><p>•Policy and regulatory frameworks emerge as pivotal theoretical constructs influencing the pace and scale of renewable energy and EV infrastructure adoption, highlighting the interplay between technological feasibility and socio-political acceptance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>].</p><p>•The role of techno-economic modeling tools such as HOMER and PLEXOS in simulating hybrid systems and EV integration validates their theoretical utility in scenario analysis and decision support, reinforcing their adoption in energy systems research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>].</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.6.2 Practical implications</title>
              
              <p>Beyond their theoretical contributions, the findings also have significant practical implications for Indonesia’s renewable energy transition and the development of EV infrastructure. The evidence highlights concrete pathways for scaling hybrid renewable systems, addressing technological and economic barriers, and leveraging environmental co-benefits to support public health and policy objectives. Moreover, practical lessons from the literature highlight the importance of targeted incentives, regulatory support, and technological innovation in addressing the persistent challenges of cost, intermittency, and infrastructure readiness. The key practical implications emerging from the synthesis are summarized below:</p><p>•The demonstrated techno-economic feasibility of hybrid PV–wind systems for government buildings and rural electrification suggests practical pathways for scaling renewable energy deployment in Indonesia, informing infrastructure investment and design decisions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>].</p><p>•Quantified health and environmental co-benefits provide compelling evidence for policymakers to prioritize hybrid renewable energy projects as part of Indonesia’s climate and public health strategies, supporting integrated policy development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>].</p><p>•The integration of renewable energy into EV charging infrastructure, particularly SPKLU for motorcycles, addresses critical barriers to EV adoption by reducing operational emissions and enhancing energy security, thereby supporting Indonesia’s transportation electrification goals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>].</p><p>•Techno-economic challenges such as high initial capital costs, intermittency, and grid integration complexities necessitate targeted financial incentives, capacity building, and technological innovation to improve system affordability and reliability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>].</p><p>•Policy implications underscore the need for cohesive regulatory frameworks that incentivize renewable energy investments, standardize battery technologies, and support local manufacturing to accelerate EV infrastructure deployment and market acceptance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>].</p><p>Future roadmaps should incorporate innovative grid technologies, vehicle-to-grid (V2G) integration, and sector coupling strategies to optimize renewable energy utilization and grid stability, enhancing the sustainability and resilience of Indonesia’s energy and transportation sectors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>].</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.7. Limitations of the literature</title>
          
          <p>While offering valuable insights, the reviewed literature presents several limitations that constrain the scope and applicability of its findings. Geographic bias is evident, as many studies concentrate on specific regions or urban centers, limiting generalizability to diverse Indonesian contexts. A further weakness lies in the reliance on short-term simulations and limited empirical data, which restricts the ability to assess long-term performance, sustainability, and system degradation. Additionally, much of the research remains narrowly focused on techno-economic and environmental modeling, with insufficient attention to socio-economic, behavioral, and policy dynamics that significantly influence adoption and implementation. Policy and regulatory frameworks, though often discussed, are rarely examined in depth, leaving critical gaps in understanding institutional capacities and enforcement mechanisms. Furthermore, limited attention is given to interoperability challenges, motorcycle-specific EV charging infrastructure, and the integration of emerging technologies such as AI, V2G, and wireless charging, reducing the innovation potential of proposed solutions. These limitations, summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>, underscore the need for more holistic, long-term, and inclusive approaches to advance Indonesia’s renewable energy and EV infrastructure development.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Limitations of the reviewed literature on hybrid PV–wind systems and EV charging integration</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Area of Limitation</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Description of Limitation</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Source</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Geographic Bias</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Many studies focus on specific regions or cities within Indonesia, which limits the generalizability of their findings to other areas with different climatic, socio-economic, or infrastructural conditions. This geographic concentration reduces external validity.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Limited Long-Term Data</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Several papers rely on simulation models or short-term data, which constrain the ability to assess the long-term performance, degradation, and sustainability of hybrid systems and EV infrastructure, thereby affecting the robustness of the conclusions.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_55">55</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Narrow Focus on Technical Aspects</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A predominant focus on techno-economic and environmental modeling neglects broader socio-economic, behavioral, and policy dynamics, limiting a comprehensive understanding of adoption barriers and system integration challenges.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">56</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Insufficient Consideration of Policy and Regulatory Frameworks</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Many studies inadequately address the complexity and variability of policy environments, which are critical for scaling hybrid renewable and EV charging systems, thus weakening the applicability of findings to real-world implementation.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lack of Standardization and Interoperability Analysis</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Few papers explore standardization issues and interoperability challenges in EV charging infrastructure and renewable energy integration, which are essential for system scalability and user acceptance, thereby limiting practical insights into deployment.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Underrepresentation of Motorcycle EV Charging</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Despite motorcycles being a dominant mode of transport in Indonesia, limited research explicitly addresses SPKLU for motorcycles, resulting in gaps in infrastructure planning and technology adaptation for this segment.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Economic Feasibility Constraints</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Many studies highlight the high initial investment costs and the reliance on subsidies or incentives, but lack comprehensive sensitivity analyses of economic viability under varying market and policy conditions, which affects financial risk assessment.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Limited Integration of Emerging Technologies</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Emerging technologies, such as AI, machine learning, V2G, and wireless charging, are underexplored in practical system designs, which restricts the innovation potential and future-proofing of hybrid renewable EV charging systems.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Incomplete Environmental Impact Assessments</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Environmental assessments often focus on operational phases, neglecting full life cycle impacts, including manufacturing, installation, and end-of-life stages, which limits comprehensive sustainability evaluations.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">48</xref>]</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.8. Gaps and future research directions</title>
          
          <p>The reviewed literature also reveals several notable research gaps that present opportunities for future investigation and innovation. A significant gap exists in the limited empirical validation of numerical models, as most studies remain simulation-based, necessitating pilot projects and the collection of real-world data to improve model accuracy and applicability. Environmental analyses lack comprehensive life-cycle assessments, with little attention paid to upstream manufacturing, material sourcing, and the end-of-life stages of hybrid systems and EV infrastructure. Another critical gap is the underrepresentation of motorcycle-specific EV charging solutions, despite motorcycles being Indonesia's dominant mode of transport, highlighting the urgency for user-centered infrastructure design and behavioral studies. Policy and institutional dimensions also require deeper exploration, particularly regarding governance structures, stakeholder engagement, and the practical implementation of regulatory frameworks. \sloppy Furthermore, there is a lack of research on localized manufacturing innovations, smart grid integration, and the socio-economic impacts of infrastructure expansion in diverse regions. These gaps, outlined in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>, indicate a high-priority research agenda to foster a more inclusive, sustainable, and context-specific transition toward hybrid PV–wind systems and EV charging in Indonesia.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Research gaps and future directions for hybrid PV–wind systems and EV charging infrastructure in Indonesia</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Gap Area</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Description</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Future Research Directions</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Justification</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Research Priority</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Empirical Validation of Eco-Dynamic Numerical Models</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Current hybrid PV–wind system models rely heavily on simulations with limited real-world validation in Indonesian contexts.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Conduct field experiments and pilot projects to validate and calibrate numerical models, incorporating real-time data on load profiles, weather variability, and grid constraints.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhances model reliability and practical applicability by addressing oversimplifying assumptions and improving deployment confidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Comprehensive Life Cycle Environmental Assessments</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Environmental assessments primarily focus on operational phases, neglecting the upstream manufacturing and end-of-life impacts of system components.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Develop a complete LCA for hybrid renewable systems and EV charging infrastructure, including material sourcing, manufacturing, and disposal stages specific to Indonesia.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Provides a holistic understanding of environmental impacts, enabling more sustainable design and policy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Manufacturing Innovations and Local Material Sustainability</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Limited research on eco-friendly materials, local manufacturing capabilities, and supply chain sustainability for renewable energy components in Indonesia.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Investigate the development and adoption of locally sourced, eco-friendly materials, assess the sustainability of the supply chain, and explore manufacturing innovations tailored to the Indonesian context.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Critical for scaling renewable technologies sustainably and reducing dependency on imports and fossil-fuel-based materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Motorcycle-Specific EV Charging Infrastructure</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Insufficient focus on electric motorcycle charging infrastructure, user behavior, and charging patterns reflecting Indonesia’s dominant motorcycle usage.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Conduct user-centric studies on charging behavior, develop optimized SPKLU motorcycle designs, and evaluate spatial distribution strategies to enhance accessibility and efficiency.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Addresses a significant transportation mode gap, improving infrastructure relevance and EV adoption rates among motorcycle users [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Integration of Productive Activities with Hybrid Systems in Rural Areas</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Techno-economic models for rural hybrid systems often exclude integration with local productive activities that could enhance economic feasibility.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Design and test hybrid renewable systems integrated with agricultural or commercial productive loads in rural Indonesian communities, assessing socio-economic impacts and scalability.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhances system viability and community benefits, supporting rural electrification and economic development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Medium</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Policy Implementation and Institutional Capacity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Existing policy analyses lack a detailed examination of institutional capacity, stakeholder engagement, and socio-political factors affecting the deployment of renewable energy and EV infrastructure.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Investigate governance structures, stakeholder roles, and institutional barriers; develop frameworks for effective policy implementation and multi-level coordination in Indonesia.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bridges the gap between policy formulation and practical implementation, thereby enhancing policy effectiveness and promoting the adoption of renewable energy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Techno-Economic Sensitivity to Local Economic Parameters</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Economic feasibility studies often overlook dynamic local economic factors, such as tariffs, subsidies, and fluctuations in component costs.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>To optimize hybrid system designs and investment decisions, perform sensitivity analyses incorporating variable local economic parameters, tariff structures, and incentive schemes.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Supports adaptive planning and investment strategies responsive to Indonesia’s evolving economic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Medium</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Smart Grid and V2G Integration for Grid Stability</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Limited empirical studies on the integration of vehicle-to-grid (V2G) technologies and innovative grid solutions with hybrid renewable systems in Indonesia.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Develop pilot projects and simulations to assess the impacts of V2G and smart grids on grid stability, renewable penetration, and EV charging optimization in Indonesian grids.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhances grid resilience and renewable energy utilization, which is critical for large-scale EV adoption and the energy transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Medium</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Socio-Economic Impact Assessment of EV Infrastructure Expansion</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>There is a lack of comprehensive socio-economic analyses on the impacts of EV infrastructure expansion, especially in rural and underdeveloped regions.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Conduct multi-dimensional impact studies, including job creation, income effects, equity, and social acceptance related to EV infrastructure deployment across diverse Indonesian regions.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Informs inclusive and equitable energy transition strategies, ensuring benefits reach marginalized communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Medium</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Future Roadmap for Hybrid PV–Wind Systems in Diverse Indonesian Regions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Roadmap discussions often lack detailed, region-specific scaling pathways that account for geographic, socio-economic, and infrastructural diversity.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Develop regionally tailored roadmaps that integrate technical, economic, social, and policy dimensions for the deployment of hybrid PV–wind systems, with a focus on rural and frontier areas.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Facilitates the targeted and effective scaling of renewable systems aligned with local needs and capacities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>].</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Conclusion</title>
      <p>To consolidate the overarching insights of this systematic review, the following key contributions are formulated to highlight the novel synthesized knowledge generated from the multi-study comparison, the clarification of contradictory findings, and the strategic recommendations for Indonesia’s policymakers and research community:</p><p>1. Synthesis of new, cross-cutting knowledge:</p><p>This review provides the first integrated mapping of technical, economic, environmental, and policy dimensions governing hybrid PV–wind systems for EV charging in Indonesia, demonstrating that system viability is shaped by multi-factor interactions—including climatic complementarity, storage integration levels, cost assumptions, and policy stability—that individual case studies rarely capture. Through the synthesis of 50 studies, a more nuanced understanding emerges, revealing region-specific feasibility thresholds, realistic cost-performance expectations, and overlooked lifecycle considerations that significantly influence long-term sustainability outcomes.</p><p>2. Resolution of conflicting evidence across studies:</p><p>By comparing diverse methodologies and assumptions, this review clarifies inconsistencies in reported LCOE values, payback periods, and environmental benefits, showing that disparities often stem from differences in resource profiles, financial parameters, and modeling constraints rather than fundamental disagreements about hybrid system performance. The analysis reconciles conflicting conclusions by demonstrating that hybrid PV–wind systems are most advantageous in regions with favorable irradiation and wind regimes. In contrast, lower-performing regions require complementary policy incentives, storage enhancements, or alternative renewable configurations to achieve similar outcomes.</p><p>3. Prioritized recommendations for policymakers and researchers:</p><p>The findings highlight the need for Indonesia to adopt regionally adaptive renewable-energy planning, strengthen grid-support frameworks, and enhance local manufacturing capacity to reduce cost volatility and technology dependency. For researchers, the review emphasizes the importance of expanding empirical field validation, incorporating lifecycle environmental assessments, and integrating socio-institutional dimensions—such as user behavior, regulatory readiness, and community acceptance—into future modeling frameworks. Collectively, these recommendations provide a strategic roadmap for accelerating Indonesia’s renewable energy and e-mobility transition through more evidence-based, resilient, and context-sensitive decision-making.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        <p>Table A1. Descriptive summary of studies on hybrid PV–wind systems, sustainability assessments, innovations, techno-economic feasibility, and policy implications in Indonesia and beyond</p><table><tbody><tr><th  ><p>Study</p></th><th  ><p>Modeling Accuracy and Optimization</p></th><th  ><p>Environmental Impact Metrics</p></th><th  ><p>Innovation Adoption Rate</p></th><th  ><p>Techno-Economic Feasibility</p></th><th  ><p>Policy and Regulatory Effectiveness</p></th></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>HOMER-based optimization for hybrid PV-wind in urban government buildings</p></td><td  ><p>CO$_{2}$ reduction and energy surplus in Denpasar</p></td><td  ><p>Limited focus on materials, emphasis on system design</p></td><td  ><p>NPC and COE favorable; 8.2 years payback</p></td><td  ><p>Highlights policy implications for renewable integration</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Multi-regional techno-economic and health co-benefit modeling</p></td><td  ><p>Quantified GHG, PM2.5, DALYs, health savings</p></td><td  ><p>Not explicitly addressed</p></td><td  ><p>Payback period improved; NPV increased by 14.6%</p></td><td  ><p>Supports policy via cost-benefit analysis of renewables</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>HOMER Pro simulation for rural hybrid system configurations</p></td><td  ><p>Emission reduction targets aligned with Net Zero goals</p></td><td  ><p>Not detailed</p></td><td  ><p>Techno-economic analysis for rural electrification</p></td><td  ><p>Policy alignment with emission reduction targets</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>HOMER with MCDM for component selection in East Java</p></td><td  ><p>Emission and pollutant reduction via component optimization</p></td><td  ><p>Component-level innovation assessment</p></td><td  ><p>COE as low as \$0.24/kWh; sensitivity analysis performed</p></td><td  ><p>Policy impact is implicit through economic-environmental tradeoffs</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Review of inverter-based integration for EV motor drives</p></td><td  ><p>Focus on efficiency gains, less on emissions</p></td><td  ><p>High innovation in inverter and motor control</p></td><td  ><p>Charging efficiency improved to 97%</p></td><td  ><p>Discusses technology adoption, but has a limited policy focus</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>HOMER optimization integrating productive activities in rural Indonesia</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits linked to productive use</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in system integration with productive loads</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility is dependent on grants and tariffs</p></td><td  ><p>Policy implications for incentives and rural development</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>HOMER simulation for grid-connected EV charging station sizing</p></td><td  ><p>COE of \$0.114/kWh; renewable fraction 75\%</p></td><td  ><p>Not emphasized</p></td><td  ><p>NPC \$2.15 million; cost-effective hybrid system</p></td><td  ><p>Supports green transportation policies</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Techno-economic evaluation of PV-based microgrid for urban EV charging</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits linked to solar irradiation levels</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in microgrid design</p></td><td  ><p>Payback period 11.2 years; IRR 13.64%</p></td><td  ><p>Policy relevance in urban infrastructure planning</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>LCA of hybrid EV charging station operation in Indonesia</p></td><td  ><p>Detailed environmental impact across multiple factors</p></td><td  ><p>Limited innovation focus</p></td><td  ><p>Not the primary focus</p></td><td  ><p>Highlights the need for a policy to reduce environmental impacts</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>PLEXOS modeling of EV and renewable integration in the grid</p></td><td  ><p>Emissions reduction up to 23.7\% with V2G</p></td><td  ><p>Not focused on materials</p></td><td  ><p>System cost reduced by 9%; battery storage optimized</p></td><td  ><p>Strong policy insights on charging strategies and V2G</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility model for public EV charging infrastructure</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental impact secondary to economic feasibility</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in cost modeling</p></td><td  ><p>NPV, IRR, and PBP are used for investment decisions</p></td><td  ><p>Policy analysis on investment incentives and market barriers</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Literature review and prediction of EV charging infrastructure needs</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental impact implicit in infrastructure expansion</p></td><td  ><p>Not addressed</p></td><td  ><p>Infrastructure scale and investment needs forecasted</p></td><td  ><p>Policy recommendations for infrastructure expansion</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Survey on barriers to EV adoption in Indonesia</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental concerns among adoption factors</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation adoption is linked to consumer awareness</p></td><td  ><p>Economic and operational cost barriers identified</p></td><td  ><p>Calls for improved policies and incentives</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>System dynamics modeling of EV adoption impacts</p></td><td  ><p>Emission reduction scenarios modeled</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in policy scenario modeling</p></td><td  ><p>Economic and environmental trade-offs analyzed</p></td><td  ><p>Emphasizes long-term policy support and technology development</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Hybrid decision-making model for electric motorcycle charging</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits through infrastructure evaluation</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in decision-making frameworks</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility of infrastructure alternatives</p></td><td  ><p>Policy support for motorcycle charging infrastructure</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Simulation of EV growth and grid balance in Jawa-Madura-Bali</p></td><td  ><p>Emission and cost impacts of EV growth scenarios</p></td><td  ><p>Not focused on materials or manufacturing</p></td><td  ><p>Economic analysis of subsidies and grid management</p></td><td  ><p>Policy insights on subsidies and regulatory adjustments</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Review of renewable energy transition progress in Indonesia</p></td><td  ><p>Emission reduction targets and challenges</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in policy and infrastructure</p></td><td  ><p>Economic challenges discussed</p></td><td  ><p>Policy framework assessment for energy transition</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Political economy analysis of renewable energy in Indonesia</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits linked to policy effectiveness</p></td><td  ><p>Regulatory barriers hinder innovation adoption</p></td><td  ><p>Economic dependencies on fossil fuels are analyzed</p></td><td  ><p>Calls for cohesive policy and economic incentives</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Review of renewable energy integration in transportation</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits and challenges are outlined</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in smart grids and AI applications</p></td><td  ><p>Economic and regulatory barriers discussed</p></td><td  ><p>Policy frameworks for renewable transport integration</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Design of renewable energy-based EV charging system (SmartLink)</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits through renewable integration</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in hardware and system design</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility projected through phased implementation</p></td><td  ><p>Policy support for renewable EV infrastructure</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Review of RE integration with EV charging systems</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits linked to grid integration</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in smart charging and storage</p></td><td  ><p>Economic challenges and opportunities analyzed</p></td><td  ><p>Policy and standardization challenges highlighted</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Sustainable EV charging using solar and wind energy</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits from renewable-powered charging</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in hybrid renewable charging infrastructure</p></td><td  ><p>Economic benefits from reduced fossil fuel reliance</p></td><td  ><p>Policy implications for sustainable transport infrastructure</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Review of solar-powered EV charging stations</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits and challenges of solar PV</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in energy storage and AI management</p></td><td  ><p>Economic barriers and incentives discussed</p></td><td  ><p>Policy role in standardization and promotion</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Review of PV-powered EV charging stations</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits and economic payback periods</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in system design and simulation</p></td><td  ><p>Payback periods 1–15 years; cost-effective solutions</p></td><td  ><p>Policy guidance for EV infrastructure expansion</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Grid-linked solar PV EV charging station design</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits via carbon emission reduction</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in grid integration and innovative technologies</p></td><td  ><p>Competitive pricing and economic viability</p></td><td  ><p>Policy relevance for renewable energy adoption</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Hybrid renewable energy EV charging station design</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits through the use of a hybrid system use</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in control algorithms and smart grid tech</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility demonstrated via simulations</p></td><td  ><p>Policy support implied for sustainable EV infrastructure</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Renewable sources for EV charging with hybrid storage</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits from reduced grid dependence</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in storage devices and MPPT control</p></td><td  ><p>Economic benefits from grid load reduction</p></td><td  ><p>Policy implications for renewable energy adoption</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Review of RES and EV integration in power systems</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits and emissions reduction</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in algorithms and optimization methods</p></td><td  ><p>Economic impacts and cost optimization discussed</p></td><td  ><p>Policy and regulatory challenges identified</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Sector coupling of electricity, transport, and cooling</p></td><td  ><p>Emission reductions via integrated renewables and EVs</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in sector coupling and demand management</p></td><td  ><p>Economic benefits from reduced fossil fuel costs</p></td><td  ><p>Policy support for sector integration and electrification</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Grid-connected renewable system for EV loads in Saudi Arabia</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits through renewable integration</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in optimization algorithms</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility via sensitivity analysis</p></td><td  ><p>Policy relevance for urban renewable energy systems</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Grid-independent hybrid system for EV charging in Malaysia</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits via hybrid renewable systems</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in hybrid system arrangements</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility with social and ecological indices</p></td><td  ><p>Policy implications for grid-independent EV charging</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Simulation of hybrid renewable EV charging in tourism districts</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental emission reductions quantified</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in integrated system design</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility is sensitive to charging prices</p></td><td  ><p>Policy relevance for sustainable tourism infrastructure</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Systematic review of hybrid renewable systems for power interruptions</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits in rural and remote areas</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in hybrid system configurations</p></td><td  ><p>Economic advantages over single-resource systems</p></td><td  ><p>Policy insights for rural electrification strategies</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Grid-integrated hybrid system for residential and EV loads</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental emission reductions with grid scheduling</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in grid integration and net metering</p></td><td  ><p>COE as low as 0.0714/kWh; NPC0.0714/kWh; NPC1.82 million</p></td><td  ><p>Policy implications for grid management and tariffs</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Interactive model for climate co-benefits of hybrid renewables</p></td><td  ><p>Quantified GHG, PM2.5, DALYs, and health savings</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation is not the primary focus</p></td><td  ><p>Payback period and NPV improvements</p></td><td  ><p>Policy support through cost-benefit analysis</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Economic viability of the PV-wind microgrid in Papua</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits via a renewable microgrid</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in microgrid design</p></td><td  ><p>NPC and COE optimized for off-grid electrification</p></td><td  ><p>Policy relevance for off-grid renewable solutions</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">44</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Evaluation of EV charging infrastructure and air quality</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental impact assessed via Air Quality Index</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation not emphasized</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility is not the primary focus</p></td><td  ><p>Policy recommendation for infrastructure planning</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Renewable energy integrated EV charging on cold roads</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits via energy harvesting technologies</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in smart roads and energy management</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility via energy production and storage</p></td><td  ><p>Policy implications for infrastructure in cold regions</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Sustainable electric shuttle services on the Bandung-Jakarta route</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits from emission reductions</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in route optimization and smart grids</p></td><td  ><p>Economic challenges due to high capital costs</p></td><td  ><p>Policy recommendations for collaboration and innovation</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">47</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Impact of green economy regulations on energy efficiency</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits via regulatory and tech adoption</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in technology adoption supported by policy</p></td><td  ><p>Economic efficiency improvements demonstrated</p></td><td  ><p>Policy effectiveness in energy efficiency promotion</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">48</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Life cycle costing of hybrid EV charging stations</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits via renewable energy use</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in hybrid charging station design</p></td><td  ><p>Economic competitiveness via life cycle costing</p></td><td  ><p>Policy relevance for sustainable charging infrastructure</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Integration of renewable energy with wireless EV charging</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits via renewable-powered wireless charging</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in wireless charging technology</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility via high system efficiency</p></td><td  ><p>Policy challenges for technology adoption</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Stakeholder perceptions in Indonesian automotive EV transition</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits linked to EV adoption</p></td><td  ><p>Industry perceptions influence innovation adoption</p></td><td  ><p>Economic and investment challenges identified</p></td><td  ><p>Policy recommendations for gradual transition support</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Renewable energy use for charging in the new capital, Nusantara</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits from solar energy predominance</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in system design for the new capital city</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility via simulation results</p></td><td  ><p>Policy alignment with decarbonization goals</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Integration of renewables, microgrids, and EV charging</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits via energy management and storage</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in smart grid and V2G technologies</p></td><td  ><p>Economic benefits from peak load reduction</p></td><td  ><p>Policy frameworks for scalable EV infrastructure</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Sustainable renewable integration for EV charging</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits via clean energy production</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in energy storage and smart charging</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility via optimization strategies</p></td><td  ><p>Policy role in promoting renewable EV charging</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Solar/wind hybrid system design for EV charging</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits from hybrid renewable sources</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in the hybrid system and grid connection</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility demonstrated by simulations</p></td><td  ><p>Policy support for renewable EV charging systems</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">50</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Renewable energy mixes for domestic electricity in Java-Bali</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits via CO$_{2}$ emission reduction</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation in energy mix optimization</p></td><td  ><p>Economic feasibility via ROI and cost analysis</p></td><td  ><p>Policy implications for renewable energy planning</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]</p></td><td  ><p>Review of EV infrastructure, policy, and economic growth</p></td><td  ><p>Environmental benefits linked to EV adoption</p></td><td  ><p>Innovation adoption is influenced by policy and market</p></td><td  ><p>Economic impacts on jobs and GDP are highlighted</p></td><td  ><p>Policy effectiveness and future roadmap emphasized</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This paper is the result of research entitled “Pengembangan Pembangkit Listrik Tenaga Surya Sebagai Sumber Energi Bersih Stasiun Pengisian Kendaraan Listrik Umum (SPKLU)” funded by Sebelas Maret University through the Mandatory Riset (mr-uns) scheme with contract number 369/UN27.22/PT.01.03/2025.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>139-143</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Himabindu</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hampannavar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deepa</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Longe</surname>
              <given-names>O. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mansani</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Komanapalli</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.egyr.2023.09.098</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessment of microgrid integrated biogas-photovoltaic powered Electric Vehicle Charging Station (EVCS) for sustainable future</article-title>
          <source>Energy Rep.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>76-82</page-range>
          <issue>02</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Syabriyana</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55377/jurutera.v11i02.10810</pub-id>
          <article-title>Progress and challenges of renewable energy transition in Indonesia’s energy mix towards net zero emissions</article-title>
          <source>JURUTERA - J. Umum Tek. Ter.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>66250-66275</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bawan</surname>
              <given-names>E. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wijaya</surname>
              <given-names>F. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>H. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasquez</surname>
              <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/access.2025.3556020</pub-id>
          <article-title>Comprehensive analysis and optimal design of hybrid renewable energy system for rural electrification in West Papua, Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Access</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>23</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suliman</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farzaneh</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zusman</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mulumba</surname>
              <given-names>A. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lestari</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Permadi</surname>
              <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Janardhanan</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cli12020023</pub-id>
          <article-title>Quantifying the climate co-benefits of hybrid renewable power generation in Indonesia: A multi-regional and technological assessment</article-title>
          <source>Climate</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>6408</page-range>
          <issue>24</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Damanik</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Octavia</surname>
              <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hakam</surname>
              <given-names>D. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en17246408</pub-id>
          <article-title>Powering Indonesia’s future: Reviewing the road to electric vehicles through infrastructure, policy, and economic growth</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>1-5</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <publisher-name>Bandung, Indonesia</publisher-name>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mangkung</surname>
              <given-names>B.G.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamdani</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>andRachmilda</surname>
              <given-names>T.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icpere63447.2024.10845728</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economicanalysisofhybridrenewableenergy system for rural area: Study case Lembor Selatan district</article-title>
          <source>, </source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>1802</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Awalin</surname>
              <given-names>L. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Khaykan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fard</surname>
              <given-names>H. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alhamrouni</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salem</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su15031802</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic and environmental study of optimum hybrid renewable systems, including PV/wind/gen/battery, with various components to find the best renewable combination for Ponorogo Regency, East Java, Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>47-52</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mudhoffar</surname>
              <given-names>Khosyi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magriasti</surname>
              <given-names>Lince</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.57251/multiverse.v3i1.1382</pub-id>
          <article-title>Ekonomi Politik Energi Terbarukan: Peluang dan Tantangan di Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Multiverse: Open Multidisciplinary Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <year>2023</year>
          <publisher-name>Mansoura, Egypt</publisher-name>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mousa</surname>
              <given-names>M.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saleh</surname>
              <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samy</surname>
              <given-names>M.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>andBarakat</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/mepcon58725.2023.10462477</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic analysis and simulation of electric vehicle charging stations based on green energy system</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>678–682</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <publisher-name>Denpasar Bali, Indonesia</publisher-name>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sutardi</surname>
              <given-names>B. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Banjar-Nahor</surname>
              <given-names>K. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hariyanto</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanadya</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Situmeang</surname>
              <given-names>R. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrian</surname>
              <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ichveps58902.2023.10257494</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno economic evaluation of in-city EV charging station empowered by PV-based microgrid in various solar irradiation levels</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>3730-3735</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pandey</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22214/ijraset.2024.61323</pub-id>
          <article-title>A review on the renewable sources based microgrid for electric vehicle charging using various emerging technologies</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Res. Appl. Sci. Eng. Technol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>422</page-range>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lazuardy</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nurcahyo</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kristiningrum</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma'aram</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farizal</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aqmarina</surname>
              <given-names>S. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajabi</surname>
              <given-names>M. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/wevj15090422</pub-id>
          <article-title>Technological, environmental, economic, and regulation barriers to electric vehicle adoption: Evidence from Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>World Electr. Veh. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>19</volume>
          <page-range>35-54</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suryani</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fadlillah</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hendrawan</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mudjahidin</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pramundito</surname>
              <given-names>R. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zahra</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chou</surname>
              <given-names>S. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dewabharata</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rizqi</surname>
              <given-names>Z. U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rahmawati</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15568318.2024.2443825</pub-id>
          <article-title>Dynamic model to assess the impacts of government support for electric vehicles on the economy and environment sectors in Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Sustain. Transp.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>1247-1267</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shafira</surname>
              <given-names>A. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrana</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muthia</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Purwanto</surname>
              <given-names>W. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ce/zkad068</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic analysis of a hybrid renewable energy system integrated with productive activities in an underdeveloped rural region of eastern Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Clean Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>295</volume>
          <page-range>114019</page-range>
          <year>2026</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trisnoaji</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arifin</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prabowo</surname>
              <given-names>A. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.solmat.2025.114019</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessment of the performance differences in PV–PCM systems with numerical analysis of different phase change materials and structural designs</article-title>
          <source>Sol. Energy Mater. Sol. Cells</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>80</volume>
          <page-range>241-258</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Das</surname>
              <given-names>B. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tushar</surname>
              <given-names>M. S. H. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aej.2023.08.057</pub-id>
          <article-title>Investigation of a grid-integrated hybrid energy system for residential and electric vehicle (3-wheeler) loads under schedule grid outage</article-title>
          <source>Alex. Eng. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>811-818</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tjahjana</surname>
              <given-names>Dominicus Danardono Dwi Prija</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suyitno</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rachmanto</surname>
              <given-names>Rendy Adhi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Juwana</surname>
              <given-names>Wibawa Endra</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasojo</surname>
              <given-names>Yudin Joko</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>Singgih Dwi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arifin</surname>
              <given-names>Zainal</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijdne.180407</pub-id>
          <article-title>Economic Feasibility of a PV-Wind Hybrid Microgrid System for Off-Grid Electrification in Papua, Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Design &amp;amp; Nature and Ecodynamics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>157–186</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ponnambalam</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ilampoornan</surname>
              <given-names>M. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4018/979-8-3693-5797-2.ch006</pub-id>
          <article-title>Integration of renewable energy technologies and hybrid electric vehicle challenges in power systems</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>317-326</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prianka</surname>
              <given-names>Yingking Mitra</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>Anik</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Biswas</surname>
              <given-names>Chanchal</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.59247/csol.v2i3.142</pub-id>
          <article-title>Integration of Renewable Energy, Microgrids, and EV Charging Infrastructure: Challenges and Solutions</article-title>
          <source>Control Systems and Optimization Letters</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>153–170</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ghai</surname>
              <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghai</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>V. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jasola</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Avikal</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cakir</surname>
              <given-names>G. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4018/979-8-3693-6844-2.ch006</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sustainable energy solutions for charging electric vehicles by integrating renewable sources</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>57-68</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lakshmipriya</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ayyappan</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gokul</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4028/p-382wdq</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sustainable charging infrastructure for electric vehicles: Harnessing solar and wind energy</article-title>
          <source>Eng. Headway</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>140527-140555</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shahin</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abdelaziz</surname>
              <given-names>A. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Houari</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nahid-Mobarakeh</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pierfederici</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abulanwar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/access.2024.3466729</pub-id>
          <article-title>A comprehensive analysis: Integrating renewable energy sources with wire/wireless EV charging systems for green mobility</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Access</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>389</volume>
          <page-range>126021</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fathoni</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kesidou</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rifansha</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiftazani</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2025.126021</pub-id>
          <article-title>Drivers and barriers of eco-innovation in electric vehicle diffusion: Evidence from Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>J. Environ. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>1-10</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anshori</surname>
              <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boedoyo</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saputro</surname>
              <given-names>G. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36982/jeg.v9i1.3965</pub-id>
          <article-title>Development of electric vehicle charging infrastructure in Indonesia to achieve the target of nationally determined contribution by 2030</article-title>
          <source>J. Ecoment Glob.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>5855</page-range>
          <issue>14</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Habiburrahman</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nurcahyo</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma'aram</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Natsuda</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su16145855</pub-id>
          <article-title>Driving the transport electrification: Exploring stakeholders’ perceptions and actions in the Indonesian automotive industry transition to electric mobility</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>6495</page-range>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>S.-W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liao</surname>
              <given-names>Y.-H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liao</surname>
              <given-names>J.-M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liou</surname>
              <given-names>J. J. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24294/jipd.v8i9.6495</pub-id>
          <article-title>Exploring public charging infrastructure development strategies with BBWM-mV integrated multi-viewpoint perspective</article-title>
          <source>J. Infrastruct. Policy Dev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>46</volume>
          <page-range>3499-3521</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Padmanabhan</surname>
              <given-names>J. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anbazhagan</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15567036.2024.2319347</pub-id>
          <article-title>A comprehensive review of hybrid renewable energy charging system to optimally drive permanent magnet synchronous motors in electric vehicle</article-title>
          <source>Energy Sources Part A</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>2037</page-range>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Amiruddin</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dargaville</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liebman</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gawler</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en17092037</pub-id>
          <article-title>Integration of electric vehicles and renewable energy in Indonesia’s electrical grid</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>25</volume>
          <page-range>141-152</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hanun</surname>
              <given-names>I. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sutopo</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rochani</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9744/jti.25.2.141-152</pub-id>
          <article-title>Feasibility study of charging infrastructure to increase vehicle electrification in Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>J. Tek. Ind.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>341</page-range>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tampubolon</surname>
              <given-names>J. V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalimi</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/wevj15080341</pub-id>
          <article-title>Simulating EV growth scenarios in Jawa-Madura-Bali from 2024 to 2029: Balancing the power grid’s supply and demand</article-title>
          <source>World Electr. Veh. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sayeed</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manikandan</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.54966/jreen.v27i2.1300</pub-id>
          <article-title>Smart integration of renewable energy into transportation: Challenges, innovations, and future research directions</article-title>
          <source>J. Renew. Energ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Trisuwito</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menalang</surname>
              <given-names>D. F. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almunir</surname>
              <given-names>M. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.70310/ccbh3n62</pub-id>
          <article-title>Renewrev: Stasiun pengisian daya cerdas untuk transformasi kendaraan listrik dengan energi terbarukan</article-title>
          <source>J. Tek. Cerdas</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhargava</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24113/ijoscience.v10i10.501</pub-id>
          <article-title>Green energy solutions for EV charging: A comprehensive review of solar-powered stations</article-title>
          <source>Smart Moves J. IJOSci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>215</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Almasri</surname>
              <given-names>Radwan A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alharbi</surname>
              <given-names>Talal</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alshitawi</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alrumayh</surname>
              <given-names>Omar</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ajib</surname>
              <given-names>Salman</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/wevj15050215</pub-id>
          <article-title>Related Work and Motivation for Electric Vehicle Solar/Wind Charging Stations: A Review</article-title>
          <source>World Electric Vehicle Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>280–285</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <publisher-name>Delhi, India</publisher-name>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pandey</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yadav</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maitra</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pachauri</surname>
              <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icpeices62430.2024.10719359</pub-id>
          <article-title>Eco-friendly ev charging: Utilizing grid-linked solar photovoltaic systems</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>859-865</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahadik</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guchhait</surname>
              <given-names>P. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32628/ijsrst523103151</pub-id>
          <article-title>Efficient integration of renewable energy for electric vehicle charging: A hybrid system approach</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>315–328</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eswar</surname>
              <given-names>K. N. D. V. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doss</surname>
              <given-names>M. A. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-99-4795-9_30</pub-id>
          <article-title>Implementation of renewable sources for designing EV charging station with hybrid storage device as reserve source</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>1544</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manousakis</surname>
              <given-names>N. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karagiannopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>P. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsekouras</surname>
              <given-names>G. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kanellos</surname>
              <given-names>F. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pr11051544</pub-id>
          <article-title>Integration of renewable energy and electric vehicles in power systems: A review</article-title>
          <source>Processes</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>100102</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Siregar</surname>
              <given-names>Yudha Irmansyah</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Möller</surname>
              <given-names>Bernd</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.segy.2023.100102</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sector coupling of electricity, transport and cooling with high share integration of renewables in Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Smart Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>1–5</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <publisher-name>College Station, TX, USA</publisher-name>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Balal</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnwal</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>andYogi</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/tpec56611.2023.10078494</pub-id>
          <article-title>Designingasolar/wind hybrid power system for charging electric vehicles</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>302</volume>
          <page-range>131686</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>F. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mekhilef</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramachandaramurthy</surname>
              <given-names>V. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ab Aziz</surname>
              <given-names>N. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pal</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yaseen</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yadav</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asim</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alshammari</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.energy.2024.131686</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design and development of grid independent integrated energy system for electric vehicle charging stations at different locations in Malaysia</article-title>
          <source>Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>4525</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abdelhady</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shaban</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app14114525</pub-id>
          <article-title>A simulation modeling approach for the techno-economic analysis of the integration of electric vehicle charging stations and hybrid renewable energy systems in tourism districts</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>2108-2156</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thango</surname>
              <given-names>B. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Obokoh</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/eng5030112</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic analysis of hybrid renewable energy systems for power interruptions: A systematic review</article-title>
          <source>Eng</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>27793-27805</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karmaker</surname>
              <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hossain</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pota</surname>
              <given-names>H. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Onen</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jung</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/access.2023.3259232</pub-id>
          <article-title>Energy management system for hybrid renewable energy-based electric vehicle charging station</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Access</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>42–75</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prasad</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>R. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwary</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>M. I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4018/978-1-6684-9214-7.ch002</pub-id>
          <article-title>Renewable energy-integrated electric vehicle charging infrastructure across cold region roads</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>611</volume>
          <page-range>03006</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pamungkas</surname>
              <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maulina</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arifianti</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muftiadi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/e3sconf/202561103006</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sustainable transportation in Indonesia: Opportunities for environmentally friendly shuttle services on the Bandung-Jakarta route</article-title>
          <source>E3S Web Conf.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>5145-5154</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bukhari</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aboulola</surname>
              <given-names>O. I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rehman</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alharbi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alosaimi</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daud</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.egyr.2024.11.019</pub-id>
          <article-title>Renewable energy driven on-road wireless charging infrastructure for electric vehicles in smart cities: A prototype design and analysis</article-title>
          <source>Energy Rep.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>225-239</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aripriharta</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adiguna</surname>
              <given-names>Satria</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Afandi</surname>
              <given-names>Arif N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bagaskoro</surname>
              <given-names>Muhammad Cahyo</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gloei.2025.01.003</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic modeling and analysis of a PV EV charged with battery energy storage system (BESS) on Kalimantan Island</article-title>
          <source>Global Energy Interconnection</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>460–465</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <publisher-name>Denpasar Bali, Indonesia</publisher-name>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heryana</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iskandar</surname>
              <given-names>H. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Furqani</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ichveps58902.2023.10257531</pub-id>
          <article-title>Utilization of renewable energy for charging station in Indonesia newappointed capital city, Nusantara</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>7461</page-range>
          <issue>22</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Diyono</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cappon</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kujawa-Roeleveld</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keesman</surname>
              <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en16227461</pub-id>
          <article-title>Designing sustainable domestic electricity supply from renewable energy mixes: Application to Java and Bali, Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>132-144</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Regannanta</surname>
              <given-names>F. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Birawa</surname>
              <given-names>A. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alfaridzi</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jse020303</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic evaluation of hybrid photovoltaic-wind energy systems for Indonesian government buildings</article-title>
          <source>J. Sustain. Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>1740-1749</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Judijanto</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mayasari</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sitompul</surname>
              <given-names>G. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.58812/jmws.v3i10.1673</pub-id>
          <article-title>Dampak regulasi ekonomi hijau dan penggunaan teknologi energi terbarukan terhadap efisiensi energi listrik di Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>J. Multidisip. West Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>20</volume>
          <page-range>291-304</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mauludin</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khairudin</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asnawi</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trisnoaji</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azizah</surname>
              <given-names>S. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiraguna</surname>
              <given-names>R. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijsdp.200127</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessing the technological and financial feasibility of PV-wind hybrid systems for EV charging stations on Indonesian toll roads</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Sustain. Dev. Plan.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>24</volume>
          <page-range>100737</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Redwan</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nadia</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chowdhury</surname>
              <given-names>N. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chowdhury</surname>
              <given-names>N.-U.-R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecmx.2024.100737</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design analysis and techno-economic assessment of a photovoltaic-fed electric vehicle charging station at Dhaka-Mawa expressway in Bangladesh</article-title>
          <source>Energy Convers. Manag. X</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>403-411</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rachmanto</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alfaiz</surname>
              <given-names>N. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bangun</surname>
              <given-names>W. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Juwana</surname>
              <given-names>W. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arifin</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijtdi.080304</pub-id>
          <article-title>Modeling future solar and wind energy source applications for power generation at public electric vehicle charging stations in airport parking areas using HOMER-Grid</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Transp. Dev. Integr.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_56">
        <label>56.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <page-range>100174</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trisnoaji</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arifin</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahadi</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.uncres.2025.100174</pub-id>
          <article-title>Harnessing unconventional resources for large-scale green hydrogen production: An economic and technological analysis in Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Unconv. Resour.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>