<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CCDJ</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.32479</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Central Community Development Journal</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Cent. Community Dev. J.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">CCDJ</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">3024-8302</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">3025-1826</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-AUzBubMgpDFb3MKPXqzLoCprbQH4-_Eb</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32479/CCDJ.11345</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Development of Agricultural Tourism Destinations as a Community Creative Economy in the Bekasi Regency Area</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <name>
            <surname>Syahwildan</surname>
            <given-names>Muhamad</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>muhamad.syahwildan@pelitabangsa.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6723-2266</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ekhsan</surname>
            <given-names>Muhamad</given-names>
          </name>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Universitas Pelita Bangsa</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>4</lpage>
      <page-range>1-4</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>09</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2021 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>This journal describes the results of community service activities in the form of a national online seminar on village tourism as the community's creative economy. This activity is motivated by the people's unconsciousness of the potential of their village. The purpose of this activity is to open the mindset of the local community that Karangmukti Village has an agricultural tourism object that has a great opportunity if it is developed seriously. Therefore, we organize online seminars related to village tourism as a community creative economy. By organizing these online seminars, it is hoped that the community will pay more attention to the opportunities that exist in Karangmukti village and can be moved to develop village tourism as one of the objects that can help improve the community's economy. The results obtained from these activities are that communication has been established between related stakeholders. For the next stage, the village government and the community are expected to follow up on existing communications to be able to develop agricultural tourism in the area.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Creative economy</kwd>
        <kwd>Tourist village</kwd>
        <kwd>Agriculture</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="2"/>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <ref-count count="16"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>In Indonesia, the implementation of regional autonomy has started in 1999. This is regulated in Law No. 22 of 1999 which is currently undergoing changes and has legal force based on Law No. 32 of 2004 concerning regional government. Currently, the regulation has gone through several phases, this can be seen with the issuance of law number 6 of 2014 concerning village government (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Ridwan &amp;amp; Surya, 2018</xref>). One of the goals of regional autonomy is to regulate oneself properly. In addition, regional autonomy is also expected to be able to encourage socio-economic equality of the community between one region and another (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Muin, 2014</xref>).</p>
      <p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Aida et al. (2017)</xref> regional economic development will run very well if the area has a sustainable principle. Creating effective collaboration and being able to utilize existing resources also helps to establish effective regional economic development. Therefore, the strategic role of the government is needed in providing opportunities for local communities to be able to participate in economic development.</p>
      <p>In the service sector, the creative industry, especially the tourism sector, has developed quite rapidly. That way the creative economy can generate income from intellectual property and play a role in creating sustainable economic value because existing resources will be renewable and will not run out or decrease.</p>
      <p>Agriculture is an attraction that is quite attractive to the tourism industry at this time. This is because tourism interest in Indonesia has experienced a shift towards agricultural tourism villages or better known as agrotourism. According to Zoto et al. (2013) in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Swastika et al. (2017)</xref> agrotourism has been developed since the 20th century where tourism is associated with the production environment of the agricultural sector. Agrotourism is defined as all activities related to tourism activities as well as being a lesson for tourists to get to know more about the production process in the agricultural sector and make the agricultural area a place to enjoy agricultural products directly. Tourism village is one of the empowerment programs that has the potential to be developed. The development of a tourist village is said to be a difference from its original form and is expected to be able to provide benefits by creating new jobs to improve the welfare of the local community.</p><p>It should also be noted that in the development of tourist villages, the community must be supported and encouraged to be able to be sustainable, so that the potential of the village and community can be developed optimally. In an effort to achieve this, synergistic guidance is needed between agricultural, tourism, and related government business actors. This will enable agricultural and tourism business actors to plan, compile, and create tourism village programs based on community capabilities and village potential. To realize this, good coordination is needed between interested parties so that with the establishment of coordination between parties, the goal of developing an agro tourism village will be achieved.</p><p>Karangmukti Village is a village that has agricultural tourism potential. This potential can be seen from the potential of its natural resources. Karangmukti Village has an area of 568.68 Ha, where most of the land is agricultural land. Currently Karangmukti Village has been used as an agricultural tourism village which is unique in terms of history. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Purwaningsih (2020)</xref>, the creative industry is an inseparable part of the creative economy. The creative economy has great potential to become one of the drivers in realizing an Indonesia that is independent, advanced, just and prosperous. This is based on 3 main pillars, namely natural resources, cultural heritage sources, and human resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Hanida et al., 2018</xref>). The Indonesian government has realized that expertise, talent, and creativity are intellectual property that is the hope for the Indonesian economy to be able to compete and become a leading country in the global economy. John Howkins said that the creative economy is all economic activities that make creativity, culture, and cultural heritage and the environment the foundation of the future.</p><p>The creative economy is linked to ideas and money. In this activity the creativity and imagination of the community will determine what they will produce. The creative economy also does not only focus on creating added value economically, but there is also the creation of social and cultural values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Pradana, 2018</xref>). The economy is a factor that can affect the welfare and life of the community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Badrianto &amp;amp; Ekhsan, 2020</xref>). Indonesia has the potential to support the development of agro-tourism, this is because Indonesia is located in a tropical climate area and has fertile soil so that it strongly supports horticultural commodity cultivation activities. Indonesia also has natural resources that support it, therefore agro-tourism is one of the important sectors in supporting the economy of farming communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Pratiwi et al., 2020</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Budiarti et al. (2013)</xref> agricultural tourism village (agrotourism) is a travel activity utilizing the location or agricultural sector. This starts from the beginning of production until agricultural products are obtained in the form of various systems and scales aimed at expanding the economy, knowledge, understanding, experience, and recreation in the agricultural sector.</p><p>The development of agricultural areas into agro-tourism areas will increase the opportunities for tourist visits, this will contribute such as increasing community income through tourism services, as happened in Ketep and Banyuroto villages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Budiarti et al., 2013</xref>). ). According to Muzha et al in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Budiarti et al. (2013)</xref> The development of agricultural tourism villages will also have a positive impact on the community.</p><p>In line with this, an increase in human resources is needed so that community participation is greater in management. Management of tourist villages can increase community capacity in organizing communities that play a role in agro-tourism activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Andini, 2013</xref>).</p><p>Damanik (2013) said that the development of rural tourism was driven by three factors. The first factor is that rural areas have natural and cultural potential that are relatively more authentic than urban areas, rural communities still carry out traditions or cultural rituals and topography that is quite harmonious. Second, rural areas have a relatively pristine physical environment or have not been heavily polluted by various types of pollution compared to urban areas. Third, to a certain extent rural areas face relatively slow economic development, so that the optimal utilization of the economic, social and cultural potential of the local community is a rational reason for the development of rural tourism.</p><p>The goal of tourism development through community empowerment can be realized if the development is not only social and cultural development. It is hoped that tourism that develops through tourist villages will not only strengthen the socio-cultural resilience of the nation and state.</p>
      <p>The data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>, obtained from the official website of the West Java tourism office. Judging from the data above, most of the tourist villages are in the Bogor and Bandung areas. Therefore, the development of tourist villages in the Bekasi Regency area has great opportunities. Bekasi Regency will not only be recognized as an industrial area, but also as an area that has agricultural land in it.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Data for tourist villages in West Java</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>No</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="609"><p>Nama Desa</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lokasi (Kabupaten)</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="609"><p>Desa Wisata Cibuntu</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kuningan</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="609"><p>Desa Wisata Mekarsari</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bogor</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="609"><p>Desa Alamendah</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bandung</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="609"><p>Desa Wisata Sakerta Timur</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kuningan</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="609"><p>Desa Wisata Pasir Eurih</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bogor</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="609"><p>Desa Lamajang</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bandung</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="609"><p>Desa Wisata Rawabogo</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bandung</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="609"><p>Desa Wisata Patengan</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bandung</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="609"><p>Desa Wisata Cibodas</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bogor</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Implementation method</title>
      <p>Karangmukti Village has a tourist attraction Batu Beureum Water Reservoir. The water reservoir was built with the aim of irrigating the surrounding rice fields. Karangmukti Village is a village that still maintains its agricultural nature. Most of the village area is agricultural land. These destinations have good potential if developed. It is unfortunate that the community does not explore the needs of the tourists so that the facilities offered are less attractive to visitors. In this era of digital technology, naturally, farmers should get interest and attention to utilize technology in agriculture. This is due to the fact that technology has been used in various places. But unfortunately, not much information is obtained by farmers due to their lack of knowledge about technological developments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Ali et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>The community does not support the development of the Batu Beureum Embung Air tourist destination as a source of income for the local community. The lack of activities to promote tourist destinations is also a factor why not many people know about the existence of tourist destinations in Karangmukti village. Access to the location of the Batu Beureum water reservoir tourist destination is also not adequate. It is necessary to repair road access and place some directions to the Batu Beureum Embung Air tourist location.</p><p>Access to the location of the Batu Beureum water reservoir tourist destination is also not adequate. It is necessary to repair road access and place some directions to the Batu Beureum Embung Air tourist location.</p><p>Based on the targets that have been set, this community service activity team determines the approach method as follows:</p><p>1. Observation Method, This approach method is carried out by conducting systematic observations and recordings of the phenomena being investigated. With this method, it is known what factors hinder the development of tourist villages in the Bekasi Regency area.</p><p>2. Methods of Technical Guidance and Mentoring, This method is intended so that community knowledge in tourism village development efforts can be practiced properly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Syahwildan, 2020</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Results and discussion</title>
      <p>By holding an online seminar entitled Development of Agricultural Tourism Destinations as a Community Creative Economy in Bekasi Regency, it is hoped that it can increase public awareness of entrepreneurship and contribute to the development of rural tourism destinations in Karangmukti village.</p><p>In addition, it is hoped that all parties who have interests starting from residents and the community; the village government to the central government and other supporters can prioritize all forms of efforts that are presented to grow the creative economy for the community, especially agricultural tourism in the Bekasi Regency environment.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>National online webinars</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/2/img_WonziD28wtB5Y_bL.jpeg"/>
        </fig>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Conclusion</title>
      <p>The service activities that have been carried out by Pelita Bangsa University Karang Mukti have conducted national online seminars with the theme "Development of Agricultural Tourism Destinations as Community Economy in Bekasi Regency" by inviting speakers who are experts in their fields. With the holding of the online seminar, it is hoped that the Bekasi district government can support the development of tourist villages in Karang mukti village and provide motivation and innovation so that the community has the enthusiasm and ability to manage agricultural tourism as a strong impetus to help the economy in Karangmukti village.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>282-296</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aida</surname>
              <given-names>E. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boedirochminarni</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nuraini</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22219/jie.v1i3.6154</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analisis peningkatan ekonomi masyarakat di agrowisata belimbing Karangsari Kota Blitar</article-title>
          <source>J. Ilmu Ekon.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>29-35</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Man</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Latif</surname>
              <given-names>I. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mellisa</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Umar</surname>
              <given-names>S. Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31015/jaefs.18005</pub-id>
          <article-title>The use of information and communication technologies in agricultural risk management by the agricultural extension services in Malaysia</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Agric. Environ. Food Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>24</volume>
          <page-range>173-188</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andini</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pengorganisasian komunitas dalam pengembangan agrowisata di desa wisata studi kasus: desa wisata Kembangarum, Kabupaten Sleman</article-title>
          <source>J. Reg. City Plan.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>168-175</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Badrianto</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ekhsan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Strategi Pengembangan Sumber Daya Manusia Melalui Pemberdayaan Dan Peningkatan Kualitas Lingkungan Desa Cikedokan</article-title>
          <source>KOMMAS: J. Pengabdi. Kpd. Masy.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>200-207</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Budiarti</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suwarto</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muflikhati</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pengembangan agrowisata berbasis masyarakat pada usahatani terpadu guna meningkatkan kesejahteraan petani dan keberlanjutan sistem pertanian</article-title>
          <source>J. Ilmu Pertan. Indones.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>491-496</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hanida</surname>
              <given-names>I. I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mulyono</surname>
              <given-names>A. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moody</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aprilani</surname>
              <given-names>R. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Setiasih</surname>
              <given-names>I. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24198/agricore.v3i2.15480</pub-id>
          <article-title>Pemberdayaan UMKM Berbasis Ekonomi Kreatif DI Pesisir Pantai Cimalaya–Subang Jawa Barat</article-title>
          <source>Agricore: J. Agribus. Sos. Ekon. Pertan. Unpad</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>158-174</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Komariah</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saepudin</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yusup</surname>
              <given-names>P. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26905/jpp.v3i2.2340</pub-id>
          <article-title>Pengembangan desa wisata berbasis kearifan lokal</article-title>
          <source>J. Pariwisata Pesona</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>69-79</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Muin</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Otonomi daerah dalam perspektif pembagian urusan pemerintah-pemerintah daerah dan keuangan daerah</article-title>
          <source>Fiat Justisia</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>267-283</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mustaqim</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pengembangan Ekonomi Kreatif Desa (Studi Atas Pengembangan Ekowisata Cengklik, Blora)</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>9-17</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pradana</surname>
              <given-names>H. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Peranan sektor ekonomi kreatif pada pertumbuhan ekonomi dan ketenagakerjaan di kalimantan selatan</article-title>
          <source>Jurnal Kebijakan Pembangunan</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>554-560</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pratiwi</surname>
              <given-names>R. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gunawan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fangohoi</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21776/ub.jepa.2020.004.03.10</pub-id>
          <article-title>Pengembangan ekonomi kreatif pemuda Karang Taruna berbasis agrowisata di Desa Tawangargo</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>783-792</page-range>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Purwaningsih</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pengembangan ekonomi kreatif desa Wisata Candirejo</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>28-33</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ridwan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surya</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23969/jrak.v10i1.1059</pub-id>
          <article-title>Pemberdayaan masyarakat desa dalam mengembangkan ekonomi kreatif di desa citengah kabupaten sumedang</article-title>
          <source>J. Ris. Akunt. Kontemp.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <page-range>4103-4136</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Swastika</surname>
              <given-names>I. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Budhi</surname>
              <given-names>M. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dewi</surname>
              <given-names>M. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analisis pengembangan agrowisata untuk kesejahteraan masyarakat di Kecamatan Petang, Kabupaten Badung</article-title>
          <source>E-Jurnal Ekonomi dan Bisnis Universitas Udayana</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>46-53</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Syahwildan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26874/jakw.v1i1.12</pub-id>
          <article-title>Pengembangan kualitas manajemen UKM Dodol dalam upaya peningkatan kuliner tradisional khas Kabupaten Bekasi</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wilopo</surname>
              <given-names>K. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hakim</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Strategi pengembangan destinasi pariwisata budaya (Studi kasus pada kawasan Situs Trowulan sebagai Pariwisata Budaya Unggulan di Kabupaten Mojokerto)</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <publisher-name>Brawijaya University</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>