<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="review-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JORIT</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Research, Innovation and Technologies</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Res. Innov. Technol.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JORIT</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2971-8317</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print"/>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-m7u9QKwfk-jeiWInffRsb3h_OXo4BpiE</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jorit040403</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Exploring Adoption Behaviours and Competitive Platforms in OTT Streaming: A Bibliometric and Systematic Literature Review (2010–2024)</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1684-9159</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Chaudhary</surname>
            <given-names>Shivendra Singh</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>shivendra12@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6639-1070</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Panwar</surname>
            <given-names>Diksha</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>dikshapanwar9090@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8614-6718</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Srivastava</surname>
            <given-names>Gautam</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>gautamshrivastav@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Amity University, Greater Noida Campus, 201308 Greater Noida, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">IILM Graduate School of Management, IILM University, 201308 Greater Noida, India</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>345</fpage>
      <lpage>360</lpage>
      <page-range>345-360</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Global research trends on Over-The-Top (OTT) media services were examined through a bibliometric and systematic review of 176 peer-reviewed documents published between 2010 and 2024, sourced from 117 journals and books. The analysis conducted using Bibliometrix, VOSviewer, and the PRISMA methodology identified a compound annual growth rate of approximately 34% in scientific output from 2010 to 2023, indicating rapid expansion in OTT research. The most prolific contributors by publication count are Chakraborty, Soren, and Sridevi. The leading countries in this field are India, South Korea, and the United States. Key research themes include platform dominance, consumer behaviour, and the impact of COVID-19 on OTT adoption, with “OTT” and “Netflix” as dominant topics in scholarly discussions. Although the data were sourced exclusively from Scopus, the findings offer a comprehensive overview of the evolution of themes, principal research networks, and prevailing trends in the OTT research domain.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Consumer behaviour</kwd>
        <kwd>Media industry</kwd>
        <kwd>OTT</kwd>
        <kwd>Platform dominance</kwd>
        <kwd>Streaming services</kwd>
        <kwd>Systematic review</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="3"/>
        <fig-count count="8"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <ref-count count="55"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.1. Over-the-top (ott)</title>
          
          <p>Internet infrastructure and digital technology have fueled the rise of OTT media streaming. Leading OTT platforms depend on the open internet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">KPMG India, 2017</xref>). Viewers have abandoned fixed broadcast schedules in favour of personalised, on-demand content from providers such as Netflix, Disney+, Amazon Prime Video, and Hulu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Green, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Lotz, 2014</xref>). Audiences now access media anywhere, anytime, using powerful devices and faster internet, removing traditional television barriers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Jones, 2009</xref>).</p><p>The COVID-19 pandemic sharply accelerated OTT platform adoption, with noticeable shifts in user behaviour toward multiple streaming services during lockdowns across major global markets, especially in India (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">BCG, 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Deloitte, 2023</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Einav, 2022</xref>). As competition intensifies and the OTT market matures, platforms emphasise advanced recommendation algorithms, user-centric strategies, and content retention through diverse libraries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Lee, 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Mondal &amp;amp; Panda, 2025</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_52">Wayne, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_55">Yoon &amp;amp; Kim, 2024</xref>). For decision-makers and scholars, the rising significance of OTT in India and other markets is clear. According to the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">Mordor Intelligence (2025)</xref>’s report, the OTT market in India is expected to grow at a compound annual growth rate (CAGR) of approximately 18.2% between 2025 and 2030.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.2. Video on demand (vod)</title>
          
          <p>VOD lets users pick from large digital media libraries. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Jain &amp;amp; Madan (2017)</xref> report viewers leaving scheduled TV for more flexible options. OTT services continue to grow as broadband access increases. Studies cite cost, flexibility, and convenience as key reasons for their selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Dwyer et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">Nam et al., 2023</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">Shah &amp;amp; Mehta, 2023</xref>).</p><p>Regional and global OTT providers compete intensely, investing in engagement tools and unique content to attract and keep users (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Deloitte, 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">PwC, 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">PwC, 2021</xref>). However, while OTT adoption grows, studies disagree on whether it is replacing traditional TV. Some evidence shows continued similarities in ease and value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">Udoakpan &amp;amp; Tengeh, 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Bouwman et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Kim &amp;amp; Kim, 2020</xref>).</p><p>For further discussion on the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on OTT adoption, see section 1.1.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Summary of previous literature reviews</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Author and Year</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Title of the Article &amp;amp; Journal</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>ABDC Ranking</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Review Focus Final</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Adoption of SLR (No or Yes)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Interval of Study Final</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Findings</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">Sridevi &amp;amp; Ajith (2024)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Switching channels: investigating the push, pull, and mooring effects of moving from cable TV to OTT services; Journal of Theoretical and Applied Electronic Commerce Research.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>OTT platforms redefine TV, altering leisure and consumer behaviour.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The research period: November to December 2022.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>No common method bias; positive correlations with switching intention, frustration, convenience, trialability, trendiness; cognitive lock-in impedes switching; multigroup analysis reveals age, income disparities; study emphasises digital leisure evolution, TV to OTT shift.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">Shin et al. (2022)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Why am I seeing this? Deconstructing algorithm literacy through the lens of users: Internet Research</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Understanding algorithmic literacy in OTT and AI systems.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study’s data collection-to-analysis interval.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High AL users trust algorithms more due to FATE factors; low AL users prioritise personalisation. The study emphasises AL’s impact on user trust and perceptions, urging tailored algorithm design and user education.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Kwon et al. (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Accurately or accidentally? Recommendation agent and search experience in over-the-top (OTT) services; Internet Research</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The review explores how recommendation agent values affect OTT search and subscription satisfaction.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The data-collection interval is not specified.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Study: OTT search linked to recommendation factors; satisfaction hinges on diagnosticity, serendipity, and impacts subscription intent.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Martínez-Sánchez et al. (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Analysis of the social media strategy of audio-visual OTTs in Spain: The case study of Netflix, HBO and Amazon Prime during the implementation of Disney+; Technological Forecasting and Social Change</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Review analyses OTT impact on Spanish AV consumption and competition among platforms.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study covers the period from March 24 to April 24, 2020.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study finds that Disney+ influenced Facebook and Instagram in Spain during its launch week, highlighting its impact within the timeframe studied.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">Soren &amp;amp; Chakraborty (2024)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Adoption, satisfaction, trust, and commitment of over-the-top platforms: An integrated approach; Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Review analyses factors affecting OTT platform usage and satisfaction, focusing on video content availability.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study covers recent years up to 2023.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study identified predictors of user intention and satisfaction on OTT platforms, suggesting future research directions for service providers.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">Sharma et al. (2023)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Determining the optimal release time of movies: A study of movie and market characteristics, Decision Support Systems</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A*</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The review assesses film release optimisation, considers consumer behaviour and digital impact, and emphasises the use of analytical tools.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Results were compared with movie releases from 2015 to 2022.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study provides valuable insights into managing movie releases on OTT platforms, highlighting the nonlinear relationships among optimal release timing, costs, and consumer preferences.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">Soren &amp;amp; Chakraborty (2023)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The formation of habit and word-of-mouth intention of over-the-top platforms; Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Study examines user habits, WOM, satisfaction in OTT context, blending IDC theory with SDT.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study uses 2022 data for analysis.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study shows how video availability on OTT platforms affects satisfaction, habit, and word-of-mouth intentions — factors critical for user retention and understanding consumer behaviour online.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Agarwal et al. (2023)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Over-the-top (OTT) retailing in the post-pandemic world. Unveiling consumer drivers and barriers using a qualitative study; Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Review explores post-pandemic factors influencing OTT service usage, identifying enablers and barriers.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The report likely includes research from the post-pandemic era.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A qualitative study aligns with UGT 2.0 and IRT, highlighting barriers such as consumption concerns and drivers such as interactivity, aiding OTT platform enhancement.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">Ryu et al. (2023)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>An exploratory study of consumer switching behaviour in platform businesses: A mixed methods approach; Journal of Consumer Behaviour</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study investigates consumer switching across platforms using a mixed-methods approach, combining LDA analysis and interviews to classify factors and bridge quantitative and qualitative research.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The investigation occurs in two stages: LDA topic analysis and customer interviews.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study uses LDA and interviews to analyse platform-switching behaviour, categorise factors, and provide insights for marketers.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Chakraborty et al. (2023)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Watching is valuable: Consumer views—content consumption on OTT platforms. Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Study examines how consumption values affect trust and repurchase intent on OTT platforms, while accounting for TCV and demographic moderators.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The research appears recent, but the time span is unclear.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study links consumption values to trust and repurchase intent on OTT platforms, offering insights for providers and for understanding consumer behaviour.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Governo et al. (2020)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Merging social computing with content: a proposal of a new film platform, Avids; Behaviour and Information Technology</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study assesses the social media features of top OTT streaming services to understand their importance and impact.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>During the unspecified interim period, the study systematically analysed OTT platforms to understand and categorise their social media features.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study emphasises the importance of social features on OTT platforms, highlighting user engagement and the need to adapt to evolving viewer preferences.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Farooq &amp;amp; Raju (2019)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Impact of Over-the-Top (OTT) Services on the Telecom Companies in the Era of Transformative Marketing; Global Journal of Flexible Systems Management</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Research outlines revenue losses in Pakistan’s telecom sector and proposes survival tactics amidst digitalisation.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study covers the mid-1990s to 2017, with a focus on 2008–2017.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study shows telecom income losses from declining traditional services due to messaging apps, urging adaptation to internet-based services for revenue stability and growth.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">Shin et al. (2016)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Strategic management of over-the-top services: Focusing on Korean consumer adoption behaviour; Technological Forecasting and Social Change</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Korean study analyses OTT market dynamics, user preferences, and interactions with traditional broadcasting, offering user-centred solutions.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study reflects recent years without specifying dates.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The study highlights customer preference for real-time broadcasting in OTT and offers insights into pricing adjustments and VOD expansion, which are valuable to scholars and industry practitioners.</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> summarises findings from earlier literature reviews on OTT streaming services, which indicate that cost, flexibility, and convenience are important reasons people choose these platforms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Dwyer et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">Nam et al., 2023</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">Shah &amp;amp; Mehta, 2023</xref>). Both regional and global OTT providers compete by offering engagement tools and exclusive content to attract and retain viewers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Deloitte, 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">PwC, 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">PwC, 2021</xref>). Although OTT services have proliferated, there is still debate over whether they will completely replace traditional TV. Some studies suggest that user experiences and the value offered by both remain similar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">Udoakpan &amp;amp; Tengeh, 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Bouwman et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Kim &amp;amp; Kim, 2020</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Research methodology</title>
      <p>Bibliometric techniques used Bibliometrix and VOSviewer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Anand et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Aria &amp;amp; Cuccurullo, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">van Eck &amp;amp; Waltman, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">Rajan et al., 2020</xref>) to analyse collaborations, citation networks, and thematic trends. In this context, these tools offer a practical view of the research landscape and are common in management studies. Consequently, they help prioritise and guide growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Garfield, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">White &amp;amp; McCain, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Ferreira et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Hota, 2023</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Acedo et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">Vogel, 2012</xref>).</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>PRISMA flow diagram for the search of literature on the factors that encourage cooperative performance</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_ZZ_eENCf9nFUNoGv.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>This investigation retrieved articles from the Scopus database. Scopus is the largest multidisciplinary citation database. It focuses on high-quality, peer-reviewed journals in business, management, social sciences, psychology, and accounting. Only journal articles in the social sciences, psychology, and business, in English, were included. The period covered was 2010 to 2024.</p><p>The primary search string was TITLE-ABS-KEY (“OTT” OR “Over The Top” OR “VOD” OR “Netflix” OR “Video on demand” OR “Video stream*”) AND (LIMIT-TO (SUBJAREA, “BUSI”) OR LIMIT-TO (SUBJAREA, “SOCI”) OR LIMIT-TO (SUBJAREA, “PSYC”)) AND (LIMIT-TO (DOCTYPE, “ar”)) AND (LIMIT-TO (SRCTYPE, “j”)) AND (LIMIT-TO (LANGUAGE, “English”)).</p><p>A total of 179 articles were found on 10 October 2024. Three were excluded as irrelevant, leaving 176 for analysis. This selection supports the study’s relevance and quality aims.</p><p>The PRISMA diagram in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> shows the search and screening process, documenting steps from topic selection to article inclusion or exclusion. This approach shows transparent, reproducible methodology.</p><p>The review primarily used the Scopus database for bibliometric analysis, focusing on peer-reviewed publications. In contrast to previous statements, articles from journals listed in the ABDC ranking were deliberately included to enhance academic quality and relevance. While journal quartiles or other ranking metrics were not directly applied during screening, the inclusion of ABDC-indexed papers provides an additional layer of quality assurance.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Data analysis and result analysis</title>
      <p>The 176 documents included author names, titles, dates, and citation details. Trends in the geography and development of the OTT service literature were analysed using descriptive statistics.</p><p>Bibliometrix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Aria &amp;amp; Cuccurullo, 2017</xref>) and VOSviewer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">van Eck &amp;amp; Waltman, 2014</xref>) analysed patterns in the OTT literature. The review spanned 14 years (2010–2024), matching the Scopus availability after application of inclusion/exclusion criteria.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Main information from the database</title>
          
          <p>A total of 176 documents were authored by 379 individuals and published in 117 peer-reviewed Scopus-indexed journals spanning psychology, business, and accounting. Of these, 38 are single-author works. The average number of co-authors per document is 2.5. International co-authorship increased by 14.77%. Each document averages 7.375 citations and is 2.54 years old. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> summarises the data.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Summary statistics of database coverage, 2010–2024</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Description</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Results</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Timespan</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2010-2024</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sources (journals, books, etc.)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>117</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Documents</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>176</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Annual growth rate %</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>34%</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Document average age</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.54</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Average citations per doc</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7.375</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>References</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8549</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Document Contents</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Keywords plus (ID)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>422</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Author’s keywords (DE)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>703</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Authors</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Authors</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>379</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Authors of single-authored docs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>35</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Authors Collaboration</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Single-authored docs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>38</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Co-authors per doc</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>International co-authorships %</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14.77</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Document Types</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>176</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Publication trends over the years</title>
          
          <p>According to Scopus data, early research on OTT services dates to 2010, when the article “Seamless Service Delivery for mHealth Applications” was published in the International Journal of Industrial Engineering and Management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Boškovic et al., 2010</xref>). This article introduced an OTT-based service delivery architecture that allowed mHealth providers to reach users regardless of location or connectivity.</p><p>Between 2010 and 2011, research in this area was limited, and publication activity remained stagnant or declined until 2015. From 2015 to 2020, there was a gradual increase in publications on various aspects of OTT services, with 56 articles published in Scopus. Researchers started focusing on topics such as business strategies, telecom competition with OTT services, user willingness to pay, viewing behaviour, regulatory issues, and more.</p><p>After 2020, there was a significant surge in publications, with 112 articles published in peer-reviewed journals. This growth was driven by the COVID-19 pandemic, which increased demand for on-demand content due to lockdowns. Research during this phase covered themes such as the global expansion of subscription video on demand (SVOD), user adoption and satisfaction, tax regulations, pricing, and content variety, with a particular focus on Netflix. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> for details.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Publication trend</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_DOzyrWXQFVIGatWM.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> reports a compound annual growth rate (CAGR) of 34% in scholarly output on OTT media services from 2010 to 2024. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> further demonstrates a substantial year-over-year increase in publication volumes during this period. Together, these results indicate a significant and sustained expansion of research activity in the field.</p><p>India leads with 49 articles, followed by South Korea with 30, and the United States with 23 (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>). Chart 1 considered countries with at least four documents.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Country-wise scientific production</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_ITsnd5vdUxArdMzB.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Noticeable country-level differences in OTT research output and citation impact are revealed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>. India emerges as the primary contributor, with substantial academic investment, rapid market expansion, and a recent policy push driving both influence and publication volume. The United States and South Korea also display high citation rates and high output, likely revealing recognised digital infrastructure, active international collaborations, and robust OTT sectors. This focus underscores how global OTT scholarship remains unequal, with specific markets—such as South Africa, European countries, and Indonesia—producing less research, mainly due to resource constraints, language, or biases in regional publishing.</p><p>Remarkably, citation metrics often outpace document counts in countries like Spain and Australia, indicating that international co-authorships or influential papers increase global visibility from these countries. The results highlight the need for broader geographic expansion in the research on OTT platforms, particularly as diverse platforms (outside the Netflix/India bloc) and emerging markets increasingly influence global consumption. Identifying the reasons behind geographic research dominance—consumer behaviour, institutional support, and policy—will be fundamental for balanced content innovation and future scholarships.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Most influential authors in ott</title>
          
          <p>The most prolific authors in OTT research are highlighted in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>, including Ramli AM and Ramli TS from Indonesia’s Universitas Padjadjaran, Park E-A from the United States’ Colorado State University, and Chakraborty S from India’s Symbiosis Institute of Business Management. South Korean scholars such as Kim J, Kim S, Lee C, and Lee S stand out, along with many U.S.-based contributors, such as Li B and Park J, and are affiliated with universities in Seoul, including Hanyang University and Konkuk University.</p><p>There are regional centres of OTT research activity, as reflected by the prominence of authors from South Korea, India, Indonesia, and the United States, likely driven by the rapid growth of academic infrastructure and OTT markets in these countries. Prolific output is fostered by the repeated emergence of multiple authors from the same institutions, suggesting collaborative networks and organised research efforts. Geographic and institutional factors shape scholarly production, as demonstrated by clustering. </p><p>Nevertheless, there is comparatively less representation from African, Latin American, and European researchers, owing to a gap in global diversity and collaboration, as the concentration of influential authors is limited to a few countries. This precedent may imply limitations in “cross-national” cooperation or research silos, which could limit innovation in OTT studies and the generalisability of findings. </p><p>Essential context is provided by understanding the drivers of abundant scholarship—whether funding opportunities, industry ties, or consumer digital behaviour in home markets. Encouraging more inclusive, multidisciplinary approaches and expanding research collaborations could strengthen OTT research globally.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Most influential authors</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Authors</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Articles</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Affiliation</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Country</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ramli</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Universitas Padjadjaran</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Indonesia</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ramli</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Universitas Padjadjaran</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Indonesia</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Park</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Western State Colorado University</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>United States</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Chakraborty</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Symbiosis Institute of Business Management, Nagpur</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>India</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kim</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>School of Business Konkuk University, Seoul</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Korea</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kim</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Korea University, Seoul</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Korea</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lee</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Department of Media and Social Informatics, Hanyang University, Ansan</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Korea</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lee</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Department of Media, College of Politics and Economics, Kyung Hee University, Seoul</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Korea</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Li</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Department of Sport Leadership and Management, Miami University, Oxford, OH</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>United States</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Park</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Western Colorado University</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>United States</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.4. Most influential works</title>
          
          <p>The diversity of research focus shaping the OTT literature is underscored by <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>, which analyses the highly cited works. The most significant articles, such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Hutchins et al. (2019)</xref> on live-streaming rights and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">So (2016)</xref> on instant messaging for education, reflect a field at the intersection of consumer psychology, a rapidly evolving media ecosystem, and technology use. This indicates that cross-disciplinary approaches within OTT studies drive substantial scholarly impact. Outstandingly, studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Kim et al. (2017)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">Meng &amp;amp; Leung (2021)</xref> focus on motivational and behavioural aspects of users, acquiring global shifts in digital engagement; however, studies fixed in the context of pandemic-led consumption of media (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Gupta &amp;amp; Singharia, 2021</xref>) uncover how real-world events can speed up citation growth and academic interests.</p><p>The importance and limitations of OTT research are highlighted here, with an emphasis on Netflix, sports streaming, and geographically diverse subjects such as India, Spain, and Korea. There is a risk of thematic saturation and rapid citations as the dominance of empirical case studies targets cultural contexts or platforms. As seen in studies that employ advanced analytics, citation patterns indicate the field’s reliance on methodological novelty and trending topics (e.g., PLS analysis or cross-national comparisons).</p><p>The Matthew effect and possible research clustering are reflected by the concentration of citations around specific platforms, countries, and technologies, which may unintentionally overlook emerging platforms, less conventional consumer behaviours, or smaller markets. Moving forward, expanding the scope of research to include underserved regions, comparative analysis, and longitudinal studies may reinforce a more durable and balanced impact across the OTT network.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_4">
              <label>Table 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Highly cited research papers on OTT</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Author</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Paper</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Source Title</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total Citations</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total Citations/Year</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">So (2016)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mobile instant messaging support for teaching and learning in higher education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The Internet and Higher Education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>180</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Hutchins et al. (2019)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Over-the-top sport: live streams, changing coverage rights markets and the growth of media sport portals</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Media, Culture and Society</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>69</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13.8</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">Meng &amp;amp; Leung (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Factors influencing TikTok engagement behaviours in China: An examination of gratification sought, narcissism, and the Big Five personality traits</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Telecommunication Policy</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>56</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18.67</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Gupta &amp;amp; Singharia (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Consumption of OTT Media Streaming in the COVID-19 Lockdown: Insights from PLS Analysis</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vision: The Journal of Business Perspective</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>47</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15.67</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Kim et al. (2017)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Willingness to pay for over-the-top services in China and Korea</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Telecommunication Policy</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>47</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.71</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">Nagaraj et al. (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Factors affecting consumers’ willingness to subscribe to over-the-top (OTT) video streaming services in India</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technology in Society</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>33</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Farooq &amp;amp; Raju (2019)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Impact of Over-the-top (OTT) services on the telecom companies in the era of transformative marketing</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Global Journal of Flexible Systems</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>31</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.2</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">Wayne &amp;amp; Castro (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SVOD global expansion in cross-national comparative perspective: Netflix in Israel and Spain</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Television and New Media</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>30</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">Shin et al. (2016)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Strategic management of over-the-top services: Focussing on Korean consumer adoption behaviour</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technological Forecasting and Social Change</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>30</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.75</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Dwyer et al. (2018)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Comparing digital media industries in South Korea and Australia: The case of Netflix take-up</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>International Journal of Communication</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>27</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.5</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.5. Co-author network analysis of authors and countries</title>
          
          <p>VOSViewer-generated illustration in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> depicts structural patterns of affiliated countries and author collaborations in OTT research. Co-authorship networks are fragmented, with isolated, small clusters of researchers (as demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>), and are organised into distinct geographic and thematic domains. This pattern suggests that cross-team collaboration is rare, even when the individual author team is broad, interdisciplinary, or productive. This division may restrain the development of unified theories, methodological innovations, slow speed, and silo case studies with international or national boundaries.</p><p>The country-level collaborations in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> show marginally greater connectivity, but they remain controlled by a few central nodes—particularly India, the United States, and South Korea. These countries serve as hubs for international research partnerships, reflecting their developed OTT markets, access to research funding, and active academic communities. Both Asian and Western countries have extensive links with the U.S., positioning the U.S. as the primary global hub for OTT scholarship.</p><p>Conversely, several countries, including Indonesia, Belgium, and Taiwan, appear to be standalone nodes with weak or absent ties to global collaboration. Such remoteness may stem from a focus on domestic markets, language barriers, or institutional limitations, which restrict the transfer of knowledge and cross-contextual understanding in research on OTT. Thus, both the challenges and opportunities of global OTT research are reflected in this network as a whole: a few remain on the periphery, in contrast to other regions that are building international bridges.</p><p>Tactically, establishing interregional research collaborations, supporting cross-institutional and multilingual projects, and minimising barriers to partnerships are crucial for expanding the field. This will foster innovation that reflects the full spectrum of international OTT experiences, enabled by more robust, generalised findings.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Co-authorship network of authors</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_-VltUbS6NII4MxVH.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_5">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Co-authorship network of affiliated countries</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_1r1_tSfRnUedImT4.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.6. Author keyword co-occurrence network</title>
          
          <p>A co-occurrence analysis of author keywords was conducted using VOSviewer 1.6.19 to identify prevalent research themes in OTT studies. Forty keywords met the minimum threshold of 3 occurrences out of 703 keywords extracted from the dataset and were included in the analysis. Visually, these keywords are clustered in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref> according to their co-occurrence and publication frequency. </p><p>Netflix and OTT platforms dominate as central nodes revealed by the analysis, signaling an evident scholarly focus on major platforms steering industry transformation. Adjoining keywords such as streaming, content, television, and Over the Top highlight broader thematic areas related to the evolution of media consumption, user experience, and content delivery. </p><p>Media technology, user behaviour, regulatory concerns, pandemic impacts, and platform competition are amongst the seven unique clusters that emerge reflecting thematic specialisations. For example, millennials and COVID-19 are highlighted clusters reflecting recent research on consumption patterns driven by demographic and pandemic-specific adoption trends. </p><p>Conversely, keywords like Netflix, associated with large global platforms, imply a skew towards conventional, technology-driven narratives. Areas such as regional content diversity, accessibility, policy development, and niche platforms are comparatively understated, highlighting potential gaps in current research on OTT platforms. </p><p>Both the research community’s response and the rapid evolution of digital media are reflected in the thematic landscape, which is focused primarily on consumption models and well-known platforms. For enduring research, developing into overlooked areas such as regional OTT ecosystem studies, inclusive policy analysis, and non-traditional content forms will be crucial for capturing the whole OTT experience. </p>
          
            <fig id="fig_6">
              <label>Figure 6</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Co-occurrence of author’s keywords</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_kl15z0NdiOQ8bqWT.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.7. Bibliographic coupling of documents</title>
          
          <p>The connection between articles is established by bibliographic coupling, which reveals common thematic linkages and standard references within the scholarly sphere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Kessler, 1963</xref>). The strength of coupling reflects the extent to which documents circle around related topics. Forty-three articles were clustered into 22 groups in VOSviewer for this study, using a minimum threshold of 10 citations to filter for primary, influential research flows and minimise fragmentation from smaller clusters.</p><p>Three clusters are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>, emphasising five major thematic areas:</p><p>Cluster 1: User interaction and consumption of OTT media during COVID-19 (Red Cluster)</p><p>The largest cluster, with 180 citations and seven documents, portrays the swift digital shift determined by pandemic-led lockdowns. It centres on how OTT platforms enabled social connectivity and remote learning, with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">So (2016)</xref> offering a seminal contribution to the education sector during this early phase. The critical contextual role of the pandemic emerges for exciting consumer behaviour shifts.</p><p>Cluster 2: Video viewing behaviour of consumers (Green Cluster)</p><p>Sixty-nine citations are covered by six documents in this cluster, investigating viewing preferences, especially for sports streaming and digital media portals. This cluster is anchored by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Hutchins et al. (2019)</xref>, offering critical insights into how the personalisation of content and the dynamics of live-streaming impact engagement.</p><p>Cluster 3: OTT/TV comparisons and Netflix’s market dominance (Blue Cluster)</p><p>Twenty-one citations and five documents describe this cluster. Netflix’s disruptive impact is disrupting traditional TV and global OTT services. This discourse, reflecting continuing scholarship on market shaping and platform competition, is led by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Park (2019)</xref>.</p><p>Cluster 4: Youth engagement in traditional TV vs. OTT (Light Green Cluster)</p><p>This cluster comprises 22 citations and four documents, focusing on generational change in media consumption and assessing how younger demographics favour OTT platforms. Crucial viewpoints on media engagement shifts are contributed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">Meng &amp;amp; Leung (2021)</xref>.</p><p>Cluster 5: OTT Subscription desire influencing factors (Purple Cluster)</p><p>This cluster comprises 47 citations across three documents that examine consumer motivations to subscribe and emphasise economic and psychological drivers. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Kim et al. (2017)</xref> conducted the most notable work by investigating these behavioural tendencies.</p><p>Apart from these five clusters, which serve as the core knowledge base in OTT research, the remaining 17 clusters describe a distributed yet expanding landscape of themes. These emerging clusters—such as policy and regulation, regional platform strategies, accessibility/disability inclusion, and technological innovations—hint at future research boundaries. These areas respond to emerging OTT market challenges and societal demands, though at an early stage.</p><p>OTT research is both fragmented and diversified, as illustrated by this bibliographic coupling. Comparative, interdisciplinary, and longitudinal studies bridge these isolated clusters and will be instrumental in consolidating, guiding, and understanding future innovations in this fast-changing media domain.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_7">
              <label>Figure 7</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Bibliographic coupling of documents</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_ed9wfjmUDaKOS8Ot.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.8. Author co-citations analysis</title>
          
          <p>The author’s co-citation network for the OTT area is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>, encompassing 126 researchers who have been cited at least 10 times together. The visual map reveals three major clusters, each demonstrating research focus areas and distinct schools of thought, and shows significant linkages between clusters, suggesting interdisciplinary engagement. </p><p>Multidomain influence and centrality are displayed by large nodes such as Dhir A, Sarstedt M, and Kim J. The boundary-spanning scholar is Kim J, who is constantly cited across clusters, enabling the integration of themes from psychological determinants, media engagement, and consumer behaviour to methodological innovation. This pronounced role is not only a function of citation frequency but also encompasses the breadth of collaboration—Kim J is referenced alongside a large group of researchers, weaving together varied conceptual approaches.</p><p>Dominant paradigms are highlighted by the structure of the network points: consumer-centric and psychological studies, media adoption models, network theory, and technological innovation in OTT platforms. Deep intellectual exchange is revealed through shared connections and overlaps between the clusters—an active interchange of ideas that advances both real-world applicability and theory in OTT research. </p><p>Research inspiration in OTT studies is driven by an individual network of scholars rather than by a single leading journal, as evidenced by the lack of robust journal-level effects in co-citation, underscoring the field’s rapidly evolving, interdisciplinary nature. </p><p>Clear evidence of collaborating yet segmented research communities is provided by author co-citation analysis, which identifies key thought leaders and charts the bridge builders who help produce emerging perspectives – vital for advancing both innovative practices and structural scholarship in OTT media research. </p>
          
            <fig id="fig_8">
              <label>Figure 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Authors’ co-citations analysis</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_HYyy-x4QIcsfVLLN.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Discussion and conclusion</title>
      <p>The bibliometric analysis conducted in this review yields substantive insights into both the theoretical and empirical aspects of OTT media services research. The results indicate a marked increase in the volume and thematic range of global OTT scholarship from 2010 to 2024. India, South Korea, and the United States emerge as the leading contributors to this body of literature, with research output accelerating significantly following the COVID-19 pandemic, which prompted notable changes in user engagement and adoption patterns. The analysis identifies thematic clusters including platform dominance, consumer behaviour, generational shifts in media consumption, pandemic-related impacts, and subscription intent, thereby demonstrating the expanding scope of scholarly inquiry within the OTT sector. This thematic mapping addresses the first research question by delineating both the scale and substance of academic work on OTT media, and by illustrating the field’s evolution to encompass technology, consumption, competitive strategy, and market structure.</p><p>These findings are contextualised through established theoretical frameworks. The Technology Acceptance Model (TAM) informs much of the platform dominance cluster, highlighting how consumer perceptions of technological sophistication, personalisation, device flexibility, and value influence adoption behaviours. The Uses and Gratification Theory (UGT) accounts for evolving user engagement, as audiences increasingly pursue personalised, on-demand entertainment, shifting media experiences from passive to interactive and goal-oriented. The COVID-19 pandemic amplified these trends, strengthening the social and informational motivations described by UGT. Additionally, the Diffusion of Innovation theory elucidates the rapid acceleration in OTT adoption, demonstrating that societal disruptions can expedite the transition of innovations from early adopters to mainstream users.</p><p>Regarding the second research question on future research directions, cluster analysis and bibliographic coupling reveal several significant gaps and opportunities. Despite the notable global expansion of OTT scholarship, certain regional markets, particularly in Africa, Latin America, and smaller Asian and European economies, remain underrepresented. There is also a critical need for further investigation into policy and regulatory frameworks, technological advancements such as artificial intelligence and 5G, and issues of accessibility and content diversity. Comparative studies examining differences between and within emerging and developed markets would further enhance and balance academic discourse. Addressing these gaps will enable policymakers, industry leaders, and researchers to navigate and influence the evolving OTT media landscape more effectively.</p><p>In summary, this study demonstrates that integrating bibliometric analysis with theoretical frameworks provides a comprehensive perspective on the development, challenges, and future research needs of OTT scholarship. The findings underscore the significance of psychological, technological, and socio-economic factors in influencing media adoption and identify new directions for research as digital platforms continue to reshape global content consumption.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Future scope of study</title>
      <p>Future research on OTT media services should rank in three significant directions. First, Regional and cultural understanding of OTT adoption is essential, specifically through a comparative study of emerging vs developed markets and the rising role of regional content. Second, the industry demands in-depth analysis of emerging cutting-edge technologies such as AI-driven recommendation engines, 5G, and hybrid business models—as well as emerging regulatory and legal frameworks, specifically around data privacy, digital sovereignty, and content moderation. Third, Creative strategies for customer retention justify intensive scholarly inquiry amid intensifying competition. This entails research on gamification, Gen Z and millennial preferences, subscription fatigue, and the convergence of professional and user-generated content. Selecting these areas will bring forth insights for both regulators and platforms, ensuring that research anticipates and tracks the major revolutions reshaping the OTT sector. </p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.1. Implications for academicians</title>
          
          <p>Neglect of smaller providers and regional dynamics, and the dominance of global OTT players, are the gaps highlighted by this review. Existing bibliometric boundaries should be breached by academic research that focuses on niches, underrepresented regions, and user experience research, particularly through participatory approaches and mixed methods to capture evolving preferences in real time. Building connections among sociological, industry-focused, and technological analyses will position the field to contribute dynamically to both practice and theory as OTT services mature alongside evolving regulations. </p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.2. Implications for policymakers and society</title>
          
          <p>The rapid growth of OTT services requires updated regulatory frameworks to address data privacy, content moderation, and platform accountability. Evidence from India and other regions highlights the effectiveness of tiered regulatory mechanisms, such as three-tiered grievance redressal guidelines, as well as the need for greater algorithmic transparency and age-based content classification. Policymakers are advised to collaborate with stakeholders from industry, civil society, and consumer groups to combat misinformation and promote digital literacy. Regulatory policies should also facilitate sustainable monetisation models and support local OTT platforms to preserve market diversity and prevent dominance by global providers. Continuous assessment of content standards and technological developments is necessary to ensure that regulatory approaches remain aligned with evolving social and ethical expectations.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Limitations of the study</title>
      <p>There are several limitations to consider when interpreting these results. This review mainly uses the Scopus database, so some relevant studies from other databases or non-English and regional sources may be missing. Although we included articles from ABDC-ranked journals, we did not systematically apply ranking metrics during screening, which could affect our assessment of publication quality. The chosen time frame of 2010 to 2024 may not capture new developments after the pandemic or the launch of recent OTT platforms. Citation-based analysis can overlook innovative, recent, or niche research that has not yet been widely cited. Since most research comes from South Korea, the United States, and India, insights from Latin America, the Middle East, and Africa may be underrepresented. The bibliometric approach may also miss detailed findings from qualitative or user-focused studies. Our keyword choices and focus on highly cited clusters might leave out social, creative, and experiential aspects of OTT. Future research could be improved by using multiple databases, including studies in different languages, and by combining different research methods to understand the global OTT landscape better.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The submitted work is original and has not been published elsewhere in any form or language. Further, the authors would like to express their gratitude to all those who contributed to the completion of this research. The authors would also like to thank the editor and the anonymous reviewer for their valuable insights.</p>
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>S.S.C.: Conceptualising the manuscript; Search for relevant literature; Curation of data; Methodology; Software use; Data analysis; Visualisation; Writing of the original draft. D.P.: Guidance; Validation; Review writing and editing; Refinement of methodology; Critical revisions; Overall project administration. G.S.: Direction; Validation; Writing the review and editing the manuscript; Quality assurance; Interpretation of results; Final approval of manuscript. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>27</volume>
          <page-range>621-636</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2006</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Acedo</surname>
              <given-names>F. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barroso</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galan</surname>
              <given-names>J. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/smj.532</pub-id>
          <article-title>The resource‐based theory: Dissemination and main trends</article-title>
          <source>Strateg. Manag. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>75</volume>
          <page-range>103529</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agarwal</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mehrotra</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Papa</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malibari</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jretconser.2023.103529</pub-id>
          <article-title>Over-the-top (OTT) retailing in the post pandemic world. Unveiling consumer drivers and barriers using a qualitative study</article-title>
          <source>J. Retail. Consum. Serv.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>28</volume>
          <page-range>111-136</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anand</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brøns Kringelum</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Øland Madsen</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Selivanovskikh</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/tlo-02-2020-0023</pub-id>
          <article-title>Interorganizational learning: A bibliometric review and research agenda</article-title>
          <source>Learn. Organ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>959-975</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aria</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cuccurullo</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joi.2017.08.007</pub-id>
          <article-title>Bibliometrix : An R-tool for comprehensive science mapping analysis</article-title>
          <source>J. Informetr.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>How homegrown streaming video can take on the global goliaths</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.bcg.com/publications/2021/how-local-players-succeed-video-streaming-markets</source>
          <year>2021</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>131–143</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boškovic</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kovačević</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ilić</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arges</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wisz</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Seamless service delivery solution for mHealth application</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Ind. Eng. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>1–12</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bouwman</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Staalman</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Reuver</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Over the top mobile TV: A field trial by public and commercial broadcasters</article-title>
          <source>Int. Conf. Mob. Bus.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>70</volume>
          <page-range>103148</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
              <given-names>Debarun</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siddiqui</surname>
              <given-names>Mujahid</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siddiqui</surname>
              <given-names>Aaliyah</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paul</surname>
              <given-names>Justin</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dash</surname>
              <given-names>Ganesh</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mas</surname>
              <given-names>Francesca Dal</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jretconser.2022.103148</pub-id>
          <article-title>Watching is valuable: Consumer views – Content consumption on OTT platforms</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>2022 media &amp; entertainment industry outlook</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.deloitte.com/za/en/Industries/telecom-media-entertainment/perspectives/media-and-entertainment-industry-outlook-trends.html</source>
          <year>2022</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>2023 digital media trends: Immersed and connected</article-title>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>4553–4572</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dwyer</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shim</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hutchinson</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparing digital media industries in South Korea and Australia: The case of Netflix take-up</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Commun.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Einav</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Media reimagined: The impact of COVID-19 on digital media transformation</article-title>
          <source>Transitioning Media in a Post COVID World: Digital Transformation, Immersive Technologies, and Consumer Behavior</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>19-28</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-95330-0_2</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>20</volume>
          <page-range>177-188</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Farooq</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raju</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40171-019-00209-6</pub-id>
          <article-title>Impact of over-the-top (OTT) services on the telecom companies in the era of transformative marketing</article-title>
          <source>Glob. J. Flex. Syst. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>67</volume>
          <page-range>2550-2558</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferreira</surname>
              <given-names>M. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Almeida</surname>
              <given-names>M. I. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reis</surname>
              <given-names>N. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2014.03.015</pub-id>
          <article-title>Mergers &amp; acquisitions research: A bibliometric study of top strategy and international business journals, 1980–2010</article-title>
          <source>J. Bus. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>359-375</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>1979</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garfield</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf02019306</pub-id>
          <article-title>Is citation analysis a legitimate evaluation tool?</article-title>
          <source>Scientometrics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>39</volume>
          <page-range>1039-1061</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Governo</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teixeira</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brochado</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0144929x.2019.1641227</pub-id>
          <article-title>Merging social computing with content: A proposal of a new film platform, Avids</article-title>
          <source>Behav. Inf. Technol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>126</volume>
          <page-range>95-105</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Green</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1329878x0812600111</pub-id>
          <article-title>Why do they call it TV when it's not on the box? ‘New’ television services and old television functions</article-title>
          <source>Media Int. Aust.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>25</volume>
          <page-range>36-46</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singharia</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0972262921989118</pub-id>
          <article-title>Consumption of OTT media streaming in COVID-19 lockdown: Insights from PLS analysis</article-title>
          <source>Vision J. Bus. Perspect.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>182</volume>
          <page-range>637-659</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hota</surname>
              <given-names>P. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10551-021-04962-6</pub-id>
          <article-title>Tracing the intellectual evolution of social entrepreneurship research: Past advances, current trends, and future directions</article-title>
          <source>J. Bus. Ethics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>41</volume>
          <page-range>975-994</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hutchins</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rowe</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0163443719857623</pub-id>
          <article-title>Over-the-top sport: Live streaming services, changing coverage rights markets and the growth of media sport portals</article-title>
          <source>Media Cult. Soc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>375-392</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1504/ijicbm.2017.084353</pub-id>
          <article-title>An empirical study on acceptance of video on demand services in Indian market</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Indian Cult. Bus. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Network television streaming technologies and the shifting television social sphere</article-title>
          <source>Media in Transition</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>10-25</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>1963</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kessler</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/asi.5090140103</pub-id>
          <article-title>Bibliographic coupling between scientific papers</article-title>
          <source>Am. Doc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>41</volume>
          <page-range>197-207</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hwang</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.telpol.2016.12.011</pub-id>
          <article-title>Willingness to pay for over-the-top services in China and Korea</article-title>
          <source>Telecommun. Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>196–207</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>Y. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>B. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The purchase motivations and continuous use intention of online subscription services</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>The digital-first journey: The rise of OTT platforms in India</article-title>
          <source>, https://assets.kpmg.com/content/dam/kpmg/in/pdf/2017/10/The-Digital-First-journey.pdf</source>
          <year>2017</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>31</volume>
          <page-range>562-586</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kwon</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Son</surname>
              <given-names>J. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/intr-03-2020-0127</pub-id>
          <article-title>Accurately or accidentally? Recommendation agent and search experience in over-the-top (OTT) services</article-title>
          <source>Internet Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <page-range>41–50</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21742/apjcri.2020.01.04</pub-id>
          <article-title>The growth and impact of OTT on video viewing behavior</article-title>
          <source>Asia-Pac. J. Converg. Res. Interchange</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lotz</surname>
              <given-names>A. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The Television Will Be Revolutionized, Second Edition</source>
          <publisher-name>New York University Press.</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>173</volume>
          <page-range>121178</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Martínez-Sánchez</surname>
              <given-names>M. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicolas-Sans</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Díaz</surname>
              <given-names>J. B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.techfore.2021.121178</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analysis of the social media strategy of audio-visual OTTs in Spain: The case study of Netflix, HBO and Amazon Prime during the implementation of Disney+</article-title>
          <source>Technol. Forecast. Soc. Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>45</volume>
          <page-range>102172</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Meng</surname>
              <given-names>K. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leung</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.telpol.2021.102172</pub-id>
          <article-title>Factors influencing TikTok engagement behaviors in China: An examination of gratifications sought, narcissism, and the Big Five personality traits</article-title>
          <source>Telecommun. Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>2249-5835</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mondal</surname>
              <given-names>M. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panda</surname>
              <given-names>B. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>AI-driven recommendation systems on OTT platforms: Shaping user experiences.</article-title>
          <source>Glob. Media J.-Indian Ed.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Over-the-top (OTT) market—Industry report</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.mordorintelligence.com/industry-reports/over-the-top-market</source>
          <year>2025</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>65</volume>
          <page-range>101534</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nagaraj</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasa</surname>
              <given-names>V. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.techsoc.2021.101534</pub-id>
          <article-title>Factors affecting consumers’ willingness to subscribe to over-the-top (OTT) video streaming services in India</article-title>
          <source>Technol. Soc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>47</volume>
          <page-range>102525</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nam</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ro</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jung</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.telpol.2023.102525</pub-id>
          <article-title>Netflix's presence: Investigating content producers' understanding of Netflix in the Korean media industry</article-title>
          <source>Telecommun. Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>177-192</page-range>
          <issue>3-4</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14241277.2019.1695257</pub-id>
          <article-title>Prevalence of business models in global OTT video services: A cluster analysis</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Media Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Global entertainment &amp; media outlook 2019–2023</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.pwc.in/industries/entertainment-and-media/global-entertainment-and-media-outlook-2019-2023.html</source>
          <year>2019</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Power shifts: Altering the dynamics of the E&amp;M industry</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.pwc.com/gx/en/entertainment-media/outlook-2021/perspectives-2021-2025.pdf</source>
          <year>2021</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>351-375</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rajan</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhir</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sushil</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/jsma-10-2019-0184</pub-id>
          <article-title>Alliance termination research: A bibliometric review and research agenda</article-title>
          <source>J. Strategy Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>1399-1414</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ryu</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>S. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cb.2220</pub-id>
          <article-title>An exploratory study of consumer switching behavior in platform businesses: A mixed methods approach</article-title>
          <source>J. Consum. Behav.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>48</volume>
          <page-range>531-547</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mehta</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0258042x221137438</pub-id>
          <article-title>Over-the-top (OTT) streaming services: Studying users’ behaviour through the UTAUT model</article-title>
          <source>Manag. Labour Stud.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>165</volume>
          <page-range>113893</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Basu</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bose</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dss.2022.113893</pub-id>
          <article-title>Determining the optimal release time of movies: A study of movie and market characteristics</article-title>
          <source>Decis. Support Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>32</volume>
          <page-range>1214-1234</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rasul</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fotiadis</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/intr-02-2021-0087</pub-id>
          <article-title>Why am I seeing this? Deconstructing algorithm literacy through the lens of users</article-title>
          <source>Internet Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>112</volume>
          <page-range>329-337</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.techfore.2016.08.004</pub-id>
          <article-title>Strategic management of over-the-top services: Focusing on Korean consumer adoption behavior</article-title>
          <source>Technol. Forecast. Soc. Change.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>31</volume>
          <page-range>32-42</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>So</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.iheduc.2016.06.001</pub-id>
          <article-title>Mobile instant messaging support for teaching and learning in higher education</article-title>
          <source>Internet High. Educ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>75</volume>
          <page-range>103460</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Soren</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jretconser.2023.103460</pub-id>
          <article-title>The formation of habit and word-of-mouth intention of over-the-top platforms</article-title>
          <source>J. Retail. Consum. Serv.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>76</volume>
          <page-range>103574</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Soren</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jretconser.2023.103574</pub-id>
          <article-title>Adoption, satisfaction, trust, and commitment of over-the-top platforms: An integrated approach</article-title>
          <source>J. Retail. Consum. Serv.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>43</volume>
          <page-range>644-661</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sridevi</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ajith</surname>
              <given-names>Nandukrishna T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02614367.2023.2256030</pub-id>
          <article-title>Switching channels: Investigating the push, pull, and mooring effects of moving from cable TV to OTT services</article-title>
          <source>Leis. Stud.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <page-range>139</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Udoakpan</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tengeh</surname>
              <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/joitmc6040139</pub-id>
          <article-title>The impact of over-the-top television services on pay-television subscription services in South Africa</article-title>
          <source>J. Open Innov. Technol. Mark. Complex.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>van Eck</surname>
              <given-names>N. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waltman</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Visualizing bibliometric networks</article-title>
          <source>Measuring Scholarly Impact: Methods and Practice</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
          <page-range>285-320</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-10377-8_13</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2012</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vogel</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Review of the use of ‘Theory of Change’in international development</article-title>
          <source>London: DFID</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>40</volume>
          <page-range>725-741</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wayne</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0163443717736118</pub-id>
          <article-title>Netflix, Amazon, and branded television content in subscription video on-demand portals</article-title>
          <source>Media Cult. Soc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>896-913</page-range>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wayne</surname>
              <given-names>Michael L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castro</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1527476420926496</pub-id>
          <article-title>SVOD global expansion in cross-national comparative perspective: Netflix in Israel and Spain</article-title>
          <source>Telev. New Media</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>49</volume>
          <page-range>327-355</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>1998</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>H. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCain</surname>
              <given-names>K. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Visualizing a discipline: An author co‐citation analysis of information science, 1972–1995</article-title>
          <source>J. Am. Soc. Inf. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>40</volume>
          <page-range>3253-3262</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yoon</surname>
              <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>H. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10447318.2023.2185732</pub-id>
          <article-title>An empirical analysis of factors affecting OTT service users’ switching intention: Focusing on Netflix and the perspective of the push-pull-mooring framework</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Hum. Comput. Interact.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>