<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Sustainability for Energy</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Sustain. Energy</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JSE</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2958-1915</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-1907</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR--P0ElKEKBW9IMqHAs63t0NBtyvC5dbRk</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jse030203</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Assessment of a Hybrid Renewable Energy System Incorporating Wind, Solar, and Storage Technologies in Makkovik, Newfoundland and Labrador</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0005-1141-7594</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Maliat</surname>
            <given-names>Afreen</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>amaliat@mun.ca</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-6495-811X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Kotian</surname>
            <given-names>Siddhanth</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>srkotian@mun.ca</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5186-8035</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ghahremanlou</surname>
            <given-names>Davoud</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>dghahremanlo@mun.ca</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Faculty of Business Administration, Memorial University of Newfoundland, A1B 3Y1 St. John's, Newfoundland and Labrador, Canada</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>05</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2024</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>87</fpage>
      <lpage>104</lpage>
      <page-range>87-104</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>05</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2024 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>This investigation addresses the critical challenge of devising robust and sustainable energy infrastructures by integrating renewable energy sources in Makkovik, Newfoundland, and Labrador. A hybrid renewable energy system (HRES) comprising wind turbines, photovoltaic (PV) solar panels, battery storage, and backup diesel generators was evaluated for its viability and efficiency. With the help of the HOMER Pro software, extensive modeling and optimization were conducted, aimed at reducing dependency on fossil fuels, cutting carbon emissions, and enhancing economic benefits via decreased operational costs. The results indicated that the energy demands of Makkovik could predominantly be met by the proposed system, utilizing renewable resources. Significant reductions in greenhouse gas emissions were observed, alongside improved cost-efficiency throughout the system's projected lifespan. Such outcomes demonstrate the system’s capability to provide an environmentally friendly and technically viable solution, marking a substantial step towards energy resilience and sustainability for isolated communities. The integration of diverse renewable energy sources underlines the potential for substantial emission reductions and operational cost savings, highlighting the importance of innovative energy solutions in enhancing the sustainability and resilience of remote areas. This study contributes vital insights into optimizing energy systems for economic and environmental benefits, advancing the discourse on renewable energy utilization in isolated regions.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>HOMER Pro</kwd>
        <kwd>Hybrid power</kwd>
        <kwd>Wind energy</kwd>
        <kwd>Solar energy</kwd>
        <kwd>Canada</kwd>
        <kwd>Newfoundland and Labrador (NL)</kwd>
        <kwd>Makkovik</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="3"/>
        <fig-count count="11"/>
        <table-count count="13"/>
        <ref-count count="43"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>The pivotal shift towards renewable energy sources marks a significant stride in the global endeavor to combat climate change and foster sustainable development, combining the goals of enhancing energy security and mitigating the environmental impacts associated with traditional fossil fuel use into a compelling narrative for change. To integrate various energy sources in a way that guarantees a steady and continuous energy supply, the HRES has emerged as a feasible solution to the inherent intermittency and dependability difficulties of renewable energy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. Research indicates that integrating renewable and conventional energy systems in parallel, is more flexible and reliable than integrating them in series. This technique greatly lowers greenhouse gas emissions by enabling a variety of energy sources to cooperate harmoniously to fulfill varying energy demands. Furthermore, the vital role that energy storage technologies play in stabilizing power systems with high renewable penetration is becoming more widely acknowledged. These devices offer crucial ancillary services like peak shaving and frequency management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>].</p><p>The majority of the electricity produced in Canada is generated by renewable sources. However, almost all microgrids in isolated Southern Canadian communities disconnected from the main grid rely on fossil fuels to provide electricity. The study "Decarbonizing Canada's Remote Microgrids" examines Canada's significant transition away from fossil fuels and toward renewable energy sources, highlighting the necessity of this change to improve energy security and reduce environmental damage. It specifically tackles the difficulties faced by isolated communities that are cut off from Southern Canada's main power grid and nearly entirely dependent on fossil fuels for electricity. It emphasizes the critical need for creative energy solutions in these remote areas to facilitate sustainable development and achieve decarbonization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>].</p><p>The increasing reliance of isolated populations on conventional energy sources, particularly fossil fuels, raises serious concerns as we move toward more sustainable energy frameworks. Opeyemi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>] represents an analysis of Nigeria's energy consumption profile and offers an empirical foundation for thinking about the replacement of non-renewable and renewable energy sources. Due to high carbon emissions and resource depletion, this research draws attention to the overwhelming reliance on non-renewable energy sources, which make up a sizable percentage of the total energy mix. This raises issues regarding sustainability and the environment.</p><p>Makkovik, an Inuit community in Canada, isolated from the mainland, is a perfect example of this problem. Its reliance on diesel, a less practical and sustainable option for the environment, highlights how urgently we need creative energy solutions. Because of this, Makkovik is a great place for studies on the adoption of HRES, to create a model for sustainability and energy independence that can be applied to comparable towns across the globe. The situation in Makkovik, Newfoundland, and Labrador highlights the urgent need for creative energy solutions that are considerate of the unique geographical, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>, and cultural factors of isolated places while also being sustainable. In addition to being a calculated step toward environmental preservation, the implementation of HRES in these areas will help them become energy-independent by lowering their need for expensive and environmentally damaging fossil fuel imports. This move is essential for helping isolated communities flourish socioeconomically since it provides a way to reduce energy expenses and lessen environmental effects. The socio-economic benefits of adopting hybrid energy systems are detailed in the study by Vurur [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>].</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Map showing the position of Makkovik, NL</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_joRmONHSaMV1kOZe.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>It is expected that Makkovik's HRES would bring about several socio-economic and environmental advantages, notably improving the community's standard of living and ecological impact. First, the transition to renewable energy sources like wind and solar offers a significant chance to create jobs. A workforce knowledgeable in renewable energy technology will be necessary for both the building phase and the continuing operation and maintenance of the energy system, in addition to trained and semi-skilled labor. This promotes employment and skill development locally, hence strengthening the economy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>]. Furthermore, the move to a renewable energy grid that is managed locally represents genuine energy independence. Less reliance on imported diesel fuel will allow the community to better manage its energy supply and lower the risks of supply chain interruptions and volatile fuel prices. The town is empowered by this energy production self-sufficiency, which guarantees a steady and dependable power supply to promote growth and development in the future. The environmental effects of switching to a HRES are significant, in addition to the financial ones. A significant improvement in air quality is anticipated since the decrease in diesel usage results in a direct reduction in the emissions of hazardous pollutants such as sulfur dioxide, nitrogen oxides, and particle matter. As a result of the reduced respiratory and cardiovascular disorders linked to air pollution, the public's health improves. In addition, by reducing greenhouse gas emissions, the initiative contributes to the larger objectives of climate action, establishing Makkovik as a model of environmentally conscious, sustainable living [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>].</p><p>Beyond technological advancements, renewable energy solutions resonate intimately with the cultural ethos, long-standing traditions of sustainability, and environmental care intrinsic to Indigenous communities like Makkovik. The community's commitment to protecting their natural surroundings for future generations is evident from the lack of direct information on Makkovik's renewable energy initiatives. These initiatives also reflect the community's practices of inclusivity and collective decision-making, which are common among Indigenous communities worldwide. Similar situations can be found, for instance, in Australia, where Indigenous communities' shift to renewable energy has been framed as an empowerment tool that preserves cultural and environmental integrity while leveraging local knowledge to combat climate change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>]. The Moloka'i village in Hawaii is spearheading renewable energy projects driven by the philosophy that “the land is the chief, and we are the servants,” highlighting a sustained dedication to environmental care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>]. Similar to this, the Igiugig village in Alaska combines renewable energy projects with traditional beliefs, making sure that these endeavors are sensitive to cultural differences and promote the community's long-term sustainability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. By drawing comparisons between these instances, it is plausible that Makkovik's strategy for renewable energy not only seeks to replace traditional energy sources but also acts as evidence of the community's tenacity, independence, and commitment to preserving its natural and cultural heritage. These initiatives highlight how crucial it is to combine cutting-edge technology with traditional wisdom and values to empower Indigenous people everywhere, including Makkovik, and pave the way for a sustainable future.</p><p>This analysis underscores the significant impact of renewable energy systems on economic development and sustainability, offering a broader perspective on the benefits of hybrid systems beyond energy generation. Furthermore, using renewable energy in these contexts supports global sustainability objectives and makes a substantial contribution to the decrease of greenhouse gas emissions and the improvement of environmental quality worldwide.</p><p>In this study, a hybrid energy system for Makkovik that makes use of solar and wind energy in addition to battery storage options along with diesel generators is proposed. With HOMER Pro, the design and analysis process are carried out to offer the area a cost-effective, efficient, and sustainable energy solution.</p><p>The paper is structured as follows: Section 2 contains the literature review, the methodology is explained in Section 3, the load profile and local resources are examined in Section 4, the hybrid system design is explained in Section 5, the results and discussion are presented in Section 6, and the study is concluded in Section 7.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Literature review</title>
      <p>As communities worldwide grapple with the effects of climate change and work toward energy independence, the switch to renewable energy is critical. Makkovik presents particular energy issues that highlight the pressing need for creative and sustainable energy solutions, just like many isolated communities throughout the world. This study delves further into these issues by investigating how HRES might transform the way remote people obtain their energy and electricity.</p><p>Makkovik is a small Inuit village home to about 360 people [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>]. The Inuit Community of Makkovik is situated roughly 210 kilometers northeast of Happy Valley-Goose Bay, Labrador, at coordinates 55°07'N and 59°03'W. Makkovik is situated from Cape Makkovik into the inland [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]. Geographically isolated and with little access to centralized grid infrastructure, isolated communities like Makkovik have difficulties finding affordable and dependable electricity. Energy security is compromised, and environmental deterioration is exacerbated by traditional fossil fuel-based generators, which also result in high energy costs. By combining renewable energy sources with conventional production and energy storage technologies, hybrid energy systems that offer resilient and sustainable energy solutions for isolated communities are becoming more and more popular as a response to these difficulties. A thorough exploration of the field of renewable energy research is undertaken in this literature review, with a particular emphasis on hybrid systems that combine the benefits of solar, wind, and energy storage technology. Our analysis spans a wide range of research, from the economic and technological feasibility of hybrid energy systems to their environmental effects, and demonstrates the rapid advancement of knowledge and innovation in this subject.</p><p>The use of renewable energy technology has been researched by academics from several jurisdictions. Most of them focused mostly on the use of solar energy, wind turbines, and batteries in conjunction with the planning, analysis, and evaluation of various hybrid power systems in various configurations. The potential of combining energy storage technologies like batteries and hydrogen fuel cells with renewable energy sources like solar PV, wind turbines, hydroelectric generators, and biomass systems has been highlighted in recent literature on hybrid energy systems for remote communities.</p><p>Several studies stand out in the rapidly changing field of renewable energy research for their contributions to the understanding and advancement of hybrid energy systems, providing complementary information to the fundamental research underpinning the Makkovik Island project. Benchmarks from the deployment of comparable systems in St. Brendan's NL, Grey River NL, and Ramea Island, and comparative studies on Al-Muthana are helpful in the development of a resilient and sustainable HRES for Makkovik. Each project highlights the flexibility and promise of hybrid systems in meeting the particular energy demands of remote communities as they are customized to fit their particular geographic and socioeconomic situation. The study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>] demonstrated integrating wind turbines and solar panels with HOMER Pro-optimized diesel generators as a complement in St. Brendan’s, NL. This model offered Makkovik a blueprint for utilizing its local wind and solar potential by demonstrating that it is feasible to integrate renewable sources and greatly reduce diesel usage. Kandil et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>] concentrated on integrating PV panels with diesel generators that were already in place for Grey River, NL. The study demonstrated the system's capacity to sustain stability and power production in the face of load changes by using MATLAB Simulink for dynamic simulations and HOMER Pro for steady-state analysis. This highlights the significance of adaptable energy solutions in Makkovik and similar areas where seasonal variations in energy demand occur. The adoption of a broader hybrid approach by Kotian et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>], which includes diesel generators, solar, wind, and battery storage for Ramea Island, NL, shows how different energy sources may improve system resilience and dependability. This technique, which suggests that a diverse energy plan may provide a steady power supply even in difficult circumstances, is especially pertinent to Makkovik. Issa et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>] highlights the crucial role that thorough system modeling and optimization play in obtaining both financial and environmental efficiency by providing insights into the design and ideal size of a hybrid power system in Al-Muthana using the HOMER simulator. Makkovik believes that project profitability and resource efficiency might be maximized by using a similarly stringent design method. The importance of context in the development and use of HRES is highlighted by this comparative analysis. It supports the case for a more nuanced interpretation of the Makkovik system, promoting a model that not only attends to the community's unique energy requirements but also adds to the international conversation on sustainable development in isolated places.</p><p>The paper by Ameur et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>] on dynamic forecasting models for PV/GES systems shows how improved predictive analytics can result in significant cost and energy savings. Furthermore, the techno-economic analysis of an optimized hybrid system on Malawali Island, Malaysia, that includes diesel generators, PV cells, wind turbines, and batteries highlights the viability and financial benefits of implementing a variety of energy sources in remote areas, supporting the systems' relevance to Makkovik's energy environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>].</p><p>The feasibility and environmental advantages of combining different energy sources are highlighted by recent research in renewable energy technology. For instance, studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>] suggest that hybrid energy systems can improve energy access, lower greenhouse gas emissions, and increase energy resilience in remote locations while remaining economically and technically feasible. Also, Ahmadi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>] offers a thorough approach to assessing the economic and environmental effects of hybrid energy systems, highlighting the vital role that sustainable design plays in attaining energy independence and reducing environmental impacts. De la Cruz-Soto et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>] highlights the importance of Power to Gas to Power (P2G2P) systems in improving microgrid sustainability through intercessional energy storage and notable reductions in <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m0gpqfroiv">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CO</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> emissions. It does this by presenting a techno-economic analysis of a hydrogen storage system within a microgrid in Baja California, Mexico. This study underscores the transformative potential of utilizing advanced energy storage, management, and predictive analytics within hybrid energy systems. Recent developments in the field of optimizing renewable energy for remote and off-grid communities provide an excellent example of an environmentally friendly and long-lasting off-grid energy system. Their study, which presents a hybrid system with PV arrays, wind generators, and battery storage, successfully met the community's energy needs while achieving almost total grid autonomy. Ghadirinejad et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>] demonstrates a system that can provide 99.9% of the annual electricity needs using particle swarm optimization (PSO) techniques validated with HOMER Pro software. This highlights the viability of attaining high reliability and sustainability in energy provision through sophisticated optimization techniques.</p><p>The conversation on the viability and optimization of hybrid energy systems in isolated and island communities is further enhanced by recent research. For instance, in the study by Costa and Villalva [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>], the possibility of integrating renewable energy sources into small island communities is explored. The importance of energy storage systems in maintaining a steady supply of electricity is emphasized. The study presents a strong argument for the use of hybrid systems to achieve sustainable electrification by highlighting the efficiency of combining PV systems with diesel generators and the critical role that batteries play in stabilizing the energy supply. Seedahmed et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>] examines the integration of wind energy, diesel generators, fuel cells, and batteries in a hybrid energy system designed to electrify a rural cluster in western Saudi Arabia. The techno-economic study is thorough. This study examines two hybrid setups and a diesel-only design, evaluating the environmental and economic feasibility of each using HOMER Pro software. The best combination of wind, diesel, fuel cell, and battery is shown in the results to be the most cost-effective and environmentally benign option, with a notable decrease in Net Present Cost (NPC) and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m8rpegh90u">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CO</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> emissions when compared to conventional diesel systems.</p><p>Miao et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>] used HOMER Pro and the reference point approach in multi-criteria decision analysis to plan an island microgrid system, with an emphasis on the integration of economic, resilience, energy, and environmental factors to discover optimal configurations. This strategy is in line with creating a reliable and sustainable energy source for remote communities. Beyene et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>] explores the viability of grid-integrated hybrid systems, which combine modern storage technologies with solar and wind energy sources to provide distant communities with a reliable and sustainable electricity supply. It emphasizes how important energy storage is to reduce the erratic nature of renewable energy sources and raise overall power supply reliability. A techno-economic analysis of a standalone hybrid system on Donoussa Island, Greece, is carried out by the study contained in the study by Katsivelakis et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]. Different scenarios are explored to determine the best environmentally and economically sustainable configuration. The research shows how PV arrays, wind turbines, and diesel generators can be combined to achieve a high rate of renewable energy penetration, drastically reduce dependency on fossil fuels, and lower energy costs using HOMER Pro software. A thorough investigation of the design and analysis of a hybrid stand-alone microgrid for an industrial facility in Iraq is included in the study described in Bhatti et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]. This study makes use of HOMER Pro for hybrid microgrid design and optimization, PVsyst for comprehensive PV plant design, and SAM for performance analysis. It demonstrates how the method may cut <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mjxfam9bcl">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CO</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> emissions dramatically, roughly 1811.6 tons over 30 years, and emphasizes the possibility of producing renewable energy.</p><p>A unique hybrid energy system for Salemo Island was created using Homer Pro software in the research by Mansur [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]. It was shown by the research that the LCOE of the hybrid system could be reduced to 1,306 IDR/kWh by adding 120 batteries and another 200 kWp Solar Power Plant (SPP). In addition to highlighting the many benefits of integrating renewable resources in remote locations, this approach also shows how a well-considered hybrid system design can significantly improve economic efficiency and reliability.</p><p>Farahmand et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>] provide an in-depth examination of Canada's potential contribution to Europe's energy problems through the export of hydrogen, in line with its 2050 carbon neutrality targets. This assessment carefully breaks down the downstream elements of the Canadian hydrogen supply chain, examining elements, decision-making procedures, and sustainability factors. With practical conclusions, it suggests ways to improve industry practices, policy formation, and research to increase the sustainability and efficiency of the hydrogen supply chain and support Canada's environmental goals.</p><p>Sakthi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>] highlight NL's ability to produce sustainable hydrogen, which is important to consider given the increased concerns about energy security brought on by the conflict between Russia and Ukraine. The analysis highlights NL's distinct advantages and strategic location as critical to contributing to Europe's energy solutions by carefully examining the body of research on the province's hydrogen potential. It looks at the sources, production processes, storage alternatives, and distribution mechanisms of hydrogen, providing business executives, decision-makers, and academics with information on how to strengthen NL's position in international energy sustainability initiatives. The study also points out current research gaps and makes recommendations for how to proceed with creating NL's all-encompassing hydrogen plan to help the state reach net-zero emissions. An extensive case study on developing a hybrid power system using Homer Pro software for Nain, Newfoundland, and Labrador, is presented by Kotian and Ghahremanlou [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>]. It demonstrates how diesel, wind, and solar energy may be integrated, highlighting the value of renewable energy sources in enhancing the sustainability and dependability of power infrastructure in isolated areas. Dr. Jean-Paul Pinard and collaborators’ “Potential for Wind Energy in Nunavut Communities” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>] thoroughly evaluate the viability of wind energy in Nunavut. It maps out the potential for wind resources using information from Environment Canada and measurements from local airports, concentrating on the technical and financial viability of installing wind turbines. This study finds localities that show promise for wind energy projects. It does this by evaluating the economic and environmental effects of the projects using HOMER and RETScreen modeling.</p><p>New developments underscore the vital role dynamic system management and optimization strategies play in improving the resilience of hybrid energy systems for remote communities. HOMER software is an important tool for the analysis and optimization of renewable energy integration in the process of creating a full hybrid energy system for Makkovik Island. This work is placed in a wider context by the novel methodologies and conclusions from recent investigations. For example, the complexity of the balance between renewable energy integration and grid stability and HOMER's role in evaluating dynamic power management solutions for AC microgrids are highlighted in the study by Nagaraju et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>]. Similarly, Linda et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>] use HOMER for energy output simulations and stresses optimizing wind turbine designs for effective hydrogen generation. This study provides important information for Makkovik's renewable energy plan by highlighting the significance of choosing the ideal turbine heights to maximize hydrogen generation. HOMER's use in the research by Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>] provides additional evidence of the program's use in raising the power electronic components of hybrid systems' operational efficiency. This work offers a framework for improving DC-DC converters' dynamic performance, which is essential for guaranteeing the smooth integration of diverse energy sources. With the help of HOMER software and fuzzy logic, the study by Kamal et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>] present a unique framework for microgrid pre-installation assessments. This approach effectively improves the cost-effective and environmentally friendly energy supply for remote places.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Literature review summary</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1"><p>System</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p> Metric Parameter</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Reference</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Location</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Type</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wind</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>DG</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Battery</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fuel Cell</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Software Used</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m1iu0hvr44">
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">NPC</mml:mi>
  </mml:mrow>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>COE</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Iran</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hybrid System</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="me3cfdmir3">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m5h4bsj2pv">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mxceqeqvyl">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mje7yglnne">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Homer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m4hnh6ra6e">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mpxi0rdo2r">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>N/A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hybrid System</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mmpl9p8oum">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mfxpa2th08">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mbmywx7g7k">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m89qdtoh2n">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m9lxiowr9l">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mn92py5oot">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mr15qiqpg4">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mm52chio36">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>19</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Western Saudi Arabia</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hybrid System</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mjxza96dji">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mj4n6buwtz">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mo5ljni16p">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mgcm1uymkp">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mgvba9bm46">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Homer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mbunq4mczv">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mlxc9qurqy">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>24</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>N/A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hybrid System</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m7lz6h425n">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mhdpz7aiin">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mjrhw5zgod">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m9d2a1bpov">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m9ifd8ulwj">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Homer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mfrvpztxgw">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mewd4uw8w3">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>27</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Nain, NL</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hybrid System</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mvsq4oapiw">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mab9e8gd4l">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m1zhe0n9nz">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mks2h8mgkr">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mpmkuleew2">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Homer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="maa6w7d2mu">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mx7ehyvtng">
  <mml:mi>✓</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p> A summary of some of the studies conducted in several locations using different combinations of hybrid systems is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>. Although the development of hybrid systems has been the subject of several international case studies, there is a particular void in the literature about the design and implementation of such systems in Makkovik, Newfoundland, and Labrador. To close this gap, this study suggests creating a customized hybrid energy system for Makkovik that makes use of solar and wind energy in addition to battery storage options. With HOMER Pro, the design and analysis process are carried out to offer the area a cost-effective, efficient, and sustainable energy solution.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Methodology</title>
      <p>The research employed a methodical approach, starting with an in-depth review of existing literature. Subsequently, comprehensive data collection was conducted, which cleared the path for detailed simulations and analyses. The HOMER Pro program was utilized to do simulations to ascertain the hybrid systems' optimal design.</p><p>A variety of engineering programs were used in this study to model and construct a hybrid energy system. Based on extensive research from the website of the NL government and geographic data from Google Maps, the study concluded that the most practical possibilities for producing electricity in the area are solar and wind power. The selection of HOMER Pro was based on its strong capabilities for renewable energy resource optimization. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> below shows the flow chart for the project.</p><p>First, we defined Makkovik's geographical location and profile of energy use, integrating regional climate data to approximate actual circumstances. We next conducted a thorough evaluation of renewable resources, properly estimating the energy potential by incorporating precise solar irradiance and wind speed data from NASA into the model. Performance, affordability, and environmental compatibility were carefully considered while choosing components, which included backup diesel generators, solar PV, wind turbines, and battery storage. The HOMER Pro system setup then made it easier to simulate different configurations and optimize for dependability, sustainability, and cost-effectiveness. The proposed design's economic feasibility and environmental effects are extensively examined using an optimization process that is based on certain criteria, as outlined in our methodology. These criteria include NPC, LCOE, and the degree of renewable integration.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_2">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Flow chart of the research</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_RlDRBz6EHBjsgORx.png"/>
        </fig>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Data collection on load profiles and local resources</title>
      <p>In this section, the details of the Load Profile, Wind Energy potential, and Solar energy potential of Makkovik are explained in detail.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Electrical load profile of makkovik</title>
          
          <p>Modeling the load profile is crucial for determining the optimal size and selection of renewable energy sources. Since the Makkovik community's power usage was not publicly available, a load profile was developed by modifying the load profile of a comparable community whose data was available, accounting for the number of homes in each location. The analysis considered all pertinent characteristics of the system components and the precise location of the Makkovik installation; hence, the electricity usage profile shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> is a reasonable estimate. The average load consumption is found to be 5454.20 kWh/day, with a peak load of 563.03 kW.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Electric load profile</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_Kyn5wchd9lmjDfy7.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Makkovik’s wind energy potential</title>
          
          <p>The monthly wind speed values for the wind power source are shown graphically in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>, which was also obtained from NASA Surface Meteorology. The average annual wind speed is found to be 8.53 m/s.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Wind energy potential of Makkovik</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_HyJJeQ8jkQlxlR4E.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.3. Makkovik’s solar energy potential</title>
          
          <p>NASA Surface Meteorology provided solar radiation data for Makkovik. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> shows the monthly values for the clarity index. The average annual solar radiation at that site was determined to be 2.92 kWh/m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mpjsdhrir3">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>/day. According to the information, there was a notable increase in solar radiation from March to October, which produced enough energy to produce a sizable amount of electricity.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_5">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Solar energy potential of Makkovik</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_3rSqDl90xTpi4PHP.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. System design</title>
      <p>In this section, the schematic design of the system is provided along with the details of each selected component.</p><p>For the design and cost analysis of hybrid energy systems, HOMER Pro software is an excellent and well-known tool for precisely sizing these kinds of systems, and it has a large database with a variety of wind turbines and converters to make the selection process easier. A visual illustration of the interrelationship of the system's components is provided by HOMER Pro, as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>. An effective DC to AC power conversion is ensured by converters, as shown in this diagram that shows how wind turbines and diesel generators are integrated with the AC busbar. These datasets serve as the foundation for creating a hybrid energy system that is specifically suited to Makkovik's climate. The details of the components used in the system are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref>.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_2">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>HOMER fronius symo 20.0-3-M details</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>Quantity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="238"><p>Value</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>Name</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="238"><p>Fronius Symo 20.0-3-M Generic PV</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>Rated Capacity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="238"><p>20kW</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>Capital Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="238"><p>$3000,000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>Replacement Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="238"><p>$3000,000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>O&amp;amp;M</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="238"><p>$10/year</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>Manufacturer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="238"><p>Fronius</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>Lifetime</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="238"><p>25 years</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_3">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>HOMER Pro WES 30 [250kW] wind turbine details</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>Quantity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="181"><p>Value</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>Name</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="181"><p>WES 30 [250kW]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>Rated Capacity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="181"><p>250kW</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>Capital Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="181"><p>$550,000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>Replacement Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="181"><p>$500,000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>O&amp;amp;M</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="181"><p>$40,000/year</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>Manufacturer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="181"><p>Wind Energy Solutions</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>Lifetime</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="181"><p>20 years</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>Hub Height</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="181"><p>48</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_4">
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>HOMER Pro CAT-250kV diesel generator details</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Quantity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="180"><p>Value</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Name</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="180"><p>CAT-250kW-60Hz-PP</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Capacity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="180"><p>250kW</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Fuel</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="180"><p>Diesel</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Capital Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="180"><p>$28,000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Replacement Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="180"><p>$24,000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>O&amp;amp;M</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="180"><p>$20/op. hour</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Fuel Price</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="180"><p>$1.79/L</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Minimum Load Ratio</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="180"><p>25%</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_5">
          <label>Table 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>HOMER Pro Trojan SAGM 12 details</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Quantity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>Value</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Name</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>Trojan SAGM 12 205</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Nominal Voltage</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>12V</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Nominal Capacity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>2.63kWh</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>String Size</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>66</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Voltage</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>792</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Maximum Capacity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>219Ah</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Capital Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>$600</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Replacement Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>$500</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>O&amp;amp;M</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>$50/year</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="177"><p>Initial state of charge</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="157"><p>100%</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_6">
          <label>Table 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>HOMER Pro Eaton2000 details</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="141"><p>Quantity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>Value</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="141"><p>Name</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>Eaton Power Xpert 2000kW</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="141"><p>Capital Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>$6,000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="141"><p>Replacement Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>$4500</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="141"><p>O&amp;amp;M</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>$100/year</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="141"><p>Lifetime</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="191"><p>15 years</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Several fail-safes and contingencies are necessary to increase Makkovik's HRES's resilience against extreme weather occurrences. First, uninterrupted operation in inclement weather is ensured by the integration of sturdy wind turbines and solar panels that are made to survive harsh weather conditions like strong winds and heavy snowfall. An intelligent battery management system that can optimize charge and discharge cycles would also be beneficial to the system since it would lengthen battery life and improve performance during prolonged periods of low sunshine or wind. Adding redundant parts to the system, such as an auxiliary diesel generator and battery storage, can ensure energy delivery even if one component fails. Technologies for predictive maintenance and real-time monitoring, which may anticipate possible system breakdowns and enable preventive measures, are equally crucial. When combined, these steps would strengthen the system's robustness and dependability, protecting the community's energy supply from the unpredictable nature of severe weather occurrences.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_6">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Schematic of the proposed system using HOMER Pro</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_iXZqAWQMQd4tj2Qh.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.1. Pv panels</title>
          
          <p>PV panels are the cornerstone of the Makkovik hybrid energy system's electricity generation. The 1 kW capacity Fronius Symo 20.0-3-M with generic PV panels that were chosen to have a capital cost of \$3,000 per. It is expected that these panels will last for a significant 25 years. The replacement costs are estimated at \$3,000 per panel after considering lifecycle costs. This amount accounts for the cost of probable future market pricing as well as technological developments. With an estimated operation and maintenance (O&amp;amp;amp;M) of \$10/year, solar energy is economically viable and should be considered in Makkovik's long-term energy planning. Preventive maintenance activities, such as routine cleaning and inspections to reduce efficiency losses from environmental waste, are what define their O&amp;amp;amp;M expenses the most. Apart from that, a significant portion of the long-term maintenance cost is associated with the inverter, a crucial component that has to be replaced over the panel's lifespan.</p><p>Given their excellent efficiency and compatibility with the chilly, fluctuating light conditions characteristic of Makkovik's environment, Fronius Symo 20.0-3-M solar panels were chosen. Their sturdy construction guarantees resilience to severe weather, which enhances the system's dependability during its anticipated 25-year operating life.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.2. Wind turbine</title>
          
          <p>A WES 30 [250kW] wind turbine with a 20-year lifespan and a 48-meter hub height is used in the simulation. The initial capital cost of this turbine is \$550,000; replacement costs are \$500,000; and yearly maintenance costs are \$40,000. Wind turbines provide distinct maintenance difficulties, particularly because of their intricate mechanical design and exposure to inclement weather. Lubrication, tension adjustments, and blade integrity checks are examples of preventive maintenance. The total O&amp;amp;amp;M expenses of the turbines are impacted by the need for planned replacements due to the longevity of some mechanical elements.</p><p>The WES 30 [250kW] wind turbines were selected because of their capacity to function well in Makkovik's erratic wind patterns and chilly weather. With a 250-kW rated capacity, the WES 30 should be able to provide a sizable power output and help Makkovik meet its energy demands. Given Makkovik's wind profile, the turbine's capacity indicates that it is intended for medium to high wind speeds. Based on its selection, it appears to provide a good mix between initial investment and ongoing operating savings.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.3. Generator</title>
          
          <p>During instances when wind or solar power generation is limited, diesel generators are included as a backup to produce electricity. The model considers the impact of fuel prices on the best configuration for the system and includes one generator: a CAT-250 kW, 60 Hz-PP. To achieve economic viability, the financial factors of the CAT-250 kW generator are thoroughly addressed. Given the estimated lifecycle expenses of the generator, a replacement cost of \$24,000 has been set in addition to the initial capital cost of \$28,000. The estimated cost of operational maintenance is \$20 per operating hour, which impacts the hybrid system's overall optimization and adds to the overall cost of operation. To ensure operational preparedness, the generators need regular maintenance. This includes checking the engine, changing the oil, and replacing worn-out parts to keep the generator running when it's needed most. There is a 1.79 \$/L fuel price. Due to its fuel economy, dependability, and ease of maintenance, a CAT-250 kW diesel generator is used as a vital backup system. Enhancing the robustness of the system, this component guarantees a continuous power supply during periods of low wind and solar output.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.4. Battery</title>
          
          <p>In an HRES, batteries are a crucial component that acts as a buffer to improve grid stability. They attain this by storing surplus energy during times of high renewable production and supplying power at times of high demand or inadequate energy generation from renewable sources. An energy storage solution in the form of a Trojan SAGM 12 205 model has been chosen for the scenario under consideration. This given battery has a string size of 66 and a nominal voltage of 12 volts. It also has a capacity of 219 ampere-hours. Its initial state of charge, which is set at 100%, is anticipated to be fully charged at the outset. This setup comprises two to eighteen of these batteries in simulations. A battery replacement will cost \$500, but the initial outlay for each battery is set at \$600. For every battery, \$50 is set aside every year for maintenance costs. Monitoring system performance, making sure the atmosphere is ideal, and cleaning the terminal are all part of maintenance. Since batteries have a limited operational life, replacing them eventually will cost a substantial portion of the system's operating budget.</p><p>With its exceptional resilience to temperature changes and low maintenance requirements, the Trojan SAGM 12 205 battery is a perfect fit for Makkovik's variable renewable energy system. It also provides excellent energy storage efficiency. Its extended service life and capacity to recover from deep discharges are guaranteed by its deep-cycle application design, which increases the dependability of systems that rely on intermittent energy sources. Priority should be given to safety and environmental concerns, and AGM technology lowers the possibility of leaks. This battery is a wise solution to meet Makkovik's energy requirements due to its affordability and compatibility with renewable technologies.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.5. Converter</title>
          
          <p>In the Makkovik hybrid energy system design, a bidirectional converter, specifically the Eaton2000 model, is used. The power output of the converter is 1 kW. Its lifespan is fifteen years. The converter costs \$6,000 to purchase, \$4,500 to replace, and approximately \$100 in maintenance each year.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Results and discussion</title>
      <p> This section discusses the results of the HOMER Pro simulation for the proposed hybrid system. Based on 8698 solutions simulated by Homer Pro, the best one was chosen. </p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.1. Homer pro selected system</title>
          
          <p>With the help of Homer Pro, a large portfolio of possible hybrid system designs was created, outlining a variety of parts and important performance indicators like operational expenses, NPC, LCOE, and initial setup costs. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_7">Table 7</xref> provides us with the ideal system configuration based on the platform's insights into various configurations and their effects.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_7">
              <label>Table 7</label>
              <caption>
                <title>HOMER Pro selected system architecture</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >Component</th><th >Name</th><th >Size</th><th >Unit</th></tr><tr><td >Generator\#1</td><td >CAT-250kW-60Hz-PP</td><td >250</td><td >kW</td></tr><tr><td >PV</td><td >Fronius Symo 20.0-3-M</td><td >6.30</td><td >kW</td></tr><tr><td >PV Dedicated Converter</td><td >Fron20 Converter</td><td >20.0</td><td >kW</td></tr><tr><td >Storage</td><td >Trojan SAGM 12</td><td >9</td><td >strings</td></tr><tr><td >Wind Turbine</td><td >WES 30 [250kW]</td><td >1</td><td >Ea.</td></tr><tr><td >System Converter</td><td >Eaton Power Xpert 2000kW</td><td >209</td><td >kW</td></tr><tr><td >Dispatch Strategy</td><td >HOMER Cycle Charging</td><td ></td><td ></td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.2. Electrical summary</title>
          
          <p> The power system's yearly data is displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>, which indicates that there is a 75,726kWh excess energy generated, a 514kWh unmet electric load (i.e., demand not satisfied), and a 1,981kWh capacity shortage (i.e., the deficit in generation capacity).</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_7">
              <label>Figure 7</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Excess electricity, unmet electric load, and capacity storage of the system</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_-pAujPBF5yyUCAzF.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_8">Table 8</xref> shows the annual output for each component of the system. The highest power, about 55.8% of the total power, was generated by the wind turbines. The PV panels generated about 7,966 kWh annually, whereas the diesel generator produced 917,038 kWh/h. The overall energy generated was 2,090,604 kWh/year. The electrical analysis of the system in Homer Pro is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_8">
              <label>Table 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Annual production of each component</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >Component</th><th >Production (kWh/yr)</th><th >Percent</th></tr><tr><td >Fronius Symo 20.0-3-M with Generic PV</td><td >7,966</td><td >0.381</td></tr><tr><td >CAT-250kW-60Hz-PP</td><td >917,038</td><td >43.9</td></tr><tr><td >WES 30 [250kW]</td><td >1,165,600</td><td >55.8</td></tr><tr><td >Total</td><td >2,090,604</td><td >100</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p> The annual distribution of energy consumption within the system is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_9">Table 9</xref>, with the AC Primary Load accounting for all of the electrical demand at 1,990,269 kWh/year. This consumption pattern is significant, particularly because neither the DC Primary Load nor the DC Deferrable Load have any usage history. The AC Primary Load's dominance highlights its vital significance in the energy consumption of the system. These kinds of findings are critical for improving energy-saving initiatives and developing load management solutions. Additionally, the data forms the basis for determining how best to utilize excess electricity or address any capacity shortages that may be found, which eventually helps to support more strategic energy use planning that maximizes system performance and supports energy sustainability.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_9">
              <label>Table 9</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Annual consumption table</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >Component</th><th >Consumption (kWh/yr)</th><th >Percent</th></tr><tr><td >AC Primary Load</td><td >1,990,269</td><td >100</td></tr><tr><td >DC Primary Load</td><td >0</td><td >0</td></tr><tr><td >Deferrable Load</td><td >0</td><td >0</td></tr><tr><td >Total</td><td >1,990,269</td><td >100</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_8">
              <label>Figure 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Electrical analysis - HOMER Pro</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_0IMHui49-OCzzSWk.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.3. Fuel summary</title>
          
          <p>Important quantitative facts about fuel use over a given period are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_10">Table 10</xref>. 360 tons of diesel were used overall. The average daily consumption was found to be 0.986 tons, or roughly 0.0411 tons per hour. These numbers offer an insightful perspective on trends in fuel consumption. For a variety of research, planning, and operational tasks, these insights are essential in industries that depend on diesel-powered machinery and vehicles. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref> shows the graphical representation of the fuel summary.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_10">
              <label>Table 10</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Fuel summary</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >Quantity</th><th >Value</th><th >Units</th></tr><tr><td >Total Feedstock Consumed</td><td >360</td><td >tons</td></tr><tr><td >Avg Feedstock Per Day</td><td >0.986</td><td >tons/day</td></tr><tr><td >Avg Feedstock Per Hour</td><td >0.0411</td><td >tons/hour</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_9">
              <label>Figure 9</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Graphical representation of fuel summary</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_ue9RIRCJbm7Tl-KO.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.4. Cost summary</title>
          
          <p>The financial analysis included in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_11">Table 11</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_10">Figure 10</xref> outlines the NPC of capital, operational, and replacement expenses, and salvage values for every system component. The CAT-250kW-60Hz-PP component's total NPC of \$1.33M represented the overall cost incurred throughout the project. Interestingly, at \$925,050, the Trojan SAGM 12 205 was the largest single investment. The total NPC of the complete system was determined to be \$5.25 million. Most of the expenses were ascribed to the initial capital outlay and continuing operational costs, highlighting the financial aspects that are essential for evaluating the project's sustainability.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_11">
              <label>Table 11</label>
              <caption>
                <title> NPC of all the components</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="228"><p>Name</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="126"><p>Capital (<mml:math id="m0e9e47juo">
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>111</mml:mn>
</mml:math>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="134"><p>Replacement (<mml:math id="mgmr6d8yf2">
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>124</mml:mn>
</mml:math>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="131"><p>Resource (<mml:math id="mmzpq9gk85">
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>115</mml:mn>
</mml:math>)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="228"><p>CAT-250kW-60Hz-PP</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="126"><p>28,000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="111"><p>1.29M</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="134"><p>18,108</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="124"><p>-5,318</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="131"><p>0.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>1.33M</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="228"><p>Eaton Power Xpert 2000kW</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="126"><p>1.25M</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="111"><p>269,604</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="134"><p>398,171</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="124"><p>-74,940</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="131"><p>0.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>1.84M</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="228"><p>Fronius Symo 20.0-3-M with Generic PV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="126"><p>18,908</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="111"><p>814.78</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="134"><p>0.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="124"><p>0.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="131"><p>0.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>19,723</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="228"><p>Trojan SAGM 12 205</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="126"><p>356,400</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="111"><p>383,947</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="134"><p>239,244</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="124"><p>-54,541</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="131"><p>0.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>925,050</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="228"><p>WES 30 [250kW]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="126"><p>550,000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="111"><p>517,101</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="134"><p>159,404</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="124"><p>-89,834</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="131"><p>0.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>1.14M</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="228"><p>System</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="126"><p>2.20M</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="111"><p>2.46M</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="134"><p>814,927</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="124"><p>-224,633</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="131"><p>0.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>5.25M</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_10">
              <label>Figure 10</label>
              <caption>
                <title>NPC of all the components</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_XUDDab6DR8QiL9mA.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>A comparison of the basic and proposed energy systems' financial and environmental aspects is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_12">Table 12</xref>. The base system's NPC is \$3.36 million, which is less than the proposed system's \$5.25 million NPC. Also, the OPEX (Operation, fuel, and maintenance) costs of the proposed system are less than those of the base system. The suggested approach, however, shows a notable reduction in environmental impact, with fuel consumption falling from 797 liters a year to 360 liters annually and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m3j4xzzoyn">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CO</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> emissions falling from 144 kg/yr to 64.4 kg/yr. The suggested system has a higher Capital Expenditures (CAPEX) of \$325,800 as opposed to the base system.</p><p>According to the comparison of LCOE figures, diesel-based generation costs \$0.131 per kWh, whereas the suggested hybrid system costs \$0.204. There are several explanations for this disparity. First, compared to diesel generator installations, the initial capital expenditure for renewable energy infrastructure such as solar panels and wind turbines is often higher. In addition, even if fuel costs for renewable energy sources are low, the hybrid system's entire life cycle costs are greatly increased by regular battery replacements and continuous maintenance. Although the proposed system's LCOE is greater as opposed to the base system, the significant environmental benefits point to a potential trade-off that could be acceptable given the objectives of eco-friendly and sustainable energy generation.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_12">
              <label>Table 12</label>
              <caption>
                <title>NPC, CAPEX, OPEX, and LCOE of base system and proposed system</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th ></th><th >Base System</th><th >Proposed System</th></tr><tr><td >NPC</td><td >3.36M</td><td >5.25M</td></tr><tr><td >CAPEX</td><td >\$73,000</td><td >\$325,880</td></tr><tr><td >OPEX</td><td >\$254,286</td><td >\$253,880</td></tr><tr><td >LCOE (per kWh)</td><td >0.131</td><td >0.204</td></tr><tr><td ><mml:math id="mu557vdsu1">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CO</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> Emitted (kg/yr)</td><td >144</td><td >64.4</td></tr><tr><td >Fuel Consumption (L/yr)</td><td >797</td><td >360</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>The thorough cost assessment over a predicted lifespan of 20–25 years is the basis of the economic study of the suggested HRES for Makkovik. The choice of this duration was made to account for the 20–25-year average operating lifecycle of main system components, such as wind turbines and solar panels. Costs during this time were broken down into four categories: replacement costs, possible salvage values after the project, operations and maintenance (O&amp;amp;M) expenses, and initial capital expenditures (CAPEX). It is anticipated that throughout this time, market conditions and technological developments will have a substantial impact on the cost trajectory of renewable energy solutions. Historically, advances in materials science, manufacturing techniques, and economies of scale have caused a steady decrease in the cost of renewable energy components, most notably solar PV modules and wind turbines, as mentioned in studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>]. We foresee a continuation of this cost drop, making renewable energy more competitive with conventional energy sources, based on industry estimates and historical trends. It is anticipated that over the next ten years, the cost of wind turbines and solar PV will drop by 20–30%, significantly improving the financial sustainability of renewable energy projects. Additionally, advances in battery storage technology might lead to more affordable and efficient energy storage systems, which are essential for controlling the erratic nature of renewable energy sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>]. The estimated NPC and LCOE estimates are based on these predicted improvements in technology costs and performance, which are essential to the project's economic analysis. Our research offers a more precise and realistic financial picture for the installation of the HRES in Makkovik throughout its anticipated operational lifetime by taking these dynamic cost trends into account."</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.5. Emissions summary</title>
          
          <p>The hybrid system, integrating diesel with wind and solar, significantly cuts pollution emissions compared to the base diesel system, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_11">Figure 11</xref>. This eco-friendly approach to electricity generation notably reduces yearly emissions to 64.4 kg of <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m8zdeo56nk">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CO</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, 1.02 kg of CO, with no <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m33jcmxzfe">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">SO</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and 6.84 kg of NOx. Whereas, the base system was producing 144 kg of <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m9fuw2aggc">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CO</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, 1.02 kg of CO, with no <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mr4zp7oqno">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">SO</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and 15.1 kg of NOx. Despite diesel's involvement, its impact is lessened by renewable energy, enhancing efficiency and environmental health.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_11">
              <label>Figure 11</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Emission comparison between the base system and the proposed system</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/5/img_tG3729zsVN9sE0b_.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.6. Project feasibility</title>
          
          <p>The viability and appeal of renewable energy projects are significantly increased in NL by a variety of laws, incentives, and funding channels. The Net Metering Program stands out because it allows users to produce electricity from renewable sources like solar, wind, and hydro, balance their energy usage, and feed any excess energy back into the grid for credits. Through this effort, people and companies may adopt a more financially feasible strategy while also encouraging the growth of renewable technology.</p><p>The establishment of the Green Fund strengthens the province's dedication to sustainable energy alternatives. The fund, which is funded by the proceeds from carbon pricing, is devoted to climate change projects, such as renewable energy projects, that try to lower carbon emissions and promote green growth. For initiatives that make a substantial contribution to energy efficiency and environmental sustainability, this financial assistance mechanism is essential.</p><p>Numerous subsidies and incentives are offered at the provincial level to help offset the upfront expenses of installing renewable energy systems. These grants provide money for a variety of purposes, such as buying energy-saving equipment or helping with small-scale renewable energy projects and home solar installations, especially in rural and isolated locations.</p><p>Federal investment tax credits for clean energy, which support provincial programs and reduce the capital costs associated with such installations, provide substantial incentives for companies investing in conservation and renewable energy systems. To promote innovation and the introduction of fresh, useful technology for renewable energy projects, the province also actively funds and awards research and development in renewable energy technologies.</p><p>Notably, the province understands the benefits of working with Indigenous communities in the field of renewable energy. Indigenous-led initiatives are supported by special financial and policy frameworks, highlighting the significance of cooperative, culturally sensitive, and sustainable energy solutions.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.7. Monte carlo analysis</title>
          
          <p>A Monte Carlo analysis was used to take into consideration the uncertainty included in predicting the HRES's economic feasibility. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_13">Table 13</xref> is a representation of a Monte Carlo analysis of the project. We can observe how input variability affects the project's financial results thanks to this statistical method. 468 iterations of the simulation were run, illustrating various scenarios that might be impacted by variations in component costs and variations in solar and wind energy supplies.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_13">
              <label>Table 13</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Representation of Monte Carlo analysis</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="94"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>Cost/NPC (<mml:math id="mdu250545b">
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>161</mml:mn>
</mml:math>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>Cost/Operating cost (<mml:math id="m0r2kpa67p">
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>167</mml:mn>
</mml:math>)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="94"><p>AVG</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>6,064,342.67</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="161"><p>0.26</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>341,455.36</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="167"><p>1,650,173.00</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="94"><p>Median</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>4,762,673.50</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="161"><p>0.20</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>345,159.55</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="167"><p>733,000.00</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="94"><p>Percentile</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>10%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>3,124,176.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="161"><p>0.13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>235,670.70</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="167"><p>70,300.78</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="94"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>20%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>3,271,725.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="161"><p>0.14</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>236,543.70</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="167"><p>77,123.93</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="94"><p>MIN</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>3,119,704.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="161"><p>0.13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>216,280.70</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="167"><p>45,000.00</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="94"><p>MAX</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>26,291,110.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="161"><p>1.13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="175"><p>925,483.70</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="167"><p>14,557,620.00</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>NPC: The NPC is the total discounted value of all project costs throughout the project. The results showed a broad range of results, with an average NPC of \$6,064,342.67 and a median of \$4,762,673.50. According to the simulation, there is a 10% possibility that the NPC will be as low as \$3,124,176.00, which would be a good result in comparison to the average.</p><p>COE: The average cost per kilowatt-hour of energy generated by the system is reflected in the COE, which is a crucial indicator of economic viability. The simulation's average COE was \$0.26, with observed values ranging from a low of \$0.13/kWh to a maximum of \$1.13/kWh. This illustrates the possible unpredictability of energy generation costs resulting from undetermined factors.</p><p>Operating Costs: \$341,455.36 was the average yearly operating cost. This amount includes all recurring costs—maintenance, repair, and labor—needed to keep the energy system operating efficiently.</p><p>Initial Capital Investment: \$1,650,173.00 was the average initial capital investment determined by the simulation. This is an important number since it shows the upfront costs associated with implementing the system. There is a lot of uncertainty in the range between the lowest (\$45,000.00) and highest (\$14,557,620.00) estimates, which are mostly determined by market conditions and technological developments.</p><p>The results of the Monte Carlo analysis provide us with a probabilistic picture of the project's economic performance and clarify the possible financial hazards. The large variation between the lowest and greatest values highlights how sensitive the project is to different inputs and how crucial risk assessment and strategic planning are. The present research bolsters the viability of the suggested approach and underscores the necessity of integrating a sturdy risk management structure to alleviate the fiscal risks linked to the project's execution.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.8. Limitations</title>
          
          <p>Although HOMER Pro offers a strong foundation for technical modeling of hybrid energy systems, it has shortcomings, especially when it comes to modeling dynamic weather and component deterioration over time. Due to these constraints, cautious assumptions on system performance are required, and field data is crucial for fine-tuning and verifying model forecasts.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>7. Conclusions</title>
      <p>By combining state-of-the-art battery storage and conversion technologies with solar arrays, wind power, and conventional diesel generation, this study offers a revolutionary method of power generation in Makkovik, Newfoundland, and Labrador. Customized to meet Makkovik's unique energy needs, this hybrid system is an outstanding example of advancement in the effort for cleaner energy. In response to the increasing need for sustainable energy solutions, it reduces the community's historical reliance on diesel by utilizing the emission-free generation of solar and wind components. Homer Pro software has been used for the simulation and analysis of this hybrid system. Based on HOMER Pro models, our results show a significant reduction in diesel consumption, paving the way for Makkovik's shift to a more dependable and sustainable energy ecology. In particular, the design of our system dramatically lowers carbon dioxide emissions to 64.4 kg/yr from a baseline of 144 kg/yr, demonstrating our dedication to reducing the effects of climate change. Furthermore, the proposed system's LCOE is \$0.204 per kWh, which captures the system's environmental and economic efficiencies while representing all costs incurred over its lifetime. These important results support the feasibility of implementing renewable energy frameworks in isolated communities, supporting local energy security and autonomy while also being in line with global sustainability goals.</p><p> The proposition of integrating a HRES in Makkovik is more than a hypothetical exercise; it is a strong cry for a paradigm change in the way isolated, diesel-dependent towns throughout the world view their energy destiny. This research not only demonstrates that renewable energy solutions are feasible in these kinds of environments, but it also shows how Makkovik may evolve into a sustainable development model, providing a path forward for other cities to follow. The study highlights the need for sustainable energy solutions that balance environmental conservation and socioeconomic growth by highlighting Makkovik's possible transition. Makkovik hybrid system can serve as an example of how locally focused and community-driven methods of renewable energy may make a substantial contribution to the global sustainability goals by posing challenges to and eventually changing the current energy dependency. Hence, the proposed transformation of Makkovik transcends both its physical and communal boundaries, serving as a symbol of hope and creativity for isolated communities worldwide. The statement indicates that the use of renewable energy as the foundation for sustainable development is necessary to build resilient, self-sufficient, and environmentally peaceful societies, among the major problems of the twenty-first century.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>24</volume>
          <page-range>38-50</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gielen</surname>
              <given-names>Dolf</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boshell</surname>
              <given-names>Francisco</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saygin</surname>
              <given-names>Deger</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bazilian</surname>
              <given-names>Morgan D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagner</surname>
              <given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gorini</surname>
              <given-names>Rosaria</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.esr.2019.01.006</pub-id>
          <article-title>The role of renewable energy in the global energy transformation</article-title>
          <source>Energy Strategy Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>47</volume>
          <page-range>39429-39442</page-range>
          <issue>93</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wen</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valipour</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nojavan</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.IJHYDENE.2022.09.115</pub-id>
          <article-title>Risk-based performance of power-to-gas storage technology integrated with energy hub system regarding downside risk constrained approach</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>228</volume>
          <page-range>120519</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Opeyemi</surname>
              <given-names>Babatunde Mufutau</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.ENERGY.2021.120519</pub-id>
          <article-title>Path to sustainable energy consumption: The possibility of substituting renewable energy for non-renewable energy</article-title>
          <source>Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fenrg.2022.977925</pub-id>
          <article-title>A review on configuration optimization of hybrid energy system based on renewable energy</article-title>
          <source>Front. Energy Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>264</volume>
          <page-range>126287</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stringer</surname>
              <given-names>Tyler</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joanis</surname>
              <given-names>Marcel</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.ENERGY.2022.126287</pub-id>
          <article-title>Decarbonizing Canada's remote microgrids</article-title>
          <source>Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>316-326</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vurur</surname>
              <given-names>N. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/JCGIRM090202</pub-id>
          <article-title>The nexus between urbanization, renewable energy, financial development, and economic growth: Evidence from Turkey</article-title>
          <source>J. Corp. Gov. Insur. Risk Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>1125-1135</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Al Hasibi</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haris</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/CE/ZKAD053</pub-id>
          <article-title>An analysis of the implementation of a hybrid renewable-energy system in a building by considering the reduction in electricity price subsidies and the reliability of the grid</article-title>
          <source>Clean Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>814-821</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>K. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chohan</surname>
              <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khalilpoor</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Issakhov</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chattopadhyaya</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dwivedi</surname>
              <given-names>S. P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ijlct/ctab012</pub-id>
          <article-title>Economic evaluation of a hybrid renewable energy system (HRES) using hybrid optimization model for electric renewable (HOMER) software—A case study of rural India</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Low-Carbon Technologies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Renewable energy and empowering Indigenous communities</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.sydney.edu.au/sydney-environment-institute/news/2021/12/16/renewable-energy-and-empowering-indigenous-communities.html</source>
          <year>2021</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>How indigenous communities are building energy sovereignty</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.yesmagazine.org/environment/2021/08/18/indigenous-communities-energy-sovereignty</source>
          <year>2021</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>People powered: Championing indigenous values in the clean energy transition</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.energy.gov/articles/people-powered-championing-indigenous-values-clean-energy-transition</source>
          <year>2022</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Profile table, census profile, 2021 census of population -- Makkovik, town (t) [census subdivision], Newfoundland and Labrador</article-title>
          <source>, https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2021/dp-pd/prof/details/page.cfm?Lang=E&amp;DGUIDlist=2021A00051011020&amp;GENDERlist=1,2,3&amp;STATISTIClist=1,4&amp;HEADERlist=0</source>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Profile of Makkovik, Labrador, Nunatsiavut</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.makkovik.ca/home/profile.htm</source>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Design and analysis of a hybrid power system for St. Brendan's, NL</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/375661634_DESIGN_AND_ANALYSIS_OF_A_HYBRID_POWER_SYSTEM_FOR_ST_BRENDAN'S_NL</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <page-range>535--540</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kandil</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aly</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akl</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iqba</surname>
              <given-names>M. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/IEMCON56893.2022.9946598</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design and analysis of hybrid power system for Grey River, NL</article-title>
          <source>2022 IEEE 13th Annual Information Technology, Electronics and Mobile Communication Conference (IEMCON), Vancouver, BC, Canada</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <page-range>589-595</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kotian</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maliat</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azeez</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iqbal</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/IEMCON56893.2022.9946552</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design and simulation of a hybrid energy system for Ramea Island, Newfoundland</article-title>
          <source>2022 IEEE 13th Annual Information Technology, Electronics and Mobile Communication Conference (IEMCON), Vancouver, BC, Canada,</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2591</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Issa</surname>
              <given-names>M. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Hamadani</surname>
              <given-names>A. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kasim</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/5.0119461</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design, analysis and optimal sizing of hybrid power system using HOMER simulator for different renewable energy sources: Al-Muthana case study</article-title>
          <source>AIP Conf. Proc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>72</volume>
          <page-range>108525</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ameur</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berrada</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Emrani</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.EST.2023.108525</pub-id>
          <article-title>Intelligent energy management system for smart home with grid-connected hybrid photovoltaic/ gravity energy storage system</article-title>
          <source>J. Energy Storage</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>100040</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>See</surname>
              <given-names>A. M. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mehranzamir</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rezania</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rahimi</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Afrouzi</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hassan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.RSET.2022.100040</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic analysis of an off-grid hybrid system for a remote island in Malaysia: Malawali Island, Sabah</article-title>
          <source>Renewable and Sustainable Energy Transition</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>262</volume>
          <page-range>121250</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jahangir</surname>
              <given-names>M. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shahsavari</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vaziri Rad</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.121250</pub-id>
          <article-title>Feasibility study of a zero emission PV/Wind turbine/Wave energy converter hybrid system for stand-alone power supply: A case study</article-title>
          <source>J. Clean Prod.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>100226</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Worighi</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maach</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hafid</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hegazy</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Mierlo</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.segan.2019.100226</pub-id>
          <article-title>Integrating renewable energy in smart grid system: Architecture, virtualization and analysis</article-title>
          <source>Sustainable Energy, Grids and Networks</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>1476</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stewart</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasan</surname>
              <given-names>S. M. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmad</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liaf</surname>
              <given-names>A. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mustayen</surname>
              <given-names>A. G. M. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasan</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howlader</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hassan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alam</surname>
              <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/EN17061476</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic performance and sensitivity analysis of an off-grid renewable energy-based hybrid system: A case study of Kuakata, Bangladesh</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>426</volume>
          <page-range>139072</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmadi</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hosseinzadeh-Bandbafha</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le</surname>
              <given-names>Q. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tran</surname>
              <given-names>T. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ikhwanuddin</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lam</surname>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Truong</surname>
              <given-names>P. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peng</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quan</surname>
              <given-names>N. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aghbashlo</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tabatabaei</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.JCLEPRO.2023.139072</pub-id>
          <article-title>A multi-approach framework for developing feasible, viable, and sustainable hybrid energy systems in remote areas: The case of Con Dao island in Vietnam</article-title>
          <source>J. Clean Prod.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>47</volume>
          <page-range>30050-30061</page-range>
          <issue>70</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cruz-Soto</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azkona-Bedia</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Velazquez-Limon</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Romero-Castanon</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.IJHYDENE.2022.03.026</pub-id>
          <article-title>A techno-economic study for a hydrogen storage system in a microgrid located in baja California, Mexico. Levelized cost of energy for power to gas to power scenarios</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Hydrogen Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>12800</page-range>
          <issue>17</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ghadirinejad</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ottermo</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nowzari</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alsaadi</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghadiri Nejad</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/SU151712800</pub-id>
          <article-title>Optimizing a green and sustainable off-grid energy-system design: A real case</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>2969</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>T. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Villalva</surname>
              <given-names>M. G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/EN13112969</pub-id>
          <article-title>Technical evaluation of a PV-diesel hybrid system with energy storage: Case study in the Tapajós-Arapiuns extractive reserve, Amazon, Brazil</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>61</volume>
          <page-range>5183-5202</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seedahmed</surname>
              <given-names>M. M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramli</surname>
              <given-names>M. A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bouchekara</surname>
              <given-names>H. R. E. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shahriar</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Milyani</surname>
              <given-names>A. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rawa</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.AEJ.2021.10.041</pub-id>
          <article-title>A techno-economic analysis of a hybrid energy system for the electrification of a remote cluster in western Saudi Arabia</article-title>
          <source>Alexandria Eng. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>284</volume>
          <page-range>129264</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miao</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kharrazi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.ENERGY.2023.129264</pub-id>
          <article-title>Multi-criteria decision analysis for the planning of island microgrid system: A case study of Yongxing island, China</article-title>
          <source>Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>48</volume>
          <page-range>30282-30298</page-range>
          <issue>78</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beyene</surname>
              <given-names>Y. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Worku</surname>
              <given-names>G. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tjernberg</surname>
              <given-names>L. B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.IJHYDENE.2023.04.192</pub-id>
          <article-title>On the design and optimization of distributed energy resources for sustainable grid-integrated microgrid in Ethiopia</article-title>
          <source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>1868</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Katsivelakis</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bargiotas</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daskalopulu</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panapakidis</surname>
              <given-names>I. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsoukalas</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/EN14071868</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic analysis of a stand-alone hybrid system: Application in Donoussa island, Greece</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>200</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bhatti</surname>
              <given-names>M. Z. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siddique</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aslam</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Atiq</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/EN17010200</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design and analysis of a hybrid stand-alone microgrid</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mansur</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hybrid electrical system optimization of remote island using HOMER</article-title>
          <source>INTEK: J. Penelitian</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>1</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Farahmand</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghahremanlou</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sakthi</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jafari</surname>
              <given-names>M. R. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5539/jsd.v17n2p1</pub-id>
          <article-title>A comprehensive systematic overview of Canadian hydrogen supply chains downstream</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>1</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sakthi</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghahremanlou</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lardi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5539/jsd.v17n1p1</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sustainable hydrogen production, storage, and distribution – A systematic review for Newfoundland and Labrador</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>1-5</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kotian</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghahremanlou</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24018/ejece.2024.8.1.598</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design for hybrid power system in Newfoundland and Labrador: A case study for Nain</article-title>
          <source>Eur. J. Electr. Eng. Comput. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Potential for wind energy in Nunavut communities</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.qec.nu.ca/sites/default/files/potential_for_wind_energy_in_nunavut_communities_2016_report_0.pdf</source>
          <year>2016</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>1-12</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nagaraju</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/JISC020101</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design and implementation of hybrid controller for dynamic power management in a DC Microgrid</article-title>
          <source>J. Intell. Syst. Control</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>123-131</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Linda</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Agarwal</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sinha</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/JISC020301</pub-id>
          <article-title>Computational fluid dynamics analysis of vertical axis wind turbine heights for enhanced hydrogen production in urban environments</article-title>
          <source>J. Intell. Syst. Control</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>143-152</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kan</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/JISC020303</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enhanced tracking of DC-DC buck converter systems using reduced-order extended state observer-based model predictive control</article-title>
          <source>J. Intell. Syst. Control</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>53</volume>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kamal</surname>
              <given-names>M. Mustafa</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asharaf</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandez</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.SETA.2022.102581</pub-id>
          <article-title>Optimal renewable integrated rural energy planning for sustainable energy development</article-title>
          <source>Sustain. Energy Technol. Assess.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>6621</page-range>
          <issue>18</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>AlHammadi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Saif</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Sumaiti</surname>
              <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marzband</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alsumaiti</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heydarian-Forushani</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/EN15186621</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic analysis of hybrid renewable energy systems designed for electric vehicle charging: A case study from the United Arab Emirates</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>70</volume>
          <page-range>1-38</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manas</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reddy</surname>
              <given-names>K. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srivastava</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/S44147-023-00290-w</pub-id>
          <article-title>A critical review on techno-economic analysis of hybrid renewable energy resources-based microgrids</article-title>
          <source>J. Eng. Appl. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>642</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agajie</surname>
              <given-names>T. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fopah-Lele</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amoussou</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Velasco</surname>
              <given-names>C. L. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanyi</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en16020642</pub-id>
          <article-title>A comprehensive review on techno-economic analysis and optimal sizing of hybrid renewable energy sources with energy storage systems</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>