<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJCMEM</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Computational Methods and Experimental Measurements</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Int. J. Comput. Methods Exp. Meas.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IJCMEM</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2046-0554</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2046-0546</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-34O_5SVFUNncAVDBfspN1hThJuK0DxrB</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/ijcmem130311</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>2D-CFD Simulation of a Syngas Burner with Experimental Validation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-3332-9985</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Trupia</surname>
            <given-names>Gabriele</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>gabrieletrupia99@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9707-4193</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Puglia</surname>
            <given-names>Marco</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>marco.puglia@unimore.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4947-3082</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Berni</surname>
            <given-names>Fabio</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>fabio.berni@unimore.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3303-4229</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Fontanesi</surname>
            <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>stefano.fontanesi@unimore.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1,2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4993-3541</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Pedrazzi</surname>
            <given-names>Simone</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>simone.pedrazzi@unimore.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1,2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9243-3369</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Tartarini</surname>
            <given-names>Paolo</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>paolo.tartarini@unimore.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Engineering “Enzo Ferrari”, University of Modena and Reggio Emilia, 41125 Modena, Italy</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">InterMech-MO.RE, University of Modena and Reggio Emilia, 41125 Modena, Italy</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>612</fpage>
      <lpage>621</lpage>
      <page-range>612-621</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>09</day>
          <month>08</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Biomass-derived syngas is a promising alternative to fossil fuels for various applications, including internal combustion engines for electricity generation and direct combustion for thermal energy. However, numerical modeling of syngas burners is still scarcely addressed in literature compared to more common fuels, posing challenges for the design of high-efficiency combustors with low pollutant emissions. This study presents a two-dimensional computational fluid dynamics (CFD) simulation of a syngas burner, validated against experimental data. The syngas adopted in the combustion tests is produced using a small-scale gasifier prototype fueled by wood pellets. At first, the syngas is premixed with air, then it moves in a cylindrical burner where the key parameters are monitored, including syngas and air volume flow rates, temperature, and syngas composition. Additionally, an emission analyzer is used to measure O$_2$, CO, NO, and NO$_2$, concentrations in the exhaust gases. Given the axial symmetry of the problem, a two-dimensional model is developed to save the computational effort. The simulation results are compared to the experimental measurements including burner temperature and emissions. Despite the simplicity and the reduced effort compared to high-fidelity simulations, the 2D model proves to be able to properly predict both temperature inside the burner and emissions at the exhaust. Therefore, it turns out to be a valuable tool to guide the design of syngas burners.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Biomass</kwd>
        <kwd>CFD</kwd>
        <kwd>Combustion</kwd>
        <kwd>Emissions</kwd>
        <kwd>Syngas</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="6"/>
        <fig-count count="9"/>
        <table-count count="5"/>
        <ref-count count="21"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Small-scale gasification systems are gaining more and more interest in the scientific community [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], due to the possibility to exploit residual biomasses in rural areas in which there is abundance of such resources. Through small-scale gasification systems, it is possible to obtain a fuel gas from solid biomass that can be used for electrical and thermal energy generation. Gasification is a thermochemical process that occurs under sub-stoichiometric (oxygen-limited) conditions, enabling the conversion of carbonaceous materials into a mixture of valuable products such as fuel gases or chemical intermediates for further synthesis. Considering an average composition, syngas is made of combustible gases (40%), such as CO, CH<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myse0m8ow3">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and H<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m419c1xf3z">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and non-combustible gases (60%) like N<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mk0t4pfw53">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and CO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mbc5od89o7">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]. Among the biomass-to-electricity conversion technologies, gasification is considered the most efficient, offering higher energy conversion efficiency and significantly lower pollutant emissions, particularly nitrogen oxides (NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="msxlt5r6s9">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>) and sulfur oxides (SO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mk46hywefb">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>), compared to conventional direct combustion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>].</p><p>Focusing on the production of thermal energy by syngas, premixed combustion is a promising mode as fuel and oxidizer are perfectly mixed before entering the burner combustion chamber. This favors the mitigation of emissions such as NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="muc6osmw9g">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and unburnt hydrocarbons. However, turbulent premixed combustion modelling in gas burners is not free of difficulties. It is necessary to consider aspects such as radiative heat transfer, turbulence-flame interaction, emission modelling and exact mixture composition, as they can lead to misleading predictions of gas temperature and emissions in the burnt gases. For instance, Bidi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>] studied the effects of radiative models on numerical simulations of methane-air premixed combustion, concluding that the results with radiation model are in much better agreement with the measurements and the effect of radiation can influence both temperature and emissions. As for the turbulence-flame interaction, Halouane and Dehbi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>] studied premixed hydrogen combustion using two different closure models, namely Eddy Dissipation Concept (EDC) and Turbulent Flame Closure (TFC). Thanks to validation against experimental data, both models proves to be able to reasonably well predict combustion for all the cases studied in the paper. However, the authors show that higher accuracy comes only at the expense higher computational cost. Regarding the emissions modelling, detailed-chemistry-based approaches are more and more diffused in order to obtain accurate estimations. In this kind of studies, detailed chemistry can be solved both online and offline. In the former case, during the CFD simulation, each cell is considered as a reactor where chemical kinetics is solved to provide source terms to the scalar transport equations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. In the latter case, chemistry is tabulated (and, then, tables are exploited in the CFD simulation) or it is solved a posteriori in reactors, such as in references [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. These studies use methane as fuel and conduct transient numerical simulations combined with the use of idealized reactors to decouple NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mjo6qxxvo3">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> prediction from CFD modeling. Such decoupled approach is found to predict reasonably well NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mnk8ypfgw7">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> emissions. Finally, literature demonstrates the importance of the gas composition. Uncertainties can lead to inaccuracies of the simulation results, especially in terms of emissions. For instance, Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>] investigated the effect that some additional reactants have on the emissions of a syngas combustor. In fact, it is likely to have impurities in the syngas as a consequence of the formation process from biomass. The results clearly indicate that, for example, the presence of ammonia in the syngas composition can significantly change the NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mnylckxl6r">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> level in the combustion process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>].</p><p>Compared to the existing literature, this study develops a two-dimensional, steady-state combustion model able to properly predict emissions and temperature profile in a syngas burner thanks to detailed modeling of turbulence-flame interaction, radiative heat transfer, gas composition and emissions formation via detailed chemistry.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Materials and methods</title>
      <p>In this section, both the experimental and the numerical setups are presented.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Experimental setup</title>
          
          <p>Gasification experiments are conducted using a laboratory-scale prototype named the “Femto Gasifier” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>), designed and constructed at the University of Modena and Reggio Emilia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>]. The system is developed to enable preliminary testing of various biomass feedstocks. It features an Imbert-type downdraft reactor and it is optimized for tests requiring limited quantities of biomass. The gasifier is operated under positive pressure conditions, with the air blower placed upstream of the reactor. A dedicated sampling port enables the collection and analysis of syngas. The tests are conducted outdoors. Wood pellets are adopted as feedstock and the produced syngas is subsequently combusted in a flare (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Femto Gasifier during a test</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_QHKc7Ft5bWpcrHLH.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Flare equipped with thermocouples</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_FJweoYWo2AzelsfK.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Two devices are employed for the cleaning of the syngas produced by the gasifier. The first, located immediately downstream of the reactor, is a cyclone separator, used to remove the majority of particulate matter from the syngas stream. The second is a filter equipped with a nylon net cartridge. It is important to note that no system is specifically included for the removal of ammonia (NH<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mo018iieyg">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>). Therefore, traces of this compound are expected to be present in the syngas, as it is commonly found in gases derived from lignocellulosic biomass [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]. </p><p>In order to evaluate the results of the test, several instruments are used. In particular, the volume flow rates of air and syngas are measured using two volumetric flow meters. </p><p>Gas samples are analyzed using a Pollution MicroGC GCX micro gas chromatograph, to obtain the gas composition. The instrument is calibrated for the main non-condensable gas species including H<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mmbztjngs9">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, O<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m8jujliitd">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, N<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mnmjrh9fht">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, CO, CO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m1pwgehyrc">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and CH<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mfv1j9x7qk">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. </p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>, the flare is shown. It is possible to notice 11 Type-K thermocouples used to estimate the temperature profile along the axis of the burner. Most of the thermocouples are placed in the initial portion of the combustion chamber, to accurately capture the temperature variations associated with the initial flame development.</p><p>In addition, emissions are measured at the burner outlet. The analysis is carried out using the “Testo Model 350” analyzer. This is a portable analyzer equipped with a probe that allows for the sampling of the exhaust gas, which are then analyzed using integrated sensors.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Numerical setup</title>
          
          <p>This section focuses on the presentation of the 2D-CFD model, whose geometry is visible in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>. One the most critical aspects of the model is represented by the boundary conditions, especially those at the inlet. In fact, in order to speed up the combustion simulations, the 2D domain starts just before the combustion chamber. Therefore, mixing simulation is not considered. Moreover, it would not be possible to simulate mixing in a 2D framework, as the experimental apparatus is such that the disposition of syngas and air pipes is not axisymmetric. Therefore, it is necessary to simulate the mixing process separately in a 3D framework, so that level of mixing before the combustion chamber as well as flow field can be estimated to generate boundary conditions for the 2D domain. </p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>2D geometrical domain</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_HWHqZos9itLbU2T4.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>In the light of this, also a 3D-CFD model is developed. The geometry includes a vertical pipe (where mixing occurs) receiving syngas and air from two lateral smaller pipes. On the top, the geometrical domain ends after the combustion chamber starts. Therefore, it includes also part of the 2D domain. In particular, the outlet is placed just after the small steel grid located at the combustion chamber inlet and used to enhance flame stabilization. A section of the grid is visible in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>. The geometry is discretized through a trimmer mesh with characteristic size of 1 mm. In order to consider the presence of the grid, a local refinement with characteristic size reduced to 0.125 mm is operated. Lastly, for a proper simulation of the gradients close to the walls, 6 prism layers are used, to guarantee a “Low-Reynolds” approach. The total number of cells is roughly 3 M. In terms of physics, the number of models is limited, as the problem consists only in a steady-state cold flow simulation. A multi-component gas is considered. Turbulence is modelled by the Realizable k-<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="msqcz3b801">
    <mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> model. Regarding the boundary types, the two inlet sections of air and syngas are “Mass Flow Inlet” boundaries, while the outlet section is a “Pressure Outlet”. For the two inlets, mass fractions are specified, according to the compositions of air and syngas. Both boundary and initial conditions are derived from the experiments.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>2D mesh</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_gBM2wyte9H9gE6IB.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Once the numerical setup of the 3D model is clarified, the attention can be focused on the 2D framework. It is important to point out that both 2D and 3D models are built within STAR-CCM+ 2210 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], licensed by SIEMENS DISW. As visible in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>, the 2D-CFD model includes pressure reducer, steel grid and the entire combustion chamber. First of all, the adoption of a 2D approach is possible thanks to the geometry of the domain. De facto, it roughly coincides with the portion of flare visible in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>, thus it is evidently axisymmetric.</p><p>To discretize the 2D domain, a characteristic size of 0.5 mm is used, while two prism layers are applied near the walls. To account for the presence of the steel grid, a local mesh refinement is performed, similarly to the 3D case, with a reduced size of 0.125 mm. The total number of cells obtained using these parameters is roughly 200 k, leading to a great advantage compared to a 3D approach. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>, a portion of the resulting mesh is shown. In particular, the refinement in correspondence of the grid is shown.</p>
          <p>Compared to the 3D model, the physical setup is similar. The flow is still a multi-component ideal gas, with turbulence modeled by the Realizable k-<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7h0mjd7n1">
    <mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. The main difference is related to the presence of combustion in the 2D framework, which has to be considered. The approach here adopted for combustion modeling is based on Complex Chemistry (CC, also known as detailed chemistry) and Eddy Dissipation Closure (EDC) models (CC+EDC). The CC model is suitable for introducing detailed chemical information into CFD simulations. The adopted chemical reaction scheme is the GRI-Mech 2.11 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>], which includes 49 species and 279 reactions. To evaluate the effect of turbulence on combustion, the Complex Chemistry model is coupled with a turbulence–chemistry interaction model. In this work, the Eddy Dissipation Concept model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>] is adopted to account for the interaction between chemical kinetics and turbulent flow.</p><p>Radiation models are included to consider the effect of radiative heat transfer. The inclusion of radiation significantly improves the accuracy of the numerical temperature profiles. In this study, the Participating Media Radiation model is used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>]. Then, the combination of Gray Thermal Radiation model and Weighted Sum of Gray Gases Method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>] is exploited for the calculation of the absorption coefficient $k<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m2pp8zuoce">
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>–</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>\kappa<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mto2pts8kg">
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>\alpha$. The relationship between these two quantities is described by the Bouguer-Lambert law, expressed by Eq. (1).</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <mml:math id="m5jhudzybz">
                <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                <mml:msup>
                  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msup>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p> where, the parameter s is called Optical Path Length (OPL).</p><p>Interestingly, in order to improve the agreement between numerical and experimental outcomes, both EDC and WSGG models undergo calibration. The EDC model accounts for the effect of turbulence on combustion by modifying the source term in the chemical species transport equations. In particular, the source term is multiplied by a scalar function $f$ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>] including two empirical constants: the “fine structure length constant” Cl and the “fine structure time constant”. At the end of the calibration process, it is found that the optimal value of Cl is 1.3, while the default value is 2.1377. In particular, reducing Cl slows down the production/consumption rates of the scalars, resulting in increased unburned species at the exhaust.</p><p>Moving to the calibration of the WSGG model, in this case the parameter of interest is OPL. The value can range from the size of a single cell to the size of the entire domain, depending on the optical depth of the region where combustion occurs. Reducing OPL results in a decrease of the temperature profile values. This adjustment enables the solver to better capture the thermal radiation absorption process by the gas-phase molecules. In this case, the optimal value of OPL resulting from the calibration process is 12.5 mm. </p><p>Compared to the 3D model which is set to adiabatic (as no reaction occurs in the mixing region), in the 2D framework the convective heat transfer is considered. Hence, the walls are characterized by a pair of heat transfer coefficient and reference temperature to mimic convection with the external ambient and the thickness of the flare is considered by means of a thermal resistance. </p><p>Regarding the inlet boundary, it is a “Velocity Inlet”. The boundary conditions in terms of velocity, turbulent kinetic energy, turbulent dissipation rate and temperature are derived from the 3D model. In particular, the profiles are obtained by averaging in the azimuthal direction the relevant quantities over a horizontal section plane corresponding to the inlet of the 2D model. </p><p>Lastly, the inlet mass fractions refer to the air-syngas mixture. As it will be shown in the results, the 3D simulation reveals a very effective mixing between air and syngas. Therefore, a homogeneous mixture is imposed at the velocity inlet. </p><p>The outlet section is defined as a “Pressure Outlet”, where ambient pressure is imposed as the outlet discharges into the environment.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>3. Results</title>
      <p>In this section the results of the experiments are shown at first. Then, the numerical results are presented, from both 3D and 2D models.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Experimental results</title>
          
          <p>The results obtained from gasification and subsequent combustion test are in terms of syngas composition, volume flow rate, emissions and temperature profile.</p><p>The operating point analyzed in this study is identified as a stable working condition of the burner. </p><p>The experimentally measured volume flow rates of air and syngas are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Volume flow rates of air and syngas</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mortq9f1cz">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math><sub> </sub>[L/s]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m4yslw1c3j">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math><sub> </sub>[L/s]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.93</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.626</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>To evaluate the syngas composition, samples are analyzed. However, it is interesting to note that, due to the adopted gas analyzer, it is not possible to evaluate the presence of ammonia. This component is usually present in syngas from woody biomass and it strongly affects NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myc3ubzmg3">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> emissions. In order to consider the presence of ammonia for the simulations, a concentration of NH3 is added to the gas composition given by the chromatograph. The adopted NH3 concentration relies on typical values found in literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]. The mass fractions of the different components, without addition of ammonia, are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>, while the results considering NH3 are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Syngas mass fractions without NH$_3$</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>H<sub>2</sub></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>N<sub>2</sub></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CH<sub>4</sub></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CO<sub>2</sub></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.008</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.5157</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0155</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1663</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2945</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Syngas mass fractions with NH$_3$</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>H<sub>2</sub></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>N<sub>2</sub></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CH<sub>4</sub></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CO<sub>2</sub></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NH<sub>3</sub></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.008</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.5153</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0155</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1664</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2945</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0002</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_4">
              <label>Table 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Thermocouple measurements</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >Thermocouples</th><th >Temperature [K]</th><th >Standard Deviation [K]</th></tr><tr><td >TC1</td><td >1292</td><td >± 14</td></tr><tr><td >TC2</td><td >1137</td><td >± 8</td></tr><tr><td >TC3</td><td >1069</td><td >± 19</td></tr><tr><td >TC4</td><td >1100</td><td >± 11</td></tr><tr><td >TC5</td><td >1038</td><td >± 7</td></tr><tr><td >TC6</td><td >1001</td><td >± 10</td></tr><tr><td >TC7</td><td >964</td><td >± 7</td></tr><tr><td >TC8</td><td >882</td><td >± 18</td></tr><tr><td >TC9</td><td >856</td><td >± 6</td></tr><tr><td >TC10</td><td >842</td><td >± 5</td></tr><tr><td >TC11</td><td >725</td><td >± 10</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>Another result comes from the combustion test, which provides the temperature profile along the axis of the flare. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>, it is possible to see the temperatures resulting from the measurements, each one presented with its standard deviation.</p><p>The last result is related to the emissions measured at the burner outlet. Similarly to temperature, measurements are performed once the burner reaches a steady-state condition. Exhaust gases are sampled, for the analysis, by a copper tube that allows to place the probe at the flare outlet. The results are reported, in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref>, in ppm for CO and NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mmy99us5o4">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and volume fraction for CO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mh631b1dom">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and O<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mhna54yjvx">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Each result is reported along with the standard deviation.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_5">
              <label>Table 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Measurement of emissions</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PPM NO<mml:math id="mugnmdze37">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PPM CO</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>%CO<mml:math id="m02ei8pg6q">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>%O<mml:math id="mfk6fkkmmm">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>181 ± 4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>51.3 ± 3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>16.6 ± 0.2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.9 ± 0.2</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Numerical results</title>
          
          <p>Since the main goal of the 3D model is to evaluate the mixing of air and syngas, the 3D results presented in the following focus on this aspect. In this regard, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref> show mass fractions of CH<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m2h39q4ycm">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and N<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mcuukzlbq7">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> on a horizontal section plane corresponding to the inlet of the 2D domain. It is possible to evaluate the mixing by means of the mass fraction homogeneity of the most relevant components. </p>
          
            <fig id="fig_5">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Mass fraction of CH$_4$</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_sywYZj_U5_yKVms7.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_6">
              <label>Figure 6</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Mass fraction of N$_2$</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_Nkfr6allCHAmyR9q.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The results show minimal (not to say negligible) variation of the concentrations of the scalars on the section plane. This indicates that the mixing obtained in the system is effective. So, on the one hand, it is possible to adopt a two-dimensional axisymmetric model for the combustion analysis. On the other hand, for the 2D simulations, it is reasonable to introduce in the computational domain a perfectly premixed mixture. </p><p>Moving to the combustion results of the 2D model, they are proposed in terms of temperature profile along the burner axis and emissions at the outlet. In the following, the results of different cases will be presented. “Base” case does not include ammonia in the composition of the syngas and both EDC and radiative heat transfer models are not adopted. In particular, neglecting EDC means that turbulence-flame interaction is neglected. The second case is referred to as “EDC”, since the EDC model is introduced (with Cl already calibrated). “EDC+Rad” case includes EDC and radiative models (both properly calibrated, thus also OPL is set to the optimal value). Lastly, “NH3” case represents the final model, namely the one characterized by the best setup, in which also the presence of ammonia in the initial composition of the syngas is considered. </p><p>In order to evaluate the temperature profile in the simulation, probes are inserted in the model in correspondence of the flare axis, where the thermocouples are placed. As for the emissions, since they are experimentally measured in a precise point of the domain, a single probe point is used to evaluate the ppm of CO and NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mb189g0ybd">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and the volume fractions of O<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mbaw2m92re">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and CO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mk45rfskmk">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. </p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>, it is possible to see the temperature profiles obtained in the different cases, while <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref> summarize the results relative to the emissions at the burner outlet. Starting from the temperature profiles, it is possible to notice that an acceptable agreement is obtained only introducing radiation in the model. As for the emissions, all the investigated setups are able to return correct concentrations of O<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mjtuhwxte3">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and CO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mcbvw3vc3d">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> at the exhaust. The main differences among the cases deal with CO and NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mjotodjtxt">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Only introducing the EDC (i.e. considering the turbulence-flame interaction) it is possible to improve the CO prediction. Finally, the concentration of ammonia has to be necessarily introduced in the gas composition, otherwise there is no way to obtain a concentration of NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mijbaat3h8">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> at the exhaust that is close to the experimental counterpart. </p>
          
            <fig id="fig_7">
              <label>Figure 7</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Temperature profile: Experimental vs numerical</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_9AzJTYlJ_OWuLHKb.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_8">
              <label>Figure 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>CO abd NO$_x$ emissions: Experimental vs numerical</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_nKFbmHjOtJWM7p_x.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_9">
              <label>Figure 9</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Numerical-experimental comparison O$_2$ and CO$_2$ emissions</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_CjHeErGQABjLZb_i.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>4. Conclusions</title>
      <p>In this work, a 2D-CFD model for the simulation of combustion in a syngas burner is developed. It includes accurate modeling of turbulence-flame interaction, radiative heat transfer, gas composition and emissions formation via detailed chemistry. The model is validated against experimental data in terms of temperature and emissions. Overall, a good agreement is obtained between CFD and experimental outcomes in terms of both gas temperature and main emissions, namely CO and NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="me0qn2sfyu">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Minor discrepancies can be noticed for the temperature estimation and they can be ascribed to the radiation model, which requires further calibration.</p><p>On the experimental side, future developments will include the implementation of an adequate gas cleaning system to remove ammonia from the produced syngas. Once ammonia is effectively removed, NO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mj0paqaakk">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> emissions can be significantly reduced, as confirmed by numerical results. On the numerical side, the modelling approach will be refined by further tuning of the radiation and other combustion models will be tested to improve the predictive capabilities of the numerical framework.</p><p>As shown in the study, the 2D-CFD numerical model demonstrates good accuracy in predicting both temperature and emissions, while maintaining a low computational cost. Therefore, it can be a very effective tool for the design of high efficiency burners. In turn, this is crucial to properly exploit the syngas potential as energy source, for the sustainable development of rural areas where biomass is readily available. </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This work was supported by “Fondo di Ateneo per la Ricerca 2024 per il finanziamento di Piani di sviluppo dipartimentale nell’ambito della ricerca (E93C24000500005) (FARD 2024/2025), Department of Engineering Enzo Ferrari, University of Modena and Reggio Emilia”.</p>
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>117</volume>
          <page-range>109486</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Situmorang</surname>
              <given-names>Y. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoshida</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abudula</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guan</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2019.109486</pub-id>
          <article-title>Small-scale biomass gasification systems for power generation (&lt; 200 kW class): A review</article-title>
          <source>Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>31620-31631</page-range>
          <issue>35</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raheem</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bao</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsomega.3c03050</pub-id>
          <article-title>Syngas production from biomass gasification: Influences of feedstock properties, reactor type, and reaction parameters</article-title>
          <source>ACS Omega</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>49</volume>
          <page-range>3634-3647</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bidi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hosseini</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nobari</surname>
              <given-names>M. R. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enconman.2008.07.010</pub-id>
          <article-title>Numerical analysis of methane–air combustion considering radiation effect</article-title>
          <source>Energy Convers. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>42</volume>
          <page-range>21990-22004</page-range>
          <issue>34</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Halouane</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dehbi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhydene.2017.07.075</pub-id>
          <article-title>CFD simulations of premixed hydrogen combustion using the Eddy Dissipation and the Turbulent Flame Closure models</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Hydrogen Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>263</volume>
          <page-range>125332</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sfriso</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berni</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fontanesi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paltrinieri</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mortellaro</surname>
              <given-names>F. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rossi</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Medda</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applthermaleng.2024.125332</pub-id>
          <article-title>A numerical framework for 3D Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) simulations of gasoline-fuelled burners to be adopted in catalyst preheating of vehicle exhaust systems</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Therm. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>25</volume>
          <page-range>1871-1878</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jin</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12206-011-0425-9</pub-id>
          <article-title>A simulation for prediction of nitrogen oxide emissions in lean premixed combustor</article-title>
          <source>J. Mech. Sci. Technol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>31</volume>
          <page-range>4933-4942</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>T. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jung</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12206-017-0942-2</pub-id>
          <article-title>CFD-CRN validation study for NO$_{\mathrm{x}}$ emission prediction in lean premixed gas turbine combustor</article-title>
          <source>J. Mech. Sci. Technol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>33</volume>
          <page-range>5051-5060</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>T. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jung</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12206-019-0944-3</pub-id>
          <article-title>A numerical study on NO<sub>x</sub> formation behavior in a lean-premixed gas turbine combustor using CFD-CRN method</article-title>
          <source>J. Mech. Sci. Technol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>102</volume>
          <page-range>318-328</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lei</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shao</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiao</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applthermaleng.2016.03.026</pub-id>
          <article-title>Experimental and numerical studies of pressure effects on syngas combustor emissions</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Therm. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>82</volume>
          <page-range>30-38</page-range>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shao</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lei</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiao</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applthermaleng.2015.02.057</pub-id>
          <article-title>Experimental and numerical studies of pressure effects on syngas combustor liner temperature</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Therm. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>37</volume>
          <page-range>6933-6941</page-range>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2012</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Joo</surname>
              <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwon</surname>
              <given-names>O. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhydene.2012.01.059</pub-id>
          <article-title>Effects of ammonia substitution on combustion stability limits and NO<sub>x</sub> emissions of premixed hydrogen–air flames</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Hydrogen Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>57</volume>
          <page-range>103224</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Puglia</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morselli</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ottani</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pedrazzi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tartarini</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allesina</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seta.2023.103224</pub-id>
          <article-title>A preliminary evaluation of different residual biomass potential for energy conversion in a micro-scale downdraft gasifier</article-title>
          <source>Sustain. Energy Technol. Assess.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>52</volume>
          <page-range>54-84</page-range>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Woolcock</surname>
              <given-names>P. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biombioe.2013.02.036</pub-id>
          <article-title>A review of cleaning technologies for biomass-derived syngas</article-title>
          <source>Biomass Bioenergy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Siemens Digital Industries Software</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Simcenter STAR-CCM + 2210 released! What's new?</article-title>
          <year>2022</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Frenklach</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldenberg</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bowman</surname>
              <given-names>C. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanson</surname>
              <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davidson</surname>
              <given-names>D. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>et al.</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>GRI-MECH: An optimized detailed chemical reaction mechanism for methane combustion</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>719-729</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>1977</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Magnussen</surname>
              <given-names>B. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hjertager</surname>
              <given-names>B. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0082-0784(77)80366-4</pub-id>
          <article-title>On mathematical modeling of turbulent combustion with special emphasis on soot formation and combustion</article-title>
          <source>Symp. (Int.) Combust.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>1383-1393</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>1979</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Magnussen</surname>
              <given-names>B. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hjertager</surname>
              <given-names>B. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Olsen</surname>
              <given-names>J. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhaduri</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0082-0784(79)80130-7</pub-id>
          <article-title>Effects of turbulent structure and local concentrations on soot formation and combustion in C$_2$H$_2$ diffusion flames</article-title>
          <source>Symp. (Int.) Combust.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <year>1981</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Magnussen</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2514/6.1981-42</pub-id>
          <article-title>On the structure of turbulence and a generalized eddy dissipation concept for chemical reaction in turbulent flow</article-title>
          <source>19th Aerospace Sciences Meeting, St. Louis, USA</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>161</volume>
          <page-range>2435-2445</page-range>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bordbar</surname>
              <given-names>M. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wecel</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hyppänen</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.combustflame.2014.03.013</pub-id>
          <article-title>A line by line based weighted sum of gray gases model for inhomogeneous CO₂-H₂O mixture in oxy-fired combustion</article-title>
          <source>Combust. Flame</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>158</volume>
          <page-range>893-901</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johansson</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leckner</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andersson</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnsson</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.combustflame.2011.02.001</pub-id>
          <article-title>Account for variations in the H₂O to CO₂ molar ratio when modelling gaseous radiative heat transfer with the weighted-sum-of-grey-gases model</article-title>
          <source>Combust. Flame</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>113</volume>
          <page-range>650-656</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>1991</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Modest</surname>
              <given-names>M. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1115/1.2910614</pub-id>
          <article-title>The weighted-sum-of-gray-gases model for arbitrary solution methods in radiative transfer</article-title>
          <source>J. Heat Transf.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>