<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JISC</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Intelligent Systems and Control</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Intell Syst. Control</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JISC</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2957-9813</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2957-9805</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-2Bpc1F1pMNjx6Rn10QKf3Fi2usTgKn6M</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jisc020101</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Design and Implementation of Hybrid Controller for Dynamic Power Management in a DC Microgrid</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8707-0615</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Nagaraju</surname>
            <given-names>Sharmila</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>sharmila.n.89@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1669-4513</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
            <given-names>Nataraj Kanathur</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>director.research@dbit.co.in</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2109-0231</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
            <given-names>Rekha Kanathur</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>rekha.sjbit@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Electrical and Electronics Engineering, JSS Science and Technology University, 570006 Mysuru, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Department of Electronics and Communication Engineering, Don Bosco Institute of Technology, 560074 Bengaluru, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">Department of Electronics and Communication Engineering, SJB Institute of Technology, 560060 Bengaluru, India</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>03</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>12</lpage>
      <page-range>1-12</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>01</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2023 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Nowadays more and more devices and appliances are operated with electricity, thus the electrical crisis is increasing exponentially day by day. In order to avoid the occurrence of electricity crisis, various power generation resources are used at the utility side to enhance the power generation to meet the consumers’ demand for electricity. Hence, a suitable control scheme has to be implemented at the microgrid to reduce the electrical fluctuation, power loss and manage the power quality. The Adaptive Proportional Integral Voltage Controller (APIVC) and hysteresis current controller (HCC) are integrated to enhance the quality of power generated. The electrical fluctuation is reduced by the proposed efficient hybrid parallel source controller model for DC Microgrid. The proposed model exerts decentralized control, which is an advanced droop control where communication is not required. The outer voltage control loop and inner current control loop provide faster control to maintain the grid voltage constant. The grid voltage is set as the reference value and the actual value is sensed to generate error value, which sets the reference value of current. The error signal is processed to provide switching signals for the converters. The performance analysis and simulation results show that the proposed mechanism performed better than the conventional methods such as Hysteresis Band Current Controller (HBCC) with Pulse Width Modulation (PWM) and Proportional Integral Voltage Controller (PIVC) with Hysteresis Current Controller (HCC), in terms of the electrical fluctuation, power loss and manage the power quality in the microgrid.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Proportional integral voltage controller (PIVC)</kwd>
        <kwd>Hysteresis current controller (HCC)</kwd>
        <kwd>DC microgrid</kwd>
        <kwd>Distributed energy sources (DES)</kwd>
        <kwd>Hysteresis Band Current Controller (HBCC)</kwd>
        <kwd>Pulse Width Modulation (PWM)</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="3"/>
        <fig-count count="11"/>
        <table-count count="2"/>
        <ref-count count="52"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>The Microgrid (MG) forms a localized electrical network, which consists of interconnected loads, communication systems, and distributed energy sources (DES). This grid can be standalone or in the network. The efficiency and reliability of the system increase with the grid connection of the microgrid. In rural electrification system, the standalone microgrid has many advantages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>]. At present, as the performance of electronic equipment increases, the integration of micro-sources and DC loads can be achieved better in microgrid design. The system is also more efficient in transmitting DC power in the absence of skin effect and reactive power [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>].</p><p>The microgrids use the static power converter between the loads and micro sources as the power interface. These converters’ output voltage is important for the microgrid for various purposes. The voltage of the converter is controlled with two methods: i) Proportional integral voltage controller (PIVC); ii) Hysteresis current controller (HCC).</p><p>The first method increases the system reliability without the need of communication and in the second method among the converters proper communication is required [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>].</p><p>In terms of PIVC technique, the output voltage of the converter is determined with the help of each source connected. The proposed method improves the voltage controller and comparative analysis of PI and HCC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. In literature, it is understood that linear controllers are less robust against the disturbance, therefore a non-linear controller is considered for better performance and regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>].</p><p>The main purpose of this research is to reduce electrical fluctuation, power loss, and manage the power quality. The proposed method efficiently integrates the two models such as an adaptive proportional integral voltage controller (APIVC) and hysteresis current controller (HCC).</p><p>This paper consists of the following sections: Section 1 Introduction; Section 2 Methodology of Proposed Work; Section 3 Mathematical Model for the Proposed Work; Section 4 Description of the Working Principle of Hybrid Parallel Source Controller Model for DC Grid; Section 5 Modeling and Simulation and Conclusion. Here, to make the system faster and to increase the steady state performance of a PIVC-based integrator, Hysteresis Mode Controller is adopted. A microgrid is modelled in the MATLAB/Simulink environment with three resistive load and solar sources. The DC Microgrid general block diagram is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> and corresponding simulated results in terms of average power and DC grid voltage are reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>].</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>DC microgrid general block diagram</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_9Df2MTNysPCokiv0.jpeg"/>
        </fig>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Methodology</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Double loop control using pi controller</title>
          
          <p>The PI controller is a classical controller which has been widely used in the control of microgrid. It finds application in many process control industries due to its robust performance. The DC offset gets removed by the integral action in the PI algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. The PI controller has slower time response which reduces the maximum overshoot and improves the damping and causes zero offset values. The major limitation of this controller is the increase in rise time. In the microgrid, the error signal is obtained by subtracting the measured voltage from the desired voltage. The PI controller can regulate the frequency at AC bus of the microgrid and causes very few oscillations when the load fluctuates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>]. For a PI controller, the standard Eq. used to denote the output signal is given in Eq. (1):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <mml:math id="m776upyc6v">
                <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                </mml:mfrac>
                <mml:msubsup>
                  <mml:mo>∫</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                </mml:msubsup>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Double loop control scheme using PI controller</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_glo5t6KOfxd9joL4.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>where, y(t) is the desired output fed into the system or processed as the modulated input; K is the controller gain and τ is the integral time constant of the controller. The PID controller is a linear controller and has low current Ripple with improved steady-state purpose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>]. A sinusoidal waveform with better quality can be obtained using a PID controller. It possesses good dynamics and high overload rejection. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> shows the PI control implemented in PWM Voltage Source Inverters (VSI). A Proportional resonant (PR) controller can be used to replace the conventional PID controllers in many systems. The PR controllers can achieve better performance in rejection of disturbance and sinusoidal reference tracking [16, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>]. Compared to the conventional PI controller, this controller has better performance in terms of disturbance rejection capability and controller’s inability to track sinusoidal reference with zero steady state error [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]. A PR controller can be implemented through discretizing pre-Tustin transformation to attain robustness in power flow [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]. The parameters of the PR controller can be adjusted through performing frequency response analysis to obtain desired performance of the controller. The frequency response analysis helps in altering the parameters of the controller to improve the overall performance. The LQR is basically a proportional controller, to which an integral action can be added to cancel the steady state error [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>]. The gain scheduling control algorithm will allow this controller to extend its application from small signal to large signal operation. LQ resonator (LQR) behaves like a proportional controller and causes a reduction in the static errors. The LQR includes improved voltage regulation, balanced load sharing and secured data in the system. However, the external noise that penetrates into the system cannot be avoided by this controller. If Kalman filter is used along with this system it can minimize the variance of the estimation error by taking into consideration the white noise (zero mean Gaussian random noise) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>]. If linear system has to be controlled, all of its states are calculated and has the criterion as a quadratic function of the states and control signal, then a linear quadratic (LQ) control system has to be designed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>].</p><p>The Hysteresis Mode Controller (SMC) is considered as a robust controller and exhibits better stability. The controller has changeable modes with switching criterion to toggle between on-off commands. The robustness and fast convergence properties of the Hysteresis mode control make it an attractive alternative for applications like unmanned aerial vehicles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]. However, there exists the chattering phenomenon when the controller traces a reference control variable. The phenomenon of chattering no doubt causes physical damage to different parts in the system and requires increased energy for a better efficiency in performance. The states decide the hysteresis variable and the hysteresis surface represents the relationship among the state variables. It is a tedious task to design a hysteresis mode control to offer suitable transient and steady state performance. It is an extremely challenging task to design a hysteresis mode control to offer suitable transient and steady state performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>]. If a suitable feed forward controller is connected to the hysteresis mode control, zero tracking speed will improve along with the improvement of performance of non-overshoot transients. An adaptive SMC has been used by the authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>] to improve the efficiency of the grid connected photo voltaic array with three level neutral point clamp inverter.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.1.1 Hysteresis current controller</title>
              
              <p>The hysteresis controller is simple in design and implementation, which has fast response. This controller incorporates feedback current control method. The comparator compares the actual current value with the desired current value within a hysteresis band. The subtraction of the instantaneous values of reference currents from the actual source currents in the respective phases gives the error in current values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]. Hysteresis controller is a simple nonlinear controller with no complex control circuitry involved for the current control. In this controller’s action, a VSI makes the grid current to follow a reference pattern. The error generated by the controller produces the switching waves, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>:</p>
              <p>A hysteresis band with the minimum width is maintained in order to minimize the error. The authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>] described a double band hysteresis current controller that monitors and controls the active power and reactive power flow from RES to the utility grid along with a voltage source inverter. In this work, in order to have efficient performance of the controller, three modes of operation have been discussed depending on availability of RES.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_3">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Hysteresis current controller</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_meB0-SpJu7N9svhW.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Paralleled sources control</title>
          
          <p>The arranging of converters in parallel structure has more advantages compared to one single high-power converter. The PIVC and HCC are the two different methods to control paralleled energy sources used in a microgrid.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.2.1 Proposed proportional integral voltage controller</title>
              
              <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> shows the voltage controller scheme to control parallel connected energy sources used in a microgrid. The output voltage of the converter reduces automatically when the current supplied raises and the controller exhibits an impedance behavior. This PIVC provides sharing proper current between converters connected in parallel. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> shows the voltage controller of the dc-dc converter. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>, we can find out <italic>P<sub>ref</sub></italic> as given in Eq. (2).</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(2)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mcusiio4mv">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mtext>ref </mml:mtext>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mtext>ref </mml:mtext>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mfrac>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mfrac>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, <italic>P<sub>ref</sub> </italic>is described as power reference of DC-DC converter,<italic> V<sub>ref</sub></italic> is identified as voltage reference, and H(s) represents cut-off frequency of low pass filter, S is described as input source, and V<italic><sub>dc</sub></italic> is described as converter output voltage. From Eq. (3), we can find required current reference for each converter, where V<italic><sub>s</sub></italic> is the DC source voltage.</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(3)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mmtzm2zep6">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              
                <fig id="fig_5">
                  <label>Figure 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Voltage controller of the dc-dc converter</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_onohHgq7b9Nspo9K.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.2.2 Adaptive master slave control</title>
              
              <p>In the adaptive master slave control method, one converter acts as Adaptive master and others are acts as slaves. The master block provides the reference current to converts of slaves and grid DC voltage is controlled by the master block. Therefore, it needs fast communicating network to make the system less reliable and higher cost than normal voltage controller method.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_4">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Voltage control scheme- DC-DC converter using parallel source controller</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_97zEeXjp-u6Qe9eO.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Design of an efficient hybrid parallel source controller model for dc microgrid</title>
          
          <p>In the regulation curve, the voltage controller characteristic has negative slope. However, the higher the slope, it provides the poor voltage regulations and better current sharing accuracy. Hence, always there is tradeoff between these parameters in the design process. In the present work, controller PI is used to control the microgrid’s parallel-connected converters.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.3.1 Proposed adaptive controller design</title>
              
              <p>The APIV controller forward path transfer function is provided in Eq. (4), where controller integral time constant is denoted as <italic>T<sub>i</sub></italic> and the proportional gain is denoted as <italic>k<sub>p</sub></italic>. In this case the effect of controller proportional gain is the same as the series of connected resistance to the dc source.</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(4)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mn65w6zost">
                    <mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mfrac>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msub>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mfrac>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>Hence, the gain <span style="font-family: Cambria Math, serif">𝑘<sub><span style="font-family: Cambria Math, serif">𝑝</sub> can be represented as Eq. (5).</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(5)</label>
                  <mml:math id="ml4l633mfu">
                    <mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, the converter number is represented by subscript<span style="font-family: 等线"> <italic><span style="font-family: 等线">i</italic><span style="font-family: 等线">. The Eq. (6) can be simplified as follows by considering the rated power of the source with 0dB gain.</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(6)</label>
                  <mml:math id="m0db3ho3h5">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mtext>rated </mml:mtext>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:msubsup>
                        <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, rated power nominal droop rate is represented as <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mirorhi16d">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mo6mgneph2">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is a controller resistance which is found through assigning <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mwzp4ufle2">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mtext>rated </mml:mtext>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="ma36d2k77u">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="ma13w83y5c">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> for each converter. There is the need of steeper controller characteristic for better sharing of load, bit it provides poor voltage regulation. Hence it requires optimum value of <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m5ekyuueja">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> which is given in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]. The authors in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>] described the time constant <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mrd0typi8y">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> of PI which is given in Eq. (7). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> shows the proposed method’s parameters for the efficient voltage controller.</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(7)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mrtlpap7eq">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>APIV controller parameters</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Parameter</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Value</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mj4hbo8cwi">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  </mml:msub>
  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12.73</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="ms499cl638">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.5</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Design of hysteresis mode controller</title>
          
          <p>The voltage controller scheme based on the Hysteresis Mode Control is discussed. Between each solar source and grid, a boost converter is connected as a power interface. The Eq. (8) represents the state space of boost converter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>].</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(8)</label>
              <mml:math id="m328q7m5jo">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mtable columnalign="left" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
                    <mml:mtr>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mtd>
                    </mml:mtr>
                    <mml:mtr>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mtd>
                    </mml:mtr>
                  </mml:mtable>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mtable columnalign="center center" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
                    <mml:mtr>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                      </mml:mtd>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mfrac>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                            </mml:msub>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mfrac>
                      </mml:mtd>
                    </mml:mtr>
                    <mml:mtr>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:mfrac>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                            </mml:msub>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msub>
                        </mml:mfrac>
                      </mml:mtd>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mfrac>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                            </mml:msub>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mfrac>
                      </mml:mtd>
                    </mml:mtr>
                  </mml:mtable>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mtable columnalign="left" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
                    <mml:mtr>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mtd>
                    </mml:mtr>
                    <mml:mtr>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mtd>
                    </mml:mtr>
                  </mml:mtable>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mtable columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
                    <mml:mtr>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:mfrac>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mfrac>
                      </mml:mtd>
                    </mml:mtr>
                    <mml:mtr>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                      </mml:mtd>
                    </mml:mtr>
                  </mml:mtable>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>In Eq. (8), <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m6i5oh03jp">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> represents the duty cycle, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m8cahy1azx">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mai24hsqvv">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the inductor current and converter output voltage, and the load resistance is denoted by <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mul90gkv09">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> shows the parameters consider during converter process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>].</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Converter parameters</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Parameter</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Range</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mzihdhc3s8">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>$7 \Omega (700 \mathrm{~W})<mml:math id="mbvxdegolt">
  <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:math>L<mml:math id="m21c2bql89">
  <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:math>1 \mathrm{mH}<mml:math id="m4qjaruucm">
  <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:math>O_C<mml:math id="mpm048l45a">
  <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:math>6 m F$</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>The inductor current and DC microgrid voltage is controlled simultaneously, for each converter the hysteresis surface is given in Eq. (9), and the law of control of proposed adaptive PI Controller is given in Eq. (10) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">44</xref>].</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(9)</label>
              <mml:math id="mflz61v86m">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(10)</label>
              <mml:math id="mqfhjoyq5b">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mtext>ref </mml:mtext>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mtext>ref </mml:mtext>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                  <mml:mspace width="1em"/>
                </mml:mstyle>
                <mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                  <mml:mspace width="1em"/>
                </mml:mstyle>
                <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m87tlebpqy">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> represents the Adoptive PI controller circuit parameter, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myuefvwjnf">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is described as the efficiency of APIVC. The law of control is given in Eq. (11) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">47</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">48</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>].</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(11)</label>
              <mml:math id="myfbizsqs1">
                <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mtable columnalign="left" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
                    <mml:mtr>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mtd>
                    </mml:mtr>
                    <mml:mtr>
                      <mml:mtd>
                        <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                        <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mtd>
                    </mml:mtr>
                  </mml:mtable>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>The existing and reaching conditions is satisfied by taking into account the above law of control as given in Eq. 12 and Eq. (13) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">50</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_52">52</xref>].</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(12)</label>
              <mml:math id="msemicv9a0">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                <mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                  <mml:mspace width="1em"/>
                </mml:mstyle>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>and</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(13)</label>
              <mml:math id="m9tkr4n52z">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                <mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                  <mml:mspace width="1em"/>
                </mml:mstyle>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>From the derivative of (6), the gain <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mihs3llkjd">
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mfrac>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mfrac>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> can be found out as given in Eq. (14) and Eq. (15). The results are described by Eq. (16):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(14)</label>
              <mml:math id="mu3alapa7i">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
                <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(15)</label>
              <mml:math id="m2nuwkm4nd">
                <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(16)</label>
              <mml:math id="mpj703ogh2">
                <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                </mml:mfrac>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>Over a wide range of operation to guarantee stability, the Hysteresis mode coefficient is found as given in Eq. (17):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(17)</label>
              <mml:math id="men1cqx8u7">
                <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                </mml:mfrac>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>min</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>min</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>The value of k is determined by replacing the converter parameters used in the <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> and mathematical condition as shown in Eq. (18).</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(18)</label>
              <mml:math id="mp9tr7e6rk">
                <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mfrac>
                <mml:mn>4.56</mml:mn>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>To obtain the robust and fast response against the system disturbances, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mq51004wz2">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0.6</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="miq9yirnwa">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>11</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> were chosen for the hysteresis coefficients. Also, stability of the system is improved as compared to normal voltage controller.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Modelling and simulation</title>
      <p>At present, three solar modules were connected in parallel. The boost converter is connected to each source hence it produces constant output voltage irrespective of the variations in solar input. The bus voltage used for simulation was 60V. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref> shows the proposed voltage controller diagram. The produced reference current of voltage controller feeds to the hysteresis controller. The hysteresis controller output is in duty ratio required for the boost converter. A hysteresis band of ±2A is used. During the first time of study for each DC sources, 24 V ideal sources were used and power rating of each source is 600W. In the designing of Proposed Adaptive Proportional Integral Voltage Controller, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mnt48znxav">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0.285</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Ὡ is used. The parameters of PI are determined by considering <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mvlminqpjp">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>π</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mecp2b1u91">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>∂</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref> show the comparison analysis between the proposed and conventional methods with respect to the bus voltage and average power respectively, with the grid voltage of steady state value being 57.5V and 0.3s time is taken by the converter to find its final value. During the analysis of the renewable sources shared average power of the grid, the final value is 182W and the time is 0.3 s.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_6">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Simulink block diagram of proposed voltage controller</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_1BzEHazBqWeqkZON.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>In the second time of study, the same load and sources are used for the simulation. But, APVC output is connected to the SM controller. Also reference voltage is determined using PI controller for the VDC in normal voltage controller technique.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_7">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison analysis between proposed model and conventional methods with respect to the bus voltage at grid voltage 57.5V</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_nGX9NaQGAUhowsbZ.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_8">
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison analysis between proposed model and conventional methods with respect to average power supplied by sources at grid voltage 57.5V</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_tQ7dKcPlNtQXxhPV.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>The bus voltage and average power sharing among each source for proposed controller and conventional controllers is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_10">Figure 10</xref>. The grid voltage of 58.5 V forms steady state value. As compared to the SM, more regulated output voltage is produced as compared to PI controller. In producing the voltage regulation, the integral component is playing an important role in the voltage controller. The time of settling the output voltage of SM controller is 0.15 s. The response of SM controller is much faster than the PI controller. The sources average power shared is around 190W, which is also better as compared to 182W in Voltage Controller. However, the integrator used in the voltage controller may cause the increase of overshoot in the system. The stable system is also not stable in varying load conditions with constant value of controller resistance. Therefore, to have system stable in varying load conditions an adaptive Hysteresis Mode controller is suggested in future work. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_11">Figure 11</xref> shows various parameters comparison like bus voltage fluctuation and average power for the proposed and conventional methods for two different grid voltage.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_9">
          <label>Figure 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison analysis between proposed model and conventional methods with respect to the bus voltage at grid voltage of 58.5V</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_nu9UMimQAaCmwYkp.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_10">
          <label>Figure 10</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison analysis between proposed model and conventional methods with respect to average power supplied by sources at grid voltage 58.5V</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_hNdwdSrYoiZ9wlgS.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_11">
          <label>Figure 11</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The various parameters comparison like bus voltage fluctuation, average power for the proposed and conventional methods for two different grid voltages</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_qqgOO4ExGBI6obIj.png"/>
        </fig>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Conclusion</title>
      <p>In this paper, a hybrid controller for dynamic power management of a DC Microgrid has been implemented. Multiple energy resources are connected to DC bus via boost converters. The proposed system is compared with conventional system on a DC microgrid fed by multiple renewable energy sources. The DC bus voltage reference is taken as 60V. The grid voltage of the conventional controller maintained at 56.2V and the grid voltage of the proposed controller scheme maintained at 57.8V, which shows better voltage regulation of the DC microgrid by the proposed controller. The settling time of the output voltage by the conventional controller is 0.32s and the proposed controller is 0.15s. This shows the proposed controller has a quick response and reduced settling time, increasing margin of stability. The system is capable of handling different renewable energy sources at the utility side and also avoids fluctuation in electricity and also minimizes power loss at consumer side.</p><p>Future Scope: The system can be improvised by adding other available energy resources. The system can be made smart by the implementation of IoT and energy consumption data can be made available to consumers.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors would like to thank JSS Science and Technology University, Mysuru, Don Bosco Institution of Technology, Bengaluru, JSS Academy of Technical Education, Bengaluru, Visvesvaraya Technological University (VTU), Belagavi, Vision Group on Science and Technology (VGST), and Karnataka Fund for Infrastructure Strengthening in Science &amp; Technology Level –2 (JSSATEB) for all their support to the research and publication of this paper.</p>
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Strajnikov</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuperman</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>DC-Link Capacitance Reduction in PFC Rectifiers Employing PI+Notch Voltage Controllers</article-title>
          <source>in IEEE Transactions on Power Electronics</source>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>977-986</page-range>
          <fpage>977</fpage>
          <lpage>986</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/TPEL.2022.3201096</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Habibullah</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mithulananthan</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Islam</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Islam</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Modelling and experimental assessment of high-frequency oscillation in DC microgrid, In 2022 IEEE Global Conference on Computing</source>
          <publisher-name>Power and Communication Technologies</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/GlobConPT57482.2022.9938270</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barik</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srinivasan</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arulvendhan</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>N</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>High step-up DC-DC converter based renewable energy system for improving power quality and low voltage stress using PI controller technique</source>
          <publisher-name>In 2022 International Conference on Edge Computing and Applications</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICECAA55415.2022.9936547</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smadi</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allehyani</surname>
              <given-names>M. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>B. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lei</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Power Quality Improvement Utilizing PV-UPQC Based on PI-SRF and PAC Controllers</source>
          <publisher-name>In 2022 IEEE Power &amp; Energy Society General Meeting</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/PESGM48719.2022.9916826</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ghosh</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>Q. Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Batarseh</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Grid-Tied Multi-Port PV Battery System with ANFIS based Model Predictive Control</source>
          <publisher-name>In 2022 IEEE 13th International Symposium on Power Electronics for Distributed Generation Systems</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/PEDG54999.2022.9923117</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Çelik</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Demirtas</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Öztürk</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Analytical Investigation of PV Panel Operated at Maximum Power Point on DC Microgrid</source>
          <publisher-name>In 2022 11th International Conference on Renewable Energy Research and Application</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>324-329</page-range>
          <fpage>324</fpage>
          <lpage>329</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICRERA55966.2022.9922864</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yuksel</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Altin</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Three-phase grid-connected five-level packed u-cell (PUC-5) inverter design</article-title>
          <source>2022 11th International Conference on Renewable Energy Research and Application, Istanbul</source>
          <publisher-name>Turkey</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>490-495</page-range>
          <fpage>490</fpage>
          <lpage>495</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICRERA55966.2022.9922807</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siddesh</surname>
              <given-names>G. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Komala</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel architecture for cluster based false data injection attack detection and location identification in smart grid</article-title>
          <source>Advances in Thermofluids and Renewable Energy, Springer</source>
          <publisher-name>Singapore</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>599-611</page-range>
          <fpage>599</fpage>
          <lpage>611</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-16-3497-0_48</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shivaji</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Implementation of an effective hybrid partial transmit sequence model for peak to average power ratio in MIMO OFDM system</article-title>
          <source>ICDSMLA, Springer</source>
          <publisher-name>Singapore</publisher-name>
          <year>2020</year>
          <page-range>1343-1353</page-range>
          <fpage>1343</fpage>
          <lpage>1353</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-16-3690-5_129</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kuperman</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On the Explicit Relation between Mains-Side Current THD and DC Link Voltage Controller Gain in Grid-Connected Converters</article-title>
          <source>2022 IEEE 26th International Conference on Intelligent Engineering Systems, Georgioupolis Chania</source>
          <publisher-name>Greece</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>000069-000072</page-range>
          <fpage>000069</fpage>
          <lpage>000072</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/INES56734.2022.9922614</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>V. T. V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>B. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design and Analysis of RBFN Based MPPT Controller for Solar Energy System</article-title>
          <source>2022 Third International Conference on Intelligent Computing Instrumentation and Control Technologies, Kannur</source>
          <publisher-name>India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>843-849</page-range>
          <fpage>843</fpage>
          <lpage>849</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ACCESS.2017.2733555</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Two Stage Power Conversion For Grid Connected PV Using Current Control Technique</article-title>
          <source>2022 Third International Conference on Intelligent Computing Instrumentation and Control Technologies, Kannur</source>
          <publisher-name>India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1021-1026</page-range>
          <fpage>1021</fpage>
          <lpage>1026</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICICICT54557.2022.9917611</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manjunath</surname>
              <given-names>T. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Komala</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manu</surname>
              <given-names>K. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An efficient hybrid reconfigurable wind gas turbine power management system using MPPT algorithm</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Power Electron. Drive Syst.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11591/ijpeds.v12.i4.pp2501-2510</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shivaji</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design and implementation of reconfigurable DCT based adaptive PST techniques in OFDM communication system using interleaver encoder</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Sci. Technol.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <page-range>2108-2120</page-range>
          <fpage>2108</fpage>
          <lpage>2120</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.17485/IJST/v13i29.976</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vasumathi</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jayalakshmi</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cascaded ANN Controller for Grid Tied PV Based EV Charging Station</article-title>
          <source>2022 International Conference on Innovative Computing</source>
          <publisher-name>Intelligent Communication and Smart Electrical Systems</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-8</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICSES55317.2022.9914305</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nagalakshmi</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krishna</surname>
              <given-names>K. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Power Quality Enhancement in DC Microgrids by Model Predictive Control of Electric Springs</article-title>
          <source>2022 IEEE 2nd International Conference on Sustainable Energy and Future Electric Transportation, Hyderabad</source>
          <publisher-name>India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/SeFeT55524.2022.9909143</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tata</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sai Veerraju</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Power quality improvement of a hybrid renewable energy systems using dynamic voltage restorer with ANN controller</article-title>
          <source>2022 IEEE 2nd International Conference on Sustainable Energy and Future Electric Transportation, Hyderabad</source>
          <publisher-name>India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-4</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/SeFeT55524.2022.9908896</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Umashankar</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramakrishna</surname>
              <given-names>M. V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design of high speed reconfigurable distributed life time efficient routing algorithm in wireless sensor network</article-title>
          <source>J Comput. Theor. Nanos.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>0</issue>
          <page-range>3860-3866</page-range>
          <fpage>3860</fpage>
          <lpage>3866</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1166/jctn.2020.8975</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Umashankar</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramakrishna</surname>
              <given-names>M. V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design of high speed reconfigurable deployment intelligent genetic algorithm in maximum coverage wireless sensor network</article-title>
          <source>2019 International Conference on Data Science and Communication, Bangalore</source>
          <publisher-name>India</publisher-name>
          <year>2019</year>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/IconDSC.2019.8816930</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Satish</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srikantaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A comprehensive review of blind deconvolution techniques for image deblurring</article-title>
          <source>Trait. Signal.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>527-539</page-range>
          <fpage>527</fpage>
          <lpage>539</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>D</surname>
              <given-names>K. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>N</surname>
              <given-names>S. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>N</surname>
              <given-names>. N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Solid State Transformers for Smart Grid Control and Applications- A Review</article-title>
          <source>2022 International Conference on Futuristic Technologies in Control Systems &amp; Renewable Energy, Malappuram</source>
          <publisher-name>India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICFCR54831.2022.9893598</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>George</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>V</surname>
              <given-names>A. O.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>D-STATCOM in Electric Vehicle for Mitigating Power Quality issues in Grid</article-title>
          <source>2022 International Conference on Futuristic Technologies in Control Systems &amp; Renewable Energy, Malappuram</source>
          <publisher-name>India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICFCR54831.2022.9893652</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Iqbal</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ansari</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Near optimal PI Control of Cascaded Buck Converters in a DC Micro Grid</article-title>
          <source>2022 IEEE 16th International Conference on Compatibility, Power Electronics, and Power Engineering, Malappuram</source>
          <publisher-name>India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/CPE-POWERENG54966.2022.9880865</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shebin</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A software tool that provides relevant information for diabetic patients to help prevent diabetic foot</article-title>
          <source>IOSR J. Comput. Eng.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>69-73</page-range>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <lpage>73</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balachandra</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design of high speed reconfigurable coprocessor for interleaver and de-interleaver operations</article-title>
          <source>J. Impact Factor</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>30-38</page-range>
          <fpage>30</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shebin</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A review on clinical decision support system and its scope in medical field</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Eng. Res. &amp; Technol.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>417-420</page-range>
          <fpage>417</fpage>
          <lpage>420</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An efficient dynamic power management model for a stand-alone DC Microgrid using CPIHC technique</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Power Electron. Drive Syst.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>1439-1449</page-range>
          <fpage>1439</fpage>
          <lpage>1449</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11591/ijpeds.v12.i3.pp1439-1449</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fang</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jin</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Enhanced Grid Frequency and DC-link Voltage Regulation in Hybrid AC/DC Microgrids through Bidirectional Virtual Inertia Support</article-title>
          <source>In IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</source>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <page-range>6931-6940</page-range>
          <fpage>6931</fpage>
          <lpage>6940</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/TIE.2022.3203757</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>Z. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raisz</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>PV-UPQC with MFA-SMC controller to mitigate power quality problems</article-title>
          <source>2022 International Conference on Electrical</source>
          <publisher-name>Computer and Energy Technologies</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICECET55527.2022.9873064</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design of high-speed reconfigurable coprocessor for next-generation communication platform</article-title>
          <source>Emerging Research in Electronics, Computer Science and Technology, Springer</source>
          <publisher-name>New Delhi</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
          <page-range>57-67</page-range>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-81-322-1157-0_7</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Puspalatha</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Performance analysis of different classifier for remote sensing application</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Eng. Adv Technol.</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>7153-7158</page-range>
          <fpage>7153</fpage>
          <lpage>7158</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.35940/ijeat.A1879.109119</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thazeen</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siddesh</surname>
              <given-names>G. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Conventional and subspace algorithms for mobile source detection and radiation formation</article-title>
          <source>Trait. Signal.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>135-145</page-range>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>145</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vahabzadeh</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baig</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ebrahimi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jatskevich</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Investigation of MIMO State Feedback Controller for Grid-Connected AC-DC Voltage Source Converters</article-title>
          <source>2022 International Conference on Electrical</source>
          <publisher-name>Computer and Energy Technologies</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICECET55527.2022.9873005</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ghosh</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Negi</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design and Implementation of Super Twisting Sliding Mode Control for PV Grid-connected Water Pumping System</article-title>
          <source>2022 IEEE IAS Global Conference on Emerging Technologies, Arad</source>
          <publisher-name>Romania</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1150-1156</page-range>
          <fpage>1150</fpage>
          <lpage>1156</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/GlobConET53749.2022.9872383</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chaitra</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harisha</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madhu</surname>
              <given-names>T. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A comprehensive review of parallel concatenation of LDPC code techniques</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Sci. Technol.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <page-range>432-444</page-range>
          <fpage>432</fpage>
          <lpage>444</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.17485/IJST/v14i5.2171</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Umashankar</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anitha</surname>
              <given-names>T. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An efficient hybrid model for cluster head selection to optimize wireless sensor network using simulated annealing algorithm</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Sci. Technol.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>270-288</page-range>
          <fpage>270</fpage>
          <lpage>288</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.17485/IJST/v14i3.2318</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>AC</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jayaram</surname>
              <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of energy efficient and secure routing protocol for M2M communication</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Performability Eng.</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>426-433</page-range>
          <fpage>426</fpage>
          <lpage>433</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shashi Raj</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siddesh</surname>
              <given-names>G. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vivek Raj</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interference resilient stochastic prediction based dynamic resource allocation model for cognitive MANETs</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Sci. Technol.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>4332-4350</page-range>
          <fpage>4332</fpage>
          <lpage>4350</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.17485/IJST/v13i41.687</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morales-Caporal</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonilla-Huerta</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ordoñez-Flores</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cabrera-Sánchez</surname>
              <given-names>H. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Artificial Neural Network-Based Control of a DC/DC-DC/AC 5-Level Inverter for Rural Power Generation</article-title>
          <source>2022 IEEE XXIX International Conference on Electronics</source>
          <publisher-name>Electrical Engineering and Computing</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-4</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/INTERCON55795.2022.9870101</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mishra</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>K. W. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Power Quality Assessment of CPUC Based Solar Photovoltaic System with NLMS for Grid-Tied Applications</article-title>
          <source>In IEEE Transactions on Power Delivery</source>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>655-665</page-range>
          <fpage>655</fpage>
          <lpage>665</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/TPWRD.2022.3200012</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>MESSAOUDI</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>FARHANI</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>ZAAFOURI</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Improved control of PV-Grid connected via a two-stage configuration transformerless: Invited Paper</article-title>
          <source>2022 8th International Conference on Control</source>
          <publisher-name>Decision and Information Technologies</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1161-1166</page-range>
          <fpage>1161</fpage>
          <lpage>1166</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/CoDIT55151.2022.9803943</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garg</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparative Analysis of PI and PR Controller for Grid-tied Solar Photovoltaic System</article-title>
          <source>2022 4th International Conference on Energy</source>
          <publisher-name>Power and Environment</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICEPE55035.2022.9798294</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An efficient classification of hyperspectral remotely sensed data using support vector machine</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Electron. Telec.</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>609-617</page-range>
          <fpage>609</fpage>
          <lpage>617</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.24425/ijet.2022.141280</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nooli</surname>
              <given-names>C. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hrishikesh</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kruthik</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vakkalanka</surname>
              <given-names>H. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cloud based centralized smart cart and contactless billing system</article-title>
          <source>2022 7th International Conference on Communication and Electronics Systems, ICCES, Coimbatore, India</source>
          <publisher-name>June 22-24</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>2022</volume>
          <page-range>820-826</page-range>
          <fpage>820</fpage>
          <lpage>826</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICCES54183.2022.9835856</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dayananda</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srikantaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Efficient detection of faults and false data injection attacks in smart grid using a reconfigurable Kalman filter</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Power Electron. Drive Syst.</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>2086-2097</page-range>
          <fpage>2086</fpage>
          <lpage>2097</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11591/ijpeds.v13.i4.pp2086-2097</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thazeen</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>S</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saqhib</surname>
              <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>N</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>DOA Method with Reduced Bias and Side Lobe Suppression</article-title>
          <source>2022 International Conference on Communication, Computing and Internet of Things, IC3IoT, Chennai, India</source>
          <publisher-name>March 10-11</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/IC3IOT53935.2022.9767996</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rathod</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An efficient reconfigurable peak cancellation model for peak to average power ratio reduction in orthogonal frequency division multiplexing communication system</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Electr Comput Eng.</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>6239-6247</page-range>
          <fpage>6239</fpage>
          <lpage>6247</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11591/ijece.v12i6.pp6239-6247</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comprehensive Review of Optimal Utilization of Clock and Power Resources in Multi Bit Flip Flop Techniques</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Sci. Technol.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>3270-3279</page-range>
          <fpage>3270</fpage>
          <lpage>3279</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.17485/IJST/v14i44.1790</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balachandra</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design of high speed reconfigurable coprocessor for interleaver and de interleaver operations</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Electronics and Communication Engineering Technology</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>30-38</page-range>
          <fpage>30</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pooja</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hybrid regularization algorithm for efficient image deblurring</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Engineering and Advanced Technology</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>141-147</page-range>
          <fpage>141</fpage>
          <lpage>147</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.35940/ijeat.F2998.0810621</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Umashankar</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>A survey on IoT protocol in real-time applications and its architectures, In Lecture Notes in Electrical Engineering</source>
          <publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-19-5936-3_12</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pooja</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Image region driven prior selection for image deblurring</article-title>
          <source>Multimedia Tools and Applications</source>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11042-023-14335-y</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>