<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="review-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HF</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Healthcraft Frontiers</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Healthcraft. Front.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">HF</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">3005-799X</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">3005-7981</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-Z6djZFRExsowfmnKM1qtOZufHv1f4R0E</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/hf030205</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Microplastics: A Multidimensional Threat to Environment, Economy, and Public Health</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-5484-8537</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Pagadala</surname>
            <given-names>Rohith Kumar</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>rohithpagadala12@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-1695-6054</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Basu</surname>
            <given-names>Anushka</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>anushkabasu10@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Independent Researcher, Ahmedabad, India</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>110</fpage>
      <lpage>120</lpage>
      <page-range>110-120</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>04</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>05</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Microplastics, commonly defined as plastic particles smaller than 5 mm, have emerged as pervasive contaminants across natural and anthropogenic systems, constituting a complex global stressor with environmental, economic, and public health implications. Since the term microplastic was first introduced in 2004, an expanding body of research has revealed the extensive diversity and abundance of these particles, which originate from both the fragmentation of larger plastic debris (secondary microplastics) and the intentional production of microscopic polymers (primary microplastics) for use in cosmetics, industrial abrasives, and synthetic textiles. Despite substantial scientific attention, the absence of a universally accepted classification framework–particularly with respect to size ranges, polymer composition, and source attribution–continues to hinder harmonized monitoring and regulatory action. Microplastics have been detected in marine and freshwater environments, terrestrial soils, atmospheric fallout, and remote regions, demonstrating their capacity for long-range transport through hydrological, atmospheric, and biogeochemical processes. Ecologically, exposure has been shown to impair feeding behavior, induce physical obstruction, and compromise reproductive success across multiple trophic levels, from planktonic organisms to higher vertebrates. Chemically, microplastics function as dynamic carriers for persistent organic pollutants, heavy metals, and microbial assemblages. Human exposure has been increasingly documented through dietary intake, drinking water consumption, and inhalation of airborne particles. Effective mitigation of microplastic pollution will require coordinated international policy frameworks, advances in materials innovation and waste management, standardized analytical methodologies, and sustained public engagement to address both sources and impacts of microplastic contamination.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Microplastics</kwd>
        <kwd>Marine environment</kwd>
        <kwd>Pollution</kwd>
        <kwd>Biodegradation</kwd>
        <kwd>Greenhouse emissions</kwd>
        <kwd>Soil contamination</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="2"/>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="29"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>The ubiquity of plastic pollution has emerged as one of the defining environmental crises of the 21st century, and within this crisis, microplastics represent a particularly insidious and complex problem. Microplastics–plastic fragments typically less than 5 mm in size–are not only a byproduct of the breakdown of larger plastic debris but are also intentionally manufactured for use in a variety of industrial and consumer products. Their widespread presence in marine, freshwater, terrestrial, and atmospheric environments signals a systemic failure in plastic production, consumption, and waste management practices worldwide. Despite the growing body of research highlighting the scale and severity of microplastic pollution, critical gaps persist in people’s understanding of their environmental fate, toxicological effects, and long-term impacts on ecosystems and human health. The lack of universally agreed-upon definitions and measurement standards complicates efforts to accurately quantify and control microplastic contamination, hindering effective policymaking and regulatory enforcement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Cole et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Thompson et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>Microplastics act as physical contaminants, disrupting soil structure, aquatic habitats, and terrestrial food webs, while their chemical components–plasticizers, dyes, additives, and adsorbed pollutants–pose severe toxicological risks. These substances interfere with biological processes, including nutrient cycling, immune function, reproduction, and development across multiple species, amplifying ecological vulnerability in already stressed environments. Of equal concern is the human dimension: microplastics have been detected in drinking water, food supplies, and the air people breathe, with emerging evidence linking exposure to adverse health outcomes such as inflammation, endocrine disruption, and carcinogenic effects. The global distribution and persistence of microplastics underscore the need for a comprehensive, interdisciplinary approach to address this challenge. This includes advancing scientific research to close knowledge gaps, enhancing waste management infrastructure, innovating in plastic alternatives and remediation technologies, and implementing stringent regulatory frameworks. Public education and awareness-raising are critical to foster behavioral shifts toward reduced plastic use and responsible disposal.</p><p>This study aims to provide a detailed overview of the sources, environmental pathways, biological impacts, and socio-economic consequences of microplastics, emphasizing the urgency for coordinated global action. Only through a multi-pronged strategy involving scientific, technological, regulatory, and societal interventions can the escalating threat of microplastics be mitigated and planetary and human health be protected for future generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Jambeck et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">OECD, 2022</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Literature selection and review methodology</title>
      <p>This review synthesizes peer-reviewed scientific literature and authoritative institutional reports addressing the sources, distribution, environmental behavior, biological impacts, health implications, and economic consequences of microplastic pollution. The literature surveyed primarily spans the period from 2004 to 2024, beginning with the formal introduction of the term “microplastics” and extending to recent advances in detection methods and impact assessment. Relevant studies were identified through systematic searches of major academic databases, including Google Scholar, PubMed, ScienceDirect, Web of Science, and selected reports from recognized scientific and governmental institutions such as the United States Environmental Protection Agency and international research organizations. Reference lists of key review articles were also examined to identify additional influential or frequently cited studies.</p><p>Search queries were constructed using combinations of keywords such as “microplastics” “nanoplastics” “plastic pollution” “environmental impacts” “marine ecosystems” “soil contamination” “atmospheric microplastics” “human health” and “economic impacts”. Variations of these terms were used to capture interdisciplinary research across environmental science, toxicology, public health, and economics.</p><p>Studies were included if they met at least one of the following criteria:</p><p>1. The provision of empirical data on the occurrence, transport, or effects of microplastics;</p><p>2. The presentation of systematic or narrative reviews of microplastic impacts; or</p><p>3. The provision of quantitative or qualitative assessments of economic or ecosystem-service consequences.</p><p>Priority was given to peer-reviewed journal articles, although selected institutional reports were included where they provided comprehensive or policy-relevant data not yet widely available in the academic literature. Exclusion criteria included non-scholarly opinion pieces, articles lacking methodological transparency, and studies focusing solely on microplastic pollution without explicit relevance to microplastics or nanoplastics. Due to substantial heterogeneity in sampling techniques, particle classification, and analytical methods across studies, no formal meta-analysis was conducted.</p><p>The selected literature was organized thematically rather than chronologically, allowing comparative discussion across environmental compartments (marine, terrestrial, and atmospheric systems), biological impacts, and economic sectors. This thematic approach facilitates identification of recurring patterns, methodological divergences, and key uncertainties within the current research landscape, while highlighting areas where further standardized investigation is required.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Definition and classification of microplastics</title>
      <p>Microplastics are broadly categorized into two types: primary and secondary microplastics. Primary microplastics are intentionally manufactured at microscopic size for specific commercial uses, such as pre-production plastic pellets (nurdles), microbeads used in personal care products, and microfibers shed from synthetic textiles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Boucher &amp;amp; Friot, 2017</xref>). Secondary microplastics result from the environmental degradation of larger plastic products. Through mechanical abrasion, photodegradation driven by UV radiation, oxidative reactions, and microbial activity, macroplastics gradually fragment into smaller particles. This degradation is accelerated in marine environments, shorelines, and landfills lacking proper containment systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Andrady, 2011</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Formation of microplastics</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Origins: crude oil, petrochemicals, and plastic genesis</title>
          
          <p>Plastic is fundamentally a fossil fuel product, derived from the distillation of crude oil or natural gas. Key feedstocks such as ethylene, propylene, benzene, toluene, and xylene are extracted during the refining process and chemically polymerized to create resins like polyethylene, polypropylene, and polystyrene. These synthetic polymers are inherently non-biodegradable, designed for durability and mass production, not environmental compatibility. This origin directly links plastic pollution to carbon-intensive industrial processes, locking in plastic as both a pollutant and a climate disruptor. Plastic production generates approximately 5% of global greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Mechanisms of microplastic formation</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.2.1 Photodegradation</title>
              
              <p>UV radiation weakens polymer bonds, particularly in polyethylene- and polypropylene-based plastics. Over time, this causes surface cracking and fragmentation. Sun-exposed plastic debris in open landfills or floating in oceans breaks down via this process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Andrady, 2011</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.2.2 Mechanical weathering</title>
              
              <p>Physical forces such as wave action, abrasion by sand, or vehicular friction (especially from tire wear particles) produce microplastics from everyday plastic waste. Road dust and atmospheric deposition also contribute to airborne microplastic pollution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Wright et al., 2013</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.2.3 Biological degradation</title>
              
              <p>Although slow and inefficient, microbial colonization (biofilm formation) can chemically degrade certain polymers. However, the majority of conventional plastics are non-biodegradable under natural conditions, leading instead to progressive fragmentation rather than true breakdown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Rillig, 2012</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.2.4 Thermal and chemical stress</title>
              
              <p>Temperature fluctuations, oxidative conditions, and acid/base exposure (e.g., in landfills or incineration zones) also accelerate the physical and chemical breakdown of plastics into micro- and nano-sized particles.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Impacts on environment</title>
      <p>Across the literature, substantial variability exists in reported concentrations, impacts, and risk assessments, reflecting differences in methodologies, environmental contexts, and analytical frameworks. Microplastics, defined as plastic particles less than 5 mm in diameter, have become ubiquitous environmental contaminants. Their origins trace back primarily to the fragmentation of larger plastic debris, as well as direct inputs like microbeads from personal care products. Unlike many pollutants, microplastics are not inert; they interact with physical, chemical, and biological systems across ecosystems, compounding environmental damage through multiple interconnected pathways. Their widespread distribution in soils, oceans, the atmosphere, and biota makes them a complex threat with consequences that ripple across global ecological and climate systems.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.1. Fossil fuel dependency, greenhouse gas (ghg) emissions, and global warming</title>
          
          <p>The link between plastic production and fossil fuels is fundamental and unavoidable under the current industrial paradigm. Plastic manufacturing relies almost exclusively on hydrocarbons derived from crude oil and natural gas–resources whose extraction, refining, and processing are inherently carbon-intensive. The initial phase involves drilling and extraction of crude oil from underground reservoirs, a process that consumes vast amounts of energy and releases GHGs, including methane, a potent climate-warming agent.</p><p>After extraction, crude oil undergoes refining to separate its complex mixture into usable fractions. One key product, naphtha, is isolated for further chemical processing to yield ethene (ethylene) and propane–essential monomers for polymer synthesis. These steps involve high-temperature cracking and catalytic reactions, each stage generating CO₂, volatile organic compounds, and other pollutants. Subsequent polymerization transforms these monomers into polymers such as polyethylene and polypropylene, forming the raw plastic pellets that serve as feedstock for consumer and industrial goods. These pellets undergo melting and molding, often requiring additional energy, further contributing to carbon emissions. Plastic production now accounts for an estimated 3.8% of global GHG emissions–a figure projected to rise sharply with increasing global plastic demand. This trajectory directly conflicts with international climate targets such as those in the Paris Agreement, which require urgent reduction of fossil fuel usage.</p><p>Moreover, plastic pollution exacerbates climate change by degrading carbon sinks. For instance, microplastics disrupt soil microbial communities responsible for carbon sequestration and degrade marine ecosystems like coral reefs and seagrasses that serve as vital carbon reservoirs. Thus, plastic production and pollution form a feedback loop intensifying global warming and ecological degradation.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.2. Soil contamination</title>
          
          <p>Soil contamination by microplastics is a rapidly emerging concern with profound implications for terrestrial ecosystem health and agricultural productivity. Microplastics enter soil environments through various pathways: application of sewage sludge (often used as fertilizer), atmospheric deposition, irrigation with contaminated water, and direct littering. Sewage sludge, a byproduct of wastewater treatment, can contain significant concentrations of microplastics, which are then introduced directly into croplands. Once embedded in soil matrices, microplastics physically alter soil texture and structure. They reduce soil porosity and water retention capacity, critical for plant root function and microbial activity. Changes in bulk density affect root penetration, while shifts in pH can alter nutrient availability. These physical disruptions impair the soil’s ability to support healthy plant growth, leading to lower crop yields and diminished food quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Zhang &amp;amp; Liu, 2018</xref>).</p><p>Chemical effects are equally alarming. Chlorinated plastics release toxic compounds, while additives such as phthalates and bisphenol A leach from microplastic particles over time. These compounds are endocrine disruptors–interfering with hormone signaling in a broad range of organisms. The nanometer-scale particles can penetrate soil microhabitats, entering microbial cells and even plant root systems. This intrusion can cause oxidative stress, inflammation, and genetic mutations, undermining microbial biodiversity critical for nutrient cycling and plant health. Such disturbances threaten soil ecosystem services that underpin global food security. Soil is not merely a substrate but a living system; the contamination by microplastics jeopardizes its resilience and sustainability, raising serious concerns for long-term agricultural viability and human health (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">de Souza Machado et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Rillig, 2012</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.3. Terrestrial ecosystem</title>
          
          <p>The presence of microplastics within terrestrial ecosystems introduces new challenges for animal health, ecological stability, and evolutionary processes. Terrestrial animals can ingest microplastics directly from soil or water sources, or indirectly through contaminated food. Once ingested, microplastics interact with the gastrointestinal tract, physically obstructing nutrient absorption and altering digestive efficiency. Such effects can cause malnutrition, weakened immune responses, and increased mortality. Microplastics also influence gut microbiota composition, an emerging area of concern. Healthy gut microbiomes are crucial for digestion, immunity, and even behavioral regulation in many species. Disruption can cascade through trophic levels, affecting predator-prey dynamics and population viability. Beyond individual organisms, microplastics interfere with ecological processes such as decomposition. Soil microbes and detritivores play critical roles in breaking down organic matter and recycling nutrients; microplastic contamination hampers their activity, slowing decomposition rates and altering nutrient availability. This disruption can lead to imbalances in carbon and nitrogen cycles, reducing ecosystem productivity and resilience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">Vethaak &amp;amp; Legler, 2021</xref>).</p><p>Furthermore, microplastics facilitate horizontal gene transfer among microbial communities, particularly genes conferring resistance to antibiotics and heavy metals. This gene exchange accelerates the evolution of resistant strains, posing risks for both ecosystem and human health by potentially promoting the spread of infectious diseases and environmental toxins. Overall, microplastics undermine terrestrial ecosystem integrity at multiple levels, threatening biodiversity, ecological functions, and the services these ecosystems provide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Horton et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Wright &amp;amp; Kelly, 2017</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.4. Atmosphere</title>
          
          <p>Microplastics suspended in the atmosphere constitute a novel and insidious form of air pollution. These particles, ranging from microscopic fibers to larger fragments, are transported by wind currents, allowing them to reach remote and previously pristine environments such as mountain ranges and polar regions. Inhalation exposure to airborne microplastics is a growing public health concern. Studies have detected synthetic fibers in human lung tissue, indicating that inhaled microplastics can deposit deep within the respiratory system. Occupational exposure among plastic industry workers has been linked to respiratory ailments, including chronic cough, bronchitis, wheezing, and occupational asthma. Health risks extend beyond mechanical irritation. Microplastics can carry adsorbed toxins–including persistent organic pollutants like dichlorodiphenyltrichloroethane, hexachlorobenzene, polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, and heavy metals–into the respiratory tract. These substances contribute to genotoxicity, carcinogenicity, and endocrine disruption. Additives within plastics, such as phthalates and perfluoroalkyl substances, have similarly deleterious health effects.</p><p>The atmospheric presence of microplastics also represents a pathway for pollutant cycling, whereby toxins are transported long distances and deposited into terrestrial and aquatic environments. This transport mechanism exacerbates the global spread of pollution, compounding ecological and human health risks. Current estimates of atmospheric microplastic concentrations differ widely among studies, largely due to methodological inconsistencies in air sampling, particle identification, and polymer verification. As a result, inhalation exposure assessments remain highly uncertain, and direct comparisons across geographic regions are limited. This variability highlights the need for standardized protocols in atmospheric microplastic research.</p><p>Evidence regarding human health impacts of microplastic exposure remains largely indirect. Many conclusions are drawn from in vitro experiments or animal models, which differ in exposure pathways and particle characteristics compared to real-world human exposure. Consequently, while associations with inflammation, oxidative stress, and endocrine disruption have been reported, causal relationships and long-term health outcomes in humans remain insufficiently established (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Allen et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Dris et al., 2016</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.5. Marine environment</title>
          
          <p>The marine environment bears the brunt of microplastic pollution, with devastating consequences for biodiversity and ecosystem function. Oceans act as a sink for plastic debris, which breaks down into microplastics through photodegradation, mechanical abrasion, and chemical processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Law &amp;amp; Thompson, 2014</xref>).</p><p>Marine organisms mistake microplastics for prey due to their size and appearance, leading to ingestion across taxa–from zooplankton and fish to seals, seabirds, and whales. Studies have reported ingestion rates as high as 47.2% in certain fish species. This ingestion causes physical damage to digestive tracts, including intestinal blockages, ulcerations, and inflammation, which impair feeding and nutrient uptake. Chemical toxicity arises from plastic-associated contaminants and additives, which bioaccumulate and biomagnify through food webs. Microplastics have been shown to alter animal behavior, reduce fertility, and suppress immune function, threatening population stability. The mortality of key species can cascade through marine food webs, destabilizing ecosystems. Additionally, microplastics accumulate in marine sediments, altering benthic habitats critical for nutrient cycling and the life cycles of many species. Sediment contamination disrupts microbial and invertebrate communities, reducing habitat quality and biodiversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Bergmann et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>The cumulative effects of physical harm, chemical contamination, and habitat degradation represent a significant risk to marine ecosystem health and the services oceans provide–such as fisheries, carbon sequestration, and climate regulation. Reported ingestion rates and toxicological effects of microplastics in marine organisms vary substantially across studies. Differences in sampling locations, species examined, particle size ranges, and analytical techniques lead to wide variability in reported ingestion prevalence. While some studies document ingestion rates approaching 40–50% in certain fish populations, others report markedly lower values, underscoring the influence of methodological and ecological context on observed outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Galloway et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Wright et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>1. Ingestion by marine animals</p><p>The rate of ingestion depends on the type of species, with some studies reporting rates as high as 47.2% in certain fish species. These rates are influenced by many factors such as the concentration of microplastics, etc. This ingestion happens because many marine organisms like planktivorous fish from the North Pacific Gyre, mussels from Belgian coastal waters, harbor seals and Fulmar from the North Sea, and whales tend to mistake microplastics for their food. This ingestion causes blockages in their intestine, leading to starvation and death. The chemicals present in microplastics cause many health implications in their body. Microplastics accumulate in many organs of these organisms, causing damage to their cell membranes and leading to toxicity and death. In addition, microplastics have been found to affect behavior, development, fertility, and immune function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Browne et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Kögel et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Smith et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>2. Disruption of food chain</p><p>This is also connected to the ingestion of microplastics as the death of many organisms can disrupt the marine ecosystem. The ingestion of microplastics in zooplankton and other consumers can cause the death of other animals which feed on them. In addition, these microplastics accumulate on marine sediments, altering the habitat and affecting the organisms which live there.</p><p>This combined effect of ingestion, habitat degradation and chemical contamination can pose a very significant risk to marine biodiversity and marine ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Carbery et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.6. Climatic and weather patterns</title>
          
          <p>Emerging research reveals microplastics’ potential role as climate and weather modifiers, an area that has received scant attention despite its profound implications. Microplastics suspended in the atmosphere can act as cloud condensation nuclei. These nuclei facilitate the formation of cloud droplets by attracting water vapor, influencing cloud microphysics. Alterations in cloud characteristics–such as droplet size, density, and albedo–can impact precipitation patterns, cloud longevity, and radiative forcing. Such changes influence local weather systems and may contribute to shifts in regional and global climate dynamics. Furthermore, microplastics’ ability to absorb and scatter solar radiation contributes to localized warming effects, particularly in the lower atmosphere where concentrations are highest. This phenomenon can modify heat balance and atmospheric stability, creating feedback loops that exacerbate anthropogenic climate warming.</p><p>Given the accelerating production and dispersal of plastics, the climatic impacts of microplastics are likely to intensify, complicating efforts to predict and mitigate climate change. Microplastics can potentially affect cloud formation by acting as cloud condensation nuclei, meaning they can attract water vapor in the atmosphere, facilitating the formation of tiny water droplets that eventually coalesce into clouds; essentially, microplastics can serve as nucleation points for cloud formation, potentially influencing cloud characteristics like size, density, and precipitation patterns, which could impact weather and climate. Microplastics are mostly present in the lower altitude regions of the atmosphere. But the increasing concentration of microplastics in the atmosphere can eventually lead to the increasing warming effect of the Earth, as microplastics have light-absorbing capability. Thus, microplastics are surely playing a major role in how the climatic system of the planet works.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Economic impacts</title>
      <p>While Section 5 examines the environmental and biological mechanisms of microplastic pollution, this section focuses specifically on how these impacts translate into economic costs across key sectors. Estimates of the economic costs associated with microplastic pollution vary widely depending on valuation methods and the ecosystem services considered. While some assessments focus on fisheries and tourism losses, others attempt broader ecosystem service valuation, leading to large ranges in reported costs. These differences reflect both methodological uncertainty and limited empirical data linking microplastic contamination directly to economic outcomes.</p><p>Microplastic pollution is not just an environmental nuisance–it poses a significant economic risk to multiple sectors worldwide. Its pervasive effects cascade through industries, communities, and government budgets, creating a tangled web of financial burdens that few are prepared to manage. Ignoring microplastics doesn’t make the problem disappear; it just shifts the cost onto future generations, already stretched thin by climate change and resource depletion. Microplastics can also pose many economic challenges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">OECD, 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Rochman et al., 2013</xref>).</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.1. Fishing industry</title>
          
          <p>As discussed in Section 5.5, microplastic ingestion adversely affects marine organism health through physical and chemical pathways. These biological impacts translate economically into declining fish stocks, reduced seafood quality, and increased uncertainty in fisheries management. This decline has tangible economic consequences. Fishers and coastal communities face shrinking catches, threatening their livelihoods and food security. Commercial fisheries, which globally contribute roughly $400 billion annually, risk severe revenue losses. Beyond direct harvest impacts, marine ecosystem degradation compromises vital services such as nursery habitats, spawning grounds, and predator-prey balances–further reducing long-term productivity.</p><p>The National Council for Environmental Law estimates that plastic pollution reduces marine ecosystem services by 1–5%, equating to annual economic losses between \$500 billion and \$2.5 trillion. This staggering figure underscores the scale: for every metric ton of plastic pollution, society loses approximately $33,000 in ecosystem service value. These costs are hidden in declining fishery yields, increased resource management expenses, and lost economic opportunities in coastal and ocean sectors. Ignoring microplastic pollution is, economically, a catastrophic gamble–a slow-motion collapse of a multi-trillion-dollar global industry.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.2. Agriculture</title>
          
          <p>Agriculture, the backbone of global food security, is not immune. Microplastics infiltrate soils primarily through contaminated sewage sludge fertilizers, plastic mulch degradation, and atmospheric deposition. Once in the soil, microplastics alter physical structure, impair water retention, and disrupt microbial communities essential for nutrient cycling and soil fertility. The soil-level effects of microplastic contamination outlined in Section 5.2 have direct economic implications for agricultural productivity. Changes in soil structure, microbial function, and contaminant uptake influence crop yields, input costs, and long-term land viability. Reduced soil health translates into declining crop yields and increased vulnerability to drought and pests. This directly hits farmers’ bottom lines, especially in regions heavily dependent on intensive farming. Crop failures and reduced productivity increase food prices and strain supply chains, exacerbating food insecurity–particularly in poorer nations already battling climate change and resource scarcity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Li et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>Furthermore, microplastic contamination introduces toxic additives and adsorbed chemicals into soils, potentially entering the human food chain through crops. The long-term health implications may translate into increased healthcare costs and lost labor productivity, creating a vicious economic cycle.</p><p>Investment in soil remediation and pollution control to sustain agricultural productivity is costly but unavoidable. Without action, the agricultural sector risks gradual degradation that could ripple into global food markets, destabilizing economies dependent on agricultural exports.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.3. Tourism</title>
          
          <p>Tourism, a critical revenue source for many coastal and natural regions, suffers directly from microplastic pollution. Tourists seek clean, pristine environments–beaches, reefs, and natural parks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Koelmans et al., 2019</xref>). Microplastic contamination visibly degrades these landscapes, undermining the aesthetic and recreational value that attracts visitors. Environmental degradation caused by plastic and microplastic pollution has measurable economic consequences for tourism-dependent regions, where ecosystem quality and aesthetic value are central to visitor demand. Coastal areas plagued by plastic debris experience measurable declines in tourist numbers. Studies show that the presence of visible plastic waste reduces beach visitation by up to 30%. This downturn impacts local businesses such as hotels, restaurants, tour operators, and retail shops, often the economic lifeline for small island nations and coastal communities.</p><p>Losses in tourism income also mean reduced tax revenues for local governments, limiting their capacity to invest in environmental protection and infrastructure. The cascading economic effects extend into employment losses and diminished community wellbeing, particularly where alternative livelihoods are scarce. Given that tourism contributes more than 10% of global GDP and supports over 300 million jobs, microplastic pollution threatens a vital economic engine. The degradation of natural capital represents a preventable erosion of wealth, with recovery requiring expensive cleanup and restoration efforts.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.4. Regulatory and mitigation costs</title>
          
          <p>The financial burden of tackling microplastic pollution inevitably falls on governments and taxpayers. Developing and enforcing policies to reduce plastic production, improve waste management infrastructure, and clean up existing pollution requires significant investment. Regulatory frameworks must encompass banning or restricting single-use plastics, improving recycling technologies, and incentivizing sustainable materials–all of which involve upfront costs and political resistance. Infrastructure upgrades–such as enhanced wastewater treatment capable of filtering microplastics–demand substantial capital and ongoing operational expenses. Cleanup operations–ranging from beach cleanups to ocean plastic collection technologies–are expensive, labor-intensive, and only partially effective. These efforts often face diminishing returns as microplastics are widespread and microscopic. Countries, especially those with limited fiscal capacity, struggle to allocate resources effectively. The diversion of funds to microplastic mitigation diverts from other critical social needs, creating a zero-sum budgeting dilemma. Failure to act promptly compounds future costs, as unchecked pollution worsens environmental degradation and intensifies associated economic losses. In essence, mitigation today is cheaper than repair tomorrow, but short-term economic and political considerations often hinder necessary investments. Microplastic pollution is not a distant environmental concern–it is an immediate economic threat with deep ramifications across critical sectors. The fishing industry faces collapsing fish stocks; agriculture risks soil infertility and food insecurity; tourism suffers dwindling visitors; and governments face soaring regulatory and cleanup costs.</p><p>This systemic economic damage feeds into global inequality, hitting vulnerable communities hardest, while industrialized nations dodge accountability. The pragmatism here is brutal: without drastic shifts in production, consumption, and regulation, the economic fallout from microplastics will grow uncontrollably–exposing economies to losses far beyond current estimates, undermining livelihoods, and destabilizing global markets. Addressing microplastic pollution is no longer optional but essential. Economically, the cost of inaction vastly exceeds the investments needed for systemic reform. But given entrenched interests and short-term thinking, this battle is uphill–making scepticism about global readiness justified, yet urgent action unavoidable.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>7. Conclusion</title>
      <p>This review synthesizes current scientific literature on the sources, formation pathways, environmental distribution, biological interactions, and economic implications of microplastic pollution. The reviewed studies consistently demonstrate that microplastics are widely distributed across marine, terrestrial, and atmospheric environments, where they interact with physical, chemical, and biological systems at multiple scales. Evidence indicates that microplastics affect ecosystem structure and function through mechanisms such as ingestion by organisms, alteration of soil properties, transport of chemical additives and adsorbed pollutants, and long-range atmospheric dispersion. Experimental and observational studies further suggest potential adverse effects on organism health, including physiological stress, altered reproduction, and immune responses. However, the magnitude and long-term consequences of these effects remain uncertain due to methodological heterogeneity, limited longitudinal data, and incomplete understanding of nanoplastic behavior.</p><p>From an economic perspective, the literature reviewed suggests that microplastic pollution may contribute to reduced ecosystem services, particularly in sectors such as fisheries, agriculture, and tourism. Existing economic estimates vary widely depending on valuation methods and assumptions, underscoring substantial uncertainty in quantifying total costs and emphasizing the need for more empirically grounded assessments.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>8. Broader implications and future research directions</title>
      <p>While the reviewed literature establishes microplastics as a pervasive and multifaceted pollutant, significant knowledge gaps remain. Future research would benefit from standardized definitions, sampling protocols, and analytical methods to improve comparability across studies. Long-term investigations are required to clarify chronic exposure risks to ecosystems and human populations, as well as to better constrain economic impact estimates. Policy and mitigation discussions surrounding microplastic pollution should be informed by this evolving evidence base. Continued integration of environmental science, toxicology, and economic analysis will be essential for developing effective and proportionate responses to microplastic contamination. Microplastics are not just fragments of broken plastic–they are fragments of broken systems. What began as an industrial marvel has metastasized into a planetary crisis that transcends environment, economy, and human health (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Leslie et al., 2022</xref>). This study has outlined in exhaustive detail how microplastics have embedded themselves in every conceivable ecosystem–marine, terrestrial, and atmospheric–and how their invisible presence silently erodes the foundations of biodiversity, public health, and global economic stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Revel et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>The ubiquity of microplastics is a grim reminder of humanity’s failure to anticipate the long-term consequences of short-term convenience. From the production line to the ocean floor, every stage in the lifecycle of plastic is rooted in fossil fuel extraction, GHG emissions, and the exponential proliferation of toxic waste. It is a feedback loop of destruction: plastics contribute to climate change, climate change stresses ecosystems, and weakened ecosystems absorb even more plastic, magnifying the damage. Ecologically, the data is irrefutable. Microplastics reduce soil fertility, degrade marine habitats, alter food chains, and disrupt hormonal and genetic processes in animals and humans alike. These are not isolated incidents–they represent systemic degradation. Microplastics undermine the very biological processes that sustain life, from nutrient cycles in soil to oxygen generation in oceans. Economically, the costs are staggering and grossly underestimated. From declining fish stocks to reduced agricultural yields, from lost tourism revenue to ballooning regulatory expenses, microplastics impose a financial toll that governments and industries are barely beginning to comprehend. When marine ecosystem services alone lose up to $2.5 trillion annually, an environmental nuisance is no longer being addressed; instead, a macroeconomic liability is being confronted.</p><p>Socially and politically, the challenge is even more complex. Most citizens remain unaware of the scope and severity of microplastic contamination. This knowledge vacuum allows industries to deflect accountability and policymakers to delay action. There is no widespread public urgency, no global consensus, and no enforceable framework strong enough to dismantle the plastic-industrial complex. Until microplastic pollution becomes a political priority, real solutions will remain on the fringes–underfunded, under-researched, and under-implemented. The fight against microplastics requires more than cosmetic reforms or awareness campaigns. It demands a multi-pronged, systemic overhaul, including:</p><p>1. A drastic reduction in plastic production, particularly single-use plastics;</p><p>2. Aggressive investment in alternative materials and closed-loop economies;</p><p>3. Mandatory producer responsibility to internalize the cost of pollution;</p><p>4. Development of cutting-edge technologies that can detect, degrade, and extract microplastics at scale;</p><p>5. Global policy coherence that moves beyond voluntary agreements to binding international legislation.</p><p>The complexity of the crisis should not be allowed to induce paralysis; rather, it should serve as a catalyst for action. Microplastics can no longer be treated as a distant issue, as their presence has already been documented in water, air, food systems, and human tissues. They are the symptoms of a civilization addicted to convenience and structurally indifferent to consequences. In the final analysis, microplastics represent a brutal question: Can economic, political, and ethical systems evolve fast enough to correct a crisis they created? Or will planetary systems continue to be fragmented into finer and finer particles until nothing functional remains? The choice remains collective, but the clock is not.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>9. Proposed solutions</title>
      <p>Addressing microplastic pollution requires coordinated interventions across production systems, technological innovation, governance frameworks, and societal behavior. The following strategies outline a comprehensive, multi-level response.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>9.1. Reducing plastic production at the source</title>
          
          <p>Prevention is more effective than remediation. A radical reduction in global plastic production, particularly single-use and low-value plastics, must become the central objective of environmental policy. This can be done through:</p><p>1. Bans and restrictions on unnecessary plastic items such as microbeads in cosmetics, single-use packaging, and non-essential plastic goods;</p><p>2. Taxation and disincentives on virgin plastic production, while simultaneously offering subsidies for sustainable alternatives;</p><p>3. Mandated reduction targets for plastic production and use across industries, enforced through regulatory frameworks at national and international levels;</p><p>4. Investment in circular economy systems where materials are reused, repurposed, or biodegraded at the end of their life cycle.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>9.2. Promoting biodegradable and sustainable alternatives</title>
          
          <p>Transitioning away from fossil-fuel-based plastic means innovating new materials that can fulfill similar functions without catastrophic environmental costs.</p><p>1. Plant-based polymers, starch-based films, cellulose-based packaging, and bioplastics offer promising, though still limited, alternatives;</p><p>2. Glass, metal, paper, and fabric-based packaging–if sourced sustainably–can replace many plastic functions without introducing new ecological problems;</p><p>3. Research and development funding must be expanded to improve the scalability, cost-efficiency, and durability of these alternatives to match industrial demand.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>9.3. Addressing and controlling primary microplastics</title>
          
          <p>A significant portion of microplastics comes from intentionally manufactured sources–plastic pellets (nurdles), exfoliating microbeads, synthetic fibers from clothing, and tire abrasion.</p><p>1. Ban microbeads and microplastics in consumer products through comprehensive legislation;</p><p>2. Mandate filters and capture technologies in washing machines, dryers, and stormwater systems to intercept synthetic fibers;</p><p>3. Redesign textiles with biodegradable or low-shedding materials to reduce fiber release during use and laundering;</p><p>4. Implement Extended Producer Responsibility schemes that hold manufacturers accountable for the lifecycle pollution of their products.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>9.4. Innovative cleanup and remediation technologies</title>
          
          <p>While prevention is critical, the legacy pollution already circulating in ecosystems should also be addressed.</p><p>1. Microbial and enzymatic degradation: Research into plastic-eating bacteria and enzymes that can safely and efficiently break down microplastics must be scaled up with urgency;</p><p>2. Nanotechnology: Advanced materials that can bind to or neutralize microplastic particles offer a frontier of hope–though environmental safety must be proven before wide deployment;</p><p>3. Adsorption and filtration systems: In both urban and natural environments, high-efficiency filtration units can be installed in water treatment facilities, drainage systems, and industrial outflows to intercept plastic debris before it spreads;</p><p>4. Ocean cleanup initiatives and river interceptors must be complemented with sediment-targeted extraction systems to address microplastics already embedded in aquatic habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Cózar et al., 2014</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>9.5. Public awareness and cultural change</title>
          
          <p>Environmental degradation is often sustained by public ignorance and apathy. For microplastics, awareness is alarmingly low (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Locritani et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>1. National campaigns must redefine microplastics as a public health issue, not merely an environmental one;</p><p>2. Curriculum integration in schools should make microplastic pollution a central theme in science and civics education;</p><p>3. Behavioral nudges–such as plastic usage trackers, rewards for sustainable habits, and visible social norm campaigns–can shift public sentiment;</p><p>4. Mass media and influencers must be strategically engaged to amplify the urgency and normalize plastic-free lifestyles.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>9.6. Global policy reform and industrial accountability</title>
          
          <p>1. No single country can tackle microplastic pollution in isolation. It is a transboundary crisis requiring enforceable, cooperative global frameworks;</p><p>2. A global plastics treaty, akin to the Paris Climate Agreement, must be established with binding commitments for plastic reduction, transparency in material use, and accountability mechanisms;</p><p>3. Trade regulations should discourage the export of plastic waste to poorer nations under the guise of recycling;</p><p>4. Industrial compliance must be enforced through clear penalties, rigorous audits, and transparent reporting of plastic use and pollution;</p><p>5. Public-private partnerships can fund innovation while ensuring that corporations contribute meaningfully to cleanup and mitigation–not just through donations, but structural change.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>9.7. Integrating microplastics into climate and health policy</title>
          
          <p>1. Microplastics are not a separate issue–they are part of broader systems of collapse;</p><p>2. Climate models must integrate plastic production and degradation emissions as a significant GHG source;</p><p>3. Public health agencies must formally classify microplastics as pollutants with carcinogenic potential;</p><p>4. Environmental justice frameworks should address how microplastic exposure disproportionately affects vulnerable communities–especially those near landfills, incinerators, and industrial corridors.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>Conceptualization, A.B.; methodology, A.B. and R.K.P.; validation, A.B.; formal analysis, R.K.P. and A.B.; investigation, R.K.P.; data curation, R.K.P.; writing–original draft preparation, R.K.P.; writing–review and editing, R.K.P. and A.B. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used in this paper has been extracted from already published material. These can be accessed through the links provided under the “References” section of the paper.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>339-344</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>Steve</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>Deonie</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phoenix</surname>
              <given-names>Vernon R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le Roux</surname>
              <given-names>Gaël</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Durántez Jiménez</surname>
              <given-names>Pilar</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simonneau</surname>
              <given-names>Anaëlle</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Binet</surname>
              <given-names>Stéphane</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galop</surname>
              <given-names>Didier</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41561-019-0335-5</pub-id>
          <article-title>Atmospheric transport and deposition of microplastics in a remote mountain catchment</article-title>
          <source>Nature Geoscience</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>62</volume>
          <page-range>1596-1605</page-range>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andrady</surname>
              <given-names>Anthony L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2011.05.030</pub-id>
          <article-title>Microplastics in the marine environment</article-title>
          <source>Marine Pollution Bulletin</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bergmann</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gutow</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klages</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Marine Anthropogenic Litter</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
          <year>2015</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>Primary Microplastics in the Oceans: A Global Evaluation of Sources</article-title>
          <source>, http:// doi.org/10.2305/IUCN.CH.2017.01.en.</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <publisher-name>IUCN</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>23</volume>
          <page-range>2388-2392</page-range>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Browne</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niven</surname>
              <given-names>Stewart J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galloway</surname>
              <given-names>Tamara S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rowland</surname>
              <given-names>Steve J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>Richard C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2013.10.012</pub-id>
          <article-title>Microplastic moves pollutants and additives to worms, reducing functions linked to health and biodiversity</article-title>
          <source>Current Biology</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>115</volume>
          <page-range>400-409</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carbery</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O'Connor</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palanisami</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2018.03.007</pub-id>
          <article-title>Trophic transfer of microplastics and mixed contaminants in the marine food web and implications for human health</article-title>
          <source>Environment International</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>62</volume>
          <page-range>2588-2597</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cole</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lindeque</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halsband</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galloway</surname>
              <given-names>Tamara S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2011.09.025</pub-id>
          <article-title>Microplastics as contaminants in the marine environment: A review</article-title>
          <source>Marine Pollution Bulletin</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>111</volume>
          <page-range>10239-10244</page-range>
          <issue>28</issue>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cózar</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Echevarría</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>González-Gordillo</surname>
              <given-names>J. Ignacio</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Irigoien</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Úbeda</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hernández-León</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palma</surname>
              <given-names>Álvaro T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Navarro</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>García-de-Lomas</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruiz</surname>
              <given-names>A. et al</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1314705111</pub-id>
          <article-title>Plastic debris in the open ocean</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>52</volume>
          <page-range>9656-9665</page-range>
          <issue>17</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Souza Machado</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lau</surname>
              <given-names>C. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Till</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kloas</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lehmann</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Becker</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rillig</surname>
              <given-names>Matthias C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.8b02212</pub-id>
          <article-title>Impacts of microplastics on the soil biophysical environment</article-title>
          <source>Environmental Science &amp;amp; Technology</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>104</volume>
          <page-range>290-293</page-range>
          <issue>1-2</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dris</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gasperi</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saad</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mirande</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tassin</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2016.01.006</pub-id>
          <article-title>Synthetic fibers in atmospheric fallout: A source of microplastics in the environment?</article-title>
          <source>Marine Pollution Bulletin</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>0116</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Galloway</surname>
              <given-names>Tamara S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cole</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41559-017-0116</pub-id>
          <article-title>Interactions of microplastic debris throughout the marine ecosystem</article-title>
          <source>Nature Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>586</volume>
          <page-range>127-141</page-range>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Horton</surname>
              <given-names>Alice A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walton</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spurgeon</surname>
              <given-names>David J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lahive</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Svendsen</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.01.190</pub-id>
          <article-title>Microplastics in freshwater and terrestrial environments: Evaluating the current understanding to identify the knowledge gaps and future research priorities</article-title>
          <source>Science of The Total Environment</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>347</volume>
          <page-range>768-771</page-range>
          <issue>6223</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jambeck</surname>
              <given-names>Jenna R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geyer</surname>
              <given-names>Roland</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilcox</surname>
              <given-names>Chris</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siegler</surname>
              <given-names>Theodore R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perryman</surname>
              <given-names>Miriam</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrady</surname>
              <given-names>Anthony</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Narayan</surname>
              <given-names>Ramani</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Law</surname>
              <given-names>Kara Lavender</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1260352</pub-id>
          <article-title>Plastic waste inputs from land into the ocean</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>155</volume>
          <page-range>410-422</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koelmans</surname>
              <given-names>Albert A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nor</surname>
              <given-names>N. H. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hermsen</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kooi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mintenig</surname>
              <given-names>Svenja M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de France</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2019.02.054</pub-id>
          <article-title>Microplastics in freshwaters and drinking water: Critical review and assessment of data quality</article-title>
          <source>Water Research</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>709</volume>
          <page-range>136050</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kögel</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bjorøy</surname>
              <given-names>Ø.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toto</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bienfait</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanden</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.136050</pub-id>
          <article-title>Micro- and nanoplastic toxicity on aquatic life: Determining factors</article-title>
          <source>Science of The Total Environment</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>345</volume>
          <page-range>144-145</page-range>
          <issue>6193</issue>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Law</surname>
              <given-names>Kara Lavender</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>Richard C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1254065</pub-id>
          <article-title>Microplastics in the seas</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>163</volume>
          <page-range>107199</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leslie</surname>
              <given-names>Heather A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Velzen</surname>
              <given-names>Martin J.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brandsma</surname>
              <given-names>Sicco H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vethaak</surname>
              <given-names>A. Dick</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garcia-Vallejo</surname>
              <given-names>Juan J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lamoree</surname>
              <given-names>Marja H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2022.107199</pub-id>
          <article-title>Discovery and quantification of plastic particle pollution in human blood</article-title>
          <source>Environment International</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>137</volume>
          <page-range>362-374</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2017.12.056</pub-id>
          <article-title>Microplastics in freshwater systems: A review on occurrence, environmental effects, and methods for microplastics detection</article-title>
          <source>Water Research</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>140</volume>
          <page-range>320-329</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Locritani</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Merlino</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abbate</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2019.01.023</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessing the citizen science approach as tool to increase awareness on the marine litter problem</article-title>
          <source>Marine Pollution Bulletin</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>Global plastics outlook: Economic drivers, environmental impacts and policy options</article-title>
          <source>, https://doi.org/10.1787/de747aef-en.</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <publisher-name>OECD Publishing</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>17-23</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Revel</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Châtel</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mouneyrac</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coesh.2017.10.003</pub-id>
          <article-title>Micro(nano)plastics: A threat to human health?</article-title>
          <source>Current Opinion in Environmental Science &amp;amp; Health</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>46</volume>
          <page-range>6453-6454</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2012</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rillig</surname>
              <given-names>Matthias C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/es302011r</pub-id>
          <article-title>Microplastic in terrestrial ecosystems and the soil</article-title>
          <source>Environmental Science &amp;amp; Technology</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>494</volume>
          <page-range>169-171</page-range>
          <issue>7436</issue>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rochman</surname>
              <given-names>Chelsea M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Browne</surname>
              <given-names>Mark Anthony</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halpern</surname>
              <given-names>Benjamin S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hentschel</surname>
              <given-names>Brian T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoh</surname>
              <given-names>Eunha</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karapanagioti</surname>
              <given-names>Hrissi K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rios-Mendoza</surname>
              <given-names>Lorena M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takada</surname>
              <given-names>Hideshige</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teh</surname>
              <given-names>Swee</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>Richard C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/494169a</pub-id>
          <article-title>Classify plastic waste as hazardous</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>375-386</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Love</surname>
              <given-names>David C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rochman</surname>
              <given-names>Chelsea M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neff</surname>
              <given-names>Roni A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40572-018-0206-z</pub-id>
          <article-title>Microplastics in seafood and the implications for human health</article-title>
          <source>Current Environmental Health Reports</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>304</volume>
          <page-range>838</page-range>
          <issue>5672</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>Richard C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Olsen</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitchell</surname>
              <given-names>Richard P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davis</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rowland</surname>
              <given-names>Steven J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>John</surname>
              <given-names>Anthony W. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McGonigle</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Russell</surname>
              <given-names>Andrea E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1094559</pub-id>
          <article-title>Lost at sea: Where is all the plastic?</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>371</volume>
          <page-range>672-674</page-range>
          <issue>6530</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vethaak</surname>
              <given-names>A. Dick</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Legler</surname>
              <given-names>Juliette</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abe5041</pub-id>
          <article-title>Microplastics and human health</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>51</volume>
          <page-range>6634-6647</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wright</surname>
              <given-names>Stephanie L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kelly</surname>
              <given-names>Frank J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.7b00423</pub-id>
          <article-title>Plastic and human health: A micro issue</article-title>
          <source>Environmental Science &amp;amp; Technology</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>178</volume>
          <page-range>483-492</page-range>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wright</surname>
              <given-names>Stephanie L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>Richard C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galloway</surname>
              <given-names>Tamara S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2013.02.031</pub-id>
          <article-title>The physical impacts of microplastics on marine organisms: A review</article-title>
          <source>Environmental Pollution</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>642</volume>
          <page-range>12–20</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>G. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Y. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2</pub-id>
          <article-title>The distribution of microplastics in soil aggregate fractions in southwestern China</article-title>
          <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>