<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JGELCD</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Green Economy and Low-Carbon Development</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Green Econ. Low-Carbon Dev.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JGELCD</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2957-9619</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2957-9600</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-0GZwcGP5hIeRklJDgm4p01SiaSX9YfBG</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jgelcd010106</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Distribution Characteristics and Spatial Correlation of Tourist Accommodation Spaces Based on Environment Information</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1">1</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Hou</surname>
            <given-names>Jiadai</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2126-852X</contrib-id>
          <email>houjiadai2020@163.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="2">2</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>Ka'Er</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8413-4492</contrib-id>
          <email>zhukaer812@163.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="1">Engineering Quality Supervision Center of Logistics Support Department of the Military Commission, 100000 Beijing, China</aff>
        <aff id="2">Chinese People’s Liberation Army Aviation School, 100000 Beijing, China</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <year>2022</year>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>54</fpage>
      <lpage>63</lpage>
      <page-range>54-63</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <month>08</month>
          <day>24</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <month>10</month>
          <day>21</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="pub">
          <month>12</month>
          <day>28</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2022 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <license>. Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the <a href='https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/' target='_blank' class='text-yellow-700 hover:underline'>CC BY 4.0 license</a>.</license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>When tourists choose their accommodation space, they tend to prefer areas with beautiful natural landscapes, or close to scenic spots, or those that have local styles. Based on existing research results of tourist accommodation space, some scholars proposed to design smaller spaces for tourist accommodation, however, in terms of the spatial correlation with tourism resources, relevant analysis is insufficient and needs to be supplemented. This paper studied the distribution characteristics and spatial correlation of tourist accommodation spaces based on environment information. At first, the paper analyzed the correlation between tourism resources and tourist accommodation spaces, gave the route of spatial correlation analysis, and analyzed the distribution characteristics of tourist accommodation spaces; then, this paper gave the determination process of optimal spatial distribution pattern of tourist accommodation spaces based on environment information, and adopted the kernel density estimation and the spatial attributes of tourist accommodation space points to study the spatial distribution characteristics. At last, combining with experiment, the distribution characteristics of the tourist accommodation spaces in the study area were given and analyzed.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Environment information</kwd>
        <kwd>Tourist accommodation</kwd>
        <kwd>Spatial distribution</kwd>
        <kwd>Spatial correlation analysis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors">2</count>
        <fig-count>6</fig-count>
        <table-count>5</table-count>
        <ref-count>24</ref-count>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>As people’s living standards have been greatly improved in recent years, their tourism activities become more frequent and are carried out in multiple forms, and the tourists' choices of destinations, accommodation, and dining have become more diversified as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. When tourists choose their accommodation space, they tend to prefer areas with beautiful natural landscapes, or close to scenic spots, or those that have local styles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. In this context, with their unique local features and special regional environment, the local style tourist accommodation and service have greatly satisfied modern tourists’ personalized requirements for travel accommodation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]. Therefore, to figure out related questions such as the distribution characteristics of tourist accommodation spaces, and the influencing factors of driving force, world field scholars have formulated various strategies for the planning of tourist accommodation spaces based on environment information, and their research results have provided certain references for transforming and upgrading regional tourism industry, improving accommodation environment, and developing accommodation conditions. </p><p>Cumo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>] analyzed the feasibility of applying renewable energy in small and medium-sized tourist destinations that depend on independent energy supply systems, the study selected a few accommodation locations with different climate conditions and geographical features in Australia to conduct investigation, and the net present value cost, renewable factor, and payback period were taken as evaluation standards in the analysis. Lim and Chan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>] described a method for designing sustainable tourism accommodation facilities in areas with high environmental values, by minimizing the impact on surrounding environment and making users be more sensitive to natural resource conservation, in the proposed method, three aspects had been taken into consideration, namely the system components, building enclosure structures, and their integration. Tigan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>] summarized the accommodation choices of international and domestic tourists in New Zealand into five categories: hotels, motels, guesthouses, hostels, and campsites. Ecolabel is an environmental policy introduced in Europe by the Ecolabel Regulation in 2000, with agricultural tourism as an example, Filimonau et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>] proposed to use Ecolabel to mark organic agricultural products with reduced pesticide use or controlled disinfectant use, so as to give more advantages to these products in the marke<span style="color: windowtext;">t. Marian et al</span>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>]<span style="color: windowtext;"> discussed the potential of applying Life Cycle Assessment (LCA) to the evaluation of tourist accommodation</span> facilities and its contribution to global carbon footprint, in order to prove its feasibility, this paper applied a simplified LCA tool to two tourist accommodation facilities located in Dorset of Britain to quantify their CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, aiming at reducing the energy consumption and carbon density of the hotel industry; besides, the study also proposed a method for analyzing the energy consumption and carbon footprint of outsourced laundry and breakfast services. </p><p>Field scholars employed various research methods, such as literature analysis, visual analysis, statistical analysis, and Analytic Hierarchy Process (AHP), to analyze the evolution process and the influencing factors of tourist accommodation spaces in different regions during their development process. Some scholars proposed to design smaller spaces for tourist accommodation, however, in terms of the spatial correlation with tourism resources, relevant analysis is insufficient and needs to be supplemented. To fill in this research gap, this paper studied the distribution characteristics and spatial correlation of tourist accommodation spaces based on environment information. The second chapter analyzed the correlation between tourism resources and tourist accommodation spaces, and gave the route of spatial correlation analysis. The third chapter analyzed the distribution characteristics of tourist accommodation spaces. The fourth chapter proposed the determination process of optimal spatial distribution pattern of tourist accommodation spaces based on environment information, and adopted the kernel density estimation and the spatial attributes of tourist accommodation space points to study the spatial distribution characteristics; based on the distance between the tourist accommodation space points to be estimated and the tourism resources, the probability density was estimated. At last, combining with experiment, the distribution characteristics of tourist accommodation spaces in the study area were given and analyzed. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>2. Correlation between tourism resources and tourist accommodation spaces</title>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>Correlation between tourism resources and tourist accommodation spaces</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/11/img_48AmEff6gWGTT5cw.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_2">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>Route of correlation analysis</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/11/img_OPzO4ZkE5ojMzAb0.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> shows the correlation between tourism resources and tourist accommodation spaces. The concept of tourism development based on environment information is the development route for the integration of regional tourism service and tourism resource, and it runs through all fields of production, life, and ecology. With tourism as impetus, the development of relevant industries could be promoted, and the “tourism+” development mode could be expanded to other industries, forming an integrated industrial development pattern. At the same time, tourist accommodation also involves three aspects of production, life, and ecology, so the environment information-based tourism development mode has fully integrated tourism with other industries and promoted them to develop rapidly.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> shows the route of correlation analysis. At first, this paper adopted the average nearest neighbor method to calculate the average distance between each tourist accommodation space point and its nearest neighbor, so as to get the nearest neighbor index which can reflect the spatial distribution pattern of tourist accommodation space points. Assuming <italic>BI</italic> represents the nearest neighbor distance coefficient; <italic>M</italic> represents the area of the study region; <italic>v</italic> represents the number of sample space points; <italic>h</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub><sub> </sub>represents the distance between space point <italic>i</italic> and space point <italic>j</italic>; <italic>h</italic><sub><italic>AV</italic></sub> represents the average nearest neighbor distance; <italic>h</italic><sub><italic>E</italic></sub> represents the expected average distance, then the calculation formula of <italic>BI</italic> could be expressed as:</p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(1)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mi>B</mi>
            <mi>I</mi>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <msub>
              <mi>h</mi>
              <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                <mi>A</mi>
                <mi>V</mi>
              </mrow>
            </msub>
            <msub>
              <mi>h</mi>
              <mi>E</mi>
            </msub>
            <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
              <mo>/</mo>
            </mrow>
            <mfrac>
              <mrow>
                <munderover>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>v</mi>
                </munderover>
                <mfrac>
                  <mrow>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">min</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>h</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>i</mi>
                          <mi>j</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>v</mi>
                </mfrac>
              </mrow>
              <mrow>
                <mn>0.5</mn>
                <msqrt>
                  <mfrac>
                    <mi>M</mi>
                    <mi>v</mi>
                  </mfrac>
                </msqrt>
              </mrow>
            </mfrac>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      <p>When <italic>BI</italic>&amp;amp;gt;1, the tourist accommodation space points distribute uniformly and discretely; when <italic>BI</italic>=1, the space points distribute randomly; and when BI&amp;amp;lt;1, the space points distribute in a clustered state.</p><p>For different research space scales, the tourism accommodation space points show different clustering patterns. In order to explore their spatial distribution characteristics under the conditions of various distance values, this paper adopted the multi-distance spatial clustering analysis method, namely the Ripley’s K function to analyze the multi-distance spatial clustering characteristics of the spatial distribution of tourism resources and tourist accommodation spaces. Assuming: <italic>r</italic> represents the number of tourism resources in the study area; <italic>h</italic> represents the distance threshold; <italic>s</italic><sub><italic>ab</italic></sub>(<italic>h</italic>) represents the distance between tourism resources <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> within distance <italic>h</italic>, then the calculation formula could be given by Formula 2 below:</p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(2)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mi>R</mi>
            <mi>K</mi>
            <mi>h</mi>
            <mi>M</mi>
            <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
            <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <munderover>
              <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
              <mi>a</mi>
              <mi>r</mi>
            </munderover>
            <munderover>
              <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
              <mi>b</mi>
              <mi>r</mi>
            </munderover>
            <mfrac>
              <msub>
                <mi>S</mi>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mi>a</mi>
                  <mi>b</mi>
                  <mi>h</mi>
                  <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                  <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                </mrow>
              </msub>
              <msup>
                <mi>r</mi>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </msup>
            </mfrac>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      <p>The spatial clustering characteristics <italic>SK</italic> (<italic>h</italic>) of various regional tourism resources within distance <italic>h</italic> can be calculated by the following formula:</p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(3)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mi>S</mi>
            <mi>K</mi>
            <mi>h</mi>
            <mi>h</mi>
            <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
            <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mo>−</mo>
            <msqrt>
              <mfrac>
                <mrow>
                  <mi>S</mi>
                  <mi>L</mi>
                  <mi>h</mi>
                  <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                  <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                </mrow>
                <mi>π</mi>
              </mfrac>
            </msqrt>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      <p>If <italic>SK</italic> (<italic>h</italic>)&amp;amp;gt;0, the tourism resources in this region are in a clustered state; if <italic>SK</italic> (<italic>h</italic>)&amp;amp;lt;0, the tourism resources in this region distribute dispersedly; if <italic>SK</italic> (<italic>h</italic>)=0, the tourism resources in this region distribute randomly.This paper used the co-location quotient <italic>Ω</italic> to measure the spatial proximity characteristics of the spatial direction of regional tourism resources and tourist accommodation spaces in areas with high environmental quality, in this way, the closeness of the correlation between different tourist accommodation space points could be measured quantitatively. Assuming: <italic>Ω</italic><sub><italic>M</italic></sub><sub>-</sub><sub><italic>N</italic></sub> represents the co-location quotient of <italic>M</italic> attracted by <italic>N</italic>; <italic>DN</italic><sub><italic>M-N</italic></sub> represents the number of <italic>M</italic>-type regional tourism resources that are close to the <italic>N</italic>-type tourism accommodation spaces; <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>M</italic></sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>N</italic></sub> represent the number of <italic>M</italic>-type regional tourism resources and the number of <italic>N</italic>-type tourism accommodation spaces; <italic>V</italic> represents the total number of tourism resources and tourism accommodation spaces, then, the calculation formula of <italic>Ω</italic> is given by Formula 4:</p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(4)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mtable columnalign="" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>C</mi>
                    <mi>L</mi>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>Q</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>A</mi>
                        <mi>B</mi>
                        <mo stretchy="false">→</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mfrac>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>C</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mi>A</mi>
                            <mi>B</mi>
                            <mo stretchy="false">→</mo>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>N</mi>
                          <mi>A</mi>
                        </msub>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo>/</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mrow>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>N</mi>
                          <mi>B</mi>
                        </msub>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo>/</mo>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                        <mo>−</mo>
                        <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                        <mi>N</mi>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </mrow>
                    </mfrac>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <msub>
                      <mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>M</mi>
                        <mi>N</mi>
                        <mo stretchy="false">→</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mfrac>
                      <mrow>
                        <mi>D</mi>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>N</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mi>M</mi>
                            <mi>N</mi>
                            <mo stretchy="false">→</mo>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>V</mi>
                          <mi>M</mi>
                        </msub>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo>/</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mrow>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>V</mi>
                          <mi>N</mi>
                        </msub>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo>/</mo>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                        <mo>−</mo>
                        <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                        <mi>V</mi>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </mrow>
                    </mfrac>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
            </mtable>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      <p>If <italic>Ω</italic><sub><italic>M-N</italic></sub>&amp;amp;lt;1, <italic>M</italic> tends to being away from <italic>N</italic>; if <italic>Ω</italic><sub><italic>M-N</italic></sub> =1, <italic>M</italic> and <italic>N</italic> distribute randomly; if <italic>Ω</italic><sub><italic>M-N</italic></sub>&amp;amp;gt;1, <italic>M</italic> tends to get close to <italic>N</italic>.</p><p>Then, from the perspectives of supple side and demand side, this paper considered the interaction between the number of regional tourism resources and the tourist accommodation space points, and adopted the 2-step floating catchment area (2SFCA) method to carry out the two searches. In the first search, search the study area, count the number, and calculate the ratio of the number of tourism resources to the number of tourist accommodation space points <italic>G</italic><sub><italic>Q</italic></sub>. Assuming: <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> represents the number of tourist accommodation space points; <italic>O</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> represents the number of tourism resources within search domain <italic>m</italic>; <italic>h</italic><sub><italic>lm</italic></sub> represents the walk distance between locations <italic>l</italic> and <italic>m</italic>, then the calculation formula of <italic>G</italic><sub><italic>Q</italic></sub> is shown as Formula 5:</p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(5)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <msub>
              <mi>G</mi>
              <mi>Q</mi>
            </msub>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mfrac>
              <msub>
                <mi>O</mi>
                <mi>m</mi>
              </msub>
              <mrow>
                <munder>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>l</mi>
                    <mo>∈</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                      <mo>≤</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>h</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>l</mi>
                          <mi>m</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>h</mi>
                        <mn>0</mn>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </munder>
                <msub>
                  <mi>A</mi>
                  <mi>l</mi>
                </msub>
              </mrow>
            </mfrac>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      <p>In the second search, search the study area, count the number, calculate the ratio of the number of tourism resources to the number of tourist accommodation space points, and sum up. Assuming: <italic>M</italic><sup><italic>J</italic></sup><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> represents the spatial accessibility of tourism resources within tourism accommodation space area <italic>n</italic>, the greater the value of <italic>m</italic>, the better the spatial accessibility of space area <italic>n</italic>; <italic>G</italic> represents the ratio of the number of tourism resources to the number of tourist accommodation space points within search domain m in the tourism accommodation space area <italic>n</italic>; and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>nm</italic></sub> represents the travel distance between space locations <italic>n</italic> and <italic>m</italic>, then the calculation formula of <italic>M</italic><sup><italic>J</italic></sup><sub><italic>m</italic></sub><sub> </sub>is shown as Formula 6:</p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(6)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <msubsup>
              <mi>M</mi>
              <mi>m</mi>
              <mi>J</mi>
            </msubsup>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <munder>
              <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
              <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                <mi>m</mi>
                <mo>∈</mo>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                  <mo>≤</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>k</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>n</mi>
                      <mi>m</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>K</mi>
                    <mn>0</mn>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
              </mrow>
            </munder>
            <munder>
              <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
              <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                <mi>j</mi>
                <mo>∈</mo>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                  <mo>≤</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>k</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>n</mi>
                      <mi>m</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>k</mi>
                    <mn>0</mn>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
              </mrow>
            </munder>
            <msub>
              <mi>G</mi>
              <mi>j</mi>
            </msub>
            <mfrac>
              <msub>
                <mi>O</mi>
                <mi>m</mi>
              </msub>
              <mrow>
                <munder>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>l</mi>
                    <mo>∈</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                      <mo>≤</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>k</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>n</mi>
                          <mi>m</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>d</mi>
                        <mn>0</mn>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </munder>
                <msub>
                  <mi>A</mi>
                  <mi>l</mi>
                </msub>
              </mrow>
            </mfrac>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>3. Spatial distribution characteristics of tourist accommodation spaces</title>
      <p>There’re three common spatial distribution patterns of space points: the clustered type, the uniform type, and the random type. This paper employed the nearest neighbor index method to study the spatial distribution patterns of tourist accommodation space points, that is, to describe and measure the proximity of tourist accommodation space points. In this paper, the ratio of average nearest neighbor distance to theoretical nearest neighbor distance was defined as the nearest neighbor index, denoted as <italic>VG</italic>, this parameter can reflect the spatial distribution characteristics of tourist accommodation space points. Assuming: <italic>g</italic><sup><italic>*</italic></sup><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> represents the average nearest neighbor distance; <italic>g</italic><sub><italic>F</italic></sub> represents the theoretical nearest neighbor distance; <italic>q</italic> represents the number of space points, then the calculation formula of <italic>VG</italic> is shown as Formula 7:</p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(7)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mi>V</mi>
            <mi>G</mi>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mo>;</mo>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mfrac>
              <msubsup>
                <mi>g</mi>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mo>∗</mo>
              </msubsup>
              <msub>
                <mi>g</mi>
                <mi>F</mi>
              </msub>
            </mfrac>
            <mfrac>
              <mn>1</mn>
              <mrow>
                <mn>2</mn>
                <msqrt>
                  <mi>q</mi>
                  <mi>M</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mo>/</mo>
                  </mrow>
                </msqrt>
              </mrow>
            </mfrac>
            <msub>
              <mi>g</mi>
              <mi>F</mi>
            </msub>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      <p>If <italic>VG</italic>&amp;amp;lt;1, the spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points exhibits the clustered distribution pattern; if <italic>VG</italic>&amp;amp;gt;1, it exhibits the uniform distribution pattern; if <italic>VG</italic>=1, it shows the random distribution pattern; if <italic>VG</italic>=0, it means that all tourist accommodation space points are concentrated in one point.</p><p>Spatial autocorrelation is mainly measured by the locations and attribute values of tourist accommodation space points, specifically, it includes the global spatial autocorrelation and the local spatial autocorrelation. For global spatial autocorrelation, the global Moran's index is used for clustering test; while for local spatial autocorrelation, the local Moran’s index is used for clustering test, and the relevant formula is given by Formula 8:</p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(8)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mi>M</mi>
            <mi>I</mi>
            <mo>.</mo>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mfrac>
              <mrow>
                <munderover>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>q</mi>
                </munderover>
                <munderover>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>j</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>q</mi>
                </munderover>
                <msub>
                  <mi>S</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mi>j</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </msub>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo>−</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>c</mi>
                    <mi>i</mi>
                  </msub>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mover>
                      <mi>c</mi>
                      <mo stretchy="false">¯</mo>
                    </mover>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo>−</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>c</mi>
                    <mi>j</mi>
                  </msub>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mover>
                      <mi>c</mi>
                      <mo stretchy="false">¯</mo>
                    </mover>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
              </mrow>
              <mrow>
                <msup>
                  <mi>U</mi>
                  <mn>2</mn>
                </msup>
                <munderover>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>j</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>q</mi>
                </munderover>
                <msub>
                  <mi>S</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mi>j</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </msub>
              </mrow>
            </mfrac>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      <p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Assuming: </span><italic>c</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> and </span><italic>c</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> represent observed values in the </span><italic>i</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">-th and </span><italic>j</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">-th area units; </span><italic>S</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> represents the spatial weight matrix, which is a binary function that describes whether two spatial areas are adjacent, 1 indicates yes, and 0 indicates no. The value range of Moran’s index </span><italic>M.I</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> is [-1, 1]. If the value of </span><italic>M.I</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> &amp;amp;gt; 0, it indicates that the areas with more or less tourist accommodation space points exhibit a clustered state; the closer the value of </span><italic>M.I</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> to 1, the more obvious the clustering of tourist accommodation space points; if value of </span><italic>M.I</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> &amp;amp;lt; 0, it indicates that there is a significant difference in the number of tourist accommodation space points between the study area and the surrounding area, the closer the value of </span><italic>M.I </italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">to</span><italic> </italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">-1, the more obvious the difference. </span></p><p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">In order to accurately measure the uniformity of tourism resource distribution in the study area, this paper analyzed the differences in the distribution of tourist accommodation space points in different regions and sub-regions based on the Gini coefficient and explored the law of space point distribution in different regions and in the entire study area. Assuming: </span><italic>ϕ</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> represents the proportion of the number of regional tourism accommodation space points in the city's total number of tourism accommodation space points; </span><italic>SV</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> represents the number of regions in the study area; </span><italic>TK</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> represents the uniformity of tourism resource distribution in the study area, then the calculation formula of </span><italic>TK</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> is:</span></p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(9)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mi>G</mi>
            <mi>N</mi>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mfrac>
              <mrow>
                <mo>−</mo>
                <munderover>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>S</mi>
                    <mi>V</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </munderover>
                <msub>
                  <mi>ϕ</mi>
                  <mi>i</mi>
                </msub>
                <msub>
                  <mi>ϕ</mi>
                  <mi>i</mi>
                </msub>
                <mi>In</mi>
              </mrow>
              <mrow>
                <mi>L</mi>
                <mi>n</mi>
                <mi>S</mi>
                <mi>V</mi>
              </mrow>
            </mfrac>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(10)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mi>T</mi>
            <mi>K</mi>
            <mi>G</mi>
            <mi>N</mi>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mo>−</mo>
            <mn>1</mn>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      <p>Gen<span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">erally, the value range of the Gini coefficient is [0, 1], and the size of the value is inversely proportional to the distribution uniformity of tourist accommodation space points, the greater the value, the higher the clustering degree of tourist accommodation space points. When the value of </span><italic>GN</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> is 0, it means that the tourist accommodation space points distribute uniformly in each region; when the value of </span><italic>GN</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> is 1, it means that the distribution of space points is too concentrated and extremely unbalanced; when </span><italic>O</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">&amp;amp;lt;</span><italic>GN</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">&amp;amp;lt;0.2, it means the distribution of space points presents an absolute equilibrium state; when 0.2&amp;amp;lt;</span><italic>GN</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">&amp;amp;lt;0.3 is, the distribution is relatively uniform; when 0.3&amp;amp;lt;</span><italic>GN</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">&amp;amp;lt;0.4, the distribution is relatively reasonable; when 0.4&amp;amp;lt;</span><italic>GN</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">&amp;amp;lt;0.5, the distribution is relatively uneven; and when </span><italic>GN</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">≥0.5, the distribution is</span> extremely unbalanced.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>4. Determination of optimal accommodation space distribution pattern</title>
      <p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Starting from </span>the perspective of envi<span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">ronment information, this paper compared four types of tourist accommodation spaces: random type (randomly scattered), axis-belt type (scattered around axes and form belts), ray type (scattered like homocentric rays), and single-kernel type (clustered around each single kernel). The random type is developed based on the self-organization form, most of these accommodation spaces are built by the residents themselves. The axis-belt type is formed along rivers and roads that have advantages in locations and landscape resources, the accommodation spaces cluster around them but their development space is limited, so it is not the optimal type. The ray type is formed based on the advantages of central urban areas in traffic, resources, supporting facilities, and population density, etc., however, similar to the axis-belt type, its development space is limited as well, and it is not the optimal type either. The single-kernel type has the same advantages as the ray type, the accommodation spaces mainly distribute in urban, rural areas or in scenic spots, they form separate regions around each single cluster center, this type meets the development requirements of tourism industry based on environment information, and it is relatively ideal.</span></p><p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">In the research on the spatial distribution characteristics of tourism accommodation space points based on environment information, to a certain extent, the concentration index of tourism resources with high environmental quality can reflect the concentration degree of spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points under different environmental quality con</span>ditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>). Assumi<span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">ng: </span><italic>FR</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> represents the concentration index of tourist accommodation space points in the study area, its value range is [0, 100]. The closer the value of </span><italic>FR</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> is to 100, the more concentrated the spatial distribution of tourism accommodation space points in regions with high environmental quality; the closer the value of </span><italic>FR</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> is to 0, the more scattered the tourism accommodation space points. Assuming </span><italic>SC</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> represents the number of tourist accommodation space points distributed in the </span><italic>i</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">-th region, </span><italic>TI</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> represents the total number of tourist accommodation space points distributed in the study area, </span><italic>SV</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> represents the number of regions in the study area, then the calculation formulas are:</span></p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(11)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mi>F</mi>
            <mi>R</mi>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mo>×</mo>
            <mn>100</mn>
            <msqrt>
              <munderover>
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mi>i</mi>
                  <mo>=</mo>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mi>S</mi>
                  <mi>V</mi>
                </mrow>
              </munderover>
              <msup>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <mfrac>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>C</mi>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>T</mi>
                      <mi>I</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </mfrac>
                </mrow>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </msup>
            </msqrt>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(12)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mover>
              <mrow>
                <mi>F</mi>
                <mi>R</mi>
              </mrow>
              <mo accent="true">―</mo>
            </mover>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mo>×</mo>
            <mn>100</mn>
            <msqrt>
              <mi>S</mi>
              <mi>V</mi>
              <msup>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <mfrac>
                    <mover>
                      <mrow>
                        <mi>S</mi>
                        <mi>C</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo accent="true">―</mo>
                    </mover>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>T</mi>
                      <mi>I</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </mfrac>
                </mrow>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </msup>
            </msqrt>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_3">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>The determination process of optimal tourist accommodation space pattern based on environment information</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/11/img_a4wAz4QOXpY82jkM.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">When the concentration index of tourist accommodation space points is greater than the average value, it means that the spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points is more concentrated in regions with better environmental quality; when the concentration index of tourist accommodation space points is smaller than the average value, it means that the spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points is more dispersed in regions with better environmental quality. </span></p><p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">In order to estimate the probability density based on the distance between the tourist accommodation space points to be estimated and the tourism resources, this paper used the kernel density estimation method and the spatial attributes of tourist accommodation space points</span><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: 宋体;"> </span><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">to study their spatial distribution characteristics, so as to better describe the concentration degree of the spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points. Assuming: </span><italic>KD</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">(</span><italic>c</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">) represents the kernel density function at a spatial location </span><italic>c</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">, </span><italic>y</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> represents the analysis threshold, </span><italic>ξ </italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">represents the number of points within the analysis threshold, </span><italic>ω </italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">represents the default spatial weight kernel function, then, there is:</span></p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(13)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mi>K</mi>
            <mi>D</mi>
            <mi>c</mi>
            <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
            <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mfrac>
              <mn>1</mn>
              <mrow>
                <mi>ξ</mi>
                <mi>y</mi>
              </mrow>
            </mfrac>
            <munderover>
              <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
              <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mn>1</mn>
              </mrow>
              <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                <mi>ξ</mi>
              </mrow>
            </munderover>
            <msub>
              <mi>ω</mi>
              <mi>q</mi>
            </msub>
            <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
              <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
              <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
              <mfrac>
                <mrow>
                  <mi>c</mi>
                  <mo>−</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>c</mi>
                    <mi>i</mi>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
                <mi>y</mi>
              </mfrac>
            </mrow>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      <p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Buffer analysis can intuitively show the spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points in regions with high environmental quality and its change trends with the distance, then, for a certain tourist accommodation space point </span><italic>X</italic><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">, Formula 14 gives the formula of its buffer analysis:</span></p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(14)</label>
          <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
            <mi>W</mi>
            <mi>c</mi>
            <mi>h</mi>
            <mi>c</mi>
            <mi>U</mi>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mo fence="false" stretchy="false">{</mo>
            <mo data-mjx-texclass="ORD" fence="false" stretchy="false">‖</mo>
            <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
            <mo>,</mo>
            <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
            <mo fence="false" stretchy="false">}</mo>
          </math>
        </disp-formula>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>5. Experimental results and analysis</title>
      <p>According to the development pattern of the tourism industry, in this paper, the study area was divided into four main regions: A, B, C, and D, and region A was further divided into sub-regions A1 and A2. From the perspective of each region, the number of tourist accommodation space points in region A was the most, accounting for 62.52% of the total number; followed by region B, accounting for 20.15%; while for regions C and D, the numbers were close, and neither exceeded 10%. According to these results, it’s known that the development scale of tourist accommodation space points in region A was significantly greater than that of the other regions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>ArcGIS10.2 was used to calculate the nearest neighbor index of tourist accommodation space points in the study area and in each region, the results are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>. The calculation results passed the 1% significance test. The values of the nearest neighbor index of the spatial distribution of tourism accommodation spatial points in the entire study area and in each region were far less than 1, so the spatial distribution patterns of tourism accommodation space points were all the clustered type. The aggregation of tourist accommodation space points can cause the scale effect more easily, and it is conducive to the rational distribution of tourism resources with higher environmental quality.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>Number and proportion of tourist accommodation space points in each region</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Region</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>B</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>D</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Number of space points</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1585</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>628</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>223</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>281</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Proportion</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>62.52</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>20.15</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7.18</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9.57</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rank</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_2">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>Nearest neighbor index of tourist accommodation space points in each region</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Study area</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Region</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>B</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>D</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Average observed distance</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>932.8574</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>315.0195</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1528.1473</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1857.3269</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3625.1748</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Average expected distance</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3628.5412</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>962.481</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3928.4758</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5284.7261</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7485.2419</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Nearest neighbor index</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.326282</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.301527</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.392547</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.574855</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.415827</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Distribution pattern</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Clustered type</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Clustered type</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scattered type</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Clustered type</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scattered type</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_3">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>Gini coefficients of spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points in different regions</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Study area</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Region</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>B</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>D</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Gini coefficient</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.52</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.41</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.32</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.41</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.48</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Distribution uniformity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.41</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.77</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.69</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.77</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.51</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_4">
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>Concentration index of spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points in each region</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Study area</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Region</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>B</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>D</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Geographic concentration index (<italic>G</italic>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>26.35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>41.28</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>36.14</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>33.51</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>62.59</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Average geographic concentration index (<italic>G</italic>’)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15.82</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>32.93</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>28.26</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>31.42</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>41.07</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_5">
          <label>Table 5</label>
          <caption>Statistics of standard deviational ellipses and mean center data of different types of tourist accommodation spaces</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Year</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Type of the tourist accommodation space</p></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Type I</p></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Type Ⅱ</p></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Type Ⅲ</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Short</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Long</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Short</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Long</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Short</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Long</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>2010</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Longitude and latitude mean center</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>101.52</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>524.17</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>115.39</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>612.74</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>112.72</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>583.64</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>21.0637</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>70.31</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22.5824</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>94.16</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>24.1901</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>86.37</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Difference between long and short axes</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3658</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.4185</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3268</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>53.01</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Azimuth</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>185.02</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>75</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>162.03</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>87</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>142.51</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>89.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>2015</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Longitude and latitude mean center</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>----</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p> </p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>102.85</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>603.41</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>133.52</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>568.47</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>----</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p> </p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>23.6255</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>95.04</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>23.6248</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>85.62</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Difference between long and short axes</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>----</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p> </p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2518</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.4152</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>42.15</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Azimuth</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>----</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p> </p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0415</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3625</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>110.27</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>2020</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Longitude and latitude mean center</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>112.035</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>78.5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>115.827</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>362.5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>111.742</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.06</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>23.85</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>76.24</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>23.16</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>715.2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22.57</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>556.23</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Difference between long and short axes</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.058</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>785</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.036</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>62</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.042</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>653</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Azimuth</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11.52</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>174</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9.326</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>845</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.623</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>805</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Also, the Gini coefficients of the spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points in the study area and in different regions were calculated, and the results are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>, wherein the Gini coefficient of the study area was 0.52, and the degree of distribution uniformity was 0.41, indicating the spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points in the study area was extremely unbalanced, and there’s a huge difference in the number of tourist accommodation space points in each region. The Gini coefficients of regions A and C were both 0.41, and the degree of distribution uniformity was 0.77, indicating that the distribution of tourist accommodation space points in these two regions was reasonable, and the difference in the number of space points between the two regions was small. the Gini coefficient of region D was 0.48, which was the highest among the four regions, indicating that the spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points in this region was unbalanced, and there’s a big difference in the number of space points between the sub-regions. The Gini coefficient of region A was 0.32, which was the lowest among the four regions, indicating that the spatial distribution of tourism accommodation space points in this region was uniform, and there wasn’t a big difference in the number of space points between the sub-regions. According to above analysis, on the whole, the spatial distribution of tourism accommodation space points in the study area was quite different, however, with in each region, the spatial distribution of tourism accommodation space points in each sub-region was not that different. </p><p>The concentration index of spatial distribution of tourist accommodation space points in the study area and in each region was calculated, the results are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>. Overall speaking, the concentration index of tourism accommodation space points in the study area was greater than the average concentration index, the distribution of tourism accommodation space points was concentrated. In terms of the four regions, their concentration index values were all greater than the average value of concentration index, and the spatial distribution pattern of tourism accommodation space points in all these four regions was the clustered type. </p><p>Except for the increase in the number of tourist accommodation space points distributed with in distance interval 2~5 km, overall speaking, as the distance from 4A-level scenic spots increases, the number of tourist accommodation space points decreases, and this trend is clearly shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_4">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>The change of the number of tourist accommodation space points distributed in the study area with the distance from 4A-level scenic spots</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/11/img_HoFNP0ghfNixCpwI.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_5">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>The change of the number of tourist accommodation space points over time</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/11/img_JmW7_FVBhOfZbhy1.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_6">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>The spatial distribution pattern of tourism accommodation spaces in the study area</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/11/img_-vrvZTKSN5zkXECf.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> shows the change of the number of tourist accommodation space points over time. In terms of the overall number, from year 2015 to 2020, the number of tourist accommodation space points in the study area showed a fast growth, with an average increase of about 200 new points each year. The study area is a famous tourist destination in China, under the support of national tourism policy, tourism industry, as well as the relevant industries developed rapidly, especially the tourist accommodation industry. In terms of the type of tourist accommodation spaces, since 2015, the three types of tourist accommodation spaces: luxury type I, comfortable type II, and economic type III all showed fast development trend, and the growth rate peaked in 2017-2018.</p><p>With the help of the standard deviational ellipse tool in ArcGIS, taking year 2010, 2015 and 2020 as three time nodes, the directionality, dispersion degree, and evolution trajectory of the spatial distribution of the three types (luxury type I, comfortable type II, and economic type III) of tourist accommodation space points could be revealed, and the evolution law of their geographical space distribution could be figured out (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref>). The long and short axes of ellipses represent the development direction and clustering range of the tourist accommodation space points. The greater the value difference between the long and short axes, the more obvious the directionality of clustering distribution; on the contrary, the smaller the value, the less obvious the directionality. Moreover, the shorter the short axis of the ellipse, the more obvious the directionality of the clustering distribution. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref> gives the spatial distribution pattern of tourist accommodation spaces in the study area.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>6. Conclusion</title>
      <p>This paper studied the distribution characteristics and spatial correlation of tourist accommodation spaces based on environment information, gave the route of the correlation analysis, and analyzed the distribution characteristics of tourist accommodation spaces. Also, based on environment information, the determination process of the optimal distribution pattern of tourist accommodation spaces was given, and kernel density estimation was adopted to study the spatial distribution characteristics based on the spatial attributes of tourist accommodation space points.</p><p>The experimental results obtained in this research gave the number and proportion of tourist accommodation space points in each region, also, the Gini coefficient and concentration index of the distribution of tourist accommodation space points in each region were calculated, the change of the number of tourist accommodation space points distributed in the study area with the distance from 4A-level scenic spots, and the change trend of the tourist accommodation space points over time were plotted. After that, the directionality, dispersion degree, and evolution trajectory of the spatial distribution of different types of tourist accommodation space points were revealed, and at last, the distribution pattern of tourist accommodation space points in the study area was obtained.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p></p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Weng</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An empirical study on the influence of the mobile information system on sports and fitness on the choice of tourist destinations</article-title>
          <source>Mob Inf. Syst.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>2021</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1155/2021/5303590</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5303590</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Cao</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Exploring the essence of distance: A framework of distance desire and tourist destination choice</article-title>
          <source>Acta. Geographica Sinica.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>860-877</page-range>
          <fpage>860</fpage>
          <lpage>877</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel evaluation approach for tourist choice of destination based on grey relation analysis</article-title>
          <source>Sci. Programming-Neth.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>2016</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1155/2016/1812094</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1812094</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Forster</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P. W.</given-names>
              <surname>Schuhmann</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>I. R.</given-names>
              <surname>Lake</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. R.</given-names>
              <surname>Watkinson</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The influence of hurricane risk on tourist destination choice in the Caribbean</article-title>
          <source>Climatic Change.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>745-768</page-range>
          <fpage>745</fpage>
          <lpage>768</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-012-0433-5</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Díez-Gutiérrez</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Babri</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Explanatory variables underlying the route choice decisions of tourists: The case of Geiranger Fjord in Norway</article-title>
          <source>Trans Res. Part A: Policy Pract.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>141</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>398-409</page-range>
          <fpage>398</fpage>
          <lpage>409</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tra.2020.09.023</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Han</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tourists’ congestion perception analysis based on ordered choice model</article-title>
          <source>J. Trans. Syst. Eng. Inf. Technol</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>138-144</page-range>
          <fpage>138</fpage>
          <lpage>144</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
              <surname>Racioppi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Marcarelli</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Squillante</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Energetic-environmental requalification for tourist accommodation facilities by analytic hierarchy process</article-title>
          <source>CCCA12, Marseille, France, IEEE</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>December 06-08</publisher-name>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>2012</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/CCCA.2012.6417854</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
              <surname>Filimonau</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Dickinson</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Robbins</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
              <surname>Huijbregts</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reviewing the carbon footprint analysis of hotels: Life Cycle Energy Analysis (LCEA) as a holistic method for carbon impact appraisal of tourist accommodation</article-title>
          <source>J. Clean Prod.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <page-range>1917-1930</page-range>
          <fpage>1917</fpage>
          <lpage>1930</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2011.07.002</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
              <surname>Tigan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
              <surname>Brinzan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Lungu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. I.</given-names>
              <surname>Milin</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ecolabeling in touristic accommodation structures-an integral part of sustainable management</article-title>
          <source>Int. Multidiscip. Sci. GeoConf. SGEM.</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>235-242</page-range>
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          <lpage>242</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>G. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Dalton</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
              <surname>Lockington</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T. E.</given-names>
              <surname>Baldock</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A survey of tourist attitudes to renewable energy supply in Australian hotel accommodation</article-title>
          <source>Renew Energ.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>0</issue>
          <page-range>2174-2185</page-range>
          <fpage>2174</fpage>
          <lpage>2185</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.renene.2007.12.016</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Wojciechowska-Solis</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Kobyłka</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Gawryluk</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Social Responsibility of Economic Units and the Well-Being of Society in the Tourism Sector: Example of Accommodation Facility</article-title>
          <source>Energies.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <page-range>6270-6270</page-range>
          <fpage>6270</fpage>
          <lpage>6270</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/en14196270</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Kozłowski</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Brzozowska-Rup</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Piotrowska-Piątek</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Information and Communication Technologies in food and accommodation sector in EU countries: Sticker or challenge for tourism development</article-title>
          <source>Technol Forecast. Soc.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>171</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.techfore.2021.120941</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">120941</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
              <surname>Provotorina</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Kazmina</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Petrenko</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Ekinil</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Organization and functioning of accommodation facilities as a component of rural tourism infrastructure in the Rostov Region</article-title>
          <source>E3S Web of conferences</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>EDP Sciences</publisher-name>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>175</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>10002-10002</page-range>
          <fpage>10002</fpage>
          <lpage>10002</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202017510002</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
              <surname>Agyeiwaah</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Exploring the relevance of sustainability to micro tourism and hospitality accommodation enterprises (MTHAEs): Evidence from home-stay owners</article-title>
          <source>J. Clean Prod.</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>226</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>159-171</page-range>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>171</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2019.04.089</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Pathumporn</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Nakapaksin</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accommodation management for integrated sustainable tourism management</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Sust Dev Plann.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>236-244</page-range>
          <fpage>236</fpage>
          <lpage>244</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.2495/SDP-V11-N3-236-244</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Z. H.</given-names>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>X. H.</given-names>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Estimating Carbon Emission of Tourism Transportation and Accommodation in China</article-title>
          <source>Advanced Materials Research</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>962</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>1327-1331</page-range>
          <fpage>1327</fpage>
          <lpage>1331</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.4028/www.scientific.net/AMR.962-965.1327</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Hernández-Romero</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L. F.</given-names>
              <surname>Fuentes-Cortés</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Nápoles-Rivera</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Conditions accommodating a dominant stakeholder in the design of renewable air conditioning systems for tourism complexes</article-title>
          <source>Energy.</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>172</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>808-822</page-range>
          <fpage>808</fpage>
          <lpage>822</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.energy.2019.02.019</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Tourism accommodation facilities in the function of responsible development of Dubrovnik</article-title>
          <source>Annals of DAAAM &amp; Proceedings</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <uri>https://go.gale.com/ps/i.do?id=GALE%7CA177174591&amp;sid=googleScholar&amp;v=2.1&amp;it=r&amp;linkaccess=abs&amp;issn=17269679&amp;p=AONE&amp;sw=w&amp;userGroupName=anon%7E5993f270</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>G. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Dalton</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
              <surname>Lockington</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T. E.</given-names>
              <surname>Baldock</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case study feasibility analysis of renewable energy supply options for small to medium-sized tourist accommodations</article-title>
          <source>Renew Energ.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>1134-1144</page-range>
          <fpage>1134</fpage>
          <lpage>1144</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Cumo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
              <surname>Garcia</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
              <surname>Stefanini</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Tiberi</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Technologies and strategies to design sustainable tourist accommodations in areas of high environmental value not connected to the electricity grid</article-title>
          <source>Int J. sus deve Plann.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>20-28</page-range>
          <fpage>20</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.2495/SDP-V10-N1-20-28</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>Lim</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Chan</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Anderssen</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R. D.</given-names>
              <surname>Braddock</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L. T. H.</given-names>
              <surname>Newham</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Forecasting tourist accommodation demand in New Zealand</article-title>
          <source/>
          <publisher-loc>Cairns, Australia</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>The Modelling and Simulation Society of Australia and New Zealand Inc</publisher-name>
          <conf-name>18th World IMACS / MODSIM Congress</conf-name>
          <conf-acronym/>
          <conf-loc>July 13</conf-loc>
          <conf-date>2009</conf-date>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>1251-1257</page-range>
          <fpage>1251</fpage>
          <lpage>1257</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
              <surname>Tigan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
              <surname>Brinzan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Lungu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. I.</given-names>
              <surname>Milin</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ecolabeling in touristic accommodation structures-an integral part of sustainable management</article-title>
          <source>Int. Multidiscip. Sci. GeoConf. SGEM.</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>235-242</page-range>
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          <lpage>242</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
              <surname>Filimonau</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Dickinson</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Robbins</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
              <surname>Huijbregts</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reviewing the carbon footprint analysis of hotels: Life Cycle Energy Analysis (LCEA) as a holistic method for carbon impact appraisal of tourist accommodation</article-title>
          <source>J. Clean Prod.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <page-range>1917-1930</page-range>
          <fpage>1917</fpage>
          <lpage>1930</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2011.07.002</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Marian</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G. R.</given-names>
              <surname>Manuela</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
              <surname>Cristina</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Developments and characteristics of net using of the accommodation capacity from the establishments of tourist reception in Romania</article-title>
          <source/>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>IBIMA</publisher-name>
          <conf-name>Business Transformation Through Innovation and Knowledge Management: An Academic Perspective-Proceedings of the 14th International Business Information Management Association Conference</conf-name>
          <conf-acronym/>
          <conf-loc>IBIMA 2010</conf-loc>
          <conf-date>2010</conf-date>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>1827-1833</page-range>
          <fpage>1827</fpage>
          <lpage>1833</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>