<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJCMEM</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.18280</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Computational Methods and Experimental Measurements</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Int. J. Comput. Methods Exp. Meas.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IJCMEM</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2046-0554</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2046-0546</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-I76BiDHwQbaSIqtZenhAaPMQPv2Hh49_</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijcmem.110206</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Dematel-Based Completion Technique Applied for the Sustainability Assessment of Bridges Near Shore</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6539-1626</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Navarro</surname>
            <given-names>Ignacio J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2435-4095</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Marti</surname>
            <given-names>José V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5488-6001</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Yepes</surname>
            <given-names>VíCtor</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>vyepesp@cst.upv.es</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Construction Engineering, Universitat Politècnica de València, Valencia 46022, Spain</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Institute of Concrete Science and Technology (ICITECH), Universitat Politècnica de València, Valencia 46022, Spain</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub"/>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>115</fpage>
      <lpage>122</lpage>
      <page-range>115-122</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>02</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>04</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2023 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">In recent times, the construction industry has been recognized as a critical sector in achieving the Sustainable Development Goals. However, construction activities and infrastructure have both beneficial and non-beneficial impacts, making infrastructure design the focus of current research in finding the best way to meet society's demands for sustainability. Although methods for economic, environmental, and social life cycle assessments of infrastructures are well-known, the challenge lies in combining these dimensions into a comprehensive indicator that aids decision-making. This study uses three decision-making techniques, namely TOPSIS, COPRAS, and VIKOR, to evaluate five different design alternatives for a concrete bridge exposed to a coastal environment. To enhance the consistency of the multi-criteria decision-making process, a DEMATEL-based approach is applied. The study's results demonstrate unanimously that concrete containing even small amounts of silica fume performs better over its life cycle than other solutions typically considered to increase durability, such as reducing the water/cement ratio or increasing concrete cover.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Sustainable design</kwd>
        <kwd>bridges</kwd>
        <kwd>Life cycle assessment</kwd>
        <kwd>DEMATEL</kwd>
        <kwd>TOPSIS</kwd>
        <kwd>VIKOR</kwd>
        <kwd>COPRAS</kwd>
        <kwd>Multi-criteria decision-making</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="3"/>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="10"/>
        <ref-count count="38"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>The pursuit of sustainable development has become a top priority for both the public and private sectors. Since the inception of the Sustainable Development Goals in 2015, our society has taken significant strides towards their implementation. An excellent example is the ambitious European Green Deal, which aims to achieve climate neutrality in Europe while promoting a circular economy. The construction industry is crucial in achieving this objective, as it is one of the sectors with the most substantial negative impact on the environment. As a result, numerous researchers are focusing on infrastructure design optimization to minimize economic and environmental impacts. Their work encompasses a wide range of infrastructures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], making it a highly significant area of interest.</p><p>When it comes to addressing sustainability concerns, society often resorts to ecological reductionism, oversimplifying the complex and multidimensional nature of these issues. In reality, assessing sustainability requires a holistic approach that acknowledges the need to consider multiple perspectives and disciplines. Multi-criteria decision-making (MCDM) techniques are highly effective tools for achieving a multidisciplinary approach to sustainability assessment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. Consequently, researchers have been working in recent years to develop various tools and methods for evaluating the sustainability of different infrastructures. A wide range of MCDM techniques has been employed to draw relevant conclusions, which can inform future design actions. However, there is no consensus on which MCDM method is best suited for sustainable infrastructure assessment. Some authors argue that using multiple MCDM techniques is necessary to achieve a comprehensive and reliable sustainability assessment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>].</p><p>The use of MCDM techniques typically depends on determining the relevance of each criterion in the final decision. This is often done through the Analytic Hierarchy Process (AHP), a widely used MCDM technique. However, there has been criticism of AHP's accuracy for complex problems since human judgment consistency is inversely proportional to problem complexity. Several approaches aim to reduce uncertainty in the results. One popular method is reducing the number of judgments requested from experts to increase the consistency of their judgments by simplifying the problem's complexity.</p><p><span style="font-family: Times, serif">This study proposes using the DEMATEL technique to reduce the number of comparisons required of experts to determine criteria weights using the AHP technique. After determining the weights, the study assesses the life cycle sustainability of five design alternatives for a concrete bridge in a coastal area, using three MCDM techniques: TOPSIS, VIKOR, and COPRAS. The sustainability assessment considered a set of nine quantitative criteria that encompassed all three sustainability dimensions: economy, environment, and society.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Materials and methods</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Ahp</title>
          
          <p>The Analytic Hierarchy Process (AHP) is a MCDM technique first defined by Saaty back in 1980 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. This method is nowadays widely used to determine the weights to be assigned to each criterion involved in decision-making problems of any kind. This technique requires an expert to compare pairwise the relevance that each criterion shall have with respect to each other when taking the decision. By doing so, a square so-called comparison matrix <italic><span style="color: black">A<sub><span style="color: black">nxn</sub></italic> is constructed, where n is the number of criteria involved in the decision-making process. The comparison between two criteria is based on the Saaty’s fundamental scale, which is used to transform linguistic judgements into numerical values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Saaty’s fundamental scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Semantic Comparison Term</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Numerical Equivalence</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Criteria A and B are equally relevant</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Criterion A is slightly more relevant than B</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Criterion A is more relevant than B</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Criterion A is much more relevant than B</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Criterion A is extremely more relevant than B</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Intermediate values can be used if required</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2, 4, 6, 8</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p><span style="color: black">The elements of the resulting comparison matrix <italic><span style="color: black">A<sub><span style="color: black">nxn</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> correspond to values of the Saaty’s fundamental scale. It shall be noted that if criterion A is considered, for example, extremely more relevant than criterion B, then criterion B is considered extremely less relevant than criterion A. This results in the comparison matrix <italic><span style="color: black">A<sub><span style="color: black">nxn</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> to be reciprocal by definition, i.e., <italic><span style="color: black">a<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub><span style="color: black"> </italic><span style="color: black">= 1/<italic><span style="color: black">a<sub><span style="color: black">ji</sub></italic><span style="color: black">. The AHP allows to extract the relevance of each criterion from a so-built comparison matrix as the values of the eigenvector associated to the greatest eigenvalue of the matrix (<italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Calibri, sans-serif">λ<sub><span style="color: black">max</sub></italic><span style="color: black">).</p><p><span style="color: black">The resulting criteria weights are considered valid only of the comparison matrix <italic><span style="color: black">A<sub><span style="color: black">nxn</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> is consistent, i.e., the judgements of the decision maker should have been coherent. If a perfect consistency of a comparison matrix was achieved, that would result in <italic><span style="color: black">a<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> × <italic><span style="color: black">a<sub><span style="color: black">jk</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> = <italic><span style="color: black">a<sub><span style="color: black">ik</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> <span style="color: black; font-family: Cambria Math, serif">∀<span style="color: black"> <italic><span style="color: black">i</italic><span style="color: black">, <italic><span style="color: black">j</italic><span style="color: black">, <italic><span style="color: black">k</italic><span style="color: black">.</p><p><span style="color: black">The consistency shall be evaluated by means of the so-called Consistency Index <italic><span style="color: black">CI</italic><span style="color: black">, of the comparison matrix <italic><span style="color: black">A<sub><span style="color: black">nxn</sub></italic><span style="color: black">, as:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <mml:math id="mbtpysi2as">
                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>max</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p><span style="color: black">where, <italic><span style="color: black">n</italic><span style="color: black"> is the total number of criteria involved in the decision-making process. The resulting weights are then valid only if the Consistency Ratio <italic><span style="color: black">CR</italic><span style="color: black"> = <italic><span style="color: black">CI</italic><span style="color: black">/<italic><span style="color: black">RI</italic><span style="color: black"> falls below a limiting value <italic><span style="color: black">CR<sub><span style="color: black">lim</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> which depends on the number of criteria <italic><span style="color: black">n</italic><span style="color: black"> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>). In the above presented equation <italic><span style="color: black">RI</italic> stands for the so-called Random Index, which indicates the consistency of a fully randomized <italic>n</italic>x<italic>n</italic> comparison matrix.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Values for RI and CRlim depending on the number of criteria involved</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Number of Criteria <italic>n</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Random Index <italic>RI</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.58</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.12</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.32</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.45</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Allowable <italic>CR<sub>lim</sub></italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.05</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.10</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Dematel-based completion technique</title>
          
          <p><span style="color: black">The weights obtained through the application of the above presented AHP technique are widely used as a basis for many other decision-making techniques, such as TOPSIS, COPRAS or VIKOR. However, one of the most criticised aspects of the AHP technique is that the resulting criteria weights are highly subjective. In fact, the ability of the decision makers to adequately reflect their view on a problem diminishes as the complexity of the problem increases. There exist several approaches to attempt reducing the subjectivity of the decisions based on the application of MCDM techniques. Research has been conducted on the application of the fuzzy theory to mathematically model the diffusivity of human thinking and include it as a source of relevant information for the decision-making process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>].</p><p><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">Another approach which is also in the spotlight of many researchers is to reduce the complexity of the problem by reducing the number of judgements to be made by the decision maker when filling the AHP comparison matrix [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>]. To do so, the DEMATEL method can be used.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.2.1 Dematel method</title>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">The goal of the MCDM DEMATEL technique is to transform intricate cause-and-effect connections among diverse elements into a well-structured and easy-to-understand visual model. This involves grouping factors into cause-and-effect categories, as explained in reference [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]. The conventional approach involves four distinct stages:</p><p><italic><u><span style="color: black">Stage 1:</u></italic><span style="color: black"> To generate a Direct Influence Matrix (<italic><span style="color: black">DIM</italic><span style="color: black">), experts are requested to complete a comparison matrix using a process similar to the Analytic Hierarchy Process (AHP). In this process, each expert estimates the degree of influence that factor <italic><span style="color: black">i</italic><span style="color: black"> has on factor <italic><span style="color: black">j</italic><span style="color: black"> using a four-level scale of integers ranging from 0 to 3. The scores represent "no influence," "low influence," "medium influence," and "high influence," respectively. The non-negative influence matrix <italic><span style="color: black">DIM<sub><span style="color: black">k</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> = {<italic><span style="color: black">z<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black">} is created for each expert <italic><span style="color: black">k</italic><span style="color: black">, where <italic><span style="color: black">z<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> denotes the assigned influence score based on the aforementioned scale. The diagonal elements in the matrix are set to zero. Finally, the Direct Influence Matrix DIM is derived by averaging the matrices <italic><span style="color: black">DIM<sub><span style="color: black">k</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> obtained from all the experts.</p><p><italic><u><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">Stage 2:</u></italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif"> The direct influence matrix shall now be normalized to the so-called <italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">NIM</italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif"> by dividing each element <italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">z<sub><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif"> by <italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">p</italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">, where:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(2)</label>
                  <mml:math id="maqmyze86q">
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:munder>
                        <mml:mo>max</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          <mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:munder>
                      <mml:munder>
                        <mml:mo>max</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          <mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:munder>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>max</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><italic><u><span style="color: black">Stage 3:</u></italic><span style="color: black"> A total relation matrix <italic><span style="color: black">TRM</italic><span style="color: black"> is now constructed by aggregating both direct and indirect influential effects as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(3)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mxhqj93dxv">
                    <mml:mtable displaystyle="true" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="3pt">
                      <mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msup>
                            <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                          </mml:msup>
                          <mml:msup>
                            <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                          </mml:msup>
                          <mml:msup>
                            <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>∞</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msup>
                          <mml:msup>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msup>
                        </mml:mtd>
                      </mml:mtr>
                    </mml:mtable>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">In the equation above, I stands for an identity <italic><span style="color: black">n</italic><span style="color: black">×<italic><span style="color: black">n</italic><span style="color: black"> matrix.</p><p><italic><u><span style="color: black">Stage 4:</u></italic><span style="color: black"> To determine the influential factors <italic><span style="color: black">R<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> and <italic><span style="color: black">C<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub></italic><span style="color: black">, the sum of each row and column of the <italic><span style="color: black">TRM</italic><span style="color: black"> must be calculated. If <italic><span style="color: black">R<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> - <italic><span style="color: black">C<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> is positive, a particular factor <italic><span style="color: black">i</italic><span style="color: black"> is classified as a cause, whereas if it is negative, it is considered an effect.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.2.2 Dematel-based ahp restoration</title>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">Zhou et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>] proposed a technique inspired by DEMATEL to restore incomplete AHP comparison matrices and ensure their initial state and consistency. This is relevant because DEMATEL is designed to uncover non-evident relationships among a group of factors, and both DEMATEL and AHP rely on the analysis of comparison matrices. This restoration technique can be used to reduce the number of pairwise comparisons to be made by the decision-maker, this reducing the complexity of the assessment and increasing the accuracy of the resulting weights. The DEMATEL-based completion technique consists in the following stages:</p><p><italic><u><span style="color: black">Stage 1:</u></italic><span style="color: black"> From an incomplete AHP comparison matrix <italic><span style="color: black">A<sub><span style="color: black">nxn</sub><sup><span style="color: black">*</sup></italic><span style="color: black"> = {<italic><span style="color: black">a<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black">}, a DIM matrix can be derived. The elements of the DIM matrix {<italic><span style="color: black">z<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black">} are set equal to <italic><span style="color: black">a<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black">, but are set to zero, when the comparison element <italic><span style="color: black">a<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> is unknown.</p><p><italic><u><span style="color: black">Stage 2:</u></italic><span style="color: black"> To generate the normalized influence matrix (<italic><span style="color: black">NIM</italic><span style="color: black">), each element <italic><span style="color: black">z<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> of the matrix shall be divided by <italic><span style="color: black">p</italic><span style="color: black"> as in the classical DEMATEL method.</p><p> <italic><u>Stage 3:</u></italic> The total relation matrix <italic>TRM</italic> = {<italic>g<sub>ij</sub></italic>} shall now be computed as in classical DEMATEL.</p><p><italic><u><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">Stage 4:</u></italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif"> Based on the relationships between factors identified in the total relation matrix (TRM), a fully reciprocal pairwise comparison matrix <italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">A<sub><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">nxn</sub><sup><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">’</sup></italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif"> = {<italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">a<sup><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">’</sup><sub><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">} as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(4)</label>
                  <mml:math id="m6639cdb5g">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">It is important to ensure that the synthetic comparison matrix <italic><span style="color: black">A'<sub><span style="color: black">nxn</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> includes reciprocal central elements. To achieve this and considering the equation above that describes the relationship between factors, any missing entry <italic><span style="color: black">a<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> in the original incomplete comparison matrix <italic><span style="color: black">A<sub><span style="color: black">nxn</sub><sup><span style="color: black">*</sup></italic><span style="color: black"> can be calculated.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Scoring mcdm techniques</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.3.1 Topsis</title>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">The TOPSIS method was introduced by Hwang and Yoon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>] and is recognised as the most popular MCDM method used in civil engineering [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. TOPSIS has been used to analyse the sustainability performance of wide variety of infrastructures, from bridges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>] to buildings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]. TOPSIS technique is applied following several steps. The first step consists in constructing a decision matrix <italic><span style="color: black">R = [r<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub><span style="color: black">]</italic><span style="color: black"> and obtaining the weight <italic><span style="color: black">w<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> of each criterion <italic><span style="color: black">i</italic><span style="color: black"> considered in the problem. Weights are usually derived using the Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]. The decision matrix <italic><span style="color: black">R</italic><span style="color: black"> is then normalized as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(5)</label>
                  <mml:math id="muwhqdvqcg">
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msqrt>
                        <mml:munderover>
                          <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                        </mml:munderover>
                        <mml:msubsup>
                          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                        </mml:msubsup>
                      </mml:msqrt>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">In the equation above, <italic><span style="color: black">n</italic><span style="color: black"> is the total number of criteria. Now, the normalized decision matrix is weighted as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(6)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mxwy6wbner">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">The ideal positive and negative solutions (PIS or NIS) are derived for each criterion. These solutions are constructed by maximising the utility criteria and minimising the cost criteria in the PIS case and vice versa in the NIS case. After that, the distance of each alternative to the <italic><span style="color: black">PIS</italic><span style="color: black"> and <italic><span style="color: black">NIS</italic><span style="color: black"> is obtained as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(7)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mdr5885m0c">
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msqrt>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:msup>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:msubsup>
                            <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msubsup>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msup>
                    </mml:msqrt>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(8)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mgwjoifecj">
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msqrt>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:msup>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:msubsup>
                            <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msubsup>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msup>
                    </mml:msqrt>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">In the equations above, <italic><span style="color: black">v<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub><sup><span style="color: black">+</sup></italic><span style="color: black"> and <italic><span style="color: black">v<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub><sup><span style="color: black">-</sup></italic><span style="color: black"> are the elements of the <italic><span style="color: black">PIS</italic><span style="color: black"> and <italic><span style="color: black">NIS</italic><span style="color: black"> respectively, <italic><span style="color: black">d<sub><span style="color: black">j</sub><sup><span style="color: black">+</sup></italic><span style="color: black"> and <italic><span style="color: black">d<sub><span style="color: black">j</sub><sup><span style="color: black">-</sup></italic><span style="color: black"> are the distances of alternative <italic><span style="color: black">j</italic><span style="color: black"> to the <italic><span style="color: black">PIS</italic><span style="color: black"> and <italic><span style="color: black">NIS</italic><span style="color: black">, respectively. Finally, a score <italic><span style="color: black">Q<sub><span style="color: black">j</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> is obtained that evaluates the relative distance of each alternative <italic><span style="color: black">j</italic><span style="color: black"> to the <italic><span style="color: black">PIS</italic><span style="color: black"> as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(9)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mw2mvd0m9v">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:msubsup>
                        <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:msubsup>
                          <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msubsup>
                        <mml:msubsup>
                          <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msubsup>
                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.3.2 Vikor</title>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">VIKOR is a MCDM method introduced by Opricovic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>] overcome the limitations of existing MCDM techniques where decision problems involve conflicting criteria. VIKOR is also a popular assessment tool, that has been used as well to solve the evaluation performance of a variety of infrastructures, such as bridges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], airport infrastructures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>] or logistic centers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>].</p><p><span style="color: black">VIKOR shares the same first step as TOPSIS: a decision matrix must be constructed <italic><span style="color: black">R = [r<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub><span style="color: black">]</italic><span style="color: black"> the criteria weights <italic><span style="color: black">w<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> must be determined. The second step consists in finding the best and worst criteria values, namely <italic><span style="color: black">r<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub><sup><span style="color: black">+</sup></italic><span style="color: black"> and <italic><span style="color: black">r<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub><sup><span style="color: black">-</sup></italic><span style="color: black">, so that the decision matrix <italic><span style="color: black">R</italic><span style="color: black"> can be normalized as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(10)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mj8j43wm0a">
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:msubsup>
                          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msubsup>
                        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:msubsup>
                          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msubsup>
                        <mml:msubsup>
                          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msubsup>
                        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">The third step requires to determine two distance measures <italic><span style="color: black">S<sub><span style="color: black">j</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> and <italic><span style="color: black">R<sub><span style="color: black">j</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> for each alternative <italic><span style="color: black">j</italic><span style="color: black"> as follows:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(11)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mgl8stu5xd">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                    <mml:munderover>
                      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                    </mml:munderover>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(12)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mvt6qkrljo">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>max</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msubsup>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msubsup>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">At last, the VIKOR measure index <italic><span style="color: black">Q<sub><span style="color: black">j</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> for each alternative <italic><span style="color: black">j</italic><span style="color: black"> is calculated as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(13)</label>
                  <mml:math id="msjtmvcmik">
                    <mml:mtable displaystyle="true" columnalign="right left" columnspacing="0em" rowspacing="3pt">
                      <mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtd>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mtd>
                        <mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mfrac>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>min</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                </mml:msub>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>max</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>min</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                </mml:msub>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                </mml:msub>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mfrac>
                          <mml:mfrac>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>min</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                </mml:msub>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>max</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>min</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                </mml:msub>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                </mml:msub>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mfrac>
                          <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mtd>
                      </mml:mtr>
                    </mml:mtable>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">It is usual to compromise both distance metrics <italic><span style="color: black">S<sub><span style="color: black">j</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> and <italic><span style="color: black">R<sub><span style="color: black">j</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> by setting <italic><span style="color: black">v</italic><span style="color: black"> = 0.5. The alternative that results in the greatest score <italic><span style="color: black">Q<sub><span style="color: black">j</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> will be the best performing one according to this decision-making technique</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.3.3 Copras</title>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">COPRAS technique was defined by Zavadskas et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>] and has been also applied in a wide range related decision-making situations related with sustainability issues, such as the design of buildings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], the choice of construction materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>] and others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>] due to its simplicity. As usual in other decision-making methods, COPRAS requires a decision matrix <italic><span style="color: black">R = [r<sub><span style="color: black">ij</sub><span style="color: black">]</italic><span style="color: black"> and the obtention of the criteria relevancies <italic><span style="color: black">w<sub><span style="color: black">i</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> as a starting point Then, the decision matrix must be normalized:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(14)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mjtzpe1z0p">
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:munderover>
                          <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                        </mml:munderover>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">The second step consists in normalizing the decision matrix elements as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(15)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mkzrg31ff6">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">Then, the sum of the weighted normalized scores for both cost and benefit criteria for each alternative <italic><span style="color: black">j</italic><span style="color: black"> are obtained as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(16)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mletr6lk4i">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                    <mml:munderover>
                      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                    </mml:munderover>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(17)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mymqy7g7ob">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                    <mml:munderover>
                      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                    </mml:munderover>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>′</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">In the equations above, <italic><span style="color: black">r’<sub><span style="color: black">ij,+</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> and <italic><span style="color: black">r’<sub><span style="color: black">ij,-</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> represent respectivelyfor the normalized scoring for the benefit and cost criteria. After doing so, the final score <italic><span style="color: black">Q<sub><span style="color: black">j</sub></italic><span style="color: black"> of each alternative <italic><span style="color: black">j</italic><span style="color: black"> is calculated:q</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Case study</title>
      <p><span style="color: black">The MCDM methods presented above are applied for the evaluation of the sustainability life cycle performance of different design alternatives to a particular concrete bridge near shore. In those environments, the aggressive chloride-laden atmosphere induces the corrosion of the reinforcing steel, thus leading to intensive maintenance demanding designs. Being the maintenance stage usually a great source of negative impacts in every dimension of sustainability (economy, environment and society), working on enhancing the durability of coastal structures results in an effective way to reduce the impacts that harm the sustainability of these structures. To prevent concrete to degrade and increase the durability of concrete structures exposed to marine environments, conventional concrete designs are usually modified. The present analysis considers five different alternatives intended to provide high durability and thus reducing maintenance. The first one consists in using a conventional concrete mix but considering a concrete cover of 50 mm, which is significantly greater than usual cover values. This design alternative will be called CC50 hereafter. The second alternative consists in using reduced water to cement ratios to reduce the porosity of the concrete cover and consequently reducing the capacity of chlorides to ingress and reach the rebars (alternative W/C35 hereafter). The third alternative consists in reducing the porosity of concrete through the addition of latex-based additives to the concrete mix (alternative PMC10). The fourth alternative is based on the addition of silica fume to the concrete mix, which also results in reduced concrete porosity. A similar effect is achieved by using fly-ash additions. These two design alternatives will be called SF5 and FA20 hereafter respectively. The characterization of each of the above-described design alternatives is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>.</p><p><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">The sustainability performance of these five design alternatives is evaluated on a functional unit consisting of a 1 m long portion of a concrete bridge deck built near shore. The considered bridge shows a conventional 2.3 m deep and 12 m wide box-girder section. The analysis considers a 100 year long maintenance stage. To investigate the different maintenance needs of each design option, a reliability analysis is conducted. The required maintenance interval for each design alternative is set to the interval for which its reliability reaches 60% of a target reliability <italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">β<sub><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">lim</sub></italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif"> = 1.3, which corresponds to a probability of failure of 9.68% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]. In the analysis, failure is assumed to occur when the chloride concentration at the rebar depth reaches the critical chloride threshold associated to each alternative. The advance of the chloride front is modelled following Fick’s second Law of diffusion, as recommended in Fib Bulletin 34 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]. The reliability analysis has been performed for each alternative running 20,000 Monte-Carlo simulations to ensure that results converge, resulting in a relative estimation error below 1%. The parameters used to characterize probabilistically each design option are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref> contains the mean value for each parameter and the standard deviation in parentheses. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>, <italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">D<sub><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">0</sub></italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif"> stands for the chloride diffusivity of concrete, and <italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">C<sub><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">cr</sub></italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif"> for the critical chloride threshold, both parameters that affect the chloride ingress into concrete.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_3">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Definition of each design alternative</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CC50</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>W/C35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PMC10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>FA20</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SF5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cement (kg/m³)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>350</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>350</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>350</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>329</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>315</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Water (l/m³)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>140</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>122</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>140</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>140</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>140</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Gravel (kg/m³)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1017</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1037</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1017</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1017</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1017</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sand (kg/m³)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1068</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1095</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1068</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1086</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1098</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Silica Fume (kg/m³)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>17.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fly Ash (kg/m³)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>70</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Plasticiser (kg/m³)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.25</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.94</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Latex (kg/m³)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Concrete Cover (mm)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>50</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_4">
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Parameters for the reliability evaluation of each design option</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Parameter</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CC50</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>W/C35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PMC10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>FA20</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SF5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>D<sub>0</sub></italic> (×10<sup>-12</sup> m²/s)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8.90 (0.90)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.80 (0.47)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.51 (0.55)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.65 (0.35)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.94 (0.23)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>C<sub>cr</sub></italic> (%)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.60 (0.10)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.60 (0.10)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.60 (0.10)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.60 (0.10)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.60 (0.06)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cover (mm)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>50 (2.5)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40 (2)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40 (2)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40 (2)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40 (2)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mainten. Interval (<italic>β<sub>lim</sub></italic>/<italic>β</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = 0.6)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9 yrs.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12 yrs.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10 yrs.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>17 yrs.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>25 yrs.</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p><span style="color: black">The sustainability performance of each design option is evaluated through a set of 9 criteria. The first two criteria deal with the economic impacts of the designs. The first criterion (C1) considers the costs associated to the construction of the functional unit defined for each of the alternatives under study. The second criterion (C2) includes the costs resulting from the maintenance along the life cycle of each of the designs. It shall be noted that a discount rate d = 2% has been considered to discount future expenses to the date of construction. The costs of materials, machinery and construction activities are taken from national databases for the construction industry.</p><p><span style="color: black">Three criteria have been defined to capture the environmental performance of each design. In particular, these three criteria stand for the three endpoint indicators associated with the environmental life cycle assessment technique ReCiPe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]. These indicators are the damage to human health (C3), the damage to ecosystems (C4) and the affection to the availability of natural resources (C5) resulting from the production of the construction materials and energy consumptions along the life cycle of each design option. The inventory data from which the relevant information for quantifying the three selected endpoint indicators was obtained came from the environmental database Ecoinvent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>].</p><p>At last, a set of four criteria are defined to assess the social impacts derived from the different design alternatives. These criteria are suggested in studys [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>] to evaluate the social impacts of bridges. The first of these criteria (C6) deals with the ability of each design to generate employment. The second social criteria (C7) considers the contribution of each alternative to the economic wealth of the regions affected by the different construction and maintenance activities associated to it. The third social criterion (C8) takes into account how the recurrent maintenance activities might affect the traffic safety and accessibility of the users of the bridge. The last social criterion (C9) accounts for the negative effect that maintenance activities can have on the public opinion of the local communities, which are affected by the noise, vibrations or dust generated by these. The inventory data to determine the values of the social impacts has been gathered from the Spanish National Statistics Institute [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>] and the Spanish Tax Office [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Results and discussion</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Life cycle assessment of the design alternatives</title>
          
          <p><span style="color: black"><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref> shows the life cycle performance of each of the design alternatives against the different economic, environmental and social impacts involved in the present decision-making problem. It shall be noted that impacts are referred to the functional unit described above and exclude the effect of every activity that might be equal between alternatives.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_5">
              <label>Table 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Life cycle impact results for each alternative under study</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Criterion ID</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Definition</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CC50</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>W/C35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PMC10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SF5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>FA20</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Construction Costs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1296.4 €</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1322.5 €</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2355.7 €</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1546.2 €</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1386.3 €</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Maintenance Costs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4014.8 €</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2301.3 €</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3269.8 €</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1025.3 €</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1489.4 €</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Human Health</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>207.8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>141.7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>203.5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>95.6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>110.3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ecosystems</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>107.8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>73.1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>100.5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>47.6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>53.9</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Resources</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>244</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>180.1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>288.8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>145.6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>145</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Employment Generation</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>67.5%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>57%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>73.2%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>53.5%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>54.4%</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Economic Wealth</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>55.8%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>45.8%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>63.4%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>44.5%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>42.2%</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Users</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8.3%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11.5%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9.1%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22.9%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18.4%</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C9</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Externalities</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7.9%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11.1%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8.8%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22.5%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18%</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p><span style="color: black">It can be observed the solution associated with the greatest life cycle costs is the solution based on the addition of latex to the baseline concrete mix, closely follower by the CC50 solution. Although close in total terms, it shall be highlighted that PMC incurs in lesser maintenance costs than CC50 solution. The reduced competitiveness of this alternative in comparison to the rest relies on its associated high construction costs (C1). The concrete mix solution with the lowest life cycle costs is the one that involves adding silica fume (SF5) to the mix. The alternative FA20 solution closely follows in terms of cost-effectiveness. It is interesting to note that in almost every case, costs resulting from maintenance along the life cycle of the different alternatives under analysis are greater than the installation costs. An exception to that conclusion is the SF5 alternative.</p><p><span style="color: black">When it comes to environmental aspects, it can be observed that, in general terms, the impact on the availability of natural resources is the most impacting effect of every alternative, followed by the impact on human health. Environmental results (criteria C3 to C5) are expressed in accordance with the ReCiPe scoring system. Regarding the life cycle performance of each alternative, similar results are obtained as for the economical assessment: PMC10 solution is again the worst environmentally performing alternative, closely followed by CC50.</p><p><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">However, in terms of social impacts, PMC10 is the most favourable solution, while W/C35 has the least impact. It's important to note that while economic and environmental criteria are cost-based (i.e., the best solution is the one that scores less), social criteria are benefit-based, meaning that the greater the social impact, the better the solution. In this study, it is observed that for the maintenance-demanding alternatives, the impacts on users and public opinion are relatively insignificant if compared to the impacts on workers and on the regional development. For SF5 and FA20, even though the impacts on workers and regional development are more significant, the impacts on users and public opinion account for up to a third of their total social score.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Sustainability performance evaluation</title>
          
          <p><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">In order to compare the various alternatives and make a decision based on sustainability performance, the results shown above must be converted into a single indicator. To achieve this, a variety of MCDM techniques are utilized, namely TOPSIS, VIKOR and COPRAS. Each of these methods uses as an input the criteria weighting resulting from the application of the AHP technique. However, in order to maximize the accuracy of the weighting calculation, the number of comparisons is reduced in order to reduce the complexity of the assessment problem and increase the reliability of the results. The above presented DEMATEL-based completion technique is used to restore complete comparison matrices out of the incomplete ones.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.2.1 Criteria weighting</title>
              
              <p><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">To derive the relevance of the above-described criteria, a conventional AHP technique is applied. The weights resulting after evaluating the maximum eigenvector are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref>. It can be observed that, according to the decision maker’s perception of the problem, environmental aspects should weight much more than economic and social impacts. In fact, the environmental criteria weights (C3 to C5) sum up to 61.7%, while the economic criteria (C1 and C2) sum up to 23.7% and the social ones (C6 to C9) sum 14.7%. The consistency of the comparison matrix is evaluated by means of the Consistency Ratio, which takes a value of <italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">CR</italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif"> = 9.6% for the present analysis. As This value is below the limiting <italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">CR<sub><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">lim</sub></italic><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif"> = 10% required for 9×9 comparison matrices, the obtained weights are consistent.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_6">
                  <label>Table 6</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Criteria weights resulting from the application of the AHP technique</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Decision Criterion</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Weight of the Criterion</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C1 - Construction Costs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.158</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C2 - Maintenance Costs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.079</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C3 - Human Health</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.149</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C4 - Ecosystem</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.181</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C5 - Resources</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.287</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C6 - Employment</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.027</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C7 - Wealth</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.031</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C8 - Users</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.049</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C9 - Externalities</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.040</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.2.2 Completion results</title>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">Three distinct incompleteness levels of the baseline matrix are considered to assess the effectiveness of the presented completion technique. For each scenario, a varying number of entries are randomly chosen and considered as missing. In particular, for scenario 1, 5 entries are removed, 8 for scenario 2 and 12 for scenario 3, which implies the elimination of 33% of the judgements required to the decision maker when completing a conventional 9×9 comparison matrix. 1000 simulations are run to generate in each of them a unique random incomplete comparison matrix based on the baseline one presented above.</p><p><span style="color: black"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> shows the dispersion of the weights resulting for each criterion depending on the number of entries missing in the baseline comparison matrix. Although 3 scenarios have been evaluated, results are shown for scenarios 1 and 3, being scenario 2 enveloped by these. It can be observed that the maximum deviation from the baseline is obtained, as expected, in scenario 4, where 33% of the judgements are omitted. The average relative deviation between these weights and the baseline weight set is 4.9%. It can be noticed that as the number of missing entries increases, there is an increase in the dispersion of the results, even though the mean fits well. However, the maximum deviation with respect to the baseline is 7.6%.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_1">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Weights of the different criteria considering incompleteness scenarios 3 and 4</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_KsiTONA81Mk_83C0.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              <p><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">Considering the outcomes, the root mean square error (RMSE) is utilized to assess the overall effectiveness of the completion model. The RMSE measures the disparities between the forecasted estimations and the baseline weights. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> shows the normalized RMSE obtained for each criterion and incompleteness scenario. It can be observed that the greatest estimation errors are associated, as expected, for the incompleteness scenario with the greatest number of entries to be restored, namely scenario 3, for which the mean normalized RMSE reaches 24.2%.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_2">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Normalized root mean square error for each criterion</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_VFNh99A2W4qv9C_b.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              <p>It can be concluded from the results presented that the weight estimation is robust even if 8 entries are missing (incompleteness scenario 2). Removing more than 8 would lead to greater error values and results dispersion, and a so-called rank reversal phenomenon could occur.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.2.3 Mcdm results</title>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">The TOPSIS, COPRAS and VIKOR methods have been adopted to calculate a relative score for each design alternative, providing insight into its sustainability performance during its life cycle. The results obtained assuming these weights are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_7">Table 7</xref>. These have been obtained considering the baseline weighting set.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_7">
                  <label>Table 7</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Alternative scores for the different MCDM techniques considering the baseline weights set</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Alternative</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>TOPSIS</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>VIKOR</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>COPRAS</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CC50</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.329</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.521</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.715</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>W/C35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.665</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.689</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.260</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PMC10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.101</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.485</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SF5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.913</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.906</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.013</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>FA20</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.888</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.854</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.035</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
              <p><span style="color: black">It can be observed that the best solution in terms of its sustainability life cycle performance is the alternative based on the use of silica fume as an addition to a conventional concrete mix (SF5), closely followed by alternative SF20. The outstanding performance of these solutions when used in chloride-laden environments is explained by the fact that the use of such additions result in a drastic reduction of the chloride diffusivity of the concrete cover, thus hindering the advance of the chloride front into the reinforcing bars. The reduced maintenance of these solutions, together with the fact that it allows a reduction in the cement content, results in the best sustainability scores among the rest of the alternatives.</p><p><span style="color: black; font-family: Times, serif">The sensitivity of the results is now checked against the different defined incompleteness scenarios. Results are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_8">Table 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_9">Table  9</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_10">Table  10</xref>. Mean weights for each of these scenarios are considered as an input to get the alternative scoring.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_8">
                  <label>Table 8</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>TOPSIS scores considering different incompleteness scenarios</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Alternative</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CC50</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>W/C35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PMC10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SF5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>FA20</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Baseline</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.329</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.665</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.101</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.913</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.888</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scenario 1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.321</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.661</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.101</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.915</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.887</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scenario 2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.317</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.659</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.100</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.916</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.887</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scenario 3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.314</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.656</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.100</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.916</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.884</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
              
                <table-wrap id="table_9">
                  <label>Table 9</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>VIKOR scores considering different incompleteness scenarios</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Alternative</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CC50</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>W/C35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PMC10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SF5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>FA20</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Baseline</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.521</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.689</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.485</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.906</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.854</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scenario 1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.519</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.689</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.485</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.909</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.855</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scenario 2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.519</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.689</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.485</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.911</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.856</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scenario 3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.519</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.688</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.487</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.911</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.855</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
              
                <table-wrap id="table_10">
                  <label>Table 10</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>VIKOR scores considering different incompleteness scenarios</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Alternative</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CC50</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>W/C35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PMC10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SF5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>FA20</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Baseline</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.715</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.260</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.013</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.035</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scenario 1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.720</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.264</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.013</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.036</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scenario 2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.723</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.265</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.012</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.036</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scenario 3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.724</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.268</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.009</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.038</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
              <p>It can be concluded that, although slight differences can be observed depending on the incompleteness scenario considered, the results are on average robust and consistent.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>5. Conclusions</title>
      <p><span style="color: black"> </p><p><span style="color: black">This research aims to evaluate the life cycle sustainability of five design alternatives to a concrete bridge exposed to a chloride-laden, marine environment. The alternatives are based on usual approaches to overcome such aggressive environments. The analysis of their life cycle performance is conducted by means of a set of 9 criteria, including a variety of economic, environmental and social criteria. The evaluation is based on a multi-criteria decision-making approach in order to derive a sustainability score for each solution that allows us to compare alternatives. As there is no consensus on the best MCDM technique, three scoring MCDM methods are used here, namely TOPSIS, VIKOR and COPRAS. All of them consider as an input the weights derived from the AHP technique. To reduce the subjectivity of the input weights, a DEMATEL-based approach is applied to reduce the number of judgements required by the decision maker, thus reducing the complexity of the assessment and increasing the reliability of the obtained results.</p><p>From the results, it can be concluded that using silica fume and fly ash additions to conventional concrete mixes increases significantly the sustainability performance of concrete designs exposed to chlorides. The use of silica fume and fly ash increases the durability of concrete against chlorides, reducing enormously the maintenance requirements along their life cycle. On the other hand, such additions allow to reduce the cement content, reducing the environmental impacts associated to the production of cement. Moreover, these products result as by-products of the industry. Its recycling also contributes significantly to the environment.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>Grant PID2020-117056RB-I00 funded by MCIN/AEI/ 10.13039/501100011033 and by “ERDF A way of making Europe”.</p>
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation/>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>