<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="editorial" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JEMSE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Engineering Management and Systems Engineering</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Eng. Manag. Syst. Eng.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JEMSE</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2958-3527</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-3519</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-a1VFFm4eTQufc_AtR8qk6-bNJkeCvgbi</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jemse010101</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Editorial to the Inaugural Issue</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1">1</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Marinkovic</surname>
            <given-names>Dragan</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3583-9434</contrib-id>
          <email>dragan.marinkovic@tu-berlin.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="2">2</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Pamucar</surname>
            <given-names>Dragan</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8522-1942</contrib-id>
          <email>dragan.pamucar@fon.bg.ac.rs</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="1">Faculty of Mechanical Engineering and Transport Systems, Technical University of Berlin, Germany</aff>
        <aff id="2">Faculty of Organizational Sciences, University of Belgrade, Serbia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <year>2022</year>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>1</lpage>
      <page-range>1-1</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <month>11</month>
          <day>14</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <month>11</month>
          <day>14</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="pub">
          <month>11</month>
          <day>29</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2022 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <license>. Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the <a href='https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/' target='_blank' class='text-yellow-700 hover:underline'>CC BY 4.0 license</a>.</license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract/>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd/>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors">2</count>
        <fig-count>0</fig-count>
        <table-count>0</table-count>
        <ref-count>0</ref-count>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>1. </title>
      <p>Dear Colleagues,</p><p> We would gladly like to welcome you all to the inaugural issue of Journal of Engineering Management and Systems Engineering.</p><p>It is a well-known fact that the number of scientific journals in the field of engineering has been growing steadily for over a century. This fact may easily raise a question what motivated us to start yet another journal in this field. The enticing field of Systems Engineering and Engineering Management implies an interdisciplinary approach to developing, designing, integrating and managing complex technical systems. Systems engineering is based on the fact that a system is more than the sum of its subsystems or parts, and, for this reason, the overall context and chain of effects must be considered. When dealing with large and complex systems, numerous issues need to be addressed adequately. This includes designing of subsystems and parts, performing tests and evaluations, resolving reliability, risk management and logistics, performing design and process optimization-to name but a few. The final outcome needs to meet the customer's desired requirements for the system to be delivered within the predefined cost and time frame. </p><p>This field of work is obviously highly attractive and has been a subject of interest for a substantial time now. But the interest has particularly grown in the recent decades and the research work has intensified dramatically. This is clearly to be attributed not only to the steadily growing complexity of engineering systems, but also to the development of modern tools, which made real and virtual testing and analyses of complex systems and their components not only possible, but literally at the fingertips of engineers. In particular, virtual testing by means of simulations has rapidly developed over the previous two decades. Furthermore, the multidisciplinary character of the field means that researchers should work together across various disciplines to tackle major challenges. The main impetus to setup the new journal was to offer a novel, high quality venue to all the interested researchers so that they can present their work and research in a timely and efficient manner. This may be done in a form of research articles, review papers and short communications in the Journal of Engineering Management and Systems Engineering.</p><p>We look forward to receiving submission from all around the world, which substantially contribute to this enticing field of work.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p></p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>