<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJEPM</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.18280</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Energy Production and Management</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Int. J. Energy Prod. Manag.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IJEPM</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2056-3280</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2056-3272</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-jYQZA3Idg6yhGWppsru7FcgWxcgnWU5E</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijepm.090402</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Modeling of Energy-Autonomous and Sustainable Solar DTN Nodes and Their Impacts on the Performances of DTN Networks in the Context of Different Mobility Models and DTN Routing Protocols</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9687-9165</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mastapha</surname>
            <given-names>Sammou El</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>sammou.elmastapha@yahoo.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Computer Science, Faculty of Sciences and Techniques, Cadi Ayyad University, Marrakesh 40000, Morocco</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2024</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>209</fpage>
      <lpage>225</lpage>
      <page-range>209-225</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>02</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>08</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2024 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Delay-Tolerant Networks (DTN) are intermittent wireless mobile networks designed to handle communications in environments where network connectivity is often disrupted due to node mobility or the absence of fixed infrastructures. These frequent disconnections lead to repeated communication attempts between nodes, thereby increasing energy consumption. DTN is often deployed in isolated and hard-to-reach environments with limited energy sources, imposing significant constraints on the performance and operational lifetime of individual DTN nodes, as well as the DTN network as a whole. Despite the significant efforts invested by researchers to develop energy-efficient algorithms and models, the problem of energy consumption persists, especially with non-renewable sources. The motivation for this research is based on the major challenges related to powering mobile nodes in DTN networks, notably due to the absence of reliable and constant energy sources. The energy constraints of the nodes, combined with their mobility, raise problems of energy consumption and durability, leading to communication interruptions, delays, data losses, and a decrease in the overall efficiency of the network. To overcome these challenges, the article proposes a long-term energy management strategy by integrating renewable energy sources, notably solar energy, into the architecture of DTN nodes. The contributions include the modeling of an energy-autonomous and sustainable solar-powered DTN node, the evaluation of the energy generated and stored by these nodes, and the validation of the effectiveness of this approach through simulations in the ONE simulator, considering realistic mobility scenarios and communication conditions. The results show that solar DTN nodes have significantly higher residual energy than those with limited power sources. Additionally, social mobility models (MBM, SPMBM) consume more energy than individual models (RW, RWP, RD), while the Spray-and-Wait and PROPHET protocols are more energy-efficient compared to Epidemic and MaxProp. These analyses reveal optimal combinations of DTN protocols and mobility models to reduce energy consumption: the Spray-and-Wait protocol aligns well with social mobility models, while PROPHET is more suited to individual mobility models.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Delay-Tolerant Networks (DTN)</kwd>
        <kwd>Mathematical and stochastic modeling</kwd>
        <kwd>Energy performance</kwd>
        <kwd>Solar DTN node</kwd>
        <kwd>Renewable energy sources</kwd>
        <kwd>Protocols</kwd>
        <kwd>Mobility model</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="1"/>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="0"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body/>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>