<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HF</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Healthcraft Frontiers</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Healthcraft. Front.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">HF</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">3005-799X</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">3005-7981</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-kmDaX0BpQ0qdwfuQNZe5Uh1n8NN3dYCI</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/hf020204</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Ethical Implications and Educational Integration of AI-Driven Predictive Analytics in Healthcare: A Comprehensive Review</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3916-9228</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Garad</surname>
            <given-names>Askar</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>askargarad@umy.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8622-1474</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Iman</surname>
            <given-names>Bud Al Iman</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>budimaniman.2024@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3515-7609</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Purnomo</surname>
            <given-names>Halim</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>halimpurnomo@umy.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Management Program, Universitas Muhammadiyah Yogyakarta, 55183 Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Faculty of Psychology, Universitas Mercu Buana Yogyakarta, 55753 Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">Universitas Muhammadiyah Yogyakarta, 55183 Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2024</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>97</fpage>
      <lpage>106</lpage>
      <page-range>97-106</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>04</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2024 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p><p style="text-align: justify">This comprehensive review investigates the ethical implications of artificial intelligence (AI)-driven predictive analytics in healthcare, with a focus on patient privacy, algorithmic bias, equitable access, and transparency. The study further explores the integration of these ethical considerations into educational frameworks to enhance the training and preparedness of healthcare professionals in the responsible use of AI technologies. A systematic literature review was conducted using databases such as PubMed, Scopus, and Google Scholar, employing keywords related to AI, predictive analytics, healthcare, education, and ethics. Articles published from 2017 onwards, discussing the ethical challenges and applications of AI in healthcare and educational settings, were included. Thematic analysis of selected articles revealed significant ethical concerns, including patient privacy, algorithmic bias, and equitable access to AI technologies. Findings underscored the necessity for robust data protection mechanisms, transparent algorithm development, and equitable access policies. The study also highlighted the importance of incorporating AI literacy and ethical training in medical education. An ethical framework was proposed, outlining strategies to address these challenges in both healthcare practice and educational curricula. This framework aims to ensure the responsible use of AI technologies, promote transparency, and mitigate biases in healthcare settings. By addressing a critical gap in understanding the ethical implications of AI-driven predictive analytics in healthcare and its integration into education, the study contributes to the development of guidelines and policies for the equitable and transparent deployment of AI. The proposed ethical framework provides actionable recommendations for stakeholders, aiming to enhance medical education and improve patient outcomes while upholding essential ethical principles.</p></p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Artificial intelligence</kwd>
        <kwd>Predictive analytics</kwd>
        <kwd>Healthcare</kwd>
        <kwd>Education</kwd>
        <kwd>Ethical implications</kwd>
        <kwd>Patient privacy</kwd>
        <kwd>Algorithmic bias</kwd>
        <kwd>Medical education</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="3"/>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <ref-count count="25"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>AI has emerged as a transformative force across various domains, with healthcare being no exception. The integration of AI into healthcare systems promises to revolutionize patient care, diagnosis, and treatment methodologies. Among the numerous applications of AI in healthcare, predictive analytics stands out as a particularly promising avenue, offering the potential to forecast patient outcomes and optimize healthcare delivery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Weng et al., 2017</xref>). This convergence of AI and healthcare represents a paradigm shift in making medical decisions and administering patient care.</p><p>However, despite the significant advancements in AI-driven predictive analytics, there remains a critical gap in understanding the ethical implications and societal impact of its implementation within healthcare systems. The novelty of this study lies in its focus on exploring the ethical considerations inherent in predictive analytics applications, particularly within the realm of healthcare. By critically examining these ethical dimensions, this study seeks to address the pressing need for ethical frameworks that can guide the responsible development and deployment of AI technologies in healthcare settings.</p><p>Moreover, as AI becomes increasingly integrated into healthcare, there is an urgent need to incorporate these ethical considerations into educational frameworks. Medical education must evolve to include AI literacy and ethical training, ensuring that future healthcare professionals are well-equipped to navigate the complexities of AI technologies. Integrating ethical considerations into the curriculum will empower medical practitioners to make informed decisions and advocate for responsible AI use in their practice.</p><p>The problem at hand stems from the potential for AI-driven predictive analytics to encroach upon patient privacy, autonomy, and equitable access to healthcare resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Char et al., 2018</xref>). Additionally, concerns regarding algorithmic bias and transparency further compound the ethical challenges associated with predictive analytics in healthcare. Without adequate ethical safeguards in place, there is a risk of exacerbating existing disparities in healthcare delivery and undermining patient trust in medical institutions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Obermeyer et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Given the transformative potential of AI in healthcare, it is imperative to proactively address these ethical considerations to ensure that the benefits of predictive analytics are equitably distributed and aligned with patient interests. Therefore, the importance of this study lies in its contribution to the development of ethically informed guidelines and policies that can mitigate potential harms and foster trust in AI-driven healthcare systems.</p><p>This study aims to conduct a comprehensive analysis of the ethical implications of predictive analytics in healthcare, and propose actionable recommendations for the ethical development and deployment of AI technologies in healthcare settings, thereby fostering a nuanced understanding of the ethical challenges posed by AI-driven predictive analytics and paving the way for responsible innovation in healthcare.</p><p>By addressing the ethical dimensions of AI-driven predictive analytics in healthcare and incorporating these considerations into medical education, this study aims to identify potential risks and challenges and propose strategies to mitigate these concerns. Ultimately, it seeks to contribute to the ongoing discourse on the responsible use of AI in healthcare, enhance educational practices, and improve patient outcomes while upholding essential ethical principles.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Methodology</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Literature search strategy</title>
          
          <p>A literature review was conducted to identify and synthesize relevant research on the intersection of AI-driven predictive analytics, healthcare, and education, with a focus on navigating ethical frontiers. A comprehensive search strategy was employed to gather pertinent articles from various databases, including PubMed, Scopus, Google Scholar, and others. The search terms included combinations of keywords such as “AI”, “predictive analytics”, “healthcare”, “medical education”, “ethical challenges” and “AI in education”.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title>
          
          <p>To ensure the selection of high-quality and relevant literature, the following inclusion and exclusion criteria were established, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>The Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) method is a widely used framework for conducting systematic reviews and meta-analyses in health and social sciences. It helps ensure a comprehensive and transparent approach to selecting and reporting articles for literature reviews. The method involves a series of steps, typically outlined in a flow diagram and a checklist. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> shows a detailed description of the PRISMA method.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria for literature selection</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Criteria Type</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Criteria Description</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Inclusion Criteria</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Relevance to AI in healthcare and education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Articles must focus on the application of AI in healthcare settings, specifically predictive analytics, and its integration into medical or health education.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ethical considerations</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Studies must discuss the ethical challenges and considerations associated with the use of AI in healthcare and educational contexts.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Publication date</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Only articles published from 2017 onwards were included to ensure that the review covers the most recent advancements and current trends in the field.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Peer-reviewed sources</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Articles must be published in peer-reviewed journals or conference proceedings to ensure the credibility and reliability of the findings.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Language</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Only articles published in English were considered due to their accessibility and comprehensibility for the research team.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Exclusion Criteria</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Irrelevant topics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Articles focusing solely on technical aspects of AI without addressing its application in healthcare or education, or without discussing ethical considerations, were excluded.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Non-peer-reviewed sources</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Papers from non-peer-reviewed sources, such as opinion pieces, blogs, or non-scholarly publications, were not included to maintain the academic rigor of the review.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Duplications</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Duplicate articles retrieved from multiple databases were removed to avoid redundancy.</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>PRISMA flow: Data collection of related literature review</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img___ZaiOxHe0u9AxC7.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Data extraction and analysis</title>
          
          <p>Once the articles were selected based on the inclusion and exclusion criteria, data extraction was performed. The following information was extracted from each article: title and author(s), publication year, journal or source, summary of findings, relevance to AI in healthcare and education, and ethical considerations discussed.</p><p>The extracted data were then organized and analyzed thematically. Key themes and sub-themes related to the application of AI in healthcare and education, as well as the ethical challenges, were identified and synthesized. This thematic analysis enabled the identification of patterns, trends, and gaps in the existing literature.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Quality assessment</title>
          
          <p>To ensure the quality and reliability of the included studies, each article was assessed based on the following criteria:</p><p>(a) Credibility of sources: Preference was given to articles published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals.</p><p>(b) Methodological rigor: Studies employing robust research methodologies, such as systematic reviews, meta-analyses, and empirical research with clear methodologies, were prioritized.</p><p>(c) Relevance to research questions: Articles were assessed for their direct relevance to the research questions, ensuring that they provided substantial insights into AI applications, ethical challenges, and educational implications.</p><p>By adhering to this methodology, the literature review aims to provide a thorough and balanced examination of the current state of AI-driven predictive analytics in healthcare and education, while highlighting the ethical considerations that are critical to advancing the field responsibly.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.5. Data analysis and synthesis</title>
          
          <p>The selected articles were carefully reviewed and analyzed to extract key findings relevant to the intersection of AI, healthcare, and education. The analysis focused on identifying common themes and patterns related to the application of AI, the ethical challenges encountered, and the implications for medical education. The following steps were taken during the analysis:</p><p>(a) Thematic analysis: The extracted data were organized into themes such as “AI applications in healthcare”, “ethical challenges”, “educational strategies” and “impact on medical training”.</p><p>(b) Comparison and contrast: Articles were compared to identify similarities and differences in findings, especially regarding ethical considerations and proposed solutions.</p><p>(c) Synthesis of findings: The synthesized findings were used to develop a comprehensive understanding of how AI-driven predictive analytics is shaping healthcare and medical education, and the ethical frontiers that need to be navigated.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>3. Results</title>
      <p>The comprehensive literature review revealed key themes and insights regarding the ethical implications of AI-driven predictive analytics in healthcare. These insights were drawn from a diverse range of studies focusing on the ethical, educational, and practical aspects of AI in healthcare settings.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Results of data analysis and synthesis</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.1.1 Thematic analysis</title>
              
              <p>(a) As for the theme of AI applications in healthcare, various articles discuss the application of AI in healthcare, including predictive analytics, diagnosis, patient management, and personalized medicine. For example, AI is used for cardiovascular risk prediction, radiomics, oral and dental healthcare, vascular surgery, and health management algorithms.</p><p>(b) As for the theme of educational strategies, several articles focus on the integration of AI into medical education, nursing education, and health professions education. Those articles discuss simulation-based education, curriculum development, training programs, and the perspectives of healthcare students and professionals on AI education.</p><p>(c) As for the theme of ethical challenges, the implementation of AI in healthcare and education is notably emphasized, including biases in algorithms, racial bias in population health management, ethical considerations in machine learning implementation, and the need to address these challenges in medical training and education.</p><p>(d) As for the theme of impact on medical training, several articles discuss the potential of AI to revolutionize medical education, enhance learning outcomes, and prepare healthcare professionals for the future of healthcare delivery. In addition, those articles discuss the shifting landscape of medical education due to AI and the need for AI education programs for healthcare professionals.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.1.2 Comparison and contras</title>
              
              <p>In terms of the similarities in research findings, the comparison shows that multiple articles recognize the transformative potential of AI in healthcare and medical education, and the recurring themes include the biases in algorithms and the need for ethical AI implementation. In addition, there is a consensus on the importance of integrating AI education into healthcare professional training programs.</p><p>However, the research findings also show differences. Some articles focus more on the technical aspects of AI applications in healthcare, while others delve deeper into the educational implications and ethical considerations. In addition, perspectives on the specific challenges and solutions vary among the articles, reflecting diverse disciplinary backgrounds and research focuses.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Synthesis of findings</title>
          
          <p>The synthesis of findings highlights the multifaceted nature of AI’s impact on healthcare and medical education. Although AI holds immense promise for improving patient outcomes, enhancing medical training, and revolutionizing healthcare delivery, it also presents ethical challenges that must be addressed. Key considerations include the need for unbiased algorithms, ethical AI implementation, and comprehensive AI education for healthcare professionals. As the field continues to evolve, interdisciplinary collaboration and ongoing ethical reflection will be essential for harnessing the full potential of AI in healthcare while ensuring patient safety, equity, and ethical integrity.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.2.1 Quantitative analysis</title>
              
              <p>This subsection provides a structured examination of numerical data extracted from the included articles. This segment focuses on the quantitative methodologies employed by researchers to analyze trends, patterns, and numerical relationships pertaining to the integration of AI in education and healthcare. Through systematic data analysis techniques, this subsection aims to offer insights into the prevalence, frequency, and statistical significance of various themes, findings, or outcomes discussed in the literature.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> presents a summary of the number of articles published annually over the span of eight years, from 2017 to 2024. It provides a clear visualization of the fluctuating publication trends over the given time period, showcasing both peaks and troughs in article output. It could be useful for analyzing the productivity and perhaps the focus of the publishing entity during these years.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_2">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Year-wise distribution of articles</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_B3kpeGQHcFdICiJx.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> illustrates the distribution of articles related to AI in education and healthcare across various journals and sources. It provides a concise overview of the number of articles published in each journal or source, indicating the diversity of publication outlets contributing to the discourse on AI’s integration into these domains.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_2">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Distribution of articles across journals</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Journal/Source</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Number of Articles</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>JMIR Medical Education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cureus</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>JMIR Nursing</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Medical Journal of Süleyman Demirel University</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The New England Journal of Medicine</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>British Dental Journal</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital Health</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Understanding AI</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>European Journal of Vascular and Endovascular Surgery</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Academic Medicine</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Medical Teacher</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Journal of Advances in Medical Education &amp;amp; Professionalism</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Science</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI &amp;amp; Society</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Journal of Dentistry</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Archives of Medicine and Health Sciences</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Personalized Medicine</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PLOS One</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
              <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> presents a comprehensive analysis derived from a literature review focusing on the intersection of AI and education or healthcare. The table encompasses a diverse range of studies and perspectives within the field of AI and its relationship with education and healthcare. The articles explore topics such as the potential impacts of AI on nursing and medical education, ethical challenges in AI implementation, the perspectives of healthcare students on AI, the integration of AI into healthcare curricula, and the role of AI in improving healthcare practices and education methods. Additionally, the table highlights the importance of addressing biases in AI-driven healthcare systems and the need for comprehensive AI training for future healthcare professionals.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_3">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Analysis results of the literature review</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Authors</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Title</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Methodology</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Findings</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Buchanan et al. (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Predicted influences of AI on nursing education: Scoping review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scoping review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Identified potential impacts of AI on nursing education, including changes in curriculum, teaching methods, and skill requirements.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Can et al. (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI in health education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Narrative review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Explored the applications of AI in health education, and discussed its potential benefits and challenges.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Char et al. (2018)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Implementing machine learning in health care—addressing ethical challenges</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Highlighted ethical challenges in implementing machine learning in healthcare and proposed strategies to address them.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Charow et al. (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI education programs for health care professionals: scoping review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scoping review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Explored existing AI education programs for healthcare professionals, and highlighted the need for standardized curricula and evaluation methods.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Dave &amp;amp; Patel (2023)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI in healthcare and education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Discussed the applications of AI in healthcare and education, and emphasized the need for ethical considerations and comprehensive training for healthcare professionals.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Ejaz et al. (2022)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI and medical education: A global mixed-methods study of medical students’ perspectives</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mixed-method study</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Investigated medical students' perspectives on AI in medical education, and highlighted the importance of integrating AI education into curricula and providing practical training.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Gray et al. (2022)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI education for the health workforce: expert survey of approaches and needs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Survey</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Conducted a survey to explore approaches and needs related to AI education for the health workforce, providing insights into expert opinions and recommendations.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Grunhut et al. (2022)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Needs, challenges, and applications of AI in medical education curriculum</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Identified the needs, challenges, and potential applications of AI in medical education curricula, and emphasized the importance of integrating AI literacy and practical training.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Hamilton (2024)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI and Healthcare Simulation: The Shifting Landscape of Medical Education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Perspective</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Explored the evolving role of AI in healthcare simulation and medical education, and discussed its potential benefits and challenges.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Komasawa &amp;amp; Yokohira (2023)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Simulation-based education in the AI era</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Explored the integration of simulation-based education in the AI era, and discussed its potential benefits and challenges.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Kreutzer &amp;amp; Sirrenberg (2020)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fields of application of AI—Health care, education, and human resource management</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Literature review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Examined various applications of AI in healthcare, education, and human resource management, highlighting its diverse roles and potential impact.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Raffort et al. (2020)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fundamentals in AI for Vascular Surgeons</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Literature review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Introduced fundamental notions of AI and discussed its potential applications in medical and surgical practice, highlighting current knowledge, limitations, challenges, and future directions.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Lee et al. (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI in undergraduate medical education: a scoping review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Scoping review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Reviewed the applications of AI in undergraduate medical education, and identified key trends and areas for future research.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Masters (2019)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI in medical education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Literature review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Explored the integration of AI in medical education, and discussed its potential impact on teaching and learning processes.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Mir et al. (2023)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Application of AI in medical education: current scenario and future perspectives</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Reviewed the current status of AI applications in medical education and provided insights into future trends and challenges.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Obermeyer et al. (2019)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Dissecting racial bias in an algorithm used to manage the health of populations</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Research study</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Investigated racial bias in an algorithm used for population health management, highlighting the need for addressing bias in AI-driven healthcare systems.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Paranjape et al. (2019)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Introducing AI training in medical education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Opinion piece</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Discussed the integration of AI training into medical education, emphasizing the importance of preparing future healthcare professionals for the AI-driven healthcare landscape.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Schiff (2021)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Out of the laboratory and into the classroom: the future of AI in education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Perspective article</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Explored the potential impact of AI on education, and discussed its implications for teaching and learning processes.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Schwendicke et al. (2023)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI for oral and dental healthcare: core education curriculum</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mixed-method study</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Explored the integration of AI into oral and dental healthcare education, and proposed a core curriculum to enhance AI literacy among dental professionals.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Shankar (2022)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI in health professions education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Perspective article</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Explored the role of AI in health professions education, and discussed its potential applications and implications for curriculum development.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Teng et al. (2022)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Health care students’ perspectives on AI: countrywide survey in Canada</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Survey</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Surveyed healthcare students in Canada to assess their perspectives on AI, highlighting the importance of incorporating AI education into healthcare curricula.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Waldman et al. (2022)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AI in healthcare: a primer for medical education in radiomics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Literature review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Provided an overview of AI applications in radiomics and medical education, emphasizing the need for integrating AI literacy into medical curricula.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Weng et al. (2017)</xref></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Can machine-learning improve cardiovascular risk prediction using routine clinical data?</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Prospective cohort study</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Investigated the effectiveness of machine learning in cardiovascular risk prediction using routine clinical data, suggesting its potential for improving risk assessment.</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.2.2 Qualitative analysis</title>
              
              <p>A qualitative analysis was conducted and the results are as follows:</p><p>(a) Ethical implications in predictive analytics</p><p>· Patient privacy and data security: A significant portion of the literature addresses concerns about patient privacy and data security. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Buchanan et al. (2021)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Char et al. (2018)</xref> emphasized the necessity for robust data protection mechanisms. Due to the demand for extensive data in AI systems, it is paramount to ensure the confidentiality and security of patient information. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Charow et al. (2021)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Gray et al. (2022)</xref> also highlighted the importance of establishing clear consent protocols and maintaining transparency about data usage.</p><p>· Algorithmic bias and fairness: Algorithmic bias remains a critical issue, as evidenced by studies from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Obermeyer et al. (2019)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Weng et al. (2017)</xref>. These biases can result from unrepresentative training data or flawed algorithmic design, potentially leading to discriminatory practices. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Kreutzer &amp;amp; Sirrenberg (2020)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Zapata et al. (2024)</xref> suggested the incorporation of diverse datasets and continuous monitoring of AI systems to mitigate bias. Transparent algorithmic development and regular audits are crucial for ensuring fairness and equity in AI applications.</p><p>· Equitable access to AI technologies: Another major concern is access to AI-driven healthcare solutions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Char et al. (2018)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Can et al. (2021)</xref> pointed out that disparities in access could exacerbate existing inequalities in healthcare delivery. Studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Paranjape et al. (2019)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Schiff (2021)</xref> advocated for policies that promote equitable access to AI technologies, particularly in under-resourced settings.</p><p>· Transparency and explainability: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Hamilton (2024)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Dave &amp;amp; Patel (2023)</xref> underscored the need for transparency and explainability in AI systems. Patients and healthcare providers must understand how AI-driven predictions are made to foster trust and facilitate informed decision-making. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Grunhut et al. (2022)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Waldman et al. (2022)</xref> suggested the integration of explainability features into AI systems and the provision of comprehensive training for healthcare professionals to interpret AI outputs accurately.</p><p>(b) Impact on healthcare delivery and medical education</p><p>· Enhancement of healthcare: AI-driven predictive analytics has demonstrated significant potential in improving healthcare delivery. Studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Weng et al. (2017)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Teng et al. (2022)</xref> highlighted predictive models can identify high-risk patients and recommend proactive interventions to enhance patient outcomes. The integration of AI in routine clinical practices can streamline diagnostic processes and personalize treatment plans, as noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Lareyre et al. (2020)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Masters (2019)</xref>.</p><p>· Transformation of medical education: The integration of AI into medical education is critical for preparing future healthcare professionals. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Charow et al. (2021)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Mir et al. (2023)</xref> emphasized the importance of incorporating AI literacy into medical curricula, including understanding AI technologies, their applications, and the associated ethical considerations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Komasawa &amp;amp; Yokohira (2023)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Ejaz et al. (2022)</xref> stressed the need for simulation-based training and practical exposure to AI tools to enhance students’ readiness for AI-driven healthcare environments.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Proposed ethical framework</title>
          
          <p>Based on the thematic analysis, the following ethical framework was proposed to guide the development and deployment of AI-driven predictive analytics in healthcare.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref> outlines a structured framework for ethically implementing AI-driven predictive analytics in healthcare. It covers key areas such as data protection, bias mitigation, equitable access, transparency, and continuous oversight. The framework emphasizes actions like implementing security measures for data protection, using diverse datasets to mitigate bias, developing equitable policies for access, ensuring transparency in algorithms, and establishing oversight committees for continuous ethical review. By following these strategies, healthcare systems can uphold ethical standards while leveraging the potential of AI to improve patient care. In recent years, the integration of AI in healthcare has presented promising opportunities for improving patient care and outcomes. However, alongside these advancements, ethical considerations have become paramount to ensuring responsible and equitable use of AI-driven predictive analytics in healthcare settings. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref> outlines a comprehensive framework for addressing these ethical concerns, drawing insights from various scholarly works.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_4">
              <label>Table 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Framework for ethical AI-driven predictive analytics in healthcare</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ethical Area</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Key Strategies</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Action Items</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Data protection and privacy</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Implement security measures.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Data encryption, and transparent data policies</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ensure transparency in data use.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Informed consent protocols</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Bias mitigation and fairness</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Use diverse datasets.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Diverse data collection</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Conduct regular audits.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Algorithm audits</p><p>Bias detection</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Promote transparency in algorithms.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Transparent development</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Equitable access</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Develop equitable policies.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Policy development</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Invest in infrastructure.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Infrastructure investment, training programs, and support systems</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Transparency and explainability</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Incorporate explainability.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Explainability features</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Educate professionals.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Professional education</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Maintain communication with patients.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Patient communication protocols</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Continuous ethical oversight</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Establish oversight committees.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ethical committees</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Regularly review guidelines.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Regular guideline reviews</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Encourage dialogue.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Stakeholder dialogue</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>Data protection and privacy emerge as fundamental ethical areas, aligning with the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Buchanan et al. (2021)</xref>, which stresses the importance of transparent data policies and encryption to safeguard patient information. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Can et al. (2021)</xref> highlighted the significance of transparent data use through protocols like informed consent. Bias mitigation and fairness, as discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Char et al. (2018)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Charow et al. (2021)</xref>, emphasize the need for diverse datasets and regular audits to detect and rectify algorithmic biases. Equitable access, as advocated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Gray et al. (2022)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Grunhut et al. (2022)</xref>, underscores the importance of developing equitable policies and investing in infrastructure to ensure fair access to AI-driven healthcare solutions. Transparency and explainability, concepts championed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Hamilton (2024)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Komasawa &amp;amp; Yokohira (2023)</xref>, call for incorporating features that provide insights into AI algorithms’ decision-making processes while maintaining clear communication with patients. Continuous ethical oversight, as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Paranjape et al. (2019)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Schiff (2021)</xref>, involves establishing oversight committees, regularly reviewing guidelines, and fostering dialogue among stakeholders to ensure ongoing adherence to ethical principles. By synthesizing insights from these sources, the table offers a structured framework that encompasses essential ethical considerations, providing guidance for healthcare practitioners and policymakers to navigate the complex landscape of AI-driven predictive analytics in healthcare responsibly and ethically.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>4. Discussion</title>
      <p>The comprehensive literature review synthesized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> highlights significant findings and contributions from various studies on the integration of AI into healthcare and education. The review reveals several novel insights and distinct differences from existing studies.</p><p>Firstly, this review underscores the transformative impact of AI on healthcare education, echoing the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Buchanan et al. (2021)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Lee et al. (2021)</xref>, who noted the need for curriculum changes and the integration of AI literacy. However, the analysis of this study goes further by emphasizing the critical necessity for standardized curricula and evaluation methods in AI education programs, as pointed out by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Charow et al. (2021)</xref>. This highlights a gap in current educational frameworks that must be addressed to ensure uniformity and comprehensiveness in AI training. The ethical implications of AI implementation in healthcare, extensively discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Char et al. (2018)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Dave &amp;amp; Patel (2023)</xref>, are another focal point of this review. The analysis of this study aligns with their concerns about algorithmic bias and patient data security but also expands on the practical strategies for bias mitigation and fairness. For example, this study highlights the need for diverse datasets and transparent algorithmic development, suggesting a proactive approach to addressing these challenges, which is an advancement over the existing literature.</p><p>Moreover, although the potential benefits of AI in improving healthcare delivery and education are well-documented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Teng et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Weng et al., 2017</xref>), this review identifies the specific need for integrating AI literacy and practical training into medical curricula. This finding is particularly supported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Mir et al. (2023)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Ejaz et al. (2022)</xref>, who emphasized the importance of hands-on experience with AI tools for healthcare professionals. The analysis of this study, therefore, provides a more detailed roadmap for incorporating AI into medical education, ensuring that future healthcare professionals are well-equipped to leverage AI technologies. Furthermore, this review brings to light the critical issue of equitable access to AI technologies in healthcare, a topic briefly touched upon by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Can et al. (2021)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Paranjape et al. (2019)</xref>. This study elaborates on this by advocating for policies that promote equitable access and infrastructure investments, addressing a significant gap in the current discourse on AI in healthcare.</p><p>Overall, this literature review not only consolidates existing knowledge on the role of AI in healthcare and education but also introduces new perspectives on standardizing AI education, addressing ethical challenges, and ensuring equitable access. These insights are crucial for academia, educators, and policymakers as they navigate the evolving landscape of AI in healthcare and work towards sustainable and ethical AI integration.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>5. Conclusions</title>
      <p>The literature review presented in this study highlights the transformative impact of AI on healthcare and medical education. Key findings include the necessity of integrating AI literacy into medical curricula, the importance of standardized education programs, and the significant ethical challenges associated with AI implementation, such as algorithmic bias and patient data security. Additionally, this review underscores the potential of AI to enhance healthcare delivery and the critical need for equitable access to AI technologies. Practical strategies for addressing ethical concerns, such as using diverse datasets and transparent algorithmic development, are also emphasized. Moreover, based on the thematic analysis, this study proposes an ethical framework to guide the development and deployment of AI-driven predictive analytics in healthcare. By following these strategies, healthcare systems can uphold ethical standards while leveraging the potential of AI to improve patient care.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Limitations</title>
      <p>This study has the following limitations:</p><p>(a) Scope limitation: Focusing primarily on the intersection of AI-driven predictive analytics, healthcare, and education, the literature review may overlook other important aspects of AI in healthcare or education that are not directly related to predictive analytics.</p><p>(b) Restriction of the publication date: The inclusion criteria specify articles published from 2017 onwards, potentially excluding relevant research published before this period that could provide valuable insights into the topic.</p><p>(c) Language bias: Only articles published in English were considered for inclusion, which may lead to language bias and the exclusion of valuable research published in other languages.</p><p>(d) Publication bias: The emphasis on peer-reviewed sources might introduce publication bias, as it may overlook valuable insights from non-peer-reviewed sources, such as grey literature, conference papers, or reports.</p><p>(e) Geographical bias: The literature review does not mention any specific efforts to include research from diverse geographical regions, which may limit the generalizability of findings and overlook important perspectives from different healthcare and educational systems worldwide.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>7. Recommendations</title>
      <p>This study makes the following recommendations:</p><p>(a) Ethical guidelines could be developed and refined for AI integration in healthcare.</p><p>(b) New ways could be explored to responsibly integrate AI in healthcare settings.</p><p>(c) Empirical studies could be conducted to evaluate the effectiveness of standardized AI curricula in various educational settings.</p><p>(d) Longitudinal studies could be performed to assess the long-term impact of AI literacy on healthcare professionals’ performance and patient outcomes.</p><p>(e) The integration of AI into under-resourced settings could be studied to develop strategies for equitable access.</p><p>(f) Methods to mitigate algorithmic bias and enhance transparency and explain ability in AI systems could be investigated.</p><p>(g) Research could be expanded to include non-English publications for a comprehensive understanding of global advancements and challenges in AI integration in healthcare and education.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>e23933</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Buchanan</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howitt</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Booth</surname>
              <given-names>R. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Risling</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bamford</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/23933</pub-id>
          <article-title>Predicted influences of artificial intelligence on nursing education: Scoping review.</article-title>
          <source>JMIR Nursing</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>28</volume>
          <page-range>355-359</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Can</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Başer</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Altuntaş</surname>
              <given-names>S. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Özceylan</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kolcu</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17343/sdutfd.876439</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence in health education.</article-title>
          <source>Med. J. Süleyman Demirel. Univ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>378</volume>
          <page-range>981-983</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Char</surname>
              <given-names>Danton S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>Nigam H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magnus</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/nejmp1714229</pub-id>
          <article-title>Implementing machine learning in health care—Addressing ethical challenges.</article-title>
          <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>e31043</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Charow</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeyakumar</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Younus</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dolatabadi</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salhia</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Mouaswas</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balakumar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clare</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhalla</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gillan</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haghzare</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lalani</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mattson</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peteanu</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tripp</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waldorf</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tavares</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiljer</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/31043</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence education programs for health care professionals: Scoping review.</article-title>
          <source>JMIR Med. Educ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>234</volume>
          <page-range>761-764</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dave</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patel</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41415-023-5845-2</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence in healthcare and education.</article-title>
          <source>Br. Dent. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ejaz</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McGrath</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>B. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guise</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vercauteren</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shapey</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20552076221089099</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence and medical education: A global mixed-methods study of medical students’ perspectives</article-title>
          <source>Digital Health</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>e35223</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gray</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Slavotinek</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dimaguila</surname>
              <given-names>G. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choo</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/35223</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence education for the health workforce: Expert survey of approaches and needs.</article-title>
          <source>JMIR Med. Educ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>e35587</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grunhut</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marques</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wyatt</surname>
              <given-names>A. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/35587</pub-id>
          <article-title>Needs, Challenges, and Applications of Artificial Intelligence in Medical Education Curriculum</article-title>
          <source>JMIR Med. Educ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>e59747</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hamilton</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.59747</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence and healthcare simulation: The shifting landscape of medical education</article-title>
          <source>Cureus</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>e40940</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Komasawa</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yokohira</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.40940</pub-id>
          <article-title>Simulation-based education in the artificial intelligence era.</article-title>
          <source>Cureus</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>167-193</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kreutzer</surname>
              <given-names>Ralf T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sirrenberg</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-25271-7_6</pub-id>
          <article-title>Fields of application of artificial intelligence—Health care, education and human resource management.</article-title>
          <source>In: Understanding Artificial Intelligence. Management for Professionals. Springer, Cham.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>59</volume>
          <page-range>870-871</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lareyre</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adam</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carrier</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chakfé</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raffort</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejvs.2020.02.030</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence for education of vascular surgeons.</article-title>
          <source>Eur. J. Vasc. Endovasc. Surg.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>96</volume>
          <page-range>S62-S70</page-range>
          <issue>11S</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kulasegaram</surname>
              <given-names>K. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/acm.0000000000004291</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence in undergraduate medical education: A scoping review.</article-title>
          <source>Acad. Med.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>41</volume>
          <page-range>976-980</page-range>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Masters</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0142159x.2019.1595557</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence in medical education</article-title>
          <source>Med. Teach.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>133-140</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mir</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mir</surname>
              <given-names>G. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raina</surname>
              <given-names>N. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mir</surname>
              <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mir</surname>
              <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miskeen</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>...</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alamri</surname>
              <given-names>M. M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30476/jamp.2023.98655.1803</pub-id>
          <article-title>Application of artificial intelligence in medical education: Current scenario and future perspectives.</article-title>
          <source>J. Adv. Med. Educ. Prof.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>366</volume>
          <page-range>447-453</page-range>
          <issue>6464</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Obermeyer</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Powers</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vogeli</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mullainathan</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aax2342</pub-id>
          <article-title>Dissecting racial bias in an algorithm used to manage the health of populations.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>e16048</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paranjape</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schinkel</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panday</surname>
              <given-names>R. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Car</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nanayakkara</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/16048</pub-id>
          <article-title>Introducing artificial intelligence training in medical education.</article-title>
          <source>JMIR Med. Educ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>65</volume>
          <page-range>254-260</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raffort</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adam</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carrier</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lareyre</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.avsg.2019.11.037</pub-id>
          <article-title>Fundamentals in artificial intelligence for vascular surgeons.</article-title>
          <source>Ann. Vasc. Surg.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>36</volume>
          <page-range>331-348</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schiff</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00146-020-01033-8</pub-id>
          <article-title>Out of the laboratory and into the classroom: The future of artificial intelligence in education.</article-title>
          <source>AI &amp; Soc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>128</volume>
          <page-range>104363</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schwendicke</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chaurasia</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiegand</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uribe</surname>
              <given-names>Sergio E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fontana</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akota</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tryfonos</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krois</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdent.2022.104363</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence for oral and dental healthcare: Core education curriculum.</article-title>
          <source>J. Dent.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>256-261</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shankar</surname>
              <given-names>P.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/amhs.amhs_234_22</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence in health professions education.</article-title>
          <source>Arch. Med. Health Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>e33390</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Teng</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singla</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yau</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lamoureux</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>...</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Field</surname>
              <given-names>T. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/33390</pub-id>
          <article-title>Health care students’ perspectives on artificial intelligence: Countrywide survey in Canada.</article-title>
          <source>JMIR Med. Educ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>19</volume>
          <page-range>445-456</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Waldman</surname>
              <given-names>C. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hermel</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hermel</surname>
              <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allinson</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pintea</surname>
              <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bransky</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>...</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhavnani</surname>
              <given-names>S. P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/pme-2022-0014</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence in healthcare: A primer for medical education in radiomics.</article-title>
          <source>Per. Med.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>e0174944</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weng</surname>
              <given-names>Stephen F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reps</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kai</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garibaldi</surname>
              <given-names>Jonathan M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qureshi</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0174944</pub-id>
          <article-title>Can machine-learning improve cardiovascular risk prediction using routine clinical data?</article-title>
          <source>PloS One</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>49</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zapata</surname>
              <given-names>R. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guerrero</surname>
              <given-names>E. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Montilla</surname>
              <given-names>R. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56294/mw202449</pub-id>
          <article-title>Emerging Technologies in Education: A Bibliometric Analysis of Artificial Intelligence and its Applications in Health Sciences.</article-title>
          <source>In Seminars in Medical Writing and Education</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>