<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="review-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ESM</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Education Science and Management</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Educ. Sci. Manag.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">ESM</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2959-6319</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2959-6300</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-p99pSBtJe-e1Hvl3gfNRyWvb-vfRtpFi</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/esm030304</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Bibliometric Analysis of Academic Resilience Research in Indonesia (2000–2025): Trends, Thematic Evolution, and Scholarly Impact</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0608-3877</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Fajari</surname>
            <given-names>Laksmi Evasufi Widi</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>laksmi.evasufi@untirta.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4901-7415</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Salimi</surname>
            <given-names>Moh</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>salimi@staff.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2241-9967</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Gunansyah</surname>
            <given-names>Ganes</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>ganesgunansyah@unesa.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_4">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-3519-8949</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Novianto</surname>
            <given-names>Anwar</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>anwarnovianto@uny.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Primary School Teacher Education, Universitas Sultan Ageng Tirtayasa, 42121 Serang, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Department of Primary School Teacher Education, Universitas Sebelas Maret, 57126 Surakarta, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">Department of Primary School Teacher Education, Universitas Negeri Surabaya, 60231 Surabaya, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_4">Department of Primary School Teacher Education, Universitas Negeri Yogyakarta, 55281 Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>09</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>184</fpage>
      <lpage>193</lpage>
      <page-range>184-193</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>07</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>The rapid expansion of research on academic resilience in Indonesia has been driven by digitalization, hybrid learning, and demands for equitable quality. However, a systematic synthesis of intellectual structure, thematic evolution, collaboration networks, and scholarly impact remains absent. In this study, a comprehensive bibliometric and science mapping analysis of academic resilience research in the Indonesian context from 2000 to 2025 was conducted. Performance analysis and science mapping techniques—including co-word analysis, co-citation analysis, bibliographic coupling, thematic evolution mapping, and burst keyword detection—were integrated and visualized using VOSviewer. Records were retrieved through Publish or Perish based on Google Scholar. The findings reveal three major patterns. First, publication trends indicate a shift from predominantly psychological and pandemic-related online learning themes toward institutional and systemic concerns and culturally embedded educational practices. Second, five dominant thematic clusters were identified: individual capacities, social support, academic outcomes, institutional and learning environments, and Indonesian cultural–linguistic contexts. Third, scholarly influence is concentrated in review articles and pandemic-era empirical studies employing validated measurement scales and mechanism-based structural models. Cross-national comparative studies were found to enhance citation reach. Overall, the intellectual trajectory of academic resilience research in Indonesia is structured around a dominant explanatory pathway linking self-efficacy and support to resilience and subsequent outcomes. Substantive research gaps remain at the lecturer and organizational levels, as well as in the systematic integration of Islamic and Indonesian linguistic–cultural frameworks into resilience theory. These findings provide a systematic intellectual mapping of the field and offer a foundation for advancing contextually grounded and policy-relevant research agendas.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Academic resilience</kwd>
        <kwd>Bibliometric analysis</kwd>
        <kwd>Science mapping</kwd>
        <kwd>Scholarly impact</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="4"/>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="31"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Academic resilience is understood as the capacity of individuals (students and lecturers), institutions, and the broader higher education ecosystem to sustain and restore the performance of teaching-learning, research, and academic services when facing disruptions or change, while maintaining core functions and output quality. Conceptually, it is often distinguished from academic buoyancy—daily coping with routine academic ups and downs—whereas academic resilience emphasizes the ability to recover from more serious or prolonged adversity. This conceptual framework is strongly shaped by the development of the academic resilience scale instrument and contextualized by explanations of buoyancy among students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Cassidy, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Martin &amp;amp; Marsh, 2008</xref>).</p><p>In Indonesia, transformations in higher education—digitalization of learning processes, hybrid instruction, curriculum and assessment adjustments, expansion of access, and increasing demands for data literacy—have heightened the urgency of studying academic resilience as a foundation for quality improvement, equity, and the sustainability of academic ecosystems. Micro-level empirical evidence indicates that psychological resources (self-regulation, self-efficacy, and optimism) and social support correlate with higher student resilience during and after online learning; these findings have been reported across multiple Indonesian campuses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Hasibuan et al., 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Khadijah et al., 2021</xref>). Correspondingly, efforts to develop and validate localized measurement tools—from discriminant content validity testing for the Indonesian version of the academic resilience scale to factor analyses—underscore the importance of contextual sensitivity in assessment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Florensia &amp;amp; Siaputra, 2023</xref>).</p><p>Despite the increasing number of publications on academic resilience, a comprehensive map of research trends, dominant themes, key actors (authors, institutions, and partner countries), publication outlets, and scholarly influence (including field- and time-normalized citations) in the Indonesian context has not yet been systematically documented. The absence of an overarching picture hampers university leaders, educators, and research funders in setting priorities, designing strategic collaborations, and closing knowledge gaps that directly affect student success and institutional robustness. At this point, a bibliometric analysis—which integrates performance analysis and science mapping—offers a quantitative, transparent, and replicable approach to mapping the structure and dynamics of a field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Donthu et al., 2021</xref>). The first research gap concerns the fragmentation of focus. Many Indonesian studies remain situated at micro-psychological levels (students or classroom practice), with limited linkage to institutional and policy levels (systemic support, funding, governance, and campus strategy) or to broader collaboration ecosystems. The second gap relates to limited data sources (often relying on a single database) and/or short time spans, resulting in incomplete detection of thematic evolution and emerging research frontiers. The third gap is the lack of mapping of collaboration networks (co-authorship), citation flows (co-citation), and corpus proximity (bibliographic coupling) at national—global scales—dimensions that shape how ideas circulate and where knowledge hubs emerge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">van Eck &amp;amp; Waltman, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Additional gaps involve the absence of cross-topic synthesis explicitly connecting academic resilience with major higher-education issues—student success, well-being, digital readiness and equity, faculty resilience and professional development, and institutional governance—and mapping knowledge hotspots and knowledge gaps across periods. In several national findings, resilience is often positioned as an individual attribute (e.g., in relation to stress or optimism), while the bridges to programmatic, institutional, and policy-level dynamics remain insufficiently articulated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Rikumahu &amp;amp; Rahayu, 2022</xref>). Moving forward, a thematic map that situates overlapping constructs—academic resilience, buoyancy, and persistence/retention—within clear conceptual relationships can better support the formulation of precise policy and intervention strategies.</p><p>In terms of urgency, bibliometric mapping is needed to: (a) sharpen national research priorities on academic resilience by identifying fast-growing themes, saturated areas, and under-explored domains; (b) strengthen inter-institutional collaboration and global connectivity by identifying bridging actors and strategic networks; and (c) align scientific evidence with policies for improving learning quality, digital literacy and inclusion, and reducing academic disparities, thereby enabling more efficient and impactful research investments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Aria &amp;amp; Cuccurullo, 2017</xref>). In line with these needs, this study offers novelty in four aspects. First, it employs multi-database analysis (Scopus and Web of Science) over a long period (2000–2025) to capture both historical trajectories and current dynamics of the Indonesian corpus. Second, it combines performance analysis and science mapping (co-word, co-citation, bibliographic coupling, thematic evolution, and burst keywords) to identify research frontiers and thematic shifts. Third, it evaluates scholarly influence using citation indicators (e.g., the Hirsch index, citations per document, and normalized citation impact) and collaboration analysis at the author, institution, and country levels. Fourth, it highlights Indonesia-centric themes—equity and inclusion, learning well-being, digital readiness, and student success—to formulate contextually grounded research agendas and policy implications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Aria &amp;amp; Cuccurullo, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">van Eck &amp;amp; Waltman, 2010</xref>).</p><p>To avoid thematic interpretation that falls into individual-level reductionism, the conceptual stance of this study adopts the analytical distinction between resilience (coping with acute/chronic adversity) and buoyancy (day-to-day academic coping) as a complementary spectrum. Within this framework, related constructs—academic resilience, student resilience, and persistence/retention—are mapped as interconnected clusters rather than mutually exclusive categories, enabling quantitative findings from the bibliometric mapping to be more readily translated into policy and institutional practice recommendations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Martin &amp;amp; Marsh, 2008</xref>).</p><p>Based on this background, the objectives of the study are to: (a) map publication trends and key outlets on academic resilience in Indonesia from 2000 to 2025; (b) identify thematic clusters and thematic evolution across time slices using co-word analysis; (c) profile key actors and scientific collaboration patterns at the levels of authors, institutions, and partner countries; and (d) assess scholarly influence through citation indicators—including field- and time-normalized metrics—to develop a research agenda and policy/institutional practice implications that strengthen the resilience of Indonesia’s higher education ecosystem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Donthu et al., 2021</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Methodology</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Research design</title>
          
          <p>This study employed a bibliometric research design that integrates performance analysis to assess productivity and citation impact and science mapping to visualize thematic structures and knowledge networks. The analysis focused on publications on academic resilience within the Indonesian context from 2000 to 2025, enabling a longitudinal reading of literature growth, thematic shifts, and configurations of scientific collaboration. Units of analysis included documents (peer-reviewed journal articles and conference papers), authors, institutions, partner countries, publication outlets, and author keywords.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title>
          
          <p>Inclusion criteria were established to ensure the relevance and consistency of the corpus. Documents were required to: (a) explicitly investigate or mention academic resilience or its conceptual equivalents within academic contexts—including academic buoyancy, academic persistence, and student retention when directly linked to academic resilience; (b) be clearly connected to Indonesia through research subjects, study settings, or policy discussion; (c) be peer-reviewed journal articles or peer-reviewed conference papers; (d) be written in Indonesian or English; and (e) be published between 2000 and 2025 with minimum metadata (title, author(s), year), ideally including abstract, keywords, outlet, affiliations, and digital object identifier. Exclusion criteria comprised publications outside academic contexts (e.g., organizational or disaster resilience unrelated to education), non-scholarly texts (editorials, letters, and prefaces), preprints without peer review unless required by the target journal, duplicate versions (the most complete version retained), and records with insufficient metadata. Screening was conducted by two independent reviewers at the title/abstract stage to maintain decision consistency.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Search strategy</title>
          
          <p>The search strategy utilized Publish or Perish as the query manager and metadata harvester. Google Scholar served as the primary source due to its broad coverage of national literature; where available, searches were supplemented through Crossref or Scopus within the Publish or Perish interface for cross-checking and metadata enrichment. The year range was set to 2000–2025. Queries combined the core term “academic resilience” with closely related terms (“academic buoyancy,” “student academic resilience,” “academic persistence,” and “student retention”) and paired them with contextual markers (“Indonesia,” “Indonesian,” and “di Indonesia”). Search results were exported from Publish or Perish in RIS/BibTeX/CSV formats containing citation data, titles, abstracts (when available), keywords, outlets, authors, affiliations, digital object identifiers/uniform resource locators, and publication years.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Network and thematic mapping</title>
          
          <p>Network and thematic mapping were conducted using VOSviewer. Four types of networks were constructed: co-word (keyword co-occurrence) to identify thematic clusters; co-authorship to map collaboration among authors, institutions, and countries; co-citation to capture works/authors/journals functioning as shared intellectual foundations; and bibliographic coupling to estimate document proximity based on overlapping reference lists. The results were visualized using network maps, overlay maps (with temporal gradients to identify emerging topics), and density maps.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Results and discussion</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Research trends on academic resilience in indonesia</title>
          
          <p>The following map is presented to help readers gain an at-a-glance view of the thematic architecture within studies on academic resilience in Indonesia. Rather than displaying numerical values, this visualization functions as a conceptual compass: it illustrates frequently co-occurring key terms, their proximities to one another, and the pathways linking psychological dimensions, learning environments, educational outcomes, and institutional cultural contexts. Such thematic maps enable readers to identify the central clusters of ideas, accompanying themes, and emerging areas, allowing the subsequent results and discussion sections to be followed with a shared orientation.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> maps the co-occurrence network of keywords, where node size represents term frequency, the distance and thickness of connecting lines indicate the strength of association (how frequently two terms appear together), and the color overlay reflects relative recency (a gradient from older to newer topics). At the center of the network, academic resilience functions as an anchor node connecting three major clusters: (i) the psychological cluster (self-efficacy, motivation, self-control, and academic motivation); (ii) the support–relationship cluster (social support, relationship, peer, and influence) that links protective factors to adaptive processes within classroom and campus settings; and (iii) the outcomes cluster (academic performance/achievement and impact) representing the ultimate goals of the construct.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Co-occurrence map of keywords in academic resilience research in Indonesia by cluster</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/2/img_v36AHQCIyTwr8Z1K.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Extending outward from the core, the institutional cluster (school and education system) signals a shift of attention toward learning environment design and policy, while the cultural–contextual cluster (Islamic boarding schools, religiosity, bilingual, and country) captures the distinctive characteristics of the Indonesian educational ecosystem. The proximity of student resilience to terms such as impact and research reflects the use of quantitative models (e.g., mediation/moderation) to connect protective factors with academic outcomes. Meanwhile, smaller peripheral nodes—mediator, significant effect, and descriptive study—can be interpreted as thematic tails indicating diversification of methodological approaches.</p><p>Overall, the map reveals a layered thematic structure: psychological factors as the engine, support–relationship elements as the medium, academic achievement as the endpoint, and institutional–cultural frames as the contextual backdrop. This configuration provides a foundation for formulating a research agenda that more effectively addresses institutional and policy levels without losing the explanatory strength of individual factors.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> maps the keyword co-occurrence network with an emphasis on thematic novelty. Node size indicates the frequency of each term, the distance and thickness of the lines reflect the strength of association between terms, and the color overlay represents the relative time of appearance—the more yellow the color, the more recent the topic within the corpus. At the center of the network, “academic resilience” (a large green–teal node) acts as a stable anchor across time, linking the psychological cluster (self-efficacy, motivation, self-control, and academic motivation) and the support–relationship cluster (social support, relationship, peer, and influence) to academic outcomes (academic performance/achievement and impact). The left side of the network is dominated by blue–purple tones on terms such as pandemic and parts of social support/influence, indicating earlier themes that contextualized learning adaptation. Extending to the right, a series of lighter nodes (green–yellow)—school, comparative study, country, Islamic boarding schools, bilingual, and religiosity—represent the most recent themes (±2024–2025). This pattern shows a shift in research focus from the micro level toward institutional dimensions (schools/education systems) and Indonesia’s cultural context (Islamic boarding schools, bilingual issues, and religiosity), along with a growing interest in comparative studies.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Co-occurrence map of keywords in academic resilience research in Indonesia based on year of publication</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/2/img_wYyhL__3VXMlzf2i.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The proximity of “student resilience” to impact and research suggests the use of quantitative models (e.g., mediation or moderation) to link protective factors to academic outcomes. Small peripheral nodes—mediator, significant effect, and descriptive study—function as thematic tails, signaling methodological diversification. Overall, the color pattern affirms a layered thematic structure: a stable psychological core at the center (green–teal), early themes related to the pandemic context (blue–purple), and a new wave of research on institutions, culture, and comparative perspectives (green–yellow). This arrangement provides a foundation for future research agendas that expand the unit of analysis to institutional and policy levels and examine cultural moderation within academic resilience models.</p><p>The observed shift from predominantly psychological constructs toward institutional and cultural dimensions may reflect a broader conceptual development rather than merely a change in keyword frequency. Earlier studies in Indonesia largely framed academic resilience as an individual capacity grounded in self-efficacy, motivation, and self-regulation, consistent with trait-based and self-regulatory models in educational psychology. However, recent publications increasingly situate resilience within institutional systems, comparative educational settings, and culturally embedded contexts such as Islamic boarding schools, indicating a gradual theoretical broadening toward ecological and systemic perspectives. At the same time, this transition may partly be influenced by indexing dynamics, as institution-focused studies are more likely to appear in internationally indexed journals. Therefore, the shift likely represents a combination of genuine theoretical maturation and evolving publication practices, suggesting that academic resilience in Indonesia is increasingly conceptualized as a multilevel construct integrating individual capacities with structural and cultural ecosystems.</p><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>, the hotspot (bright yellow–green) is concentrated around “academic resilience,” indicating that this term serves as the densest node and the primary connector within the corpus. Surrounding it, high-density areas also appear around self-efficacy, relationship, resilience, social support, student resilience, research, and impact—a combination that highlights a psychological core (efficacy/relations/support) linked to outcomes (impact/performance) as the dominant stream of research.</p><p>The green zone extending toward the education system, motivation, academic performance/achievement, and school reflects medium density: these themes occur frequently and form meaningful connections, though not as strongly as the central cluster. On the right side, Islamic boarding schools and bilingual schools appear as isolated density islands (standalone green nodes): the topics are present and active but remain weakly linked to the core—signaling an emerging area whose connections could be strengthened (for example, by integrating cultural variables with efficacy/support and academic outcomes). Peripheral blue zones (mediator, significant effect, and descriptive study, with academic motivation further below) indicate terms that are infrequent or weakly connected; they function as thematic tails that remain sporadic within the field.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Density map of keywords in academic resilience research in Indonesia by year of publication</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/2/img_rLOEZ5QkCUlgdmMc.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Research themes on academic resilience in indonesia</title>
          
          <p>The first theme concerns the linkage between academic resilience and personal capacities. Based on the title mapping, terms such as self-efficacy, self-control, self-regulation, and motivation repeatedly appear. This indicates that many studies in Indonesia view academic resilience as rooted in students’ self-beliefs and their ability to manage learning. The logic is straightforward: when students believe in their capabilities and can regulate their time, tasks, and attention, they are more able to withstand exams, workload pressure, or changes in learning systems. This reasoning aligns with self-efficacy and self-regulated learning theories, which position personal control as a driver of academic adaptation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Bandura et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">Zimmerman, 2002</xref>). This trend is also reflected in commonly used research instruments: resilience measures often include items related to efficacy and motivation because these constructs are considered central (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Cassidy, 2016</xref>). Practically, a focus on personal capacities offers clear directions for intervention: strengthen efficacy, train self-regulation, and then assess the impact on academic resilience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Martin &amp;amp; Marsh, 2008</xref>).</p><p>However, the strong emphasis on personal capacities does not necessarily imply that academic resilience should be understood solely as a stable individual trait. Contemporary resilience scholarship increasingly conceptualizes resilience as a dynamic and developmental process shaped by interactions between individuals and their environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Rachmawati et al., 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Ye et al., 2021</xref>). Within this perspective, self-efficacy and self-regulation are not fixed attributes but adaptive capacities that can be cultivated through supportive institutional practices, instructional design, mentoring systems, and inclusive school climates. Therefore, the prominence of psychological variables in Indonesian research should be interpreted not as evidence of an individualistic bias, but as part of a broader resilience process in which institutional support plays a formative and enabling role. This interpretation aligns with ecological and process-oriented models of resilience that emphasize reciprocal influences between personal agency and structural conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Liaqat et al., 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Rachmawati et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>The second theme concerns the connection between academic resilience and social support. Research titles frequently include terms such as social support, peer, and teacher/parent/family support. The message is intuitive: supportive relationships help students endure when learning becomes challenging. Peer support fosters a sense of belonging; lecturer support offers guidance; and family support provides stability. The recurring vocabulary of “role” and “influence” in titles signals models that link social support to resilience in the face of academic stressors. This is consistent with the stress-buffering hypothesis, which posits that adequate support can reduce the adverse effects of stress and enhance academic adjustment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Cohen &amp;amp; Wills, 1985</xref>). Findings in educational psychology also reinforce this: positive relationships at school or university promote engagement and persistence, which in turn strengthen resilience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Wentzel, 1998</xref>).</p><p>The third theme examines the relationship between academic resilience and academic success. Many titles reflect a consistent pattern: factor X → resilience → achievement. Here, resilience is positioned as a bridge toward academic performance or academic achievement. In other words, psychological factors (e.g., efficacy and motivation) and social support are believed to influence achievement through academic resilience. This pattern aligns with meta-analytic evidence showing that psychosocial factors are indeed correlated with performance, persistence, and graduation outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Robbins et al., 2004</xref>). Titles in the dataset reinforce this message: resilience is not merely the ability to “endure,” but a mechanism that channels the influence of personal and social factors into measurable learning outcomes. Thus, placing resilience at the center of the causal pathway provides a clear basis for designing and evaluating classroom or campus interventions.</p><p>The fourth theme relates academic resilience to the broader educational environment. Several titles highlight school, the education system, comparative study, and contexts such as online/blended/pandemic learning. This theme reflects a shift from individual-level factors to environmental-level considerations: not only who the students are but also what institutional systems and practices they experience. Online or hybrid learning contexts and pandemic-related changes often serve as backgrounds that explain challenges and forms of adaptation. This aligns with student engagement and institutional integration frameworks, which emphasize that classroom policies, academic services, and campus climate strongly influence student success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Astin, 1997</xref>). In bibliometric terms, the emergence of institutional keywords signals a broadening of the unit of analysis: studies are no longer examining only internal student factors but also the design of learning environments.</p><p>The fifth theme concerns the cultural context of academic resilience in Indonesia. Many titles link resilience with Islamic boarding schools/pesantren, religiosity, and language-related issues such as bilingualism/English/literacy. This reflects how Indonesian research gives considerable attention to values, religious educational institutions, and linguistic practices. These three aspects shape how students interpret challenges and seek support in daily life. Ecological developmental theory posits that academic adaptation is shaped by the systems surrounding learners—family, institutions, community, and values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Bronfenbrenner, 1979</xref>). Meanwhile, bilingual education studies highlight the relationship between language competence, identity, and academic success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Cummins, 2000</xref>). From a bibliometric perspective, this cluster adds a distinctive local character to the thematic landscape and encourages future research on context-based moderation/mediation—such as how religiosity or linguistic factors strengthen the effects of efficacy and social support on achievement.</p><p>These five themes are better understood as complementary rather than competing perspectives. The first three themes, namely personal capacities, social support, and academic outcomes, are grounded in psychological and social–cognitive traditions that explain how protective factors contribute to achievement. The fourth and fifth themes expand this foundation by incorporating institutional conditions and cultural influences within the Indonesian educational system. Instead of indicating theoretical fragmentation, the clustering pattern points to an increasingly integrated understanding of academic resilience that connects individual, relational, institutional, and cultural levels of analysis. Such a configuration is consistent with ecological approaches to resilience, in which adaptive processes emerge from the interaction between personal agency and structural contexts rather than from isolated variables.</p><p>The identified thematic patterns may be understood as a response to both educational challenges and theoretical developments within the Indonesian context. The dominance of personal capacities and social support reflects the strong influence of psychological and stress-buffering frameworks in educational research, which offer measurable constructs and clear causal pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Aria &amp;amp; Cuccurullo, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">van Eck &amp;amp; Waltman, 2010</xref>). The subsequent expansion toward institutional and cultural themes likely corresponds to increasing recognition that academic resilience cannot be fully explained at the individual level alone, particularly in a diverse educational system shaped by religious schooling, multilingual environments, and policy reforms. These patterns suggest that future research design should move beyond cross-sectional predictor–outcome models and adopt multilevel and longitudinal approaches that integrate individual, relational, and institutional variables simultaneously. In particular, studies could employ hierarchical modeling, mixed-method designs, or comparative institutional analyses to examine how school systems, religious values, and linguistic contexts moderate or mediate resilience processes. Such designs would strengthen theoretical integration and enhance the contextual relevance of academic resilience research in Indonesia.</p><p>The prominence of Islamic boarding schools, religiosity, and bilingual contexts in the Indonesian literature also invites reflection on how far Western-origin theories of academic resilience adequately capture local realities. Most dominant resilience frameworks were developed in Western settings that emphasize individual autonomy and personal achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Elnaem et al., 2024</xref>). In contrast, Indonesian educational contexts, particularly in pesantren and other faith-based institutions, are deeply shaped by collective values, spiritual meaning, and communal responsibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Julaihah et al., 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Putri &amp;amp; Nursanti, 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Ramdani et al., 2020</xref>). In such environments, resilience may be nurtured not only through personal efficacy but also through religious commitment, moral discipline, and shared identity. Similarly, multilingual and bilingual settings introduce additional adaptive demands that are less visible in monolingual Western models. These contextual features suggest that Indonesian research does not merely apply Western theories, but implicitly extends them by embedding resilience within spiritual, communal, and linguistic dimensions that deserve more explicit theoretical articulation.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Scientific influence of academic resilience research in indonesia</title>
          
          <p>First, in terms of the most influential studies, review articles occupy the top positions in citation counts—“Academic resilience among students: A review of literature” serves as a key reference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Radhamani &amp;amp; Kalaivani, 2021</xref>). Studies on the pandemic and online learning also receive high citations: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Eva et al. (2021)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Kumalasari &amp;amp; Akmal (2021)</xref> show that resilience helps reduce stress and improve well-being in online learning contexts. From Indonesia, a series of works by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Rachmawati et al. (2021)</xref> on resilience prevalence and the roles of social support and self-efficacy are also highly cited. Cross-national studies such as the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Elnaem et al. (2024)</xref> further broaden citation reach.</p><p>Second, the frequently cited articles share several common characteristics. Review or synthesis papers and articles that validate measurement scales (for example, using Rasch analysis or other measurement models) tend to be widely reused, resulting in high citation counts. Articles that explain mechanisms—such as the relationship between self-efficacy or social support and resilience, which then influences reduced stress or improved performance—are more frequently cited because they offer causal pathways that can be easily adopted by other studies. In addition, timely topics such as the pandemic and online learning attract rapid scholarly attention, thereby increasing visibility and citation counts.</p><p>In this field, systematic reviews and standardized instruments (Rasch/measurement models) function as “public goods,” heavily reused by researchers → thus highly cited. Many influential articles position self-efficacy, social support, mindfulness, or self-compassion as predictors, with resilience serving as a mediator/moderator, leading to lower stress, better well-being, or improved performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Kotera et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">Salsabila &amp;amp; Widyasari, 2021</xref>). Pandemic- and online-learning-related articles (2020–2022) show exceptionally high citation numbers because they addressed an urgent scholarly need (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Eva et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Kumalasari &amp;amp; Akmal, 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Sholichah &amp;amp; Hasanah, 2022</xref>).</p><p>Third, in terms of research foci reflected in the field’s landscape, the variables most commonly found in influential articles include personal capacities (self-efficacy, self-regulation, mindfulness, and self-compassion), social support (peers, lecturers, and family), and outcomes such as stress, well-being, and achievement. The efficacy + support → resilience → lower stress/higher well-being &amp;amp; performance formula is the dominant pattern among highly cited articles. Common methods include instrument validation and measurement modeling (Rasch), comparative and cross-context designs (e.g., studies across 12 countries and comparisons between schools/countries), and mediation/moderation analyses involving psychological variables.</p><p>Many titles explicitly refer to “college/university/adolescents.” Studies on lecturers or organizational settings remain rare among the top-cited works. Islamic and cultural contexts are beginning to appear but have not yet reached top citation ranks (e.g., spiritual well-being, pesantren, and religiosity)—representing a growing frontier. Additionally, some influential works are purely Indonesia-based, while others involve cross-national collaboration; both can achieve high citation impact when they offer relevant tools, syntheses, or findings.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>4. Conclusions</title>
      <p>Based on the results and discussion above, several conclusions can be drawn. First, research trends indicate a shift—illustrated in the network and overlay maps—from a focus on psychological factors and pandemic/online learning toward institutional environments and Indonesian cultural contexts. Second, five major themes emerge from the titles: personal capacities (self-efficacy/self-regulation), social support (peers–lecturers–family), learning outcomes (achievement/well-being), educational environments and institutions (school/education system/online–blended learning), and cultural–linguistic contexts (Islamic boarding schools, religiosity, and bilingualism). Third, the most influential articles are typically review papers and pandemic/online-learning studies, frequently employing validated measurement scales and mechanism-based models (factor → resilience → outcome), with cross-national research further expanding citation reach. Overall, the dominant pattern in the academic resilience literature follows efficacy + support → resilience → outcomes, while future research gaps lie at the institutional/lecturer level and in strengthening Islamic and linguistic contextualization to enhance relevance and impact.</p><p>Nevertheless, the findings should be interpreted in light of methodological limitations related to data sources. While Google Scholar provides broad coverage of Indonesian publications, its indexing of Indonesian-language journals is not always systematic, which may result in the underrepresentation of locally published studies with limited digital visibility. Consequently, the thematic and citation patterns identified in this study may reflect not only intellectual developments but also database visibility structures. Future bibliometric investigations are therefore encouraged to integrate national journal portals and institutional repositories to ensure a more balanced representation of Indonesian scholarship.</p><p>In relation to broader resilience scholarship, the theoretical orientations found in Indonesian academic resilience research largely align with established Western frameworks, particularly those grounded in self-efficacy theory, stress-buffering models, and ecological perspectives. The frequent use of predictor–resilience–outcome models reflects strong continuity with international literature. However, the increasing attention to Islamic educational settings, religiosity, and multilingual learning environments suggests that Indonesian research is beginning to extend these frameworks by embedding resilience within spiritual, communal, and linguistic dimensions that are less emphasized in Western contexts. Although a fully articulated indigenous theoretical model has not yet clearly emerged, the thematic patterns indicate the potential development of a contextually grounded perspective in which academic resilience is understood as both an individual and culturally situated adaptive process.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>Conceptualization, L.E.W.F. and M.S.; methodology, L.E.W.F.; software, L.E.W.F.; validation, L.E.W.F., M.S., G.G., and A.N.; formal analysis, L.E.W.F.; investigation, L.E.W.F.; resources, L.E.W.F.; data curation, L.E.W.F.; writing—original draft preparation, L.E.W.F.; writing—review and editing, L.E.W.F. and A.N.; visualization, L.E.W.F.; supervision, M.S., G.G.; project administration, L.E.W.F.; funding acquisition, M.S. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>959-975</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aria</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cuccurullo</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joi.2017.08.007</pub-id>
          <article-title>Bibliometrix: An R-tool for comprehensive science mapping analysis</article-title>
          <source>J. Informetr.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Astin</surname>
              <given-names>A. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>What Matters in College? Four Critical Years Revisited</source>
          <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
          <year>1997</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>158-166</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1999</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bandura</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Freeman</surname>
              <given-names>W. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lightsey</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1891/0889-8391.13.2.158</pub-id>
          <article-title>Self-efficacy: The exercise of control</article-title>
          <source>J. Cogn. Psychother.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bronfenbrenner</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The Ecology of Human Development: Experiments by Nature and Design</source>
          <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>
          <year>1979</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>1787</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cassidy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2016.01787</pub-id>
          <article-title>The Academic Resilience Scale (ARS-30): A new multidimensional construct measure</article-title>
          <source>Front. Psychol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>98</volume>
          <page-range>310-357</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1985</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cohen</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wills</surname>
              <given-names>T. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.98.2.310</pub-id>
          <article-title>Stress, social support, and the buffering hypothesis.</article-title>
          <source>Psychol. Bull.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cummins</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Theory as dialogue</article-title>
          <source>Language, Power and Pedagogy: Bilingual Children in the Crossfire</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <page-range>1-7</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>133</volume>
          <page-range>285-296</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Donthu</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mukherjee</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pandey</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lim</surname>
              <given-names>W. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2021.04.070</pub-id>
          <article-title>How to conduct a bibliometric analysis: An overview and guidelines</article-title>
          <source>J. Bus. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>88</volume>
          <page-range>100693</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elnaem</surname>
              <given-names>M. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wan Salam</surname>
              <given-names>W. N. A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thabit</surname>
              <given-names>Abrar K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mubarak</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abou Khatwa</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramatillah</surname>
              <given-names>D. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Isah</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barakat</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Jumaili</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mansour</surname>
              <given-names>N. O. et al</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajpe.2024.100693</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessment of academic resilience and its associated factors among pharmacy students in twelve countries</article-title>
          <source>Am. J. Pharm. Educ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>202–214</page-range>
          <issue>15</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eva</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parameitha</surname>
              <given-names>D. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farah</surname>
              <given-names>F. A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nurfitriana</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18502/kss.v4i15.8206</pub-id>
          <article-title>Academic resilience and subjective well-being amongst college students using online learning during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>
          <source>KnE Soc. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>83-94</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Florensia</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siaputra</surname>
              <given-names>I. B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30595/psychoidea.v21i1.16014</pub-id>
          <article-title>Optimizing academic resilience measurement: Discriminant content validity test on the Indonesian version of the ARS-30</article-title>
          <source>Psycho Idea</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>102–108</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hasibuan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Astuti</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hafnidar</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2910/insight.v2i1.14536</pub-id>
          <article-title>Gambaran resiliensi akademik pada mahasiswa Universitas Malikussaleh</article-title>
          <source>INSIGHT J. Penelit. Psikol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>128–136</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Julaihah</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laily</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Achmad</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sasi</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zahro</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18860/24360</pub-id>
          <article-title>Academic resilience among undergraduate students: The analysis of psycho-social and religious aspects</article-title>
          <source>J-PIPS</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>66–72</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khadijah</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maharani</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khasanah</surname>
              <given-names>M. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24014/egcdj.v4i2.14373</pub-id>
          <article-title>Resiliensi akademik mahasiswa terhadap pembelajaran daring</article-title>
          <source>Educ. Guid. Couns. Dev. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>2092</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kotera</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aledeh</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnes</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rushforth</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adam</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riswani</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/healthcare10102092</pub-id>
          <article-title>Academic motivation of Indonesian university students: Relationship with self-compassion and resilience</article-title>
          <source>Healthcare</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>12</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumalasari</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akmal</surname>
              <given-names>S. Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7454/proust.v4i1.115</pub-id>
          <article-title>Less stress, more satisfied in online learning during the COVID-19 pandemic: The moderating role of academic resilience</article-title>
          <source>Psychol. Res. Urban Soc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>1467544</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liaqat</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Islam</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azim</surname>
              <given-names>M. U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lodhi</surname>
              <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1467544</pub-id>
          <article-title>Investigating academic resilience in learning English: An ecological context of undergraduate students</article-title>
          <source>Front. Psychol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>46</volume>
          <page-range>53-83</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marsh</surname>
              <given-names>H. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsp.2007.01.002</pub-id>
          <article-title>Academic buoyancy: Towards an understanding of students' everyday academic resilience</article-title>
          <source>J. Sch. Psychol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>122-130</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Putri</surname>
              <given-names>W. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nursanti</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17509/ije.v13i2.24547</pub-id>
          <article-title>The relationship between peer social support and academic resilience of young adult migrant students in Jakarta</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Educ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>55-60</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rachmawati</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Astuti</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurniasari</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17977/um059v4i12024p55-60</pub-id>
          <article-title>Students’ academic resilience: A descriptive study</article-title>
          <source>Bul. Konseling Inovatif</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>49-62</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rachmawati</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Setyosari</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Handarini</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hambali</surname>
              <given-names>I. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1504/ijlc.2021.111664</pub-id>
          <article-title>Do social support and self-efficacy correlate with academic resilience among adolescence</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Learn. Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>360-369</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Radhamani</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalaivani</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.52403/ijrr.20210646</pub-id>
          <article-title>Academic resilience among students: A review of literature</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Res. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>105-120</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramdani</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanurawan</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramli</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lasan</surname>
              <given-names>B. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Afdal</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.29333/IJI.2021.1417A</pub-id>
          <article-title>Development and validation of Indonesian academic resilience scale using Rasch models</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Instr.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>575-584</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rikumahu</surname>
              <given-names>M. C. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rahayu</surname>
              <given-names>M. N. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30872/psikoborneo.v10i3.8467</pub-id>
          <article-title>Academic resilience in students: How does it relate to optimism during online learning?</article-title>
          <source>Psikoborneo J. Ilm. Psikol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>130</volume>
          <page-range>261-288</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robbins</surname>
              <given-names>S. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davis</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lauver</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Langley</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carlstrom</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.130.2.261</pub-id>
          <article-title>Do psychosocial and study skill factors predict college outcomes? A meta-analysis</article-title>
          <source>Psychol. Bull.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>139-152</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Salsabila</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Widyasari</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26555/humanitas.v18i2.19027</pub-id>
          <article-title>Mindfulness and academic resilience among unprivileged college students: The mediating role of self-compassion</article-title>
          <source>Humanitas Indones. Psychol. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>119-130</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sholichah</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasanah</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5220/0010809500003347</pub-id>
          <article-title>Covid-19 pandemic: Academic resilience and academic stress among college students in Gresik</article-title>
          <source>, http://dx.doi.org/10.5220/0010809500003347</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>84</volume>
          <page-range>523-538</page-range>
          <year>2010</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>van Eck</surname>
              <given-names>N. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waltman</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11192-009-0146-3</pub-id>
          <article-title>Software survey: VOSviewer, a computer program for bibliometric mapping</article-title>
          <source>Scientometrics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>90</volume>
          <page-range>202-209</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1998</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wentzel</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-0663.90.2.202</pub-id>
          <article-title>Social relationships and motivation in middle school: The role of parents, teachers, and peers.</article-title>
          <source>J. Educ. Psychol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>33</volume>
          <page-range>169-202</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strietholt</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blömeke</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11092-020-09351-7</pub-id>
          <article-title>Academic resilience: Underlying norms and validity of definitions</article-title>
          <source>Educ. Assess. Eval. Account.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>41</volume>
          <page-range>64-70</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2002</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zimmerman</surname>
              <given-names>B. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/s15430421tip4102_2</pub-id>
          <article-title>Becoming a self-regulated learner: An overview</article-title>
          <source>Theory Pract.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>