<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CIS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Challenges in Sustainability</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Chall. Sustain.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">CIS</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2297-6477</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print"/>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-FuQBrhgwaOx5TVo8c84b_eZUhwXfbWDV</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/cis120405</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Impacts of Anthropogenic Activities on Morocco’s Ecological Footprint: A Long-Run STIRPAT Analysis Using VAR/VECM Modeling</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-8365-6238</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Hamdi</surname>
            <given-names>El Asli</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>hamdielasli@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1,2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1205-1908</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohamed</surname>
            <given-names>Azeroual</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>m.azeroual@usms.ma</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Economy and Management, Poly Disciplinary Faculty of Khouribga, Sultan Moulay Slimane University, 23000 Beni Mellal, Morocco</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Laboratory MFMDI, SUPMTI, 10000 Rabat, Morocco</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2024</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>292</fpage>
      <lpage>309</lpage>
      <page-range>292-309</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2024 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>This study assesses the long-term impacts of anthropogenic activities on Morocco's Ecological Footprint (EF), employing a dataset from 1980 to 2022 within the framework of the STIRPAT model and utilizing a model (VAR/VECM) approach. Results indicate that Demographic Growth (DG) and Economic Growth (EG) have contributed to an increase of EF by 13.76% and 119.13% per unit output, respectively. Conversely, Higher Educational (HE) attainment scores is shown to alleviate EF, reducing its output by 50.59%. This analysis underscores the urgent need for policy pathways in Morocco that prioritize ecosystem preservation, foster green growth, and promote Human Capital (HC). Recommendations include enhancing the valorization and expansion of the natural ecosystem, aligning economic and demographic trajectories with the region's Bio-Capacity (BC) regeneration limits, and optimizing EF management through sustainable consumption and production practices.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Anthropogenic activities</kwd>
        <kwd>Ecological footprint</kwd>
        <kwd>Morocco</kwd>
        <kwd>STIRPAT</kwd>
        <kwd>VAR</kwd>
        <kwd>VECM</kwd>
        <kwd>Green growth</kwd>
        <kwd>Bio-capacity</kwd>
        <kwd>Sustainable development</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="2"/>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="17"/>
        <ref-count count="85"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>The stress placed on the biosphere by resources human’s is quantified by a measure called EF, this concept was introduced in mid-nineties by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_78">Wackernagel &amp;amp; Rees (1996)</xref> for the evaluation of environmental impacts associated with human activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_57">Nautiyal &amp;amp; Goel, 2021</xref>), which represents a conception of the manner that humans are affecting the environment considering production, energy use, management of land for living space, fooding, goods extracting etc. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Dietz et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_62">Rafindadi &amp;amp; Usman, 2020</xref>). However, few studies around the world have shown interest to the impact of environmental stressors on global biosphere degradation using EF as an indicator such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_85">Zhang et al. (2020)</xref>, unlike the other popular indicators in the matter, such as CO<sub>2</sub> emissions like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Ansari et al. (2019)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_59">Naz et al. (2024)</xref>, or GHG emissions like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_66">Sarkodie &amp;amp; Strezov (2018)</xref>, or even energy consumption like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Belloumi &amp;amp; Alshehry (2015)</xref>, or more than one indicator as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_74">Ullah &amp;amp; Lin (2024)</xref> did, even less in the Moroccan context excepting one single study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Farouki &amp;amp; Aissaoui, (2024</xref>). Morocco, like many countries, has reached critical limits of resources consumption and waste production compared to the bio-capacity potential of regeneration and waste absorption, supposing that any rise in EF reduces the environmental ecosystem quality, this implies that a country become more globalized and technologized, productive and popularized, the more likely it is to experience an ecological overshoot as soon as imaginable. The idea that any rise in EF reduces eventually the ambient ecosystem quality implies that as a country become more globalized and technologized, productive and popularized, the more likely it is to experience an ecological overshoot. Morocco is taking significant steps to reduce its ecological footprint, particularly through investments in clean energies, sustainable agriculture and HC promotion, however, challenges such as water scarcity, waste management, amplified DG correlated to consumption intensification and the climate change effects are posing significant hurdles; which is putting on stake the Moroccan vital ecosystem survival, and subsequently, the harsh issue of the urgent need to conserve the environmental patrimony.</p><p>Few studies around the world have shown interest in the impact of environmental stressors on global biosphere degradation using EF as an indicator such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_85">Zhang et al. (2020)</xref>, unlike the other popular indicators in the matter, such as CO<sub>2</sub> emissions like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Ansari et al. (2019)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_59">Naz et al. (2024)</xref>, GHG emissions like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_66">Sarkodie &amp;amp; Strezov (2018)</xref>, or even energy consumption like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Belloumi &amp;amp; Alshehry (2015)</xref>, or more than one indicator as did <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_74">Ullah &amp;amp; Lin (2024)</xref>, even less in the Moroccan context excepting one single study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Farouki &amp;amp; Aissaoui (2024)</xref>. Actually, Morocco, like many countries, has reached critical limits of resource consumption and waste production compared to the bio-capacity potential of regeneration and waste absorption, supposing that any rise in EF reduces the environmental ecosystem quality. This implies that a country such as Morocco when it becomes more globalized, technologized, productive, and popularized, the more likely it is to experience an ecological overshoot as soon as imaginable. The idea that any rise in EF eventually reduces the ambient ecosystem quality implies that as a country becomes more globalized, technologized, productive, and popularized, the more likely it is to experience an ecological overshoot. Therefore, a scientific formulation and a constructive description of the linkage between environmental degradation and anthropogenic activities in the Moroccan context are required to first diagnose the state of ecological gangrene and to assess efficient and targeted policies in order to undermine it. After an in-depth literature review, the research methodology is largely schemed step by step and sufficiently presented method by method, abreast with the variable presentation and the model construction in the 2<sup>nd</sup> Section , results issued from the empirical evidence are exposed and given an economic interpretation in the 3<sup>rd</sup> Section, and then discussed and compared with other similar studies outputs in the 4<sup>th</sup> Section, where also included a critical reflection on the limitations of the study and its potential biases along with future prospects. before it gets concluded with constructive remarks in the 5<sup>th</sup> and built upon political implications underneath in the 6<sup>th</sup> section.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Literature review</title>
      <p>On one hand, the EKC hypothesis that dissects the long matter-of-debate nexus between environmental degradation and EG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Adhikary &amp;amp; Hajra, 2021</xref>) takes the form of an inverted U-shape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">Kuznets, 1955</xref>), supposing that in the primer phase of an economic cycle, affluence and environmental degradation increase simultaneously, but when a specific level of individual income is reached, the relationship reverses, and further EG leads to a reduction in environmental impact as societies can afford cleaner technologies and stronger environmental regulations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Beyene &amp;amp; Kotosz, 2019</xref>). This pattern is more observed in developed economies than in the emerging ones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Dinda, 2004</xref>). In the wake of the EKC hypothesis, some researchers founded that demographic and EG are the main causes of human environmental stressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">Dietz &amp;amp; Rosa, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_58">Nautiyal et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_76">Varun &amp;amp; Chauhan, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_69">Shree et al., 2021</xref>), while others largely considered other endogenous factors such as urban growth, demographic structure, and income distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Danish et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">Liddle, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_82">Yu &amp;amp; Du, 2019</xref>). An effective combination of these factors can make possible promoting EG without the environmental resources and ultimately, to ensure human well-being and sustainable development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Farouki &amp;amp; Aissaoui, 2024</xref>), in fact many studies have addressed this issue through CO<sub>2</sub> as a target key indicator to asses effective environmental management <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Abbasi et al. (2021)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Bekun et al. (2019)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Bélaïd &amp;amp; Youssef (2017)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">Mirziyoyeva &amp;amp; Salahodjaev (2022)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_63">Raihan &amp;amp; Tuspekova (2022)</xref>, but as this indicator was subject to waves of massive critics regarding the lack of its exhaustiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Altıntaş &amp;amp; Kassouri, 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Aziz &amp;amp; Sarwar, 2023</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Destek et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">Nathaniel et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_73">Ullah et al., 2023</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_75">Usman et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_64">Ramezani et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_71">Sun et al., 2023</xref>). Thus, particular attention has been given to EF as an exhaustive indicator which takes into account a panoply of different ecological stressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">Galli et al., 2013</xref>), especially those related to production and consumption from a human behavior perspective. This is why it is substantially more suited to assess comprehension about the linkage of humans with the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_62">Rafindadi &amp;amp; Usman, 2020</xref>). The following <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> highlights some recent works close to the present paper, treating the fluctuations of anthropogenic activities on EFs applied to homologous countries, groups of countries, and regions quasi-identic to Morocco regarding the economic affluence and the demographic structure, in order to define precise references to the hypotheses that guide the study.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Similar studies of the impacts of anthropogenic activities on ecological footprint</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Study Purpose</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Coverage</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Main Results</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Analyzing the nexus between economy, renewable energy, DG and EF with an empirical evidence using STIRPAT model in Morocco” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Farouki &amp;amp; Aissaoui, 2024</xref>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1980 to 2021</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Long term incidence of individual income, renewable energy consumption, urban growth, trade openness on EF in Morocco in parallel with the confirmation of the EKC hypothesis” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Farouki &amp;amp; Aissaoui, 2024</xref>)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Examining the incidence of, economic factors, HC, energy consumption, and urbanization on CO<sub>2</sub> in Morocco: with an ARDL approach” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Asli et al., 2024</xref>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1970 to 2019</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“HC rise leads to a fall-down in carbon emissions, conversely, when EG and energy consumption upsurge, the opposite is resulted” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Asli et al., 2024</xref>)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Examining the cause-effect fluctuations in EF and CO<sub>2</sub> in Pakistan of GDP, renewable energy, natural resources and DG” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_74">Ullah &amp;amp; Lin, 2024</xref>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1990 to 2018</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Natural Ressources and Renewable Energy have an asymmetric impact on environmental quality. While GDP was found to have positive impact with EFP and CO<sub>2</sub>” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_74">Ullah &amp;amp; Lin, 2024</xref>)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Investigating the asymmetric impact of patents on green technologies on Algeria’s EF” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Bergougui &amp;amp; Aldawsari, 2024</xref>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1990 to 2022</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Upsurge in green technologies (renewable energies and the HC in back up) significantly reduces EF” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Bergougui &amp;amp; Aldawsari, 2024</xref>)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Studying the nexus between renewable energy production, energy consumption and sustainable EG in Turkey using a VECM approach” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Dinç &amp;amp; Akdoğan, 2019</xref>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1980 to 2016</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Causal relationship between renewable energy and EG both in the short and long runs, also a causal relationship running from energy consumption to EG both in the short and long runs, support” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Dinç &amp;amp; Akdoğan, 2019</xref>)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Analyzing the relationship between Renewable energy, urban growth, and EF in MENA” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">Nathaniel et al., 2020</xref>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1990 to 2016</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Energy consumption, urbanization, EG, and energy use contribute to environmental degradation” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">Nathaniel et al., 2020</xref>)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Weighting the impact of HC on the EF in India through an empirical analysis” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Ali et al., 2022</xref>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1990 to 2016</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Natural resources exploitation, financial inclusion, EG, and urban growth increase the entire panel's EF pressure. While Economic governance institutions, renewable energy consumption, and HC reduce the EF on the ECOWAS economies” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Ali et al., 2022</xref>)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Associating EG and EFs through BC and HC and in South Asia” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">Mehmood et al., 2023</xref>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1990 to 2022</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>“Positive contribution of GDP, HC, BC, and urban growth to EF” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">Mehmood et al., 2023</xref>)</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>In the anthropogenic-environmental-degradation field research, the main adopted theoretical framework is unequivocally STIRPAT pioneered by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">Ehrlich &amp;amp; Holdren (1971)</xref>, well known as an analytic practical tool for empirical analysis based on statistical regressions of between human activity variables and environment-dependent indicators, supposing the incidence on natural capital as a commutative product imputed to three categories of environmental stressors: primo (P) for population dynamics and activities, secondo (A) for EG, and tertio (T) for technological progress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_81">York et al., 2003</xref>). STIRAPT is the top celebrity among the IPAT family, from which some derived models merit some attention, like the "ImPACT indentity," which identifies “actors with the forces” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_79">Waggoner &amp;amp; Ausubel, 2002</xref>). In the same line, some authors proposed the ImPACTs identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">Lin et al., 2009</xref>). Some others proposed the "IPBAT identity" <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_67">Schulze (2002)</xref> which was criticized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Diesendorf (2002)</xref>, who argued that the behavior is already implicit in the IPAT equation as reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_77">Vélez-Henao et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>In the wake of all these efforts and debates, this study is projected into the Moroccan context with the purpose of clearly responding to the sequential following questioning:</p><p>How are human activities, incorporated by EG, DG, and HE, affecting the EF in Morocco?</p><p>What is the singular effect of each one of these factors on the EF in Morocco?</p><p>And how are these three factors jointly manifesting their impact on the EF in Morocco?</p><p>In response to these queries, the following hypothesis has been formulated:</p><p>H<sub>0</sub>: EG, DG, and HE are affecting the EF in Morocco. From which are to be verified the following sub-hypothesis:</p><p>H<sub>0a</sub>: EG has a negative impact on EF in Morocco.</p><p>H<sub>0b</sub>: DG has a negative incidence on EF in Morocco.</p><p>H<sub>0c</sub>: HE has a negative effect on EF in Morocco.</p><p>By bringing constructive demonstrations, the purpose of this study is to measure the incidence of anthropogenic activities on the EF in Morocco.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Research methodology</title>
      <p>This study uses a VAR model, which makes able the forecast for future values of multiple data based on their past tendencies. The VAR is estimated after differencing non-stationary series, while the VECM incorporates the co-integrating relationship to model the series in levels. They both exhibit an equilibrium relationship over the long-run. The VECM has an error correction term (ECT) that accounts for short-run deviations from this equilibrium. While a VAR uses only lagged values for the variables as predictors, a VECM also includes the ECT. This study's procedural logarithm is exhaustively schematized in steps in the following <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>:</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The VAR/VECM approach procedure</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/11/img_wrgMUnuf_FoMv7_f.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Model presentation</title>
          
          <p>This study applies the STIRPAT model in line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Abbas et al. (2023)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Bargaoui et al. (2014)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_81">York et al. (2003)</xref> with the following specifications:</p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mbt2vg54jf">
    <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:msubsup>
      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    </mml:msubsup>
    <mml:msubsup>
      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    </mml:msubsup>
    <mml:msubsup>
      <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    </mml:msubsup>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p>where, <italic>P</italic> stands for Population quantity, <italic>A</italic> for Affluence and e for Technological progress and vary simultaneously across the observational units through the subscript i, while <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>d</italic> are their respective exponents, the constant <italic>θ</italic> scales the model, <italic>e</italic> represents the white noise term. Nevertheless, the designation of the technology term is a matter of ceaseless debate, in some papers it is the error term, in some others it is taken for an independent variable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_77">Vélez-Henao et al., 2019</xref>). In this paper, Technology is recuperated by HE, because, intuitively, a technological society is a highly educated society, since adopting technology and handling it, especially for production, is necessarily requiring a high level of education and technical knowledge, hence, the relationship between technology and education can be described from an epistemological perspective as “bidirectional, impacting graduates' skills and necessitating educational adaptation to equip students with relevant technology and strategy skills for the modern workplace” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Efthymiou et al., 2022</xref>). Accordingly, the following functional form is adopted:</p><p style="text-align: center"><italic>EF</italic> = <italic>f</italic> (<italic>EG</italic>, <italic>DG</italic>, <italic>HE</italic>)</p><p>where, <italic>EF</italic> stands for Ecological footprint, <italic>EG</italic> for Economic Growth, <italic>DG</italic> for Demographic Growth and <italic>HE</italic> for Higher Education, with f defined as a linear function.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> below describes the variables above, their relative data and provide their respective resources:</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Variables and data presentation</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>STIRPAT Determinants</p></td><td><p>Variables</p></td><td><p>Acronym</p></td><td><p>Unit of Measure</p></td><td><p>Data Source</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>I</p></td><td><p>Ecological Footprint of consumption per capita</p></td><td><p>EF</p></td><td><p>Global hectare</p></td><td><p>Global Footprint Network</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>P</p></td><td><p>Demographic Growth</p></td><td><p>DG</p></td><td><p>Unitless</p></td><td><p>World Development Indicators</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>A</p></td><td><p>Economic Growth </p><p>(GDP per capita)</p></td><td><p>EG</p></td><td><p>Constant 2015 USD</p></td><td><p>World Development Indicators</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>T</p></td><td><p>Higher Education enrolments</p></td><td><p>HE</p></td><td><p>Number</p></td><td><p>UNESCO Institute for Statistics (UIS)</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> provides a graphic description of the variables key’s data evolution over the period of study.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>The variables keys' data evolution</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/11/img_mUdKhesiq8_U3wxx.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Model construction</title>
          
          <p>This study is conducted by using a representative sample of 43 annual observations from 1980 to 2022. In which the collected data is expressed in a numeric form, dedicated for second use, and already been published under free common licenses from their original sources, and chosen based on their adequacy for VAR modeling. Hence, the STIRPAT model was applied in the strict sense, in which no control variables were added for the purpose of getting authentic and credible interpretations.</p><p>Based on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>, the time series plots are showing upward trends and tend to show relative stability over time except for ecological footprint, which is manifesting a saw tooth curve over time in a rising trend. It is obvious, in the long of the study coverage, that pressure made on natural resources was getting progressively intensive, that the part of each capita of the national production was increasing quasi-expandingly, that DG was sustained at a stable rate, while the portion of highly educated people in Morocco kept increasing significantly. The fallback observed towards the plots’ ends concerning EF and DG is essentially due to the fallouts of the Covid-19 conjecture.</p><p>By applying the natural log on the functional form, the following specifications are attained:</p><p>The initial model:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <mml:math id="mwz3izt1p7">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnEF</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnEG</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnHE</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                <mml:mi>LnDG</mml:mi>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>The VAR model:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(2)</label>
              <mml:math id="ms3yyix8l3">
                <mml:mtable columnalign="right" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
                  <mml:mtr>
                    <mml:mtd>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>LnEF</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnEF</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnEG</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnDG</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnHE</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mtd>
                  </mml:mtr>
                  <mml:mtr>
                    <mml:mtd>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnEF</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnEG</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnDG</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnHE</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mtd>
                  </mml:mtr>
                </mml:mtable>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where,<span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif"> <italic><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">λ</italic><sub><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0...4</sub><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">,<italic><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif"> λ</italic><sub><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1...4</sub><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif"> represent the variables coefficients, <italic><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">ε</italic><sub><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">t </sub><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">the error term, t time periods.</p><p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">The VECM model:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(3)</label>
              <mml:math id="m507u8njez">
                <mml:mtable displaystyle="true" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="3pt">
                  <mml:mtr>
                    <mml:mtd>
                      <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>LnEF</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>LnEF</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>LnEG</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LnDG</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:munderover>
                    </mml:mtd>
                  </mml:mtr>
                  <mml:mtr>
                    <mml:mtd>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:munderover>
                        <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:munderover>
                      <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>LnHE</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">ECT</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mtd>
                  </mml:mtr>
                </mml:mtable>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <italic>λ</italic><sub>0...5</sub> represent the short run coefficients,<italic> μ</italic><sub>0 </sub>the error term, t time periods.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Methods</title>
          
          <p>The empirical evidence of this study is conducted following the methods explained below:</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.1 Descriptive analysis</title>
              
              <p>Descriptive analysis is affected by three techniques: common descriptive statistics, multiple correlation analysis (MCA) introduced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Bonett &amp;amp; Wright (2000)</xref>, and principal component analysis (PCA) pioneered by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_60">Pearson (1901)</xref>, all in line with El <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Asli et al. (2024)</xref>. Descriptive statistics are to be interpreted based on the dispersion indicators (mean, median, and Std Dev), besides Skewness, Kurtoisis, and the Jarque-Bera normality test.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.2 Pairwise granger causality</title>
              
              <p>The causality test between the variables in the short run is conducted via the direct <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">Granger (1969)</xref> Method which was introduced under the following specification:</p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mz7ut317e7">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:munderover>
      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:munderover>
    <mml:munderover>
      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    </mml:munderover>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p>Expressed in the reverse direction:</p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mlwc66rnnu">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:munderover>
      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:munderover>
    <mml:munderover>
      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    </mml:munderover>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mz6clzco7e">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mzim9prpdg">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> represent the variables to study the short run causality between; <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mv6u799405">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m3e42jgznl">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> are coefficients endorsing previous periods, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m1fnn9qsx0">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="ml153fvvm1">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> are constants, t is time and k is the number of lags, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mfz2xlk9uf">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m63nund5oy">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> are error terms.</p><p>The hypotheses to be tested are: <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mgjg6metrg">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> against <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mb8vg888pv">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> against <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7pskgvf5h">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>.</p><p>If <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mhj35vsw2w">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> but <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mm1k34scci">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> then <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mnogdzcbuu">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> cause <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mci3rtcyxl">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and if <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="md4vtri1z7">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> but <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mc5h4c3h99">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> then <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m5357cef8b">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> cause <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mves00wq3x">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>.</p><p>If both <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="meknm0yw52">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mebdj41l6p">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, then causality is bi-directional.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.3 Unit root test</title>
              
              <p>ADF for Augmented <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Dickey &amp;amp; Fuller (1979)</xref>, tests the possibility that a unit root might be present in an autoregressive (AR) time series when it’s not the case we are talking about stationarity or trend-stationarity. It was developed in order to tackle the problem of autocorrelation, which usually arises in time series during empirical analysis. ADF underlies three mathematical versions, implying the existence of the constant and the trend among time series; one version at least must be satisfied fulfilled to judge the realization of stationarity:</p><p>∆Y<sub>t</sub>= λ<sub>1</sub>+ZY<sub>t-1 </sub>+ θ<sub>i</sub>+ μ<sub>t </sub>(constant only)</p><p>∆Y<sub>t</sub>= λ<sub>1 </sub>+ λ<sub>2</sub>t + Z Y<sub>t-1 </sub>+ θ<sub>i</sub>+ μ<sub>t </sub>(trend and constant)</p><p>∆Y<sub>t</sub>= Z Y<sub>t-1 </sub>+ θ<sub>i</sub>+ μ<sub>t </sub>(without trend and constant)</p><p>A couple of hypotheses are to be tested through the test: H<sub>0</sub>: the variable has unit root / H<sub>a</sub>: it doesn’t.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.4 Stability check</title>
              
              <p>Stability is checked by undertaking the inverse roots of autoregressive process (AR(p)) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_52">Lütkepohl, 1991</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.5 Lag order selection</title>
              
              <p>Choosing the appropriate lag order length is primordial in VAR models because it enables to reduce the number of unnecessary lags besides the insignificant coefficients, prevent loosing extra degrees of freedom and avoid the multi-collinearity between series. </p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.6 Var/vecm approach</title>
              
              <p>This study adopts the VAR/VECM approach, in line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Chamalwa &amp;amp; Bakari (2016)</xref> for Nigeria, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">Georgantopoulos &amp;amp; Tsamis (2011)</xref> for Hungary, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_55">Musa &amp;amp; Joseph (2014)</xref> for Uganda, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Azeroual (2016)</xref> for Morocco, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_72">Toudas et al. (2017)</xref> for Greece based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">Engle &amp;amp; Granger (1987)</xref> as well as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">Granger (1986)</xref> method.</p><p>A VAR (p) model, there can include three terms: a constant (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mvzsh6k32i">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>), a trend (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="me0xo9aez3">
    <mml:mi>Φ</mml:mi>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>), both, or any of. Its specification can be expressed as:</p><p style="text-align: center"><italic><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m9yq8ip78d">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>Φ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0">
      <mml:mspace width="1em"/>
    </mml:mstyle>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> </italic>from 1 to T</p><p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="moue52qzrn">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the representative vector of n stochastic variables, with p as the lag length taken on each variable, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m5miilett5">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the variables respective coefficients across periods, while <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mmbtxsdwhg">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> represents the disturbance term.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.7 Johansen co-integration</title>
              
              <p>A VAR can be transferred to VECM using the difference operator (Δ) thanks to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">Johansen &amp;amp; Juselius (1990)</xref> co-integration method, under the condition of the entire data integration in the first order before proceeding to test, the VECM specification is:</p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mlafaxjeng">
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>Π</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> t= from 1 to T</p><p>It can also be expressed as:</p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="ms4py2nu6f">
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>Π</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>Φ</mml:mi>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:munderover>
      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:munderover>
    <mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0">
      <mml:mspace width="1em"/>
    </mml:mstyle>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mtext> </mml:mtext>
      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p>where,</p><p><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mlgponiozn">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>: vector representing the deterministic variables.</p><p><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m5a8dykvnq">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>Π</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:munderover>
      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    </mml:munderover>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, where I is the 1<sup>st</sup> order of integration.</p><p><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mk4okj0g03">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:munderover>
      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    </mml:munderover>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, is the long run matrix impact.</p><p>Where the number of cointegrating variables is directly proportional to the number of stationary relationships in the П-matrix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Chamalwa &amp;amp; Bakari, 2016</xref>). If there is no co-integration, all the rows in П will be zero, while some will be non-zero if there is a stationary combination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Chamalwa &amp;amp; Bakari, 2016</xref>). The rank of the matrix П determines the number of the independent variables as well as the number of the cointegrating variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Chamalwa &amp;amp; Bakari, 2016</xref>). The rank is given by significant eigenvalues found in П, where each stands for a significant stationary relation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Chamalwa &amp;amp; Bakari, 2016</xref>). Hence, if the matrix has a reduced rank, there is a cointegrating relationship among the variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Chamalwa &amp;amp; Bakari, 2016</xref>). Therefore, rank (П) = 0. It means the absence of stationarity among the variables; as such, it is advisable to difference it first before modelling.</p><p>If rank (П) = p then П has full rank, therefore all the variables must be cointegrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Chamalwa &amp;amp; Bakari, 2016</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.8 Likelihood ratio (lr) statistics</title>
              
              <p>The co-integration conducts to two likelihood ratio test statistics: Trace statistics and Max-Eigen statistic proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">Johansen (1988)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">Johansen (1991)</xref> in line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">Granger (1981)</xref>.</p><p>Trace statistic is expressed as:</p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mrc9otdmy6">
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>Ln</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:munderover>
      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
    </mml:munderover>
    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p>where, $T<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myjc5rlf7z">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>\lambda_{\mathrm{i}}$ is the ith largest canonical correlation. Two hypotheses are being confronted in Trace test, H<sub>0</sub> of r cointegrating vectors vs H<sub>a</sub> of n cointegrating vectors.</p><p>Max-Eigen statistic is expressed as:</p><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">8<sub><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">max</sub><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif"> = T Ln(1-8<sub><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">r+1</sub><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">)</p><p>where,  8<sub>r+1</sub>, ...., 8<sub>N </sub>are the N-r lowest canonical correlations raised to square between X<sub>t-k</sub> and X<sub>t</sub> series, corrected for the effect of the lagged differences of the X<sub>t</sub>. Two hypotheses are being confronted in Max-eigen test, H<sub>0</sub> of r cointegrating vectors vs H<sub>a</sub> of at least (r+1) cointegrating vectors.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.9 Normalization of the cointegrating vectors</title>
              
              <p>The VAR cointegrating vectors require normalization for plausible economic interpretations, the normalization to unity generates long-run fashion compatible with economic interest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_65">Rossana, 2004</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.10 Error correction model (ecm)</title>
              
              <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">ECM is a VECM mechanism by which deviations over the long-run equilibrium are corrected over time, from a period to the following one; in other words, it measures the adjustment speed toward the long-term equilibrium. The basic form of ECM that can exist between two variables under an OLS approach is:</p><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mfh95fa5og">
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:munderover>
      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:munderover>
    <mml:munderover>
      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:munderover>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">ECT</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p>where, ECT indicates the speed at which disequilibrium between variables is corrected back towards the long-run equilibrium after a shock.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.11 Variance decomposition</title>
              
              <p>Variance decomposition is a partition tool of the total variance in an outcome variable into components of interest based on each component’s performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_83">Zaefarian et al., 2022</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.12 Impulse response function (irf)</title>
              
              <p>IRF in a VAR model, track down the response over time on a standard deviation (shock or innovation) to one or many variables of the model's variables.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.13 Residuals stability</title>
              
              <p>Residual normality in a VAR model is checked via Cholesky orthogonalization of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_52">Lütkepohl (1991)</xref>, serial correlation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">Godfrey, 1978</xref>), Heteroscedasticity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Breusch &amp;amp; Pagan, 1979</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>4. Results</title>
      <p>The different test results are detailed, below following the sequence illustrated in scheme 1, and the hierarchy of methods presented in subsection 2.3 above. </p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> below summarizes a common statistic description of the model variables:</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_3">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Descriptive statistics</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><p>LNEF</p></td><td><p>LNEG</p></td><td><p>LNDG</p></td><td><p>LNHE</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Mean</p></td><td><p>0.349936</p></td><td><p>7.665149</p></td><td><p>17.16267</p></td><td><p>12.78485</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Median</p></td><td><p>0.385262</p></td><td><p>7.635713</p></td><td><p>17.18039</p></td><td><p>12.64993</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Max</p></td><td><p>0.593327</p></td><td><p>8.118390</p></td><td><p>17.43873</p></td><td><p>14.11684</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Min</p></td><td><p>0.009950</p></td><td><p>7.145083</p></td><td><p>16.79503</p></td><td><p>11.37660</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Std. Dev.</p></td><td><p>0.163452</p></td><td><p>0.310901</p></td><td><p>0.184344</p></td><td><p>0.710913</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Skewness</p></td><td><p>-0.363321</p></td><td><p>-0.011988</p></td><td><p>-0.291771</p></td><td><p>0.218039</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Kurtosis</p></td><td><p>2.047929</p></td><td><p>1.657456</p></td><td><p>2.011907</p></td><td><p>2.370205</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Jarque-Bera</p></td><td><p>2.570053</p></td><td><p>3.230375</p></td><td><p>2.359355</p></td><td><p>1.051361</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>p-value</p></td><td><p>0.276643</p></td><td><p>0.198853</p></td><td><p>0.307378</p></td><td><p>0.591153</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Sum</p></td><td><p>15.04725</p></td><td><p>329.6014</p></td><td><p>737.9949</p></td><td><p>549.7483</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Sum Sq. Dev.</p></td><td><p>1.122096</p></td><td><p>4.059694</p></td><td><p>1.427271</p></td><td><p>21.22670</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Observational units</p></td><td><p>43</p></td><td><p>43</p></td><td><p>43</p></td><td><p>43</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Results from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> show that the dispersion indicators are generally too close to each other, while Skewness negative values are supposing that (LnEF, LnEG, LnDG) tails are moderately displaced on the left oppositely to LnHE, which seems to be inclined to the right; subsequently, their respective distributions can be described as almost symmetrical. Concerning kurtosis, all variables’ plots seem to be platykurtic, having like a flat tail distribution. Finally, Jarque-Bera statistics are supposing that data has normal distribution.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref> below is illustrating the pair wise correlation matrix:</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_4">
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Pair-wise correlations matrice</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><p>LNEF</p></td><td><p>LNEG</p></td><td><p>LNDG</p></td><td><p>LNHE</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNEF</p></td><td><p>1.000000</p></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNEG</p></td><td><p>0.924114</p></td><td><p>1.000000</p></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNDG</p></td><td><p>0.903823</p></td><td><p>0.984526</p></td><td><p>1.000000</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNHE</p></td><td><p>0.853813</p></td><td><p>0.957561</p></td><td><p>0.964229</p></td><td><p>1.000000</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Results from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref> show a vigorous positive correlation between variables in all the possible bi-directions, which is witnessing the solidity of the STIRPAT theoretical framework and the pertinence of the chosen variables for VAR modeling.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref> illustrates principal analysis components through principal component matrix:</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_5">
          <label>Table 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Principal component matrix</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Number</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Value</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Difference</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Proportion</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cumulative Value</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cumulative Proportion</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.795490</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.638686</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9489</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.795490</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9489</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.156804</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.123066</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0392</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.952295</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9881</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.033738</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.019771</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0084</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.986033</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9965</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.013967</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>---</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0035</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.000000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Results from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref> show that the EF 1<sup>st</sup> direction explains widely 95% of the information detained by the component matrix, while the EG 2<sup>nd</sup> one explains 4%, while the portions of the 3<sup>rd</sup> and the 4<sup>th</sup> directions, which correspond to DG and HE, respectively, are quite neglected. Moreover, the gap between the first direction and the following ones is enormous (more than 90%), which is supposing the autoregressive aspect of the model.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref> below summarizes the ADF stationarity test applied on the four variables under the three main mentioned versions (with constant [WC], with constant and trend [WCT], nor constant or trend [NCT]) at levels and at the 1<sup>st</sup> difference.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_6">
          <label>Table 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>ADF unit root test</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>At Level</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LNEF</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LNEG</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LNDG</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LNHE</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>WC</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>t-Statistic</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-2.1494</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.1383</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.8715</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.6677</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>Prob.</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.2274</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.6914</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.3419</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.8438</italic></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>WCT</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.4330</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.0677</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.8902</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.5858</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.8351</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.9223</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.6409</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.7818</italic></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NCT</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.6916</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.1913</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.9411</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.6779</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.8607</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>1.0000</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.9988</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>1.0000</italic></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>At 1<sup>st</sup> Difference</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>d(LNEF)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>d(LNEG)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>d(LNDG)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>d(LNHE)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>WC</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.6149</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-12.6033</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.2236</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-5.6053</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0100</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0000</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0263</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0000</italic></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>**</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>**</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>WCT</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-4.1573</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-12.6279</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.8775</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-5.5183</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0117</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0000</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0229</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0003</italic></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>**</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>**</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NCT</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.9509</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.3764</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.6446</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.9759</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0499</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.1540</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0938</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>0.0002</italic></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>**</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>n0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>*</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Results from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref> show that all variables become stationary after a first differentiation, this proves that the empirical evidence must be exclusively done with the VAR/VECM approach. </p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> below illustrates the AR(p) graphical representation. </p>
      
        <fig id="fig_3">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Inverse roots of AR characteristic polynomial</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/11/img_xcVxM91H9cktElbr.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> shows that all points are dispersedly lying within the unit circle in the complex plan. This implies that the VAR model satisfies the stability condition, that data exhibit a stationary tendency in the long run. </p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_7">Table 7</xref> below summarizes the optimal lag selection estimations following five tests: </p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_7">
          <label>Table 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Lag length order selection</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lag</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LogL</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LR</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>FPE</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AIC</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SC</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>HQ</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>147.4221</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NA</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9.03e-09</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-7.171104</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-7.002216</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-7.110040</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>413.2930</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>465.2741</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.41e-14</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-19.66465</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-18.82021</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-19.35933</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>479.5775</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>102.7411</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.83e-15</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-22.17888</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-20.65889</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-21.62930</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>509.2397</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40.04395*</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.53e-15*</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-22.86199*</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-20.66644*</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-22.06815*</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><p>* lag order selected by the criterion</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_7">Table 7</xref>, on the basis of the rule of thumb (the lowest calculated value), the optimal lag by the unanimity of the five criterions is 3, at which the VAR model is to be set. </p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_8">Table 8</xref> below summarizes the Pairwise Granger causality test:</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_8">
          <label>Table 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Granger causality test</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td><p>H<sub>0</sub>: Variable x Does not Granger Cause Toward Variable y</p></td><td><p>F-Statistic</p></td><td><p>Prob.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNEG toward LNEF</p></td><td><p>17.9470</p></td><td><p>0.0001</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNEF toward LNEG</p></td><td><p>3.76845</p></td><td><p>0.0595</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNDG toward LNEF</p></td><td><p>23.9704</p></td><td><p>2.E-05</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNEF toward LNDG</p></td><td><p>0.18814</p></td><td><p>0.6669</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNHE toward LNEF</p></td><td><p>9.30883</p></td><td><p>0.0041</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNEF toward LNHE</p></td><td><p>0.53426</p></td><td><p>0.4692</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNDG toward LNEG</p></td><td><p>8.29287</p></td><td><p>0.0064</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNEG toward LNDG</p></td><td><p>43.1061</p></td><td><p>9.E-08</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNHE toward LNEG</p></td><td><p>0.45520</p></td><td><p>0.5039</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNEG toward LNHE</p></td><td><p>4.31605</p></td><td><p>0.0444</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNHE toward LNDG</p></td><td><p>1.91578</p></td><td><p>0.1742</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNDG toward LNHE</p></td><td><p>0.09433</p></td><td><p>0.7604</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Results from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_8">Table 8</xref> reveal the existence of two bidirectional causalities running: one between EG and EF and between EG and DG. They also show a unidirectional causality running from DG to ecological footprint, HE to ecological footprint, and EG to HE.</p><p>Usually in the co-integration test, the maximum lag length for the VAR model for annual data in Eviews10 is set to 1, with the null hypothesis of the absence of any co-integration.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_9">Table 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_10">Table 10</xref> below represent the respective results of the two following tests:</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_9">
          <label>Table 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Trace test</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Number of </p></td><td></td><td><p>Trace</p></td><td><p>0.05</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><p>Co-integrations </p></td><td><p>Eigenvalue</p></td><td><p>Statistic</p></td><td><p>Critical Value</p></td><td><p>Prob.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>None *</p></td><td><p>0.489435</p></td><td><p>52.28184</p></td><td><p>47.85613</p></td><td><p>0.0181</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>At most 1</p></td><td><p>0.263244</p></td><td><p>24.72009</p></td><td><p>29.79707</p></td><td><p>0.1717</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>At most 2</p></td><td><p>0.179804</p></td><td><p>12.19467</p></td><td><p>15.49471</p></td><td><p>0.1478</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>At most 3 *</p></td><td><p>0.094455</p></td><td><p>4.067972</p></td><td><p>3.841466</p></td><td><p>0.0437</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><p>* H<sub>0</sub> rejection at 5%</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_10">
          <label>Table 10</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Maximum eigenvalue test</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Number of </p></td><td></td><td><p>Max-Eigen</p></td><td><p>0.05</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><p>Co-integrations </p></td><td><p>Eigenvalue</p></td><td><p>Statistic</p></td><td><p>Critical Value</p></td><td><p>Prob.**</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>None</p></td><td><p>0.489435</p></td><td><p>27.56175</p></td><td><p>27.58434</p></td><td><p>0.0503</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>At most 1</p></td><td><p>0.263244</p></td><td><p>12.52542</p></td><td><p>21.13162</p></td><td><p>0.4967</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>At most 2</p></td><td><p>0.179804</p></td><td><p>8.126700</p></td><td><p>14.26460</p></td><td><p>0.3660</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>At most 3 *</p></td><td><p>0.094455</p></td><td><p>4.067972</p></td><td><p>3.841466</p></td><td><p>0.0437</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><p> * H<sub>0</sub> rejection at 5%</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>The co-integration trace results from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_9">Table 9</xref> show the existence of at most one co-integration equation at 5%, while those from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_10">Table 10</xref>, which correspond to the Max-Eigenvalue test, indicate that no co-integration equation can exist between the variables. However, when Trace statistics and Max-Eigen statistics produce little contradictions, more importance must be given to Trace statistics as it takes into consideration all of the lowest eigenvalues; subsequently, it has more treatment power than the Max-Eigen statistics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">Kasa, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_68">Serletis &amp;amp; King, 1997</xref>). Moreover, it is recommended to privilege the trace statistics when the two statistics provide uneven results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">Johansen &amp;amp; Juselius, 1990</xref>). Thus, it exists at most a unique co-integration equation at 5% in a linear fashion.</p><p>The normalization of the revealed co-integration equation, which describes the main long-run dynamics between the explanatory variables and the dependent one, is represented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_11">Table 11</xref> below:</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_11">
          <label>Table 11</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The normalized cointegrating coefficients</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td><p>LnEF</p></td><td><p>LnEG</p></td><td><p>LnDG</p></td><td><p>LnHE</p></td></tr><tr><td><p> 1.000000<sup>*</sup></p></td><td><p>-1.191282<sup>*</sup></p></td><td><p>-0.137644<sup>*</sup></p></td><td><p> 0.505900<sup>*</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p> (0.51378)</p></td><td><p> (1.15828)</p></td><td><p> (0.09269)</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_12">
          <label>Table 12</label>
          <caption>
            <title>VECM parameters estimations</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Variables </p></td><td><p>Co-integrated Equation Values</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNEF (-1)</p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNEG (-1)</p></td><td><p>-1.191282</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>0.51378</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>[-2.31864]</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNDG (-1)</p></td><td><p>-0.137644</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>(1.15828)</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>[-0.11883]</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>LNHE (-1)</p></td><td><p>0.505900</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>(0.09269)</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>[5.45818]</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>C</p></td><td><p>4.672998</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Error Correction</p></td><td><p>D(LNEF)</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>CointEq1</p></td><td><p>-0.348196</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>(0.10978)</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>[-3.17177]</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>The inversed <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_11">Table 11</xref> results of the normalized cointegrating coefficients (inversed in order to have proper interpretations as the long run part of the VECM is not normalized by Eviews10) are 1.191282, 0.137644 and -0.505900 as long run coefficients for EG, DG and HE to ecological footprint, respectively, meaning that whenever economic and DG increase in the correspondent proportions, EF goes with simultaneously, otherwise, whenever higher-education upsurges in the correspondent proportion, EF decreases, suggesting the movement of these variables conjointly to generate a one unit of ecological footprint. As co-integration is proven, an ECM is required.</p><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_12">Table 12</xref>, the ECT from VECM estimates is significantly expressed as:</p><p style="text-align: center">ECT= LnEF(-1) +1.191282LnEG(-1) + 0.137644LnDG(-1) - 0.505900 LnHE(-1) - 4.672998.</p><p>This specification reflects the long run adjustment from a previous period deviation to the following, with an estimated speed of 34.81% as suggests the negative and statistically significant CointEq1 coefficient; in other words, 34.81% of the previous error is adjusted in the next, and so on, thus, the convergence from short dynamics toward long-run equilibrium is unequivocally confirmed by the VECM (1) test.</p><p>Each coefficient of the co-integration equation is checked in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_13">Table 13</xref>:</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_13">
          <label>Table 13</label>
          <caption>
            <title>VCEM co-integration model coefficients summary</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Coint-Coefficient</p></td><td><p>Value</p></td><td><p>Std. Error</p></td><td><p>T-Statistic</p></td><td><p>Prob.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>(1)</p></td><td><p>-0.348196</p></td><td><p>0.109780</p></td><td><p>-3.171768</p></td><td><p>0.0031</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>(2)</p></td><td><p>-0.250562</p></td><td><p>0.158110</p></td><td><p>-1.584736</p></td><td><p>0.1220</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>(3)</p></td><td><p>-0.960668</p></td><td><p>0.355361</p></td><td><p>-2.703360</p></td><td><p>0.0105</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>(4)</p></td><td><p>-5.367274</p></td><td><p>3.311009</p></td><td><p>-1.621039</p></td><td><p>0.1140</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>(5)</p></td><td><p>0.205504</p></td><td><p>0.145236</p></td><td><p>1.414963</p></td><td><p>0.1659</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>(6)</p></td><td><p>0.103466</p></td><td><p>0.051423</p></td><td><p>2.012053</p></td><td><p>0.0520</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Results from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_13">Table 13</xref> show that C1 is negative and significant at 5%, which is definitively confirming the longevity of the VECM co-integration model and its adequacy for economic interpretation.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_14">Table 14</xref> presents the VAR variance decomposition for ten successive periods. </p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_14">Table 14</xref> results show that the historical trend of EF explains a large part of its own variations, which tend to decrease period over period. Thus, within 10 periods, about 75% of the variance in EF is explained by itself, which is indicative of its exogenous nature. This suggests that we should consider 10 periods for the IRF. </p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_14">
          <label>Table 14</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Variance decomposition</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Period</p></td><td><p>S.E.</p></td><td><p>LNEF</p></td><td><p>LNEG</p></td><td><p>LNDG</p></td><td><p>LNHE</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>1</p></td><td><p>0.063081</p></td><td><p>100.0000</p></td><td><p>0.000000</p></td><td><p>0.000000</p></td><td><p>0.000000</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>2</p></td><td><p>0.064599</p></td><td><p>95.39088</p></td><td><p>2.144422</p></td><td><p>1.221182</p></td><td><p>1.243514</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>0.073026</p></td><td><p>86.91455</p></td><td><p>7.959742</p></td><td><p>1.325283</p></td><td><p>3.800421</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>0.075953</p></td><td><p>85.87297</p></td><td><p>7.667727</p></td><td><p>1.555385</p></td><td><p>4.903919</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>0.077857</p></td><td><p>81.91722</p></td><td><p>11.51414</p></td><td><p>1.879545</p></td><td><p>4.689101</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>6</p></td><td><p>0.079447</p></td><td><p>79.55589</p></td><td><p>12.39112</p></td><td><p>1.928336</p></td><td><p>6.124650</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>7</p></td><td><p>0.080166</p></td><td><p>78.73599</p></td><td><p>12.59060</p></td><td><p>1.898786</p></td><td><p>6.774625</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>8</p></td><td><p>0.081058</p></td><td><p>77.61359</p></td><td><p>12.47848</p></td><td><p>1.916751</p></td><td><p>7.991173</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>9</p></td><td><p>0.082116</p></td><td><p>76.44101</p></td><td><p>12.20092</p></td><td><p>2.089680</p></td><td><p>9.268398</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>10</p></td><td><p>0.083276</p></td><td><p>75.50059</p></td><td><p>11.99747</p></td><td><p>2.349423</p></td><td><p>10.15251</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> establishes the graphic representation of the respective responses to one S.D. (shock or innovation) of EG (represented by LnEG), DG (LnDG), and HE (LnHE) to EF (LnEF) combined in one presentation.</p><p>Results from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> show that a one S.D. (shock or innovation) gradually declines the response of EG from periods 1 to 2, then it rises progressively until the 4<sup>th</sup> period; this oscillation is regenerated one again until the end of the 6<sup>th</sup> period; meanwhile, it remains negative from the 4<sup>th</sup> period until the 10th. That one S.D. (shock or innovation) initially decreases softly DG until the 4<sup>th</sup> period, and then a stagnation of the response is noticeable for the rest of the interval, remaining negative all along. That one S.D. (shock or innovation) initially increases the response of HE until the 3<sup>rd</sup> period; this positive response gently declines until the 5<sup>th</sup> then remains stable, all the way above the horizontal axis. It is concluded that shocks to the EF will have a negative impact on EG, a positive impact on HE, and a negative impact on DG in the short as well as in the long run.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_4">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Impulsive response function graphic representation</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/11/img_nB8f8y-aKRxcofHJ.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>VAR residuals normality, serial correlation, and heteroscedasticity, respectively, are presented in the following <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_15">Table 15</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_16">Table 16</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_17">Table 17</xref>, respectively.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_15">
          <label>Table 15</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Cholesky orthogonalization of Lutkepohl test</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="5"><p>H<sub>0</sub>: Residuals are Normal</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>Chi-sq</p></td><td><p>Df</p></td><td><p>p-value</p></td><td><p>Interpretation</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Skewness</p></td><td><p>0.192706</p></td><td><p>1</p></td><td><p>0.6188</p></td><td rowspan="3"><p>No rejection of H<sub>0</sub></p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Kurtosis</p></td><td><p>2.903381</p></td><td><p>1</p></td><td><p>0.9007</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Jarque-Bera</p></td><td><p>0.263129</p></td><td><p>2</p></td><td><p>0.8767</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_16">
          <label>Table 16</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Serial correlation test</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="4"><p>H<sub>0</sub>: No Serial Correlation</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Lags</p></td><td><p>LM-Stat</p></td><td><p>Prob</p></td><td><p>Interpretation</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>1</p></td><td><p>24.95343</p></td><td><p>0.0707</p></td><td rowspan="3"><p>No rejection of H<sub>0</sub></p></td></tr><tr><td><p>2</p></td><td><p>26.02040</p></td><td><p>0.0537</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>16.36447</p></td><td><p>0.4278</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_17">
          <label>Table 17</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Heteroscedasticity test</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="3"><p>H<sub>0</sub>: Residuals are Heteroscedastic</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Chi-sq</p></td><td><p>Df</p></td><td><p>Prob.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>231.4145</p></td><td><p>230</p></td><td><p>0.4614</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><p>Interpretation: Fail to reject H<sub>0</sub></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Results from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_15">Table 15</xref> are suggesting that residuals are normally distributed; those from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_16">Table 16</xref> show the absence of serial correlation among residuals, which are supposed to be homoscedastic with no cross terms (absence of white noise), as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_17">Table 17</xref>. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Discussions</title>
      <p>This paper's findings and dynamics seem to be quite logic and credible because intuitively, a growing economic activity hangs together with more and more consumption, and subsequently, overexploitation of natural resources, idem for DG, which is supposing the increase of population needs in parallel with natural resource attrition, while acquiring HE and professional qualifications by individuals is correlated with good awareness of the dangers of environmental degradation, and consequently, the adoption of ecological behavior and pro-nature gesture as a life style at both dimensions, individually and collectively. Compared to similar studies—for example and not limited to—these results prove once again that EG coupled with energy consumption and urbanization have long-run impacts on EFs in Morocco itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Farouki &amp;amp; Aissaoui, 2024</xref>), in Turkey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">Nathaniel et al., 2020</xref>), in Pakistan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_74">Ullah &amp;amp; Lin, 2024</xref>), and in ECOWAS, a group of African countries neighboring Morocco (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Ali et al., 2022</xref>). These findings converge with those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Asli et al. (2024)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Bergougui &amp;amp; Aldawsari (2024)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Dinç &amp;amp; Akdoğan (2019)</xref> in terms of HC role in diminishing both CO<sub>2</sub> and EF in Morocco and Algeria, respectively, and from a panel of ECOWAS countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Ali et al., 2022</xref>). Furthermore, these results are supporting recent research outputs in the Indian context proving that HC acquired mainly through HE not only reduces EFs but also acts as a driving force behind environmental policies where HC was found to cause reductions in EFs without feedback effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Ahmed &amp;amp; Wang, 2019</xref>). In the same context but in the opposite direction, while economic and DG pose environmental challenges, some recent studies proved that they present also opportunities for positive impacts through sustainable practices as tested in China by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">Li et al. (2023)</xref>. In addition, a recent study highlights a connection in which EG, HC, BC, and urban growth all have a beneficial impact on the EF in five South Asian countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">Mehmood et al., 2023</xref>). Hence, encouraging sustainable consumption habits can significantly mitigate the effects of EG and subsequently reduce ecological footprints, for example, by promoting renewable energies, reducing waste, and enhancing recycling efforts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_61">Population Media Center, 2023</xref>). In the same line, while many studies support the positive impact of HC on reducing ecological footprints, some research suggests that in certain contexts—particularly in low-income countries—high HC might lead to increased consumption patterns that could elevate EFs due to greater access to resources and technologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Chen et al., 2021</xref>). Furthermore, it was proved that coupling HC promotion with EG serves to augment the adoption of sustainable practices, which enhances BC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">Mehmood et al., 2023</xref>). However, future prospects are still to be discovered, such as the fluctuations of other factors, including, but not limited to, urbanization, energy intensity, age distribution, the working force, the structure of the economy, clean energies, etc., on the EF in particular and environmental sustainability in general, as for Morocco as for other countries. However, this study, as any other study, manifests some limitations, mainly on three levels:</p><p>Econometrically, as the VAR/VECM model excels in capturing multivariate dynamic interactions, revealing short- and long-term behaviors, providing efficient coefficient estimates, and handling perfectly complex analyses, especially in co-integrated time series, it is exclusively suitable for first integrated series I(1) analysis, with controversial divergences on the appropriate lag length order selection. In fact, the more explanatory variables there are, the more numerous coefficients induced, and the more degrees of freedom there are, which makes it relatively complicated to handle, interpret, and fill all the validity conditions.</p><p>Epistemologically, as this study doesn’t background the findings to predict future fluctuations of the studied variables, it is also restricted to classical STRPAT determinants already well-documented in existing literature in other contexts, in time when other variables such as energy consumption, institutional governance, clean energies, smart environmental gestures, etc. are getting more and more involved in other recent studies.</p><p>Limited scope, as this study focuses exclusively on Morocco, which limits its broader applicability and appeal. The findings may not resonate with a wider international audience, reducing the manuscript’s overall impact.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Conclusion</title>
      <p>This research purpose was to examine the way that humans are affecting the vital biosphere in Morocco through the fluctuations of, EG and DG besides the promotion of HC on EF in the last fourth decades, the basic result deduced from empirical evidence is that a solid long run relationship is established between those variables over time, results show that EG is immensely amplifying the environmental stress on the vital ecosystem of Morocco by more than one entire unit of EF output, followed by DG with above a tenth unit, while ensuring HE level to population is diminishing it by a half unit approximatively. In line with these results, H<sub>0a</sub> and H<sub>0b</sub> hypotheses, according to which EG and DG are negatively impacting EFs in Morocco, are confirmed, while the H<sub>0c</sub> hypothesis, according to which HE is negatively impacting EFs in Morocco, is refuted in favor of the positive impact. Results from the Impulsive Response Function (IRF) are confirming this logic sequence; accordingly, the more the economic activity prospers and the population size gets larger, the more stress there is on environmental resources, while the more people get educated and acculturated, the more their EF gets reduced and limited.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>7. Policy implications</title>
      <p>In order to undermine the noxious effect of EG and DG and promote HC accumulation, in line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_84">Zafar et al. (2019)</xref>, it is of the Moroccan government duty to address various policies across these domains, in line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">Khan et al. (2024)</xref>, such as enhancing public awareness through education programs touching upon the benefits of energy conservation and the reduction of energy consumption by inculcating an eco-friendly behavior chart among citizens. Valorising HC and increasing it through public spending on the education sector, public as private (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">El Asli &amp;amp; Azeroual, 2023a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">El Asli &amp;amp; Azeroual, 2023b</xref>). Controlling the demographic expansion by providing access to family planning services and providing affordable programs for new couples in order to help manage population growth, besides empowering women with gender approaches and healthcare options, which often lead to smaller, healthier families. Following a sustainable urbanization program by promoting urban planning that emphasizes high-density, innovative practices in sustainable urban planning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_80">Xu, 2024</xref>), mixed-use development, this reduces land use, conserves resources, and decreases the need for extensive infrastructure. Integrate parks, green roofs and corridors into urban areas to rise biodiversity, and to improve air quality, and manage stormwater, developing affordable housing that is also energy-efficient, reducing both the EF and the cost burden on low-income families. Adopting economic incentives and policies such as carbon pricing through the implementation of carbon taxes or cap-and-trade systems to make CO<sub>2</sub> more costly and encourage businesses and consumers to reduce their carbon footprint, by fostering renewable energy installations, electric vehicles etc.; regulation of high-impact sectors for industries with high ecological impacts, such as mining, agriculture, and manufacturing. Watch over the quality of institutions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Awad et al., 2024</xref>) by enhancing ruling governance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Ali et al., 2022</xref>). Accelerate energy transition through industrial decarbonizing and fixing an ultimatum for total carbon neutralization objective, continuing to invest in renewables, keeping reliance on fossil fuels, and incentives for technological innovation related to renewable energy consumption to “encourage structure energy adjustment and reduce carbon footprint” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_70">Su et al., 2022</xref>). Act on the determinants of EG in Morocco in order to align it on a green growth model (El <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Asli et al., 2024</xref>). And finally, incite eco-friendly products by promoting the production and consumption of products that have lower environmental impacts through fiscal incitements such as those made from recycled materials, produced locally, or with reduced packaging. The eco-friendly production processes that minimize waste, energy use, and emissions suppose adopting cleaner technologies and sustainable supply chains. The success of Morocco's efforts relies on the continued implementation of these sustainable policies and practices, along with public awareness and international cooperation, especially aligning local growth with sustainable development goals (SDGs), especially SDG 9 for environmental sustainability policies.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abbas</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghosh</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sucharita</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dogan</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Değer</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mariev</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10668-023-04154-4</pub-id>
          <article-title>Going green: Understanding the impacts of Economic complexity, clean energy and natural resources on EF in complex economies</article-title>
          <source>Environ. Dev. Sustain.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>180</volume>
          <page-range>1439-1450</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abbasi</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adedoyin</surname>
              <given-names>F. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abbas</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hussain</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.renene.2021.08.078</pub-id>
          <article-title>The impact of energy depletion and renewable energy on CO2 emissions in Thailand: Fresh evidence from the novel dynamic ARDL simulation</article-title>
          <source>Renew. Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>133-155</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adhikary</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajra</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-16-4273-9_9</pub-id>
          <article-title>Environmental Kuznets curve: A revisit in the case of SAARC</article-title>
          <source>Urban Growth Environ. Issues India</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>26</volume>
          <page-range>26782-26796</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-019-05911-7</pub-id>
          <article-title>Investigating the impact of HC on the EF in India: An empirical analysis</article-title>
          <source>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>79</volume>
          <page-range>103115</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jianguo</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kirikkaleli</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resourpol.2022.103115</pub-id>
          <article-title>Modeling the natural resources and financial inclusion on ecological footprint: The role of economic governance institutions. Evidence from ECOWAS economies</article-title>
          <source>Resour. Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>113</volume>
          <page-range>106187</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Altıntaş</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kassouri</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2020.106187</pub-id>
          <article-title>Is the environmental Kuznets Curve in Europe related to the per-capita EF or CO2 emissions?</article-title>
          <source>Ecol. Indic.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>31</volume>
          <page-range>32-53</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ansari</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haider</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>N.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/MEQ-12-2018-0205</pub-id>
          <article-title>Does trade openness affects global carbon dioxide emissions: Evidence from the top CO2 emitters</article-title>
          <source>Manag. Environ. Qual.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>656-668</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Asli</surname>
              <given-names>H. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamid</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zineb</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohamed</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32479/ijeep.15601</pub-id>
          <article-title>Impact of, human capital, economic factors, energy consumption, and urban growth on environmental sustainability in Morocco: An ARDL approach</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Energy Econ. Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>369</volume>
          <page-range>122298</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Awad</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ebaidalla</surname>
              <given-names>E. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasin</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozturk</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122298</pub-id>
          <article-title>Navigating the impact of remittances on environmental quality in Africa: The crucial role of institutional quality</article-title>
          <source>J. Environ. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>41</volume>
          <page-range>191-213</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Azeroual</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Investissements directs étrangers au Maroc: Impact sur la productivité totale des facteurs selon le pays d’origine (1980-2012)</article-title>
          <source>Afr. Dev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>20</volume>
          <page-range>5118</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aziz</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarwar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph20065118</pub-id>
          <article-title>Empirical evidence of environmental technologies, renewable energy and tourism to minimize the environmental damages: Implication of advanced panel analysis</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>109</volume>
          <page-range>449-458</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bargaoui</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liouane</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nouri</surname>
              <given-names>F. Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sbspro.2013.12.489</pub-id>
          <article-title>Environmental impact determinants: An empirical analysis based on the STIRPAT model</article-title>
          <source>Procedia-Soc. Behav. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>657</volume>
          <page-range>1023-1029</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bekun</surname>
              <given-names>F. V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alola</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarkodie</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.12.104</pub-id>
          <article-title>Toward a sustainable environment: Nexus between CO2 emissions, resource rent, renewable and nonrenewable energy in 16-EU countries</article-title>
          <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>102</volume>
          <page-range>277-287</page-range>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bélaïd</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Youssef</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enpol.2016.12.012</pub-id>
          <article-title>Environmental degradation, renewable and non-renewable electricity consumption, and EG: Assessing the evidence from Algeria</article-title>
          <source>Energy Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>5153-5170</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Belloumi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alshehry</surname>
              <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su7055153</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sustainable energy development in Saudi Arabia</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>355</volume>
          <page-range>120426</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bergougui</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aldawsari</surname>
              <given-names>M. I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.120426</pub-id>
          <article-title>Asymmetric impact of patents on green technologies on Algeria’s ecological future</article-title>
          <source>J. Environ. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>77</volume>
          <page-range>636-654</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beyene</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kotosz</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00207233.2019.1695445</pub-id>
          <article-title>Testing the environmental Kuznets curve hypothesis: An empirical study for East African countries</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Environ. Stud.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>65</volume>
          <page-range>23-28</page-range>
          <year>2000</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bonett</surname>
              <given-names>D. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wright</surname>
              <given-names>T. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf02294183</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sample size requirements for estimating Pearson, Kendall and spearman correlations</article-title>
          <source>Psychometrika</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>47</volume>
          <page-range>1287-1294</page-range>
          <year>1979</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Breusch</surname>
              <given-names>T. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pagan</surname>
              <given-names>A. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1911963</pub-id>
          <article-title>A simple test for heteroscedasticity and random coefficient variation</article-title>
          <source>Econometrica</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chamalwa</surname>
              <given-names>H. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bakari</surname>
              <given-names>H. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12691/ajma-4-1-1</pub-id>
          <article-title>A Vector Autoregressive (VAR) Cointegration and Vector Error Correction Model (VECM) approach for financial deepening indicators and EG in Nigeria</article-title>
          <source>Am. J. Math. Anal.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>33</volume>
          <page-range>487-510</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0958305x211008610</pub-id>
          <article-title>Ecological footprint, HC, and urbanization</article-title>
          <source>Energy Environ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>54</volume>
          <page-range>101996</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Danish</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ulucak</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>S. U.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scs.2019.101996</pub-id>
          <article-title>Determinants of the ecological footprint: Role of renewable energy, natural resources, and urbanization</article-title>
          <source>Sustain. Cities Soc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>25</volume>
          <page-range>29387-29396</page-range>
          <issue>29</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Destek</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ulucak</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dogan</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-018-2911-4</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analyzing the environmental Kuznets curve for the EU countries: The role of ecological footprint</article-title>
          <source>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>74</volume>
          <page-range>427-431</page-range>
          <issue>366a</issue>
          <year>1979</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dickey</surname>
              <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fuller</surname>
              <given-names>W. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01621459.1979.10482531</pub-id>
          <article-title>Distribution of the estimators for autoregressive time series with a unit root</article-title>
          <source>J. Am. Stat. Assoc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>42</volume>
          <page-range>3</page-range>
          <issue>1-2</issue>
          <year>2002</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Diesendorf</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0921-8009(02)00085-x</pub-id>
          <article-title>I=PAT or I=PBAT?</article-title>
          <source>Ecol. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>277-300</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1994</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dietz</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosa</surname>
              <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rethinking the environmental impacts of population, affluence and technology</article-title>
          <source>Hum. Ecol. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>13-18</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2007</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dietz</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosa</surname>
              <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>York</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Driving the Human Ecological footprint</article-title>
          <source>Front. Ecol. Environ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>1273</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dinç</surname>
              <given-names>D. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akdoğan</surname>
              <given-names>E. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su11051273</pub-id>
          <article-title>Renewable energy production, energy consumption and sustainable economic growth in Turkey: A VECM approach</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>49</volume>
          <page-range>431-455</page-range>
          <year>2004</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dinda</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2004.02.011</pub-id>
          <article-title>Environmental Kuznets curve hypothesis: A survey</article-title>
          <source>Ecol. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>2099-2103</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Efthymiou</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ktoridou</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Epaminonda</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Michailidis</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/educon52537.2022.9766467</pub-id>
          <article-title>The relationship of strategy and technology in education: Bidirectional pedagogical considerations</article-title>
          <source>, http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/EDUCON52537.2022.9766467</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>171</volume>
          <page-range>1212-1217</page-range>
          <issue>3977</issue>
          <year>1971</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ehrlich</surname>
              <given-names>P. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holdren</surname>
              <given-names>J. P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Impact of population growth</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>44-74</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>El Asli</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azeroual</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Impact of social public expenditure on the formation of HC: The case of Morocco</article-title>
          <source>Rev. Fr. Econ. Gest.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>218-255</page-range>
          <issue>20</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>El Asli</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azeroual</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/ZENODO.8402869</pub-id>
          <article-title>Le secteur éducatif privé au Maroc: Déterminants d’investissement, rentabilité et résilience face aux crises</article-title>
          <source>Afr. Sci. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>225-255</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>El Asli</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azeroual</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mekkaoui</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jamil</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/eoik-2024-0040</pub-id>
          <article-title>How productivity, capital investment, employment, HC and energy are affecting EG in Morocco? An ARDL, FMOLS, DOLS and CCR approaches</article-title>
          <source>Econ.-Innov. Econ. Res. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>55</volume>
          <page-range>251-276</page-range>
          <year>1987</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Engle</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Granger</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1913236</pub-id>
          <article-title>Cointegration and error correction: Representation, estimation and testing</article-title>
          <source>Econometrica</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>236</volume>
          <page-range>67-74</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Farouki</surname>
              <given-names>E. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aissaoui</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procs.2024.05.005</pub-id>
          <article-title>Nexus between economy, renewable energy, population and ecological footprint: Empirical evidence using STIRPAT model in Morocco</article-title>
          <source>Procedia Comput. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>173</volume>
          <page-range>121-132</page-range>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Galli</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wackernagel</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iha</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazarus</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocon.2013.10.019</pub-id>
          <article-title>Ecological footprint: Implications for biodiversity</article-title>
          <source>Biol. Conserv.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>27</volume>
          <page-range>12-20</page-range>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Georgantopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>A. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsamis</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The causal links between FDI and economic development: Evidence from Greece</article-title>
          <source>Eur. J. Soc. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>227-236</page-range>
          <year>1978</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Godfrey</surname>
              <given-names>L. G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-4076(78)90031-3</pub-id>
          <article-title>Testing for multiplicative heteroscedasticity</article-title>
          <source>J. Econom.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>37</volume>
          <page-range>424-438</page-range>
          <year>1969</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Granger</surname>
              <given-names>C. W. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Investigating causal relations by econometric models and cross-spectral methods</article-title>
          <source>Econometrica</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>121-130</page-range>
          <year>1981</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Granger</surname>
              <given-names>C. W. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-4076(81)90079-8</pub-id>
          <article-title>Some properties of time series data and their use in econometric model specification</article-title>
          <source>J. Econom.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>48</volume>
          <page-range>213-228</page-range>
          <year>1986</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Granger</surname>
              <given-names>C. W. J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-0084.1986.mp48003002.x</pub-id>
          <article-title>Developments in the study of cointegrated economic variables</article-title>
          <source>Oxf. Bull. Econ. Stat.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>231-254</page-range>
          <issue>2-3</issue>
          <year>1988</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johansen</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1889(88)90041-3</pub-id>
          <article-title>Statistical analysis of cointegration vectors</article-title>
          <source>J. Econ. Dyn. Control</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>59</volume>
          <page-range>1551-1580</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>1991</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johansen</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2938278</pub-id>
          <article-title>Estimation and hypothesis testing of cointegration vectors in gaussian vector autoregressive models</article-title>
          <source>Econometrica</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>52</volume>
          <page-range>169-210</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1990</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johansen</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Juselius</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-0084.1990.mp52002003.x</pub-id>
          <article-title>Maximum likelihood estimation and inference on co-integration —with appucations to the demand for money</article-title>
          <source>Oxf. Bull. Econ. Stat.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>95-124</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>1992</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kasa</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-3932(92)90025-w</pub-id>
          <article-title>Common stochastic trends in international stock markets</article-title>
          <source>J. Monet. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <page-range>199-214</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>M. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmad</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>e Ali</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azhar</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.52131/joe.2024.0601.0202</pub-id>
          <article-title>Role of climate policies and environmental regulations for business growth: Evidence from sustainable development perspective</article-title>
          <source>iRASD J. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>45</volume>
          <page-range>1-28</page-range>
          <year>1955</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kuznets</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>EG and income inequality</article-title>
          <source>Am. Econ. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>154</volume>
          <page-range>110881</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shi</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2023.110881</pub-id>
          <article-title>The impact of high-quality development on ecological footprint: An empirical research based on STIRPAT model</article-title>
          <source>Ecol. Indic.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>24</volume>
          <page-range>749-770</page-range>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liddle</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4054/demres.2011.24.30</pub-id>
          <article-title>Consumption-driven environmental impact and age structure change in OECD countries: A co-integration -STIRPAT analysis</article-title>
          <source>Demogr. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>341-347</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marinova</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eiar.2009.01.009</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analysis of the environmental impact of China based on STIRPAT model</article-title>
          <source>Environ. Impact Assess. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lütkepohl</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Introduction to Multiple Time Series Analysis</source>
          <publisher-name>New York: Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
          <year>1991</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>598-611</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mehmood</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aslam</surname>
              <given-names>M. U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Javed</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/world4030037</pub-id>
          <article-title>Associating economic growth and ecological footprints through human capital and biocapacity in South Asia</article-title>
          <source>World</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>192</volume>
          <page-range>507-512</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mirziyoyeva</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salahodjaev</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.renene.2022.04.137</pub-id>
          <article-title>Renewable energy and CO2 emissions intensity in the top carbon intense countries</article-title>
          <source>Renew. Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>81-98</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Musa</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joseph</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22004/AG.ECON.206135</pub-id>
          <article-title>Macroeconomic effects of budget deficits in Uganda: A VAR-VECM approach</article-title>
          <source>Adv. Manag. Appl. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_56">
        <label>56.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>27</volume>
          <page-range>14601-14613</page-range>
          <issue>13</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nathaniel</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anyanwu</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-08017-7</pub-id>
          <article-title>Renewable energy, urbanization, and ecological footprint in the Middle East and North Africa region</article-title>
          <source>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_57">
        <label>57.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nautiyal</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goel</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sustainability assessment: Metrics and methods</article-title>
          <source>Methods in Sustainability Science</source>
          <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
          <year>2021</year>
          <page-range>27-46</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/b978-0-12-823987-2.00017-9</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_58">
        <label>58.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nautiyal</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goel</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Water footprints of hydropower projects</article-title>
          <source>Environ. Water Footprints</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <page-range>35-46</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-13-2739-1_2</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_59">
        <label>59.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>138</volume>
          <page-range>107848</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Naz</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanveer</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karim</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dowling</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eneco.2024.107848</pub-id>
          <article-title>The decoupling dilemma: Examining EG and CO2 in emerging Economic blocs</article-title>
          <source>Energy Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_60">
        <label>60.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>559-572</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>1901</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pearson</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786440109462720</pub-id>
          <article-title>On lines and planes of closest fit to systems of points in space</article-title>
          <source>Lond. Edinb. Dubl. Philos. Mag. J. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_61">
        <label>61.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Measuring the EF of population growth</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.populationmedia.org/the-latest/measuring-the-ecological-footprint-of-population-growth</source>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_62">
        <label>62.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>64</volume>
          <page-range>905-929</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rafindadi</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Usman</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09640568.2020.1791058</pub-id>
          <article-title>Toward sustainable electricity consumption in Brazil: The role of EG, globalization and EF using a nonlinear ARDL approach</article-title>
          <source>J. Environ. Plan. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_63">
        <label>63.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>20</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raihan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tuspekova</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s44246-022-00019-z</pub-id>
          <article-title>Dynamic impacts of economic growth, renewable energy use, urbanization, industrialization, tourism, agriculture, and forests on carbon emissions in Turkey</article-title>
          <source>Carbon Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_64">
        <label>64.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>11708</page-range>
          <issue>18</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramezani</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abolhassani</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shahnoushi Foroushani</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burgess</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aminizadeh</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su141811708</pub-id>
          <article-title>Ecological footprint and its determinants in MENA countries: A spatial econometric approach</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_65">
        <label>65.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Normalization and mixed degrees of integration in cointegrated time series systems</article-title>
          <year>2004</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rossana</surname>
              <given-names>R. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_66">
        <label>66.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>201</volume>
          <page-range>98-110</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sarkodie</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strezov</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2018.08.039</pub-id>
          <article-title>Empirical study of the Environmental Kuznets curve and Environmental Sustainability curve hypothesis for Australia, China, Ghana and USA</article-title>
          <source>J. Clean. Prod.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_67">
        <label>67.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>40</volume>
          <page-range>149-150</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2002</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schulze</surname>
              <given-names>Peter C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0921-8009(01)00249-x</pub-id>
          <article-title>I=PBAT</article-title>
          <source>Ecol. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_68">
        <label>68.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>65</volume>
          <page-range>44-57</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>1997</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Serletis</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Common stochastic trends and convergence of European stock markets</article-title>
          <source>Manch. Sch.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_69">
        <label>69.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>55-70</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shree</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nautiyal</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goel</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-33-4373-3_3</pub-id>
          <article-title>Carbon footprint estimation for academic building in India</article-title>
          <source>LCA Based Carbon Footprint Assess.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_70">
        <label>70.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>182</volume>
          <page-range>121798</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Su</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pang</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tao</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shao</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Umar</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.techfore.2022.121798</pub-id>
          <article-title>Renewable energy and technological innovation: Which one is the winner in promoting net-zero emissions?</article-title>
          <source>Technol. Forecast. Soc. Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_71">
        <label>71.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>121</volume>
          <page-range>383-403</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raza</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>K. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gr.2023.05.007</pub-id>
          <article-title>The nonparametric causal effect of sustainable governance structure on energy efficiency and ecological footprint: A pathway to sustainable development</article-title>
          <source>Gondwana Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_72">
        <label>72.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>23-40</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Toudas</surname>
              <given-names>K. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Christopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalantonis</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kravaritis</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4018/ijcfa.2017070102</pub-id>
          <article-title>The correlation of non-performing loans between the four Greek systemic banks before and during the recent crisis based on accounting information</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Corp. Finance Account.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_73">
        <label>73.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>12855</page-range>
          <issue>17</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ullah</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tekbaş</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doğan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su151712855</pub-id>
          <article-title>The impact of EG, natural resources, urbanization and BC on the ecological footprint: The case of Turkey</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_74">
        <label>74.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>90</volume>
          <page-range>104788</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ullah</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resourpol.2024.104788</pub-id>
          <article-title>Natural resources, renewable energy-environment nexus for Pakistan: A policy perspective</article-title>
          <source>Resour. Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_75">
        <label>75.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>27</volume>
          <page-range>30681-30693</page-range>
          <issue>24</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Usman</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akadiri</surname>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adeshola</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-09170-9</pub-id>
          <article-title>Role of renewable energy and globalization on EF in the USA: Implications for environmental sustainability</article-title>
          <source>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_76">
        <label>76.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>53-79</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Varun</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chauhan</surname>
              <given-names>M. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-4585-75-0_3</pub-id>
          <article-title>Carbon footprint and energy estimation of the sugar industry: An Indian case study</article-title>
          <source>Assess. Carbon Footprint Ind. Sectors</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_77">
        <label>77.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>129</volume>
          <page-range>1372-1381</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vélez-Henao</surname>
              <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vivanco</surname>
              <given-names>D. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hernández-Riveros</surname>
              <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enpol.2019.03.044</pub-id>
          <article-title>Technological change and the rebound effect in the STIRPAT model: A critical view</article-title>
          <source>Energy Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_78">
        <label>78.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wackernagel</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rees</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Our Ecological Footprint: Reducing Human Impact on the Earth</source>
          <publisher-name>New Society Publishers, Philadelphia</publisher-name>
          <year>1996</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_79">
        <label>79.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>99</volume>
          <page-range>7860-7865</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2002</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Waggoner</surname>
              <given-names>P. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ausubel</surname>
              <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.122235999</pub-id>
          <article-title>A framework for sustainability science: A renovated IPAT identity</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_80">
        <label>80.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/amns-2024-0736</pub-id>
          <article-title>AI-driven decision support system for green and sustainable urban planning in smart cities</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Math. Nonlinear Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_81">
        <label>81.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>46</volume>
          <page-range>351-365</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2003</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>York</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosa</surname>
              <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dietz</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0921-8009(03)00188-5</pub-id>
          <article-title>STIRPAT, IPAT and ImPACT: Analytic tools for unpacking the driving forces of environmental impacts</article-title>
          <source>Ecol. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_82">
        <label>82.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>152-161</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Du</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apr.2018.07.005</pub-id>
          <article-title>Impact of technological innovation on CO2 emissions and emissions trend prediction on ‘New Normal’ economy in China</article-title>
          <source>Atmos. Pollut. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_83">
        <label>83.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>107</volume>
          <page-range>315-322</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zaefarian</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iurkov</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koval</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indmarman.2022.10.020</pub-id>
          <article-title>Variance decomposition analysis: What is it and how to perform it – A complete guide for B2B researchers</article-title>
          <source>Ind. Mark. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_84">
        <label>84.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>63</volume>
          <page-range>101428</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zafar</surname>
              <given-names>M. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zaidi</surname>
              <given-names>S. A. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>Naveed R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mirza</surname>
              <given-names>F. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hou</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kirmani</surname>
              <given-names>S. A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resourpol.2019.101428</pub-id>
          <article-title>The impact of natural resources, human capital, and foreign direct investment on the Ecological footprint: The case of the United States</article-title>
          <source>Resour. Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_85">
        <label>85.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>63</volume>
          <page-range>102461</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Su</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scs.2020.102461</pub-id>
          <article-title>Using a new two-dimensional decoupling model to evaluate the decoupling state of global energy footprint</article-title>
          <source>Sustain. Cities Soc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>