<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PEET</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Power Engineering and Engineering Thermophysics</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Power Eng. Eng Thermophys.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">PEET</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2957-9635</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2957-9627</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-PcliQ3AuiUWOtD48BKtuGKVsVYMrg6yf</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/peet050103</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Hybrid Photovoltaic–Solar Desalination System: Recovery of Panel Waste Heat to Improve Water Evaporation in Desalination Process</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <name>
            <surname>Malakmahmoudi</surname>
            <given-names>Farshid</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>farshidmalakmahmoudi@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6266-920X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Rashidi</surname>
            <given-names>Saman</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>samanrashidi@semnan.ac.ir</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4289-3420</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Rafee</surname>
            <given-names>Roohollah</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>rafee@semnan.ac.ir</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1357-0470</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mirhosseini</surname>
            <given-names>Mojtaba</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>momi@iust.ac.ir</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Energy, Faculty of New Sciences and Technologies, Semnan University, 35131-19111 Semnan, Iran</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Faculty of Mechanical Engineering, Semnan University, 35131-19111 Semnan, Iran</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">School of Advanced Technologies, Iran University of Science and Technology, 16846-13114 Tehran, Iran</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>02</month>
        <year>2026</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>34</fpage>
      <lpage>46</lpage>
      <page-range>34-46</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>01</month>
          <year>2026</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>02</month>
          <year>2026</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2026 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2026</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>The idea of freshwater production has long attracted attention due to the significant depletion of natural freshwater resources caused by human activities. At the same time, the demand for electricity continues to increase with technological advancement. The use of fossil fuels, in addition to their limited and non‑renewable nature, leads to the emission of greenhouse gases and environmental pollution. Solar desalination systems are one of the methods used for freshwater production, while photovoltaic (PV) panels are a common approach for electricity generation. In this study, two passive stepped solar stills are experimentally compared. In one system, a dark-colored plate is installed beneath the basin steps to enhance the absorption of solar energy. In the other system, PV panels that are in direct contact with the water are installed beneath the basin. This configuration enables the PV panel to operate at a lower temperature, thereby improving its efficiency. In addition, the heat generated by the PV panels accelerates the evaporation process and enhances the overall system performance. The water level in the basins was kept constant to prevent the formation of dry spots on their bottoms. Based on the results of experiments conducted on several different days during the cold season, the effects of solar radiation intensity, ambient temperature, wind speed, and inlet water temperature on the performance of the constructed systems were investigated. An increase in ambient temperature raises both the inlet and outlet water temperatures, which directly contributes to a higher evaporation rate. Ambient temperature has an inverse effect on the performance of the PV panel, while it has a direct effect on the output voltage. The results indicate that using a PV panel beneath the desalination chamber, in some hours of the experiments, increased freshwater production and energy efficiency by more than three times.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Stepped solar still</kwd>
        <kwd>Photovoltaic panel</kwd>
        <kwd>Simultaneous production of electricity and freshwater</kwd>
        <kwd>Experimental study</kwd>
        <kwd>Water desalination</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="4"/>
        <fig-count count="9"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <ref-count count="26"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Freshwater scarcity is one of the most critical global challenges of current century, as increasing pressure on renewable water resources has intensified the need for efficient and sustainable technologies for water production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>]. In many arid and semi‑arid regions, limited access to clean water, together with the high cost and environmental impacts of fossil‑fuel‑based desalination systems, has driven strong interest toward solar‑powered freshwater production. Among the existing technologies, passive solar stills have gained considerable attention owing to their simple design, low operating cost, and suitability for remote or off‑grid communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. Nevertheless, their relatively low distillate output and restricted thermal efficiency remain significant obstacles to widespread practical application. Recently, hybridization of solar stills with emerging renewable technologies has been suggested as a promising strategy to improve their performance. One particularly effective approach involves integrating photovoltaic (PV) panels with solar distillation units, enabling simultaneous electricity generation and recovery of the panels’ waste heat to accelerate water evaporation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>]. This combined configuration not only enhances the thermal behavior of the desalination system and increases freshwater productivity but also improves the electrical efficiency of PV modules through direct cooling. Therefore, the development of PV‑assisted solar desalination systems offers a high‑potential, economical, and multi‑functional solution for addressing global freshwater shortages while promoting low‑carbon and sustainable energy utilization.</p><p>The simplest and most traditional form of this technology is the single slope or double slope basin solar still, in which solar radiation directly heats saline water in an insulated basin and the generated vapor condenses on a cooler glass surface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. The main limitation of these systems is their relatively low efficiency and freshwater productivity per unit area. Extensive research has been conducted to overcome this limitation, mainly focusing on increasing the evaporation surface area, improving heat transfer, and reducing thermal losses. The design of stepped solar stills is one of the effective approaches in this regard. In this configuration, saline water flows over a series of blackened steps, which increases the effective surface exposed to solar radiation and prolongs the residence time of the water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. Another strategy involves the use of enhanced thermal absorber materials, additional fins inside the basin, or corrugated absorber plates to increase the rate of heat transfer and improve the evaporation process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>]. Gawande et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>] investigated the performance of a stepped solar still at different water depths. In their study, additional factors affecting the desalination and distillation processes, such as climatic conditions and other operational parameters, were also examined. The experiments were conducted at three different water depths. Furthermore, several design parameters influencing the system performance were analyzed, including insulation thickness, glass cover area, packing density of the cover materials, absorber plate geometry, conditioned absorbing materials applied to the basin surface, and the inclination angles of the solar still. Omara et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>] attempted to enhance the productivity and efficiency of a stepped solar still by incorporating internal mirrors within the system to increase the absorption of solar radiation. El-Samadony and Kabeel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>] reported that the freshwater productivity of a stepped solar still equipped with a condenser, and with both a condenser and a reflector, was approximately 66% and 161% higher, respectively, than that of a conventional solar still. Kabeel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>] reported that increasing the inlet water temperature can enhance freshwater productivity by up to 65% in the stepped solar still. Sharon et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>] investigated the stepped solar still. Their comparative analysis revealed that the annual average freshwater productivity of the stepped inclined solar still was approximately 19.76% higher than that of a conventional basin-type solar still. Muftah et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>] investigated the performance of a stepped solar still. In order to enhance the efficiency of the stepped solar still, several modifications were implemented, including the use of internal and external reflectors, different absorber materials, and an external condenser. Abujazar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>] investigated the performance of stepped inclined solar stills. In this system, an inclined tray was used as part of the distillation unit. Experimental data were collected from the system and used to validate their simulation model. They calculated hourly radiative and convective heat transfer coefficients, evaporation rate, freshwater productivity, and overall efficiency. The results of their study indicated that the hourly freshwater production was about 605 mL, while the daily efficiency was approximately 28%. Tarahomi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>] used the sponge layer to improve the performance of the stepped solar still. They concluded that the amount of freshwater produced in one day by the stepped solar still modified by the sponge layer is 35.5% higher than the conventional one. Zarei et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>] integrated the thermal energy storage unit and solar water preheater with the stepped solar still. They found that the daily freshwater production for the conventional solar still was 3.262 L and for the modified solar still with solar water preheater, Phase Change Material (PCM), and fins was 3.806 L. Mosahebi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>] studied the performance of a stepped solar still equipped with internal reflector and concave steps. They found that the amounts of freshwater produced by the stepped solar stills with the flat steps and the modified concave steps are 466 and 621 mL/m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mr00ur11qk">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, respectively.</p><p>Many multifunctional systems are based on photovoltaic/thermal (PV/T) technology. As mentioned earlier, PV cells convert only a small portion of the solar spectrum into electricity, while a significant fraction of the absorbed solar energy is dissipated as heat. This excess heat not only reduces the electrical efficiency of the PV cells with every degree Celsius increase in temperature, but also imposes long-term thermal stress on the modules. The fundamental concept of PV/T systems is to recover this waste heat by using a cooling fluid (water or air) that flows behind the PV cells. In this way, two useful outputs are simultaneously produced: electricity (with higher efficiency due to cooling) and thermal energy. Numerous studies have focused on optimizing the performance of such systems. For example, Chen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>] investigated concentrated PV/T collectors and reported that electrical and thermal efficiencies of approximately 25% and 45% can be achieved. Similarly, Elsafi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], in an analysis of a concentrated PV/T device, highlighted its potential for the cost effective production of both electricity and freshwater. The performance of these systems strongly depends on the design of the heat exchanger, the properties of the working fluid, and the intensity of solar radiation. Dev and Tiwari [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>] conducted experiments on an active hybrid PV/T system. The system consisted of a single‑slope solar still with an area of 1 m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mcspzrvlw4">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, covered with a compact cover and inclined at an angle of 30° relative to the ground. This unit was integrated with two flat‑plate collectors (FPC) having a total area of 4 m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="meyo5dn7vc">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, each inclined at 45° with respect to the ground. A 75 W PV module was installed beneath one of the FPC to supply electricity for a DC motor, which was used to circulate water forcibly from the solar collector to the basin. During non‑sunny hours, the pump was turned off to prevent reverse circulation and subsequent heat loss. It was observed that the productivity of the hybrid active solar still was about 3.5 times higher than that of the passive solar still at a water depth of 5 cm during nine hours of pump operation. The maximum and minimum freshwater yields were reported to be 7.223 kg and 2.006 kg, respectively. Kumar and Tiwari [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>] compared PV/T active solar still and passive solar still under different climatic conditions during various months of the year. The highest freshwater production in the warmest month was reported as 7.22 kg/m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mhbgslhc9x">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> for the hybrid active solar still and 2.26 kg/m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mx84uf6cdb">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> for the passive solar still. In the coldest month, the freshwater yield for active solar still and passive solar still was 1.96 kg/m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m2q32oe2ue">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and 0.825 kg/m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mg063ij3cf">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, respectively. Their results indicated that the productivity during the warm season was approximately 3.3 times higher than that in the cold season. Gaur and Tiwari [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>] optimized the performance of a PV/T system integrated with several FPC. This system, referred to as a PV/T‑FPC system, was fully covered with a semi‑transparent PV module to generate direct electricity, which was used to operate the water pump. The PV /thermal collectors were connected in series. Each FPC contains ten tubes, providing a total surface area of 2 m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mw68z5fla6">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and is installed at an inclination angle of 45° with respect to the ground. At the lower section of all FPC units, a semi‑transparent PV module with dimensions of 1.2 × 0.27 m is integrated. The electrical output of the PV panel is 37 W, which is sufficient to operate the DC pump throughout the daytime. The system proposed by Al-Nimr and Al-Ammari [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>] is a single‑slope basin solar still in which a PV/T cell is installed beneath the basin, while a finned condenser is mounted on one of its side walls. In addition, a reflective mirror is installed on the wall to increase the reflection of solar radiation toward the basin. The proposed system is environmentally friendly and is capable of simultaneously producing distilled water and electricity. In addition, a low‑power fan powered by a portion of the electricity generated by the PV cell can be used to enhance the removal of water vapor from the evaporation chamber to the condensation chamber, particularly during midday. Ashtiani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>] designed a solar cogeneration system for freshwater and electricity production. Their results showed that despite the PVT collector, the daily efficiency of the solar still increases to 34.8% that indicates improvement of 13.9% in comparison with the passive solar still.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Experimental setup</title>
      <p>The constructed system for the simultaneous production of freshwater and electricity was designed in such a way that freshwater is produced using a passive stepped solar still, while electricity is generated by PV panels that serve as the bottom surface of the basin in each step. To conduct the experiments and enable a more accurate comparison of the data, two similar devices were constructed with identical dimensions, number of steps, basin volume, and desalination chamber size. The only difference between them was the bottom surface of each basin. In one device, a dark-colored plate was used to maximize the absorption of solar energy, while in the other device; PV panels in direct contact with the water were used. A schematic of the dimensions of the solar desalination unit and its frame is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>. In this study, a glass chamber mounted on a metal frame was used to construct the solar desalination unit. The dimensions of the glass chamber, which serves as the solar still, were considered to be 70 cm in width, 80 cm in length, 70 cm in rear height, and 15 cm in front height.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>(a) Schematic of the dimensions of the solar desalination unit; (b) frame of the solar desalination unit</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_Ut5x9KPBYJv6pMnu.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img__tHoXrv5H_OvB9w1.jpeg"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>The steps used in the solar desalination unit are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>. Inside the glass chamber, another stepped metallic platform was constructed to accommodate the water basins. The width of each step was 20 cm, the length was 50 cm, and the height of each step was 10 cm, with a total of three steps. These dimensions were selected based on the size and dimensions of the PV panel used in the experiments. The edges of the panels were enclosed with transparent glass sheets with a height of 5 cm, forming the basin of the solar still. The joints were sealed and waterproofed using aquarium adhesive. Similarly, another basin with the same dimensions was constructed using glass sheets. To ensure both devices appear visually similar, the bottom of this basin was covered with black-colored glass. The experiments were conducted simultaneously in two configurations: basins without PV panels and basins with PV panels. In one desalination chamber, three basins made of glass sheets with a black-coated bottom were placed on the steps, while in the other chamber, PV panels enclosed with glass sheets were installed on the steps. The volume of water entering the two chambers is controlled by a valve. In both configurations, water enters the first basin from the top and is transferred to the next basin through the outlet located at the bottom of each basin. The outlets are arranged alternately in a spiral pattern to guide the flow through all basins. Excess water is discharged outside the desalination chamber through a hose. In addition, a butterfly valve was used to more precisely control the inlet water flow rate to the basins. In this experiment, the inlet water is in direct contact with the PV panels in order to cool them, increase their efficiency, and enhance the evaporation rate. After some time, the water inside the basins evaporates due to the heat generated within the desalination chamber by solar radiation. The produced vapor rises and contacts the inner surface of the glass cover of the chamber. Because of the temperature difference between the inner surface of the glass and the outside environment, condensation occurs and the vapor turns into water droplets. Due to the slope of the glass cover, the formed droplets move downward along the inclined surface and are collected at the bottom of the chamber. To remove the produced freshwater, a hole is provided at the bottom of the desalination chamber. The collected droplets exit through this hole and are transferred via a hose to a sealed container to prevent evaporation from the container and avoid affecting the accuracy of the experimental data.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_2">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>(a) Schematic of the dimensions of the steps in solar desalination unit; (b) steps of the solar desalination unit</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_XdeFYLQFePisygQD.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_OI6CT9maqGYBGfqr.jpeg"/>
        </fig>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Experimental procedure</title>
      <p>The experiment was conducted during October and November in the city of Semnan. No rainfall occurred during the experimental period, and the tests were carried out under sunny weather conditions. Although the sky was slightly cloudy during some hours, the duration was short and therefore had no significant effect on the experimental process.</p><p>For the experiment, two devices with the same number of steps and identical basin dimensions were constructed. Each device was placed separately inside a glass chamber that served as the main body of the solar desalination unit. In the basins of one device, a dark coating was used at the bottom to maximize the absorption of solar radiation, while in the other device PV panels were used, with the water being in direct contact with the panels. The inlet water flow to the basins was regulated using a butterfly valve so that the incoming water volume was neither too high nor too low. If the inlet flow were too high, the water could leave the desalination chamber before reaching the evaporation stage. Conversely, if the flow were too low, the basins might become dry. A controlled and intermittent water flow also helps cool the surface of the PV panels, which, according to previous studies, can improve their efficiency.</p><p>All basins are equipped with overflow outlets that connect them to one another, allowing excess water to flow sequentially between the basins. The excess water from the last basin is discharged through an outlet and transferred outside the desalination chamber. The evaporated water, after striking the inclined glass surface at the top of the chamber, cools due to the temperature difference between the outer glass surface and the air inside the desalination chamber. As a result, condensation occurs and the condensed water is directed through a designated outlet into a container for collecting the produced freshwater.</p><p>Every hour, several parameters were measured, including the glass surface temperature, inlet and outlet water temperatures, ambient temperature, solar radiation intensity, wind speed, air humidity, and the amount of freshwater produced.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Evaluation procedure</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Economic analysis</title>
          
          <p>The economic evaluation of solar desalination systems has been presented by Maghsoudian et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]. The main factors involved in the cost analysis of a solar desalination system are as follows:</p><p>If $P$ is considered as the initial investment cost of the system and CRF as the capital recovery factor, the fixed annual cost (FAC) of the system can be calculated using the following relation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>]:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <mml:math id="md3zzhp6os">
                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    <mml:msup>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msup>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    <mml:msup>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msup>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(2)</label>
              <mml:math id="mbtb4vewa8">
                <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, $i<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mvi8fivsk0">
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>20</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m5qjx1p9cd">
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>10</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>S$, is assumed to be 201% of the cost of the reusable components that remain after the end of the system's lifetime. Sinking fund factor (SSF), annual salvage value (ASV), annual maintenance and operational cost (AMC), annual cost (AC), and cost per liter (CPL) are calculated by:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(3)</label>
              <mml:math id="mqfox7ejep">
                <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    <mml:msup>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msup>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(4)</label>
              <mml:math id="mej9svfac4">
                <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(5)</label>
              <mml:math id="m123vvhjrx">
                <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                <mml:mn>0.15</mml:mn>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(6)</label>
              <mml:math id="m1mxpmsg02">
                <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(7)</label>
              <mml:math id="mfdav944oj">
                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, $M$ is the average annual productivity of the device.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Important parameters</title>
          
          <p>In general, the exergy efficiency of solar desalination systems can be calculated as follows [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(8)</label>
              <mml:math id="mdo94qwgm7">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>η</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mtext> Exergy of output </mml:mtext>
                  <mml:mtext> Exergy of input </mml:mtext>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>The output exergy of the system can be expressed as follows [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(9)</label>
              <mml:math id="m1bx7gbowg">
                <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">Output</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mover>
                        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mover>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">fg</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mn>3600</mml:mn>
                </mml:mfrac>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mlr5gjm3sa">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7o7h2i9hu">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> represent the ambient temperature and the water temperature, respectively, expressed in degrees Celsius. The total input exergy of passive solar desalination systems consists of the received solar energy, which includes the total solar radiation incident on the surface of the saline water basin of the device. Accordingly, the input exergy of the system can be expressed as follows [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(10)</label>
              <mml:math id="mzsqefxsub">
                <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">Input</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                    <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:msup>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mfrac>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mfrac>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                  </mml:msup>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mr9wthuo18">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the effective sun temperature (℃), <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mo010owhru">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the ambient temperature (℃), $I<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="migg911nsc">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>^2<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mab2rotehm">
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>A<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m290wt2qea">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>^2$). The effective temperature of the sun is taken as 6000 K.</p><p>The energy efficiency of solar desalination systems can be calculated as follows [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(11)</label>
              <mml:math id="mkrhusluec">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>η</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mover>
                        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mover>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">fg</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mj58uwdsxt">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">fg</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the latent heat of vaporization of water at the mean ambient temperature, with units of kJ/kg. In this study, the value of <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mhw70pt03a">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">fg</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is taken as 2260 kJ/kg; the term <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m3q3seske8">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mover>
        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo>
      </mml:mover>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes the distillate production rate in kg/s; <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mktfuo02iv">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> represents the basin area of the solar still in square meters; and $I<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="me28e5slb0">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>^2$.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Uncertainty analysis</title>
      <p>The standard uncertainty of measuring devices can be expressed by the following relation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]:</p>
      
        <disp-formula>
          <label>(12)</label>
          <mml:math id="mbj0n68ea0">
            <mml:mi>U</mml:mi>
            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
            </mml:mrow>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
            </mml:mrow>
            <mml:msqrt>
              <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
            </mml:msqrt>
          </mml:math>
        </disp-formula>
      
      <p>where, $a<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mg2sj81byx">
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>u$ denotes the standard uncertainty. In this study, due to the experimental conditions and the characteristics of the measuring instruments, the uncertainty is considered to be of Type B. Uncertainty of the measuring instruments can be found in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>. </p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Uncertainty of the measuring instruments</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Measuring Instrument</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Equipment Model</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Accuracy</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Range</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Standard Uncertainty</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Laser thermometer (surface)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Infrared Thermometer-Tes1327</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1 ℃</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>35–500 ℃</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.058 ℃</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Solar radiation meter</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Solar Power Meter-TES-132</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1 W/m<mml:math id="mvw7a86hkm">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0–2000 W/m<mml:math id="mqu991hoa2">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.058 W/m<mml:math id="m5dphuea8n">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Anemometer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hot-Wire Anemometer-TSE-1341N</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.01 m/s</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0–30 m/s</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.006 m/s</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Thermometer (ambient)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hot-Wire Anemometer-TSE-1341N</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1 ℃</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10–60 ℃</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.058 ℃</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hygrometer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hot-Wire Anemometer-TSE-1341N</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10–95%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.058%</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Probe thermometer (water)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital Termometer-TPM10-ZU-1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1 ℃</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0–70 ℃</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.577 ℃</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ambient thermometer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>DYWSJ-TEMP.HUM</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2 ℃</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0–50 ℃</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.1 ℃</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ambient hygrometer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>DYWSJ-TEMP.HUM</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5% RH</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.8% RH</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Graduated cylinder</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5 mL</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.887 mL</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ruler</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1 mm</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.577 mm</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Results and discussion</title>
      <p>As mentioned in the previous sections, two stepped solar stills with identical dimensions were constructed. In one of them, a black plate was installed at the bottom of the basin to maximize solar energy absorption, while in the other system a PV panel was used as the basin floor. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> shows the variations of ambient temperature, inlet water temperature, and outlet water temperature at different hours during three testing days for both systems with and without PV. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> illustrates the variations of ambient temperature, inlet water temperature, and outlet water temperature for the stepped solar stills with and without the PV panel during three different days. On all three days, as solar radiation increases toward noon, the inlet and outlet water temperatures as well as the ambient air temperature increase; afterward, with the reduction of solar radiation, these temperatures show a decreasing trend. The comparison of the results shows that the outlet water temperature in both systems is higher than the inlet water temperature and the ambient temperature. However, differences in performance between the two systems can be observed at certain hours. In general, the system equipped with a PV panel, in addition to generating electrical energy, provides better thermal performance (higher outlet water temperature) compared with the system without PV. The multilayer structure of the PV panel (glass, silicon cells, and back layers), despite producing electricity (with a certain efficiency), can also act as a thermal absorbing surface. Due to its higher mass, it can store more heat than a simple plate and transfer it to the water. Consequently, the combination of electricity generation and heat absorption in the PV panel may cause the outlet water temperature in some conditions to be even higher than that of the system without PV. On 5 November 2024 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>a), when solar radiation was more favorable, the outlet water temperature in both systems reached its maximum values (36.6 ℃ and 34.2 ℃). In the PV assisted system, this temperature is higher than that of the system without PV due to the additional heat absorbed by the PV panel. On 7 and 8 December 2024 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>b and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>c), the ambient temperature dropped significantly (about 12–18 ℃), which led to a reduction in the maximum outlet water temperature of the PV assisted system to 35.4 ℃ and 27.5 ℃, respectively. Nevertheless, the system equipped with the PV panel still maintained its temperature advantage compared with the system without PV.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_3">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Ambient temperature, inlet water temperature, and outlet water temperatures for the systems with and without a photovoltaic (PV) panel: (a) on 5 November 2024; (b) on 7 December 2024; (c) on 8 December 2024</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_w4W5RgDUfl9XBQvz.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_MApxN2kKGsJ9crW7.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> shows the variations of ambient temperature, glass surface temperature, and wind speed for the two systems at different hours of the test days. On days with favorable solar radiation, the system equipped with the PV panel, despite electrical power extraction, was able to maintain the internal temperature (water and humid air) at a level where the glass surface temperature—and consequently the outlet water temperature—remained close to or slightly higher than that of the system without PV. This observation is consistent with the results presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>. The maximum difference in glass surface temperature between the two systems on the test days was 1.7 ℃, 1.9 ℃, and 0.9 ℃, respectively. On colder days or under higher wind conditions, e.g. 7 and 8 December, both systems were affected by increased wind speed and reduced ambient temperature, leading to a decrease in the glass surface temperature. However, if the glass surface temperature in the PV equipped system does not fall significantly behind that of the system without PV, it indicates that the PV panel, acting as a thermal absorbing surface, has been able to partially compensate for the negative effects of wind and low ambient temperature. Overall, the graphs in the figure confirm that the thermal behavior of both systems is influenced by the combined effects of ambient temperature and wind speed. Nevertheless, the system equipped with the PV panel, despite electrical energy extraction, demonstrates acceptable and competitive thermal performance compared with the system without PV, particularly in terms of glass surface temperature and outlet water temperature (in conjunction with the results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_4">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Ambient temperature, glass surface temperature, and wind speed for the systems with and without a photovoltaic (PV) panel: (a) on 5 November 2024; (b) on 7 December 2024; (c) on 8 December 2024</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_muKrTB2mGw79U67g.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_N08TziqfsmIUILhA.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> shows the variations of solar radiation intensity and freshwater production during different hours of the test days for the two systems. On all three test days, as solar radiation increased toward midday, the freshwater production rate in both systems increased, and then decreased as the radiation declined. On the warmer day (5 November 2024) and during periods of higher solar radiation (with a maximum value of 572 W/m<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m4ul456qv1">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>), the system equipped with the PV panel produced 2.45 times more freshwater than the system without PV. On the colder days (7 and 8 December 2024), with lower solar radiation intensity, the absolute freshwater production in both systems decreased; however, the PV assisted system still maintained its relative advantage, producing about three times more freshwater than the system without PV. Therefore, for the same level of received solar radiation, the system equipped with a PV panel demonstrates a higher evaporation–distillation efficiency, while simultaneously generating electrical power.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_5">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Variations of solar radiation intensity and freshwater production for the systems with and without a photovoltaic (PV) panel: (a) on 5 November 2024; (b) on 7 December 2024; (c) on 8 December 2024</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_AJsadCEw4SyQ73PD.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_PKnBjPYUDUmOqYl8.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>

<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref> shows the variations of current intensity and output voltage under different resistances on 5 November, 7 December, and 8 December 2024. As observed, as the output voltage increases, the current intensity decreases, following an approximately uniform downward trend. However, at a resistance of 160 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mahfzkymep">
    <mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, the current suddenly drops. This indicates that, for the considered time period, a resistance of 160 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="me2pao6luv">
    <mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> represents an optimal value.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_6">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Variations of current versus voltage at different resistances for the photovoltaic (PV) panel: (a) at 13:00 on 5 November 2024; (b) at 12:00 on 7 December 2024; (c) at 14:00 on 8 December 2024</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_EnakH_tFxHXzWvTW.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_imQ_ip0zi3OHSavH.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>

This behavior is also observed in the power–voltage curves of the PV panel, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>. As illustrated in this figure, as the output voltage increases, the output power also increases, following an approximately uniform upward trend. However, at a resistance of 160 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mzl9kmlycb">
    <mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, a turning point occurs and the power suddenly decreases.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_7">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Variations of power versus voltage at different resistances for the photovoltaic (PV) panel for the system with a PV panel: (a) on 5 November 2024; (b) on 7 December 2024; (c) on 8 December 2024</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_BiE0s0zvujLqMw5P.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_O-WOgzCv4gyIDns6.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref> compares the energy efficiency at different hours of the experiment conducted on 7 December 2024, along with the solar radiation intensity and the amount of freshwater produced for the systems with and without a PV panel. In both graphs, it can be observed that the system equipped with a PV panel exhibits higher energy efficiency compared with the system without the panel. The main reason for this behavior is the energy storage capability of the PV panel and the resulting greater thermal inertia in the system, especially during the afternoon hours and when solar radiation decreases. This helps maintain freshwater production and increases the overall desalination efficiency. At noon, the freshwater production of the system equipped with the PV panel is more than twice that of the conventional system. However, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>, during the afternoon hours, with the reduction of solar radiation, both the freshwater production and the system efficiency decrease.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_8">
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Energy efficiency at different hours for the experiment conducted on 7 December 2024, along with the solar radiation intensity and the amount of freshwater produced for the systems: (a) with a photovoltaic (PV) panel; (b) without a PV panel</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_K4ypRm5O3wmSxeBQ.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_Ho-C-yyp-FJqw6Hj.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref> compares the temperature difference between the inlet and outlet saline water for 5 November and 8 December 2024. As observed, the temperature difference increases from the beginning of the process until around noon and then decreases afterward. In both test days, the temperature difference between the inlet and outlet water in the system equipped with the PV panel is significantly higher than that of the simple system without PV. This greater temperature difference leads to increased evaporation of saline water, resulting in higher freshwater production and improved efficiency of the PV assisted system.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_9">
          <label>Figure 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Variations of the temperature difference between inlet and outlet saline water with time for the two systems: (a) on 5 November 2024; (b) on 8 December 2024</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_NLyi5WbxLtPGvth_.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/4/img_ZbOWv2PWqChvsvxr.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>7. Conclusions</title>
      <p>In this study, two passive stepped solar stills were experimentally investigated during several days of the cold season to evaluate the effect of integrating a PV panel beneath the desalination chamber. One system employed a conventional dark absorber plate, while the other utilized a PV panel in direct contact with the saline water. The experimental results showed that the PV assisted system consistently produced higher outlet water temperatures and a larger temperature difference between the inlet and outlet saline water compared with the conventional system. This enhanced thermal behavior increased the evaporation rate and significantly improved freshwater production. Despite variations in solar radiation, ambient temperature, and wind speed during the test days, the PV based configuration maintained a clear performance advantage. The results also indicated that the PV panel operated at a relatively lower temperature due to direct contact with water, which helped improve its electrical performance while simultaneously transferring heat to the saline water. This dual function enabled the system to generate electricity while enhancing the desalination process. Under certain operating hours, the freshwater productivity and energy efficiency of the PV integrated system were more than three times higher than those of the conventional stepped still. Overall, integrating PV panels beneath the basin of stepped solar stills can effectively improve both thermal and electrical performance, offering a promising approach for simultaneous freshwater and electricity production, particularly in regions with limited water resources.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>Conceptualization, S.R., R.R., and M.M.; methodology, F.M., S.R., R.R., and M.M.; investigation, F.M., S.R., R.R., and M.M.; resources, F.M., S.R., R.R., and M.M.; writing—original draft preparation, F.M., S.R., R.R., and M.M.; writing—review and editing, F.M., S.R., R.R., and M.M.; supervision, S.R., R.R., and M.M. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahmoudi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bostani</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rashidi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valipour</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2023.113543</pub-id>
          <page-range>113543</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <source>Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev.</source>
          <article-title>Challenges and opportunities of desalination with renewable energy resources in Middle East countries</article-title>
          <volume>184</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>G. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Solar Distillation Practice for Water Desalination Systems</source>
          <publisher-name>Anshan Publisher</publisher-name>
          <year>2008</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alwan</surname>
              <given-names>N. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>B. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alomar</surname>
              <given-names>O. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abdulrazzaq</surname>
              <given-names>N. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>O. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abed</surname>
              <given-names>R. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37693</pub-id>
          <source>Heliyon</source>
          <article-title>Performance of solar still units and enhancement techniques: A review investigation</article-title>
          <page-range>e37693</page-range>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecmx.2025.101212</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>O. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Algburi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daoud</surname>
              <given-names>R. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khaoula</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>Z. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aziz</surname>
              <given-names>E. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Energy Convers. Manag. X</source>
          <article-title>Performance of the solar distillation systems integrated with PV/thermal systems: A review</article-title>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <year>2025</year>
          <page-range>101212</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Experimental analysis on single and double basin single slope solar still with energy storage material and external heater</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matpr.2020.12.444</pub-id>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <source>Mater. Today Proc.</source>
          <page-range>10288-10292</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raj Kamal</surname>
              <given-names>M. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parandhaman</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madhu</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magesh Babu</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sathyamurthy</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Velmurugan</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naveen Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Noorul Haq</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srithar</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.energy.2009.04.029</pub-id>
          <page-range>1179-1186</page-range>
          <article-title>Performance analysis in stepped solar still for effluent desalination</article-title>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <source>Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Desalination</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shalaby</surname>
              <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>El-Bialy</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>El-Sebaii</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>247-255</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.desal.2016.07.042</pub-id>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>398</volume>
          <article-title>An experimental investigation of a v-corrugated absorber single-basin solar still using PCM</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Int. J. Energy Eng.</source>
          <page-range>137</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gawande</surname>
              <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhuyar</surname>
              <given-names>L. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deshmukh</surname>
              <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of depth of water on the performance of stepped type solar still</article-title>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <year>2013</year>
          <issue>4</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Enhancing the stepped solar still performance using internal reflectors</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.desal.2013.01.007</pub-id>
          <source>Desalination</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Omara</surname>
              <given-names>Z. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kabeel</surname>
              <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Younes</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>314</volume>
          <year>2013</year>
          <page-range>67-72</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>El-Samadony</surname>
              <given-names>Y. A. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kabeel</surname>
              <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>744-750</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <source>Energy</source>
          <article-title>Theoretical estimation of the optimum glass cover water film cooling parameters combinations of a stepped solar still</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.energy.2014.01.080</pub-id>
          <volume>68</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>46</volume>
          <source>Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <article-title>Techniques used to improve the performance of the stepped solar still—A review</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2015.02.053</pub-id>
          <page-range>178-188</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kabeel</surname>
              <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Omara</surname>
              <given-names>Z. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Younes</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>30-54</page-range>
          <volume>410</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharon</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reddy</surname>
              <given-names>K. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krithika</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Philip</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Desalination</source>
          <article-title>Experimental performance investigation of tilted solar still with basin and wick for distillate quality and enviro-economic aspects</article-title>
          <year>2017</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.desal.2017.01.035</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Desalination</source>
          <page-range>198-209</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Muftah</surname>
              <given-names>A. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sopian</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alghoul</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>435</volume>
          <year>2018</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.desal.2017.07.017</pub-id>
          <article-title>Performance of basin type stepped solar still enhanced with superior design concepts</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2018</year>
          <page-range>94-103</page-range>
          <source>Desalination</source>
          <article-title>Performance evaluation of inclined copper-stepped solar still in a wet tropical climate</article-title>
          <volume>425</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abujazar</surname>
              <given-names>M. S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fatihah</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lotfy</surname>
              <given-names>E. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kabeel</surname>
              <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharil</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.desal.2017.10.022</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Performance improvement in stepped solar still modified by sponge layer</article-title>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tarahomi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rashidi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hormozi</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashtiani</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>1973-1982</page-range>
          <source>J. Cent. South Univ.</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11771-024-5693-5</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Effects of thermal energy storage and solar water preheater on the performance of cascade solar still—An experimental study</article-title>
          <source>J. Energy Storage</source>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <page-range>115520</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.est.2025.115520</pub-id>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zarei</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rashidi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rafee</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtice.2023.104727</pub-id>
          <volume>148</volume>
          <source>J. Taiwan Inst. Chem. Eng.</source>
          <article-title>Experimental investigation of performance of cascade solar water desalination system equipped with internal reflector and concave steps</article-title>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mosahebi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rashidi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mirhosseini</surname>
              <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>10472</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Q.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burhan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akhtar</surname>
              <given-names>F. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ybyraiymkul</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shahzad</surname>
              <given-names>M. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ng</surname>
              <given-names>K. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2021</year>
          <source>Energy</source>
          <article-title>A decentralized water/electricity cogeneration system integrating concentrated photovoltaic/thermal collectors and vacuum multi-effect membrane distillation</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.energy.2021.120852</pub-id>
          <volume>230</volume>
          <page-range>120852</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>424</volume>
          <page-range>17-26</page-range>
          <article-title>Integration of humidification-dehumidification desalination and concentrated photovoltaic-thermal collectors: Energy and exergy-costing analysis</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elsafi</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2017</year>
          <source>Desalination</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.desal.2017.09.022</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2010</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.desal.2009.12.004</pub-id>
          <volume>254</volume>
          <page-range>126-137</page-range>
          <source>Desalination</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dev</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>G. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characteristic equation of a hybrid (PV-T) active solar still</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>1219-1229</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enconman.2009.12.033</pub-id>
          <source>Energy Convers. Manag.</source>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <year>2010</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design, fabrication and performance of a hybrid photovoltaic/thermal (PV/T) active solar still</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>1763-1772</page-range>
          <article-title>Optimization of number of collectors for integrated PV/T hybrid active solar still</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apenergy.2009.10.019</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gaur</surname>
              <given-names>M. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>G. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Appl. Energy</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Nimr</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Ammari</surname>
              <given-names>W. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>135</volume>
          <source>Sol. Energy</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <article-title>A novel hybrid PV-distillation system</article-title>
          <page-range>874-883</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.solener.2016.06.061</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2024</year>
          <article-title>Experimental study on a solar-powered cogeneration system for freshwater and electricity production</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ashtiani</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hormozi</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zamzamian</surname>
              <given-names>A. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rashidi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>30703-30715</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-024-33166-4</pub-id>
          <source>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.</source>
          <volume>31</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applthermaleng.2025.127261</pub-id>
          <year>2025</year>
          <source>Appl. Therm. Eng.</source>
          <volume>287</volume>
          <article-title>Solar still performance enhancement with reflectors and various shapes of absorber plates</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maghsoudian</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rashidi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rafee</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>127261</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>86</volume>
          <page-range>1995-2004</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>G. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Appl. Energy</source>
          <article-title>Life cycle cost analysis of single slope hybrid (PV/T) solar still</article-title>
          <year>2009</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apenergy.2009.03.005</pub-id>
          <issue>10</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>