<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Sustainability for Energy</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Sustain. Energy</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JSE</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2958-1915</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-1907</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-m3BrfNaWgxFhS9d3ptQL3ezeTCYQBlKz</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jse020303</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Techno-Economic Evaluation of Hybrid Photovoltaic-Wind Energy Systems for Indonesian Government Buildings</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5391-5819</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
            <given-names>Singgih Dwi</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>singgihdwipras@student.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0002-5825-2596</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Regannanta</surname>
            <given-names>Farrel Julio</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>farrelregannanta@student.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0002-5813-4143</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Birawa</surname>
            <given-names>Anom Respati</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>anomrespati@student.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-2861-0393</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Alfaridzi</surname>
            <given-names>Muhammad Salman</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>msalmanal458@student.uns.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Mechanical Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, Sebelas Maret University, 57126 Surakarta, Indonesia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>09</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>132</fpage>
      <lpage>144</lpage>
      <page-range>132-144</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>08</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2023 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>The burgeoning population in Indonesia necessitates an escalation in energy provision. The reliance on diminishing fossil fuels, coupled with their adverse environmental repercussions, propels the exploration of renewable alternatives. This study investigates the techno-economic viability of implementing hybrid photovoltaic (PV) and wind turbine systems across government edifices within five urban locales: Semarang, Surabaya, Yogyakarta, Jakarta, and Denpasar. Employing the Hybrid Optimization Model for Electric Renewables (HOMER), simulations and optimizations of the hybrid systems were conducted, aiming to fulfil an electrical demand of 2636.1 kWh. The analysis is predicated on a 25-year operational lifespan. Results indicate that Denpasar presents the optimum potential for the hybrid system, with an annual electricity generation of 1,360,195 kWh surpassing the consumption demand of 1,214,136 kWh. The Net Present Cost (NPC) is calculated at IDR 27,529,340,000.00 and the Cost of Energy (COE) at IDR 997.17, yielding an attractive investment prospect with a Break Even Point (BEP) at 8.2 years. The estimated initial outlay for the Denpasar government building's PV system stands at IDR 4,149,376,743.96. The findings underscore the financial and technical feasibility of harnessing solar and wind synergies for sustainable energy solutions in Indonesian government infrastructure. These outcomes have pivotal implications for policy-making and strategic energy planning, demonstrating a replicable model for renewable integration in similar tropical regions.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Renewable energy</kwd>
        <kwd>Hybrid systems</kwd>
        <kwd>Hybrid Optimization Model for Electric Renewables (HOMER)</kwd>
        <kwd>Techno-economic analysis</kwd>
        <kwd>Solar-wind energy</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="4"/>
        <fig-count count="8"/>
        <table-count count="13"/>
        <ref-count count="35"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>An escalating population trajectory is directly proportional to the burgeoning demand for energy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>]. It is observed that primary energy reserves, specifically oil and coal, are diminishing, heralding the potential onset of energy deficits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]. The depletion of fossil fuel reserves, coupled with the exacerbation of the greenhouse effect, has catalyzed a quest for alternative, eco-friendlier energy sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. Renewable energy is being widely researched and developed to overcome these various problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. Intensive development has positioned solar energy as a renewable frontrunner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. The intrinsic characteristics of solar energy, notably its chemical-free and non-radioactive nature, render it benign to the environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. The application of solar energy is diverse, spanning electricity production, water heating, air heating, and support for various industrial drying processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>]. Nevertheless, the uneven distribution of solar irradiance necessitates sophisticated technology for optimization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. It has been posited that hybrid power plants could offer an economical and efficient solution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>]. The present study models an optimal generating system to address renewable energy requirements.</p><p>Solar and wind energy are burgeoning in popularity, with economic potential that is becoming increasingly competitive with that of conventional power plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>]. These renewable sources are profuse in nature and their utilization does not contribute to CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, thereby affirming their environmental soundness. Indonesia, straddling the equator, reaps substantial solar irradiance annually [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>]. As an archipelagic nation subjected to monsoonal winds, it experiences two distinct seasons, offering opportunities to harness wind energy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. The synergy of solar and wind energy promises a complementary power source, with solar being predominant during the dry season and wind during the rainy season and nocturnal hours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>]. The use of hybrid solar and wind energy has proven more effective than relying solely on solar energy in various regions of Indonesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>].</p><p>Techno-economic analysis has been established as a necessary component in designing generating systems. This analytical approach quantifies in monetary terms the feasibility of engineering projects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]. Such analysis has corroborated the viability of projects like the rooftop PLTS System on the Denpasar mayor's office [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>]. Furthermore, Arifin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>] have conducted simulations on the potential of interconnected PV-Wind hybrid systems in urban Java. This analysis aimed to create effective, renewable energy with technical, economic and environmental security to solve Indonesian energy crisis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>]. The current research utilizes the HOMER software to examine cost-effectiveness and economic feasibility for power generation systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>].</p><p>The objective of this research is to simulate PV-Wind hybrid energy as a sustainable, efficient, and eco-friendly source of electrical energy for government buildings in Semarang, Surabaya, Yogyakarta, Jakarta, and Denpasar cities. The adoption of an on-grid system configuration, connecting with the PLN (Perusahaan Listrik Negara) electricity network, is considered. This study analyses the techno-economic aspects of PV-Wind hybrid power generation for Indonesian government buildings, with simulation outcomes offering comparative insights and evaluation of factors affecting cost-effectiveness in system design.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Research methods</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Research flow</title>
          
          <p>The methodology of this study was systematically approached, initiating with a comprehensive literature review, followed by rigorous data collection, leading to detailed simulations and subsequent analyses. Simulations of the PV-Turbine Hybrid PLTS (solar power plants) were executed using the HOMER software to ascertain the optimal configuration of the hybrid systems, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Flow of hybrid PLTS for government buildings</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/10/img_CkYSkI2NYpXIQJql.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Description of the hybrid pv-turbine system design model</title>
          
          <p>The design of the Hybrid PV-Wind Turbine System was modeled utilizing the HOMER software, developed by the National Renewable Energy Laboratory (NREL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>]. This tool facilitates the optimization of microgrid configurations, allowing for the computation of total energy output and variations in system costs, as well as the economic and financial feasibility of different designs. HOMER is instrumental in the assessment of power generation systems, determining their suitability for grid-connected (On-Grid) or off-grid (Off-Grid) applications.</p><p>In this methodology, HOMER was employed to identify the most efficient system configuration, prioritizing the results based on the NPC from the lowest to the highest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]. Such a prioritization ensures the selection of the most cost-effective system to fulfill the electricity requirements of government buildings. Within the scope of this research, the specifications for the solar panel comprised the Schneider Conext CL25000 E with a generic PV model. The wind turbine selected was the Bergey Excel 6-R series, and the inverter was the KEHUA France KF-BCS 630K-B series. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> presents the On-Grid system design as conceptualized using the HOMER software.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Modeling scheme for a Hybrid PV-Turbine PLTS System for government buildings</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/10/img_bW0h1Go5M_T1swp3.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Within the configuration under study, the solar panel array is connected to a wind turbine, serving as a direct current (DC) input. An inverter is then employed to transform the DC voltage from the PV cells and the turbine into alternating current (AC) voltage, which is subsequently delivered to the electrical load. Should the voltage generated by the renewable sources prove insufficient for the demands of government buildings, the national electricity utility, PLN, is posited to supplement the shortfall, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Electric load profile of PLTS Hybrid PV-Turbine for government building</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/10/img_wFlrimWUnHwaac_6.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Hybrid PV-Turbine PLTS System components for government buildings</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Parameter</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Schneider Conext CL25000 E with Generic PV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bergey Excel 6-R</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>KEHUA France KF-BCS 630K-B</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Capital Costs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp. 320,000.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp. 38,500,000.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp. 5,100,000.00</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Replacement Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp. 38,500,000.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp. 10,200,000.00</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>O&amp;amp;M Costs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp. 320,000.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp. 3,850,000.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp. 500,000.00</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lifetime</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>25 years</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>20 years</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10 years</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>Prior to the commencement of simulations with the HOMER Pro software, requisite data are inputted into the system. These encompass load profiles, renewable energy source data (inclusive of solar irradiance, ambient temperature, and wind velocity), along with technical and economic parameters. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> delineates the list of components integrated into the aforementioned system. It is to be noted that these components are readily procurable within Indonesia, with particular availability on the island of Java.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Description of the hybrid pv-turbine system design location</title>
          
          <p>Simulations for the design of the Hybrid PLTS destined for governmental structures are to be conducted within several notable urban centers across Indonesia, including Semarang, Surabaya, Jakarta, Yogyakarta, and Denpasar. The objective of these simulations is to ascertain the economic viability and potential of the aforementioned systems within five major Indonesian cities. The locations selected for the proposed development are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Location of Hybrid PV-Turbine PLTS design for government building</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/10/img_x2OIj-IxSVUgUGZ0.png"/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/10/img_9mhUOacFm4X3GWYb.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Potential use of solar energy</title>
          
          <p>Solar power plants (PLTS) harness solar radiation, with the efficacy of conversion to electrical energy being contingent upon the PV cells' capacity to absorb this radiation. It has been observed that an augmentation in the intensity of solar radiation impinging upon the photovoltaic cell corresponds to an increased electrical output [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>].</p><p>Data pertaining to solar radiation intensity across various urban locations, namely Semarang, Surabaya, Jakarta, Yogyakarta, and Denpasar, has been collated and is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>. These measurements were procured from the archives of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA).</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Solar radiation intensity data</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >Month</th><th >1</th><th >2</th><th >3</th><th >4</th><th >5</th></tr><tr><td >January</td><td >2.55</td><td >2.53</td><td >1.87</td><td >2.69</td><td >3.35</td></tr><tr><td >February</td><td >2.62</td><td >2.71</td><td >1.63</td><td >2.7</td><td >3.83</td></tr><tr><td >March</td><td >3.29</td><td >3.01</td><td >2.37</td><td >3.13</td><td >4.32</td></tr><tr><td >April</td><td >3.59</td><td >3.46</td><td >2.64</td><td >3.52</td><td >5.33</td></tr><tr><td >May</td><td >4.19</td><td >4.28</td><td >2.79</td><td >3.85</td><td >5.16</td></tr><tr><td >June</td><td >4.33</td><td >4.75</td><td >2.75</td><td >3.95</td><td >5.01</td></tr><tr><td >July</td><td >4.76</td><td >5.5</td><td >3.04</td><td >3.99</td><td >4.63</td></tr><tr><td >August</td><td >5.06</td><td >6.09</td><td >3.31</td><td >4.01</td><td >4.96</td></tr><tr><td >September</td><td >5.06</td><td >6.13</td><td >3.26</td><td >3.74</td><td >5.18</td></tr><tr><td >October</td><td >4.04</td><td >4.92</td><td >2.57</td><td >3.01</td><td >5.02</td></tr><tr><td >November</td><td >3.16</td><td >3.23</td><td >2.08</td><td >2.52</td><td >4.24</td></tr><tr><td >December</td><td >2.42</td><td >2.21</td><td >1.80</td><td >2.40</td><td >3.10</td></tr><tr><td >Average</td><td >3.76</td><td >4.07</td><td >2.51</td><td >3.29</td><td >4.45</td></tr><tr><td >Minimal</td><td >2.42</td><td >2.21</td><td >1.63</td><td >2.4</td><td >3.1</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>Denpasar City, exhibiting an average solar radiation intensity of 4.45 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mmu2zhb4h4">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">kWh</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, presents considerable prospects for the deployment of the Hybrid PLTS System. It is postulated that the efficiency of the energy output from such systems is positively correlated with higher intensities of incident solar radiation.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.5. Potential use of wind energy</title>
          
          <p>Wind velocity data, sourced from the NASA, facilitate the analysis of wind energy's potential integration into Hybrid PLTS, specifically within Semarang, Surabaya, Jakarta, Yogyakarta, and Denpasar. The wind velocity metrics for these municipalities are delineated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Wind speed data</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >Month</th><th >1</th><th >2</th><th >3</th><th >4</th><th >5</th></tr><tr><td >January</td><td >5.13</td><td >4.41</td><td >4.33</td><td >3.86</td><td >3.78</td></tr><tr><td >February</td><td >5.09</td><td >4.54</td><td >4.24</td><td >3.95</td><td >3.75</td></tr><tr><td >March</td><td >3.62</td><td >3.40</td><td >3.73</td><td >3.35</td><td >3.27</td></tr><tr><td >April</td><td >3.12</td><td >3.25</td><td >3.19</td><td >3.49</td><td >3.77</td></tr><tr><td >May</td><td >3.65</td><td >3.92</td><td >3.01</td><td >4.12</td><td >4.66</td></tr><tr><td >June</td><td >3.99</td><td >4.44</td><td >3.16</td><td >4.52</td><td >5.12</td></tr><tr><td >July</td><td >4.15</td><td >4.86</td><td >3.19</td><td >5.04</td><td >5.47</td></tr><tr><td >August</td><td >4.08</td><td >5.02</td><td >3.14</td><td >5.29</td><td >5.42</td></tr><tr><td >September</td><td >3.72</td><td >4.70</td><td >2.89</td><td >5.09</td><td >4.91</td></tr><tr><td >October</td><td >3.15</td><td >3.76</td><td >2.73</td><td >4.52</td><td >4.34</td></tr><tr><td >November</td><td >2.80</td><td >2.89</td><td >2.95</td><td >3.90</td><td >3.72</td></tr><tr><td >December</td><td >3.83</td><td >3.42</td><td >3.99</td><td >3.74</td><td >3.60</td></tr><tr><td >Average</td><td >3.86</td><td >4.05</td><td >3.38</td><td >4.24</td><td >4.32</td></tr><tr><td >Minimal</td><td >2.80</td><td >2.89</td><td >2.73</td><td >3.35</td><td >3.27</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>Elevated wind speed values correlate with enhanced efficiency in energy output from the generation system. The data presented indicates that Denpasar City exhibits the highest mean wind speed, registering at an average of 4.32 m/s, thereby underscoring its substantial potential for the deployment of the Hybrid PLTS System.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.6. Main system components</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.6.1 Total expense</title>
              
              <p>To list the total expense, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref> summarizes the data daily total load.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_4">
                  <label>Table 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Daily total load data</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Afternoon (07:00-17:00)</p></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Evening (17:00-07:00)</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>O'clock</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Load (kW)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>O'clock</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Load (kW)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7.5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>210</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>19</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.8</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>228</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>20</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.75</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>245</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>21</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.75</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>250</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>243</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>23</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>240</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.4</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>238</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.4</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>235</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>16</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>220</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.6</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>17</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>129.5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.75</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.9</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.9</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total (kW)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2109</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>87.75</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Increase the load by 20%, so the total power (kW)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2530.8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>105.3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total load per day (kW)</p></td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><p>2636.1</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.6.2 Photovoltaic solar panels</title>
              
              <p>Photovoltaic solar panels are a device that can produce electrical energy from solar radiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>]. The power produced by the solar panel module can be calculated using the following Eq. (1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>].</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(1)</label>
                  <mml:math id="m902xvpgwa">
                    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where,</p><p>PPV: Power produced by the PV module (kW)</p><p>Fpv: PV derating factor</p><p>Ypv: Power output PV at standard conditions (kW)</p><p>GT: Instantaneous radiation on the surface of the PV module (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mp5q9e5vjb">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">kW</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>)</p><p>GT, STC: Instantaneous radiation under standard conditions (1 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="meyzmkq39n">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">kW</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>)</p><p>The type of solar panel used in this Hybrid PLTS System is the Schneider Conext CL25000 E solar panel with generic PV. This solar panel has the specifications shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref> and can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref>.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_5">
                  <label>Table 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Solar panel specifications</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technical Specifications</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mark</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Maximum power (Pmax)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>25000 Wp</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Maximum voltage (Vmp)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1000 V</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Maximum current (Imp)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>37 A</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Open circuit voltage (Voc)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>480 V</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Short circuit current (Isc)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>36 A</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Module efficiency</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>98%</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Derating factors</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>85%</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
              
                <fig id="fig_5">
                  <label>Figure 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Schneider conext CL25000 E with generic PV</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/10/img_RIFQ_Ya5cHSmyUO4.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.6.3 Wind turbine</title>
              
              <p>A wind turbine is a device that captures kinetic energy in the form of wind energy and converts mechanical energy (turbine movement) into electrical energy through a generator [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>]. The following equation is used to calculate the potential power produced by a wind turbine <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m2f4u4h3qh">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> every day [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>].</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(2)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mm3s1e4s3t">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                    <mml:msup>
                      <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                    </mml:msup>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where,</p><p><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mc4cczhse3">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>: The potential power produced by a wind turbine</p><p><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mdkqe4nbdd">
    <mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>: Density of air (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mstckpv79r">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">kg</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>)</p><p>$v<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mjdf22cuiy">
    <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>A<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m6qeclr9lh">
    <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>m^2<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m0ov7vjmkd">
    <mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>cp$: Turbine efficiency</p><p>The type of wind turbine used in this Hybrid PLTS System is Bergey Excel 6-R. This wind turbine has the specifications shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref> and can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_6">
                  <label>Table 6</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Bergey excel 6-R specifications</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tr><th >Technical Specifications</th><th >Mark</th></tr><tr><td >Output power</td><td >5.5 kW</td></tr><tr><td >Maximum voltage (Vmp)</td><td >230 V</td></tr><tr><td >Furling wind speed</td><td >14-20 m/s</td></tr><tr><td >Cut-in wind speed</td><td >2.5 m/s</td></tr><tr><td >Number of blades</td><td >3</td></tr><tr><td >Rotor speed (RPM)</td><td >0-400 RPM</td></tr></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
              
                <fig id="fig_6">
                  <label>Figure 6</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Bergey excel 6-R</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/10/img_9IN8krwfspfZRWpf.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.6.4 Inverters</title>
              
              <p>The inverter functions to change the current from DC electric voltage (direct current) produced by the PV array into AC electric voltage (alternating current) with a frequency of 50Hz/60Hz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]. Hybrid PLTS for Government Buildings uses a KEHUA France KF-BCS 630K-B inverter. The specifications of this inverter are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_7">Table 7</xref> and depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_7">
                  <label>Table 7</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title> KEHUA France KF-BCS 630K-B specifications</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Type of Technical Specification</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mark</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Output power</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>700 kW</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Maximum power</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1400 kW</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Output frequency</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>50-60 Hz</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Input dc voltage</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>48 V</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Efficiency</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>94%</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
              
                <fig id="fig_7">
                  <label>Figure 7</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>KEHUA France KF-BCS 630K-B</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.7. Economy</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.7.1 Npc</title>
              
              <p>The optimality of the system configuration is ascertained by the magnitude of the NPC, which reflects the aggregate cost of the system over its lifespan. The HOMER software sequences the optimization outcomes by ascending NPC values, thereby privileging the most cost-effective configurations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]. The total NPC encompasses the entirety of the project expenditures, encapsulating component costs, replacement, maintenance, operational fuel, and the cost of capital. The NPC is calculable by employing the following Eq. (3) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>].</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(3)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mp8221vaa9">
                    <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mtext>proj</mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where,</p><p>Cann, tot: Total annual fee (Rp/year)</p><p>CRF: Capital recovery factor</p><p style="text-align: justify"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mftoevby7c">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>: interest rate</p><p>Rproj: life of use (years)</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.7.2 Coe</title>
              
              <p>In conjunction with the determination of NPC, the analysis further extends to the computation of the COE, representative of the average cost per kilowatt-hour for the electricity generated by the system. The COE is derived by the division of the total annualized system cost <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mxc7cepva8">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mtext>ann,tot </mml:mtext>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> by the annual electrical energy output accommodated by the system <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m4880escdc">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mtext>served</mml:mtext>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. This relationship is succinctly captured in the mathematical expression for COE, presented as Eq. (4) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>].</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(4)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mpscv25b5g">
                    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mtext>ann </mml:mtext>
                          <mml:mtext> tot </mml:mtext>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mtext>prim </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mtext>prim </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p> where,</p><p>Lprim,AC: AC loads per year (kWh/year)</p><p>Lprim,DC: DC loads per year (kWh/year)</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Results and discussion</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Homer simulation results</title>
          
          <p>Utilizing the HOMER software, the simulation conducts an optimization process to ascertain the most efficacious configuration of the proposed system. The optimal system configuration, as determined by HOMER, favors an on-grid setup. The annual energy output produced by the system across five cities is delineated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_8">Table 8</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_8">
              <label>Table 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Total electric power production per year</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>City</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Production</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Amount of Production Power (kWh/year)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total Production</p><p>(kWh/year)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Semarang</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>102,528</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>952,947</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wind Turbines</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>45,771</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grid</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>804,647</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Yogyakarta</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>101,978</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>1,255,760</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wind Turbines</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>599,786</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grid</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>553,996</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Surabaya</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>101,468</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>976,729</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wind Turbines</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>94,641</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grid</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>780,620</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Jakarta</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>104,456</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>998,089</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wind Turbines</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>181,173</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grid</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>712,460</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Denpasar</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>102,096</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>1,360,195</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wind Turbines</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>770,987</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grid</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>487,112</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_9">
              <label>Table 9</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Electrical power consumption per year</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>City</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Consumption</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Amount of Power Consumption (kWh/year)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total Consumption</p><p>(kWh/year)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Semarang</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AC primary load</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>924,180</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>943,170</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grid sales</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18,990</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Yogyakarta</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AC primary load</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>924,180</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>1,143,912</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grid sales</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>219,732</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Surabaya</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AC primary load</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>924,180</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>958,797</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grid sales</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>34,617</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Jakarta</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AC primary load</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>924,180</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>991,486</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grid sales</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>67,306</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Denpasar</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AC primary load</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>924,180</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>1,214,136</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grid sales</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>289,956</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>The HOMER simulation additionally yielded results for the annual electricity load consumption for each city, as detailed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_9">Table 9</xref>.</p><p>Drawing from the data presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_8">Table 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_9">Table 9</xref>, it emerges that Denpasar City exhibits the most substantial potential, boasting the highest total electric power production at 1,360,195 kWh/year. Conversely, Semarang City demonstrates the least total power consumption, recorded at 943,170 kWh/year.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Npc</title>
          
          <p>The NPC serves as a financial metric to ascertain the cumulative expenditure associated with the establishment and operational maintenance of a power generation facility. The NPC encompasses a multitude of financial aspects within each system configuration, such as initial capital outlay, costs of component replacement, operations and maintenance (O&amp;amp;amp;M), fuel expenditures, and end-of-life salvage value [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]. The NPC figures play a pivotal role in evaluating the financial viability of each proposed system configuration; configurations with lower NPC values are indicative of greater economic potential. The simulation-derived NPC values for the various configurations under consideration are delineated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_10">Table 10</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_10">
              <label>Table 10</label>
              <caption>
                <title>NPC value</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >City</th><th >NPC (IDR)</th></tr><tr><td >Semarang</td><td >28,459,450,000.00</td></tr><tr><td >Yogyakarta</td><td >27,918,600,000.00</td></tr><tr><td >Surabaya</td><td >28,392,380,000.00</td></tr><tr><td >Jakarta</td><td >27,770,060,000.00</td></tr><tr><td >Denpasar</td><td >27,529,340,000.00</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>Based on the data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_10">Table 10</xref>, it can be concluded that the city with the highest potential is Denpasar City, with an NPC value of IDR 27,529,340,000.00.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Coe</title>
          
          <p>The COE represents the average monetary expense incurred for each kilowatt-hour of electricity generated by the system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>]. This metric is integral to gauging the economic efficiency of the system configurations devised. Optimal configurations are characterized by lower COE values, which denote a higher economic advantage. The simulation results yield the COE values for the respective configurations, which are systematically cataloged in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_11">Table 11</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_11">
              <label>Table 11</label>
              <caption>
                <title>COE value</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >City</th><th >COE (IDR)</th></tr><tr><td >Semarang</td><td >1,327.01</td></tr><tr><td >Yogyakarta</td><td >1,073.35</td></tr><tr><td >Surabaya</td><td >1,302.31</td></tr><tr><td >Jakarta</td><td >1,231.77</td></tr><tr><td >Denpasar</td><td >997.17</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>Based on the data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_11">Table 11</xref>, it can be concluded that the city with the most potential is Denpasar City, with a COE value of IDR 997.17.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.4. Bep</title>
          
          <p>The BEP delineates the juncture at which revenue equals the costs, signifying a neutral financial position wherein neither profit nor loss is realized over a specified duration. It is a critical measure for evaluating the financial viability of energy systems. A lower BEP suggests a swifter recovery of investment, indicating a system with enhanced economic potential. The BEP values derived from the HOMER-based simulation across the various cities are delineated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_12">Table 12</xref>, illustrating the comparative economic outcomes for each locale.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_12">
              <label>Table 12</label>
              <caption>
                <title>BEP value</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >City</th><th >Year of BEP Occurrence</th></tr><tr><td >Semarang</td><td >3.1</td></tr><tr><td >Yogyakarta</td><td >8.2</td></tr><tr><td >Surabaya</td><td >4.2</td></tr><tr><td >Jakarta</td><td >9.8</td></tr><tr><td >Denpasar</td><td >8.2</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>Based on the data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_12">Table 12</xref>, it can be concluded that the city with the most potential BEP value is Semarang City, with a BEP value of 3.1 years.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.5. Proposed system</title>
          
          <p>The outcomes of the HOMER software simulations have identified Denpasar as the city offering the most auspicious prospects for the PLTS configuration in government edifices. The optimization facilitated by the HOMER software enabled the ascertainment of the most favourable system configuration, which was determined by assessing various metrics including the total electrical energy generated, total electrical energy utilized, NPC, COE, and BEP. The monthly electrical output from the optimized system configuration is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>, whilst the cash flow projections for the proposed model, as simulated for Denpasar City, are exhibited in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_13">Table 13</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_8">
              <label>Figure 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Monthly electricity production using the proposed model</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/10/img_sh8Lax5yem3wj_h-.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_13">
              <label>Table 13</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Cash flow on the proposed system</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Components</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Capital</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Replacement</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>O&amp;amp;M</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Salvage</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bergey Excel 6-R</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 2,964,500,000.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 2,556,512,248.36</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 6,740,821,567.91</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR -1,847,707,607.68</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 10,414,126,208.60</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>KEHUA France KF-BCS 630K-B</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 1,139,966,366.24</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 4,083,398,945.89</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 2,541,284,238.72</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR -947,354,597.13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 6,817,294,953.73</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PLN</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 10,150,892,323.82</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 10,150,892,323.82</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Schneider Conext CL25000 E with generic PV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 44,910,377.72</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 102,119,360.01</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 147,029,737.74</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Systems</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 4,149,376,743.96</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 6,639,911,194.25</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 19,535,117,490.48</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR -2,795,062,204.80</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IDR 27,529,343,223.88</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Conclusion</title>
      <p>In this investigation, an evaluative comparison was conducted of on-grid hybrid PV-Wind Turbine PLTS tailored for governmental structures across five major Indonesian urban centers: Semarang, Yogyakarta, Surabaya, Jakarta, and Denpasar. Utilising the HOMER software, system configurations were simulated and optimized. The results indicate a superior efficiency and cost-effectiveness for the hybrid (PV/Wind) system over a standard PV system, given identical electrical loads.</p><p>It was revealed through modelling that the hybrid system, when connected to the grid, obviates the need for supplementary battery storage under standard operational parameters. Moreover, surplus renewable energy is seamlessly integrated into the grid. Pertinent metrics considered in the assessment of system design potential encompassed total electrical output, consumption figures, NPC, COE, and BEP.</p><p>The simulations executed via the HOMER software identified Denpasar as the city with the highest potential for the implementation of hybrid PV/Wind Turbine systems in government buildings. The findings demonstrate Denpasar's capability to generate 1,360,195 kWh/year, with total electricity consumption recorded at 1,214,136 kWh/year. The NPC was determined at approximately IDR 27,529,340,000.00, and the COE was ascertained at IDR 997.17, suggesting a viable investment with the BEP projected at 8.2 years. The estimated initial construction cost for the PLTS at government edifices in Denpasar stands at IDR 4,149,376,743.96.</p><p>It is envisaged that the outcomes of this study will contribute to the advancement of renewable energy utilization, notably in harnessing solar and wind energy. The innovation presented by this hybrid PLTS design is anticipated to facilitate a reduction in future investment costs for componentry. Consequently, such hybrid power generation systems are poised for escalated development in the ensuing years.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>176</volume>
          <page-range>106760</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lange</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pohl</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santarius</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2020.106760</pub-id>
          <article-title>Digitalization and energy consumption. Does ICT reduce energy demand?</article-title>
          <source>Ecological Economics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>82</volume>
          <page-range>102311</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krane</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Idel</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.erss.2021.102311</pub-id>
          <article-title>More transitions, less risk: How renewable energy reduces risks from mining, trade and political dependence</article-title>
          <source>Energy Research &amp;amp; Social Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>161</volume>
          <page-range>112279</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rahman</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farrok</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haque</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2022.112279</pub-id>
          <article-title>Environmental impact of renewable energy source based electrical power plants: Solar, wind, hydroelectric, biomass, geothermal, tidal, ocean, and osmotic</article-title>
          <source>Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>215-222</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rachmanto</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Regannanta</surname>
              <given-names>F. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ubaidillah</surname>
              <given-names/>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arifin</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Widhiyanuriyawan</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yohana</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijtdi.070305</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analysis development of public electric vehicle charging stations using on-grid solar power plants in Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Transport Development and Integration</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>169-175</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arifin</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosli</surname>
              <given-names>M. A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasojo</surname>
              <given-names>Y. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alfaiz</surname>
              <given-names>N. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mulyani</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijepm.080305</pub-id>
          <article-title>Economic feasibility investigation of on-grid and off-grid solar photovoltaic system installation in central Java</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Energy Prod. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <volume>2019</volume>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guangul</surname>
              <given-names>F. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chala</surname>
              <given-names>G. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ICBDSC.2019.8645580</pub-id>
          <article-title>Solar energy as renewable energy source: SWOT analysis</article-title>
          <source>2019 4th MEC International Conference on Big Data and Smart City (ICBDSC), Muscat, Oman</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>42</volume>
          <page-range>100886</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sadiq</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bashir</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shabbir</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.esr.2022.100886</pub-id>
          <article-title>The dynamic association between different strategies of renewable energy sources and sustainable economic growth under SDGs</article-title>
          <source>Energy Strategy Reviews</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>44</volume>
          <page-range>782-791</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pradhan</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matpr.2020.10.708</pub-id>
          <article-title>A review of recent advances and the role of nanofluid in solar photovoltaic thermal (PV/T) system</article-title>
          <source>Materials Today: Proceedings</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>282</volume>
          <page-range>125296</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chaitanya</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>N. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.125296</pub-id>
          <article-title>Solar thermal energy technologies and its applications for process heating and power generation – A review</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Cleaner Production</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>229</volume>
          <page-range>52-68</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lingayat</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balijepalli</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chandramohan</surname>
              <given-names>V.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.solener.2021.05.058</pub-id>
          <article-title>Applications of solar energy based drying technologies in various industries – A review</article-title>
          <source>Solar Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>100006</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dey</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sreenivasulu</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Veerendra</surname>
              <given-names>G. T. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rao</surname>
              <given-names>K. V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Babu</surname>
              <given-names>P. S. S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.igd.2022.100006</pub-id>
          <article-title>Renewable energy present status and future potentials in India: An overview</article-title>
          <source>Innovation and Green Development</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>52</volume>
          <page-range>102155</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pandiyan</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sitharthan</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saravanan</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prabaharan</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramji Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chinnadurai</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yuvaraj</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Devabalaji</surname>
              <given-names>K.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seta.2022.102155</pub-id>
          <article-title>A comprehensive review of the prospects for rural electrification using stand-alone and hybrid energy technologies</article-title>
          <source>Sustainable Energy Technologies and Assessments</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>52</volume>
          <page-range>102195</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nasser</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tamer  Megahed</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ookawara</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hassan</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seta.2022.102195</pub-id>
          <article-title>Techno-economic assessment of clean hydrogen production and storage using hybrid renewable energy system of PV/Wind under different climatic conditions</article-title>
          <source>Sustainable Energy Technologies and Assessments</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>812</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alam</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chowdhury</surname>
              <given-names>T. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhar</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Ismail</surname>
              <given-names>F. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choudhury</surname>
              <given-names>M. S. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shafiullah</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rahman</surname>
              <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en16020812</pub-id>
          <article-title>Solar and wind energy integrated system frequency control: A critical review on recent developments</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>998</volume>
          <page-range>012052</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gunawan</surname>
              <given-names>F. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Budiman</surname>
              <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pardamean</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Djuana</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Romeli</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hananda</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harito</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aji</surname>
              <given-names>D. P. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Putri</surname>
              <given-names>D. N. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stevanus</surname>
              <given-names/>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1755-1315/998/1/012052</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design and energy assessment of a new hybrid solar drying dome-enabling low-cost, independent and smart solar dryer for Indonesia agriculture 4.0</article-title>
          <source>IOP Conference Series: Earth and Environmental Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>244-253</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Putra</surname>
              <given-names>M. G. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zamani</surname>
              <given-names>N. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nyoman Metta  Natih</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yuliardi</surname>
              <given-names>A. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24843/jmas.2022.v08.i02.p09</pub-id>
          <article-title>Potensi sumber dan sebaran sampah laut di ekosistem terumbu karang perairan pulau kelapa, pulau kelapa dua, dan pulau harapan, DKI jakarta</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Marine and Aquatic Sciences</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>055011</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nyenah</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sterl</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thiery</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/2515-7620/ac71fb</pub-id>
          <article-title>Pieces of a puzzle: Solar-wind power synergies on seasonal and diurnal timescales tend to be excellent worldwide</article-title>
          <source>Environmental Research Communications</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>162</volume>
          <page-range>112480</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jin</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jia</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2022.112480</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessment of climate change impacts on the hydro-wind-solar energy supply system</article-title>
          <source>Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>811-818</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tjahjana</surname>
              <given-names>D. D. D. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suyitno</surname>
              <given-names/>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rachmanto</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Juwana</surname>
              <given-names>W. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasojo</surname>
              <given-names>Y. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arifin</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijdne.180407</pub-id>
          <article-title>Economic feasibility of a PV-wind hybrid microgrid system for off-grid electrification in Papua, Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Design &amp;amp; Nature and Ecodynamics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>43–49</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nababan</surname>
              <given-names>W. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sihombing</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peranginangin</surname>
              <given-names>S. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Napitupulu</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36655/sprocket.v5i1.1197</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analisis tekno ekonomi atap surya studi kasus di kota medan, Indonesia</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>185-194</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Putra</surname>
              <given-names>I. W. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumara</surname>
              <given-names>I. N. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hartati</surname>
              <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24843/mite.2022.v21i02.p05</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analisis tekno ekonomi implementasi sistem PLTS atap pada gedung kantor walikota denpasar</article-title>
          <source>Majalah Ilmiah Teknologi Elektro</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>55</volume>
          <page-range>477-483</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arifin</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tjahjana</surname>
              <given-names>D. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Danardono</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muqoffa</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alfaiz</surname>
              <given-names>N. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanusi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/jesa.550406</pub-id>
          <article-title>Grid-connected hybrid PV-wind system simulation in urban Java</article-title>
          <source>Journal Européen des Systèmes Automatisés</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>56</volume>
          <page-range>519-527</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Juwana</surname>
              <given-names>W. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rachmanto</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alfaiz</surname>
              <given-names>N. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arifin</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/jesa.560401</pub-id>
          <article-title>Economic analysis of PV-generator hybrid off-grid systems in underdeveloped Indonesian regions</article-title>
          <source>Journal Européen des Systèmes Automatisés</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>2967-2973</page-range>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rachmanto</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Juwana</surname>
              <given-names>W. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akbar</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasetyo</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bangun</surname>
              <given-names>W. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arifin</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijsdp.180935</pub-id>
          <article-title>Economic analysis of on-grid photovoltaic-generator hybrid energy systems for rural electrification in Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Sustainable Development and Planning</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>47</volume>
          <page-range>S110-S115</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khalil</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liaquat Bhatti</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arslan Iqbal Awan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riaz</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khalil</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alwaz</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matpr.2020.06.054</pub-id>
          <article-title>Optimization and designing of hybrid power system using HOMER pro</article-title>
          <source>Materials Today: Proceedings</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>170-178</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Giyatno</surname>
              <given-names>D. W. F. S. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Subekti</surname>
              <given-names>L. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pradana</surname>
              <given-names>A. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nurmawati</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wibowo</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22146/teknosains.46109</pub-id>
          <article-title>Optimalisasi kapasitas energi angin dan matahari dengan konfigurasi mikrogrid berdasarkan karakteristik beban</article-title>
          <source>Jurnal Teknosains</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>41-47</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Widianto</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santoso</surname>
              <given-names>D. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kardiman</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fauji</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30595/jrst.v3i1.3653</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analisis potensi pembangkit listrik tenaga photovoltaicwind turbines di pantai sedari karawang</article-title>
          <source>JRST (Jurnal Riset Sains dan Teknologi)</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>18-29</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prahastono</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Setiawan</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilopo</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Perancangan pemanfaatan energi baru terbarukan berbasis tenaga hibrida untuk meningkatkan rasio elektrifikasi (studi kasus: Kecamatan tulakan, kabupaten pacitan)</article-title>
          <source>J. Electron., Sci. Energy Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>94–98</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akbar</surname>
              <given-names>D. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gumilang</surname>
              <given-names>B. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zuroida</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33795/elposys.v10i1.1384</pub-id>
          <article-title>Studi potensi pengembangan pembangkit listrik hybrid genset-PV di wilayah pesisir kabupaten malang</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>1029–1037</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sinaga</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hermawan</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nugroho</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14710/transient.v4i4.1029-1037</pub-id>
          <article-title>Optimasi sistem pembangkit listrik hibrida tenaga surya, angin, biomassa, dan diesel di pulau nyamuk karimunjawa jawa tengah dengan menggunakan perangkat lunak HOMER</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abdullah</surname>
              <given-names>A. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wasri Hasanah</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Perencanaan pembangunan sistem pembangkit listrik tenaga bayu off grid 1200w untuk penerangan lampu taman kampus institut teknologi-PLN</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <publisher-name>INSTITUT TEKNOLOGI PLN</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>67–72</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Asri</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kananda</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30736/je.v3i2.253</pub-id>
          <article-title>Desain dan analisa kelayakan PV-diesel-grid sistem hibrid di institut teknologi sumatera (ITERA)</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>29–35</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zulni</surname>
              <given-names>M. Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.57152/ijeere.v3i1.475</pub-id>
          <article-title>Planning on solar power plant 900 Va power grid using micropower homer household application</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>154-160</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sari</surname>
              <given-names>D. A. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wijaya</surname>
              <given-names>F. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>H. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22146/jnteti.v11i2.3849</pub-id>
          <article-title>Optimasi sistem pembangkit listrik tenaga hybrid di pulau enggano</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>33-46</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huda</surname>
              <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurniawan</surname>
              <given-names>I. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30595/jrre.v5i1.14708</pub-id>
          <article-title>Perancangan sistem pembangkit listrik tenaga hibrida (tenaga angin dan tenaga surya) di daerah widuri kabupaten pemalang menggunakan perangkat lunak homer</article-title>
          <source>Jurnal Riset Rekayasa Elektro</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>