<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Sustainability for Energy</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Sustain. Energy</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JSE</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2958-1915</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-1907</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-KoKxcOatXTSGkhqHie-KNKKFDSnomYjH</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jse040103</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Performance Evaluation of a Locally Assembled Split-Unit Air Conditioning System Using Indigenous Components for Residential Cooling Efficiency</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9069-9676</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ikpe</surname>
            <given-names>Aniekan Essienubong</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>aniekan.ikpe@akwaibompoly.edu.ng</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8973-9260</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ekanem</surname>
            <given-names>Imoh Ime</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>imoh.ekanem@akwaibompoly.edu.ng</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0864-9974</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Udoh</surname>
            <given-names>Victor Etok</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>victor.udoh@akwaibompoly.edu.ng</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Mechanical Engineering Technology, Akwa Ibom State Polytechnic, PMB. 1200 Ikot Ekpene, Nigeria</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Department of Welding and Fabrication Engineering Technology, Akwa Ibom State Polytechnic, PMB. 1200 Ikot Ekpene, Nigeria</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>03</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>34</fpage>
      <lpage>47</lpage>
      <page-range>34-47</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>01</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>02</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>The growing reliance on air conditioning (AC) systems in residential and commercial buildings has led to significant increases in energy consumption and associated greenhouse gas emissions, underscoring the need for cost-effective and sustainable cooling technologies. In this study, the feasibility and performance of a 1-horsepower (1 HP) non-inverter split-unit AC system assembled entirely from locally sourced components were evaluated under controlled residential conditions. Essential parts, including copper tubing, aluminum fins, compressor units, and refrigerant gases, were procured from regional suppliers and integrated following standard Heating, Ventilation, and Air Conditioning (HVAC) design protocols. Performance tests were conducted across five rooms in a residential apartment-comprising a lounge (largest), masters bedroom, and three additional bedrooms of decreasing size-to assess cooling effectiveness. Using an infrared thermometer (IR8895), temperature metrics including saturation temperature, cooling rate, and peak cooling temperature were recorded. Initial room temperatures ranged from 23.5${ }^{\circ} \mathrm{C}$ to 26.2${ }^{\circ} \mathrm{C}$, while final cooling temperatures ranged from 16.1${ }^{\circ} \mathrm{C}$ to 16.9${ }^{\circ} \mathrm{C}$. Cooling time increased progressively with room size, extending from 10 to 100 minutes. Corresponding saturation temperatures were observed at 24.9${ }^{\circ} \mathrm{C}$ to 26.6${ }^{\circ} \mathrm{C}$, with saturation times between 3.24 and 5.43 minutes, and peak temperatures consistent with the final cooling levels. Calculated cooling loads were 28.8 W (small rooms), 47.0 W (medium rooms), and 65.93 W (large rooms), with respective power consumption values of 85.5 W, 142.6 W, and 199.6 W. The Energy Efficiency Ratio (EER) and Coefficient of Performance (COP) were determined to be 9.25 and 2.7, respectively, across room types. The results indicated that the locally assembled split-unit AC system delivered competitive cooling performance relative to commercial equivalents, particularly in terms of thermal regulation, response time, and energy efficiency. The use of indigenous materials and components did not compromise operational reliability or compliance with HVAC standards. These findings support the viability of locally fabricated AC systems as a sustainable alternative for effective residential cooling in resource-constrained settings.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Split-unit air conditioner</kwd>
        <kwd>Local sourcing</kwd>
        <kwd>Energy efficiency</kwd>
        <kwd>Thermal performance</kwd>
        <kwd>Sustainable cooling</kwd>
        <kwd>Indigenous assembly</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="3"/>
        <fig-count count="11"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <ref-count count="33"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Assembling and testing of split unit AC systems using locally sourced materials is a critical aspect of the HVAC industry. This process involves the construction and evaluation of AC units often used in residential and commercial buildings. These are a type of HVAC system that consists of two main components: an indoor unit (IU) and an outdoor unit (OU). The IU is typically installed inside the building, while the OU is placed outside [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]. These two units are connected by refrigerant lines, which allow for the transfer of heat from the indoor space to the outdoor environment. Assembling and testing of split unit AC systems involve the construction and evaluation of these components to ensure proper functioning and efficiency. The process of assembling a split unit AC system using locally sourced materials begins with the selection of high-quality components such as compressors, condensers, evaporators, and refrigerant lines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. These materials are then assembled according to the manufacturer's specifications to create the indoor and outdoor units (IOUs). Once the units are assembled, they are connected by refrigerant lines and electrical wiring to complete the system. These systems are often more affordable than central AC systems, rendering them a desired choice for homeowners and businesses on a budget. Additionally, locally assembled split unit AC systems do not require complex installation and maintenance, as the overall cost is quite affordable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. These systems are designed to cool specific areas or rooms, rather than the entire building, which can lead to significant energy savings. By only cooling the spaces that are in use, locally assembled split unit AC systems help reduce energy waste and lower utility bills. However, locally assembled split unit AC systems also have some drawbacks. One potential issue is the noise generated by the OU, which can be disruptive in residential areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. Additionally, these systems may not be as effective in cooling large spaces or multiple rooms, as they are designed for more localized cooling.</p><p>Locally assembled split unit AC systems offer a cost-effective and energy-efficient cooling solution for many homeowners and businesses. While they may have some drawbacks, such as noise and limited cooling capacity, their affordability and ease of installation make them a popular choice in many regions. One of the primary issues is the lack of availability of high-quality materials that meet the required standards for the construction of AC systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. Locally sourced materials may not always meet the necessary specifications for durability, efficiency, and safety, leading to potential malfunctions and breakdowns in the system. This can result in increased maintenance costs, reduced energy efficiency, and decreased overall performance of the AC unit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>]. Furthermore, the lack of standardized testing procedures for locally assembled AC systems poses a significant challenge. Without proper testing protocols in place, it is difficult to ensure that the system functions optimally and meets the required performance standards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. This can lead to inconsistencies in the performance of the AC unit, as well as potential safety hazards for users. Additionally, the lack of technical expertise and training in assembling and testing AC systems using locally sourced materials is a major concern. Without proper training and knowledge, technicians may not be able to effectively troubleshoot and address issues that arise during the assembly and testing process. This can result in delays, errors, and inefficiencies in the construction of the AC system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>].</p><p>The assembling and testing of split unit AC systems using locally sourced materials is a technically challenging process that must be addressed carefully. By addressing the issues outlined in this problem statement, indigenous companies can work towards developing solutions that improve the quality, efficiency, and reliability of locally assembled AC systems. The primary technological innovation presented in this study lies in the design and assembly of locally sourced components for split unit AC systems. Unlike conventional systems that rely heavily on imported parts, the locally assembled units leverage indigenous materials and technologies, thus reducing the carbon footprint associated with transportation and manufacturing. This approach not only enhances local economies but also fosters a sense of ownership and responsibility towards sustainable practices within communities. The main objectives of this study are to investigate the potential of utilizing indigenous resources for achieving sustainable cooling solutions, to demonstrate the effectiveness of locally sourced materials in the assembly and testing of split unit AC systems and to evaluate the performance of the assembled split unit AC system through standard testing procedures.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Materials and methods</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Materials for the split unit ac system</title>
          
          <p>The procedure adopted for selecting appropriate materials for the assembly of split unit AC systems included the following:</p><p>i. Identify the required components</p><p>ii. Evaluate material compatibility</p><p>iii. Assemble the identified components</p><p>iv. Conduct performance testing</p><p>v. Finalize material selection</p><p>Split unit AC systems are widely used in both residential and commercial settings to provide cooling and comfort. These systems comprise a number of components that synergize to cool the air and maintain a comfortable indoor environment. Some of the key components include expansion valve, capillary tube line, Copper $3 / 4<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m9gnkfec7c">
    <mml:merror data-mjx-error="Misplaced &amp;amp;">
      <mml:mtext>Misplaced &amp;amp;</mml:mtext>
    </mml:merror>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>1 / 4$ nobs, water drain tray, evaporator coil, air dust filter, air return, evaporator fan, air swing blade, air swing electric motor, fan blade, remote sensor detector, power park panel, fan capacitor, display indicator, thermostat, indoor to outdoor wire, water drainage rain hoses, high pressure pipes, low pressure pipes, pipe amoflex, indoor brackets, power cord cable, cooling sensor, fan mounting rubber, flaring pipe, fan bracket, coarse filter, motor fan, horizontal flaps, compressor, condenser, cooling fan, air filter, condensation drain, evaporator coil, motor fan, refrigerant, air blower, condensing coil, drainage tray, control board, vertical deflectors, outer case and front panel.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Research methodology</title>
          
          <p>The procedure adopted for selecting appropriate materials for the assembly of split unit AC systems included the following:</p><p>i. Identify the required components</p><p>ii. Evaluate material compatibility</p><p>iii. Assemble the identified components</p><p>iv. Conduct performance testing</p><p>v. Finalize material selection</p><p>Split unit AC systems are widely used in both residential and commercial settings to provide cooling and comfort. These systems comprise a number of components that synergize to cool the air and maintain a comfortable indoor environment. Some of the key components include expansion valve, capillary tube line, Copper $3 / 4<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mb18bdfv3k">
    <mml:merror data-mjx-error="Misplaced &amp;amp;">
      <mml:mtext>Misplaced &amp;amp;</mml:mtext>
    </mml:merror>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>1 / 4$ nobs, water drain tray, evaporator coil, air dust filter, air return, evaporator fan, air swing blade, air swing electric motor, fan blade, remote sensor detector, power park panel, fan capacitor, display indicator, thermostat, indoor to outdoor wire, water drainage rain hoses, high pressure pipes, low pressure pipes, pipe amoflex, indoor brackets, power cord cable, cooling sensor, fan mounting rubber, flaring pipe, fan bracket, coarse filter, motor fan, horizontal flaps, compressor, condenser, cooling fan, air filter, condensation drain, evaporator coil, motor fan, refrigerant, air blower, condensing coil, drainage tray, control board, vertical deflectors, outer case and front panel.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Installation procedure for split unit ac systems</title>
          
          <p>A detailed procedure that was adopted during the installation process of split unit AC systems are as follows:</p><p>i. Site Survey and Preparation: Before beginning the installation process, conduct a thorough site survey to ascertain adequate location for the IOUs. Ensure that there is sufficient space for proper airflow and access for maintenance. Clear any obstacles that may obstruct the installation process.</p><p>ii. Mounting the IU: Start by mounting the IU on the wall at a height of at least 7 feet above the floor. Use a level to ensure that the unit is mounted evenly. Make sure to leave enough space around the unit for proper airflow and maintenance access.</p><p>iii. Installing the Refrigerant Lines: Next, connect the refrigerant lines from the IU to the OU. Use insulated copper tubing to prevent heat loss and ensure efficient cooling. Make sure to properly flare and connect the tubing to prevent leaks.</p><p>iv. Electrical Wiring: Connect the electrical wiring from the IU to the OU, following the manufacturer's instructions. Ensure that the wiring is properly grounded and insulated to prevent electrical hazards. Test the electrical connections to ensure they are secure.</p><p>v. Mounting the OU: Mount the OU on a stable surface, such as a concrete pad or mounting brackets. Make sure the unit is level and secure to prevent vibration and noise. Ensure that there is proper clearance around the unit for airflow and maintenance.</p><p>vi. Refrigerant Charging: Once the IOUs are properly installed and connected, it is time to charge the system with refrigerant. Use a manifold gauge set to measure and adjust the refrigerant levels according to the manufacturer's specifications. Proper refrigerant charging is essential for optimal cooling performance.</p><p>vii. Testing and Commissioning: After completing the installation process, test the system to ensure it is functioning properly. Check for any leaks in the refrigerant lines and ensure that all electrical connections are secure. Test the cooling performance of the system in different operating modes to verify proper operation.</p><p>Proper installation of split unit AC systems is essential for optimal performance and longevity. By following this comprehensive procedure, HVAC professionals can ensure a successful installation that meets industry standards and manufacturer specifications. Adhering to best practices in installation will result in a reliable and efficient cooling system for residential and commercial spaces.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Infrared thermometer ir 8895</title>
          
          <p>This device, which has a high level of accuracy, works seamlessly in the measurement of non-contact temperature (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>). Technical details for the infrared temperature measuring device are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>. The device is primarily employed in capturing the surface temperature of mobile objects, particularly those that are challenging to access [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. To achieve optimal measuring output, the IR device is equipped with a laser pointer that accurately focuses on the measuring point. There is room for adjusting the emissivity in order to prevent error-prone results. A variety of distinct materials as well as their corresponding emission levels are provided in the user guide for effective operation. The infrared thermometer IR 8895 is ergonomically designed with simplified principles of operation and features an intuitive button interface, with temperature results presented either in Celsius or Fahrenheit. The measuring instrument features a hold mode to promptly retain the measured results. Moreover, the portable case that comes with the infrared temperature measurement gadget includes a protective pouch [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>].</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Technical details of the handheld infrared temperature measuring device</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_Tx6bNTxKe8esAbrk.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Dimensions of rooms where the assembled AC unit was tested on</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >Rooms</th><th >Length</th><th >Breath</th><th >Height</th></tr><tr><td >Lounge</td><td >4.440</td><td >4.200</td><td >3.00</td></tr><tr><td >Masters Room</td><td >3.840</td><td >4.250</td><td >3.00</td></tr><tr><td >Room 2</td><td >3.600</td><td >3.100</td><td >3.00</td></tr><tr><td >Room 3</td><td >3.290</td><td >3.200</td><td >3.00</td></tr><tr><td >Room 4</td><td >3.190</td><td >2.690</td><td >3.00</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> is an illustration of the plan view of the building that the locally assembled split unit AC system was tested on. From the illustration, the building consisted of the lounge, which had the highest dimension and size, followed by the Masters Room, Room 2, Room 3 and Room 4, which had the smallest size in the category.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Building plan that the locally assembled split unit AC system was tested on</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_uTLXxOD0VwnKBqgm.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Theoretical framework based on thermodynamic equations of split unit ac</title>
      <p>Split unit AC systems rely on mathematical formulas and thermodynamic equations to operate effectively and provide optimal cooling comfort. One of such mathematical formulas used in split unit AC systems is the heat transfer equation, which is based on the first law of thermodynamics. This equation is used to calculate the amount of heat absorbed by the evaporator coil and the amount of heat rejected by the condenser coil. Another one is the refrigeration cycle equation, which describes the process by which refrigerant absorbs heat via indoor air and releases it to the outdoor air. This equation is based on the second law of thermodynamics and includes terms such as enthalpy, entropy, and temperature to calculate the efficiency of the refrigeration cycle. Some common mathematical equations related to split AC units are as follows:</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Latent heat loads</title>
          
          <p>One of the most effective techniques for dehumidification is cooling the air below its dew point, therefore, 100\% saturation. The latent heat to be extracted is given by Eq. (1):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <mml:math id="ml57wm8jvp">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p> where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mad0jylbb9">
    <mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Cooling energy, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myz1ilwd63">
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Mass flow rate of air, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mhkvw9lxac">
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Latent heat of vaporization of water, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mqvt5pyjwl">
    <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Moisture content of air.</p><p>Moisture content present in the air must be extracted in order to achieve the humidity requirements. This is given by Eq. (2):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(2)</label>
              <mml:math id="mh6woti4oq">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                  <mml:mn>840</mml:mn>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p> where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mrhijt2bsg">
    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Air circulation flow, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mwdpl0yy3x">
    <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Outside moisture content of air and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mwt12i5q27">
    <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Inside moisture content of air.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Heat loss by conduction</title>
          
          <p>The method for calculating heat loss in the cooling process is by conduction, determined by Eq. (3):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(3)</label>
              <mml:math id="m83abmhlig">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p> where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mt5f8soiq0">
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Thermal conductivity of materials, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mjrzk10k9e">
    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Area, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mzu5ilnggo">
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Average temperature difference across the material, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m2zjvoxws0">
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Thickness of a wall of some material. Substances with higher specific heats require more heat energy to lower temperature than do substances with a low specific heat. Therefore, the heat energy required to lower the air temperature is given by Eq. (4):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(4)</label>
              <mml:math id="mjcg9asu2x">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p> where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mihbp5dcts">
    <mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Heat energy needed, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mb0t5vrbot">
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Mass of a substance, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mqgyrgr3w1">
    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> Specific heat of air, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mh0c6s4647">
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> $=$ Dry Bulb temperature of air change.</p><p>The exergy input into the split unit AC unit in the form of electric energy transfer to the electric motor of the compressor is determined via Eq. (5).</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(5)</label>
              <mml:math id="m7qdd3bnsy">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msup>
                    <mml:mn>10</mml:mn>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msup>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>Or, as a percentage of the exergy that is transferred to the split unit AC unit is given by Eq. (6):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(6)</label>
              <mml:math id="myh778rmk8">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p> where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mx6q978png">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mtext>beg </mml:mtext>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m2ebvlpwtq">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mtext>end </mml:mtext>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> are values of the specific exergy of the refrigerant at the beginning and end of the split unit AC cooling cycle. Exegetic balance of the one-stage compressor of the split unit AC for $1 {~kg} / {s}$ flow of a circulating working refrigerant is given by Eq. (7):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(7)</label>
              <mml:math id="myxkkfgy4j">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>Or as a percentage of <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m5wxl7azie">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(8)</label>
              <mml:math id="mzksv7y8hc">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mkzud39l90">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the specific exergy transfer to the split unit <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mfdi6vm7xs">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">AC</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m897xlve2n">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the quantity of the specific exergy going out of the split unit <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mb8anznfdk">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">AC</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the total losses of specific exergy in all component of the AC unit, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mp876w9cy7">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mtext>in </mml:mtext>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mtext>out </mml:mtext>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> are exergy of the split unit AC , which is spent in maintaining the cooling process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>]. Exergy loss in the AC comprises losses of exergy in the compressor, due to the irreversible heat transfer in the condenser, the capillary tube (throttle) and the losses of exergy in the evaporator, which are represented by Eq. (9) or (10):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(9)</label>
              <mml:math id="mwco8gfxxm">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msubsup>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(10)</label>
              <mml:math id="mk0ckxcpyt">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msubsup>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p> where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mmuaxxy4ul">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mja5fzmkn1">
    <mml:msubsup>
      <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
          <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
          <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msubsup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mstj15z4o0">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="muf6dkov9d">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> are exergy losses in the compressor, condenser, capillary tube as well as the evaporator.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Energy analysis</title>
          
          <p>To determine the cooling capacity, actual load, power consumption and COP of a locally assembled 1HP split unit AC, an outside temperature of 28<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="max02qcist">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mrow/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>∘</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> was measured using the handheld infrared temperature measuring device shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>. Considering that cooling load is a function of room sizes, insulation as well as heat sources, part load ratio (PLR) of 0.3, 0.5 and 0.7 were considered for small, medium and large rooms. In this case, Rooms 3 and 4 were considered as small rooms, Room 2 and Masters Room were considered as medium rooms, while the Lounge was considered as a large room. These considerations were based on the dimensions of the rooms presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>Since the 1HP split unit AC used in this study has a cooling capacity of about 9000BTU/hr, converting BTU/hr to watts yields:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(11)</label>
              <mml:math id="m8it8lwkv3">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mn>9000</mml:mn>
                  <mml:mn>2637</mml:mn>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>U</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>The cooling capacity of the AC unit is 2637 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m2i7sqxaux">
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. To determine the actual cooling load (ACL), Eq. (12) was employed:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(12)</label>
              <mml:math id="m3sk41zk8j">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mtext> Actual cooling loading </mml:mtext>
                  <mml:mtext> Part Load Ratio </mml:mtext>
                  <mml:mtext> Cooling Capacity </mml:mtext>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>÷</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mtext>outside </mml:mtext>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>Applying Eq. (12), for small, medium and large rooms yielded the following ACLs:</p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mkrccj577t">
    <mml:mtext> ACL for small rooms </mml:mtext>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>÷</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0.3</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>2637</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>28</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>28.3</mml:mn>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mtext> </mml:mtext>
      <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mvr1hhwzrq">
    <mml:mtext> ACL for medium rooms </mml:mtext>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>÷</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>2637</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>28</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>47</mml:mn>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mtext> </mml:mtext>
      <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="msyaybcvzd">
    <mml:mtext> ACL for large room </mml:mtext>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>÷</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>2637</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>28</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>65.93</mml:mn>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mtext> </mml:mtext>
      <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mlzc1ur9de">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mtext>outside </mml:mtext>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the outside temperature, which was measured at $28^{\circ} \mathrm{C}$, which is the average annual temperature in Nigeria. To determine power consumed by the split AC unit, Eq. (13) was considered:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(13)</label>
              <mml:math id="mixzzgs4hb">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mtext> Power consumption </mml:mtext>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:mtext> Cooling load </mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, EER is the Energy Efficiency Ratio.</p><p>Considering that the 1HP non-inverter split unit AC had an EER of 9.25, power consumptions (PC) for small, medium and large rooms were determined as:</p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m09unmdezu">
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
    <mml:mtext> for small rooms </mml:mtext>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mfrac>
      <mml:mn>791</mml:mn>
      <mml:mn>9.25</mml:mn>
    </mml:mfrac>
    <mml:mn>85.5</mml:mn>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mtext> </mml:mtext>
      <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mg1kpultoq">
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
    <mml:mtext> for medium rooms </mml:mtext>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mfrac>
      <mml:mn>1319</mml:mn>
      <mml:mn>9.25</mml:mn>
    </mml:mfrac>
    <mml:mn>142.6</mml:mn>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mtext> </mml:mtext>
      <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="me7napgei9">
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
    <mml:mtext> for large room </mml:mtext>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mfrac>
      <mml:mn>1846</mml:mn>
      <mml:mn>9.25</mml:mn>
    </mml:mfrac>
    <mml:mn>199.6</mml:mn>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mtext> </mml:mtext>
      <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p>To determine the COP of the split AC unit, Eq. (14) was applied:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(14)</label>
              <mml:math id="mqz3801bd1">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mn>3.412</mml:mn>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mhus03f0yw">
    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mfrac>
      <mml:mn>9.25</mml:mn>
      <mml:mn>3.412</mml:mn>
    </mml:mfrac>
    <mml:mn>2.7</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p>where 3.412 is a conversion factor from Watts to British Thermal Unit (BTU).</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Results and discussions</title>
      
        <fig id="fig_3">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Lounge cooling temperature and cooling time at different testing intervals</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_iUaBqgXFKuXOJLCQ.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_4">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Masters room cooling temperature and cooling time at different testing intervals</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_cJYRcGSU2wSNzg_Z.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>Testing a locally assembled split AC unit in an apartment requires a detailed process that involves several steps that must be followed carefully to evaluate the performance and efficiency of the unit. The necessary equipment and tools were prepared for the testing exercise. Additionally, it was ensured that the apartment is airtight, although not with 100% certainty, while also ensuring a stable temperature and humidity level to provide consistent testing conditions. The room temperature prior to commencement of the testing was measured using an infrared thermometer, IR 8895 model. The split AC unit was installed following the procedure outlined earlier in the methodology. It was ensured that the unit was securely mounted and connected to the power source, while checking for leaks or damages in the installation process to prevent any inaccuracies in the test results. The installation was carried out in specified rooms based the sizes and dimensions specified in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>. The split AC unit was turned on and allowed to run for a specified period to stabilize the temperature in the apartment. Using an infrared thermometer, the temperature was measured at different locations in the room to ensure uniform cooling. A constant split unit AC temperature of $16^{\circ} \mathrm{C}$ was maintained throughout the testing process. It was ensured that the time it took for the split unit to reach the desired temperature was measured and recorded [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]. Data collected from the testing process were properly compiled and analysed. The data was analysed via the Microsoft Excel package, 2022 version. The analysed data, which focused mainly on the split unit cooling temperature and cooling time, are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref> respectively. The cooling temperature refers to the temperature at which the system is set to cool the air, while the cooling time refers to the amount of time it takes for the system to reach the desired temperature. From the plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>, it took the assembled split AC unit a longer time interval to cool a bigger/larger room than a smaller room with the same AC conditions. For proper understanding of this occurrence, it is significant to acquire the basic principles of thermodynamics that govern the operation of an AC unit. The cooling process in an AC unit involves the transfer of heat from the indoor environment to the outdoor environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]. This transfer of heat is achieved via the refrigeration cycle, which is described in the following sequence: Absorption of available heat within the room by the evaporator coil and dispensing to the refrigerant, which flows directly to the compressor, for further compression into liquid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>]. The liquid is conveyed to the condenser coil, where the available heat is dissipated to the environment via the effect of ambient cooling, and the motor fan, while the gaseous state is maintained again. The warm liquid refrigerant travels to the expansion valve, where it is de-pressurized and further cooled to a low temperature. The cooled low-pressure liquid travels to the evaporator coil, via the air blower to cause cooling of the room. The process is repeated as long as the AC unit is on, and the cooled air continues to circulate in the room, providing comfort to the users.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_5">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Room 2 cooling temperature and cooling time at different testing intervals</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_MVtc6WvpowIY9iQ3.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_6">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Room 3 cooling temperature and cooling time at different testing intervals</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_Bbq339mxoSiDi9vj.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>Thermodynamically, the reason why the assembled split AC unit took a longer time interval to cool bigger/larger rooms than smaller rooms could be attributed to factors such as the size of the room and insulation of the room. In the smaller rooms (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>), the AC unit was able to cool the space more quickly because the volume of air that needed to be cooled is relatively small. This means that the AC unit can effectively remove the heat from the room and maintain a comfortable temperature in a shorter period of time. However, in the larger rooms (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref>), the volume of air that needed to be cooled was significantly higher, which posed a challenge for the AC unit to effectively remove heat from the space. The size of the room also affected the air circulation within the space. In a smaller room (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>}), the air circulation is more efficient, allowing the cooled air to spread evenly throughout the space. This resulted in a quicker cooling process as the temperature is more evenly distributed. On the other hand, in a larger room (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref>), the air circulation may have been less efficient, leading to pockets of warm air that took longer to cool down. This uneven distribution of temperature prolonged the cooling process in the larger rooms. The insulation of the room played a crucial role in the cooling process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>]. In a smaller room with good insulation, the heat transfer between the indoor and outdoor environments is minimized, allowing the AC unit to cool the space more efficiently. However, in a larger room with poor insulation, the heat transfer is more significant, requiring the AC unit to work harder to maintain a comfortable temperature. This increased workload results in a longer time interval to cool a larger room compared to a smaller room. The thermodynamic principles governing the operation of a split AC unit provide a compelling explanation for why it takes a longer time interval to cool a bigger/larger room than a smaller room. Factors such as the volume of air, air circulation, and insulation of the room all contribute to the efficiency of the cooling process. By understanding these principles. The performance of AC units in different room sizes can be optimized to achieve optimal cooling efficiency.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_7">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Room 4 cooling temperature and cooling time at different testing intervals</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_xEnYrTbbKd8xQk4m.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Saturation temperature and time</title>
          
          <p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref> is a graphical representation of room saturation temperature and saturation time. The plot illustrates that rooms of small sizes and dimensions (such as rooms 3 and 4) exhibit lower saturation temperatures, which implies rapid cooling at shorter time durations. On the other hand, larger rooms, particularly the lounge and master’s room, exhibit increased saturation temperature at a slightly higher time duration, which implies that there may be a delay in the cooling processes of the room. </p>
          
            <fig id="fig_8">
              <label>Figure 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Plot of room saturation temperature and saturation time</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_m-i8uVdW1WWj7Hd4.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>In terms of energy efficiency, room saturation temperature is important for preventing overcooling and reducing energy consumption, while room peak temperature is crucial for ensuring that the AC system operates efficiently and effectively. In the context of split unit AC systems, saturation temperature is a critical parameter that determines the refrigerant's state within the system. By controlling the saturation temperature, the system can effectively regulate the cooling capacity and maintain a consistent temperature output. Room cooling saturation temperature is a critical parameter in the operation of split unit AC systems. It refers to the temperature at which the refrigerant in the evaporator coil reaches a state of saturation, where it exists as a mixture of liquid and vapour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>]. This temperature is directly related to the cooling capacity of the AC system and plays a key role in determining the efficiency and performance of the system. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>, the saturation temperature can be observed as a key point where the cooling process begins to take effect. As the room temperature rises above the set point on the thermostat, the AC system activates and begins to cool the room by circulating refrigerant through the evaporator coil. As the refrigerant absorbs heat from the room air, it undergoes a phase change from liquid to vapour, reaching its saturation temperature in the process. The saturation temperature is a critical parameter because it represents the point at which the refrigerant is able to absorb the maximum amount of heat from the room air [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>]. This is important for ensuring that the room is cooled efficiently and effectively, as any deviation from the saturation temperature can result in reduced cooling capacity and decreased performance of the AC system. By monitoring the room cooling temperature and cooling time in a split unit AC system, it is possible to optimize the operation of the system and ensure that the room is cooled to the desired temperature in a timely manner. Moreover, by maintaining the saturation temperature within the optimal range, it is possible to achieve maximum cooling efficiency and performance, resulting in a comfortable indoor environment for occupants.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Peak temperature and time</title>
          
          <p>Similar to the case of saturated temperature and time in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>, rooms with small sizes and dimensions quickly attended the lowest peak temperature at the shortest time interval, which implies efficient cooling as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref>. However, rooms with larger sizes were observed to approach the peak temperature with prolonged time interval.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_9">
              <label>Figure 9</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Plot of room peak temperature and peak temperature duration</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_wccvqVG_0fagdAGv.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>On the other hand, peak temperature refers to the highest temperature reached within the system during operation. In other words, it is the highest temperature reached in a room during a cooling cycle of the split unit AC system. A room peak temperature that is too high can lead to discomfort and reduced productivity, while a room peak temperature that is too low can result in energy wastage and increased operating costs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]. Monitoring and controlling the peak temperature is essential for preventing overheating and ensuring the system's overall efficiency and longevity. The relationship between saturation temperature and peak temperature in split unit AC systems is crucial for achieving optimal performance. By maintaining the saturation temperature within a specified range, the system can effectively manage the peak temperature and prevent overheating. Additionally, proper insulation and refrigerant charge levels are essential factors that influence both saturation and peak temperatures in the system.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.3. Energy performance</title>
          
          <p>The EER is a critical metric that quantifies the cooling output of an AC system relative to its energy consumption. The EER, defined as the ratio of cooling output (in BTUs) to the electrical input (in watts), provides a direct measure of energy efficiency. An EER of 9.25 indicates that for every watt of electrical energy consumed, the system delivers approximately 9.25 BTUs of cooling. Conversely, the COP, which represents the ratio of useful heating or cooling provided to the energy consumed, is crucial for understanding the operational efficiency of the system. A COP of 2.7 suggests that for every unit of energy consumed, the system provides 2.7 units of cooling. From Eq. (12), the actual cooling loads of 28.8, 47, and 65.93 W for small, medium, and large rooms (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_10">Figure 10</xref>), present a clear framework for assessing the performance of cooling systems.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_10">
              <label>Figure 10</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Plot of actual cooling loads for various room sizes</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_PdocjJIbxziVoOQ_.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The relationship between room size and cooling load is not linear; larger rooms typically require disproportionately higher cooling loads due to increased surface area and heat gain from external sources. However, the ACL for the various rooms is discussed as follows:</p><p>i. Small Rooms (28.8 W): In smaller spaces, the non-inverter AC system operates closer to its optimal efficiency. The lower cooling load allows the system to maintain a high EER, as the compressor can run at a more consistent speed without frequent cycling. This results in reduced energy consumption and enhanced cooling efficiency.</p><p>ii. Medium Rooms (47 W): As the cooling load increases, the system's efficiency may begin to decline. The non-inverter design, characterized by its fixed-speed compressor, may struggle to adapt to varying thermal loads. Consequently, the system may experience periods of inefficiency, particularly during transitional phases when the compressor cycles on and off, leading to increased energy consumption relative to the cooling output.</p><p>iii. Large Rooms (65.93 W): In larger spaces, the limitations of a non-inverter system become more pronounced. The fixed-speed compressor is less capable of modulating its output to match the higher cooling demand, resulting in significant energy waste. The system may operate at a lower EER due to frequent cycling, which not only increases energy consumption but also affects the overall comfort level within the space. The relationship between cooling loads and the efficiency of the 1HP non-inverter AC system is multifaceted. While the system demonstrates commendable performance at lower loads, its efficacy diminishes as the cooling demand escalates. This phenomenon underscores the importance of selecting appropriate AC systems based on room size and cooling requirements.</p><p>Moreover, the inherent design limitations of non-inverter systems, which lack the ability to modulate compressor speed, exacerbate inefficiencies in larger spaces. This raises critical questions regarding the sustainability of such systems in the context of rising energy costs and environmental concerns. The argument for transitioning to inverter technology, which offers variable-speed compressors capable of adjusting to fluctuating cooling demands, becomes increasingly compelling. The findings suggest that there is a critical need for the development of advanced cooling technologies that can adapt to varying load requirements without sacrificing efficiency. Innovations such as variable refrigerant flow systems, smart thermostats, and improved insulation materials could enhance the performance of cooling systems across different room sizes. From Eq. (13), the power consumption rates of 85.5, 142.6, and 199.6 W (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_11">Figure 11</xref>) represent distinct operational states of the non-inverter AC unit, which can be attributed to varying load conditions and ambient temperature fluctuations. </p>
          
            <fig id="fig_11">
              <label>Figure 11</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Plot of power consumption for various room sizes</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/5/img_aKg8LTpFbtiJmwC-.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The power consumption and COP from 1HP non-inverter AC in this study differ from 2HP non-inverter AC, ranging from 311 to 1214 W, and 2.34 to 2.74 in the study of Pham et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]. In a similar study by Alghamdi and Krarti [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>], COP ranging from 1.8 to 3.5 was reported for conventional systems, which imply that the COP of 2.7 obtained in this study is ideal, indicating that locally sourced materials for AC assembly align with the 3 R’s sustainable waste management of reuse, reduce and recycle. The lowest power consumption of 85.5 W suggests an optimal operational state, likely under moderate cooling demands. In contrast, the higher consumption levels of 142.6 and 119.6 W indicate optimum energy usage under normal thermal loads. The EER, defined as the ratio of cooling output (in BTUs) to electrical input (in watts), provides a quantitative measure of efficiency. An EER of 9.25 implies that for every watt consumed, the unit delivers approximately 9.25 BTUs of cooling. This efficiency rating, while indicative of the unit's performance, must be contextualized within the framework of its power consumption levels. The observed power consumption levels, coupled with the EER and COP, suggest that an ideal energy saving has been achieved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Conclusion</title>
      <p>The findings from this study on assembling and testing of split unit AC systems using locally sourced materials have provided valuable insights into the feasibility and effectiveness of utilizing indigenous resources for the production of such systems. The results of the study have demonstrated that it is indeed possible to construct high-quality AC units using materials that are readily available within the local market. One of the key benefits of using locally sourced materials for the production of split AC systems is the potential cost savings that can be achieved. By sourcing materials locally, manufacturers can reduce their reliance on expensive imported components, thereby lowering production costs and making the final product more affordable for consumers. This can be particularly beneficial in Nigeria, where access to imported goods may be limited or more expensive. Furthermore, the study has also highlighted the importance of rigorous testing and quality control measures in ensuring the performance and reliability of locally assembled AC units. By subjecting the systems to a series of comprehensive tests, it is possible to identify and address potential issues before the units are brought to market. This not only helps to maintain high standards of quality but also enhances the overall credibility and reputation of locally produced AC systems. The findings from this study underscore the potential for leveraging locally sourced materials in the production of indoor split unit AC systems. By harnessing the resources that are readily available within the local environment, manufacturers can create products that are not only cost-effective but also of high quality and reliability. Further research and development in this area could help to unlock even greater potential for utilizing indigenous resources in the production of AC systems, ultimately benefiting both manufacturers and consumers alike.</p><p>As recommendation for further studies, the precision of the experimental setup would be enhanced by conducting a controlled experiments to examine the frequency and accuracy of data recording, including power consumption measured, and other critical information.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>123</volume>
          <page-range>874-890</page-range>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nada</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Said</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applthermaleng.2017.05.104</pub-id>
          <article-title>Performance and energy consumptions of split type air conditioning units for different arrangements of outdoor units in confined building shafts</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Therm. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>131</volume>
          <page-range>295-310</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nada</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Said</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applthermaleng.2017.12.016</pub-id>
          <article-title>Solutions of thermal performance problems of installing AC outdoor units in buildings light wells using mechanical ventilations</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Therm. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>233</volume>
          <page-range>121171</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>DDhamodharan</surname>
              <given-names>Palanisamy</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ayalur</surname>
              <given-names>Bakthavatsalam Kannappan</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prabakaran</surname>
              <given-names>Rajendran</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>A Santhosh</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>Gyu Sang</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>Sung Chul</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applthermaleng.2023.121171</pub-id>
          <article-title>Current state of research in air-conditioning condensate utilization and challenges: A review approach</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Therm. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>104</volume>
          <page-range>87-104</page-range>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chua</surname>
              <given-names>Kian Jon</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chou</surname>
              <given-names>Siaw Kiang</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>W M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>Jinyue</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apenergy.2012.10.037</pub-id>
          <article-title>Achieving better energy-efficient air conditioning–A review of technologies and strategies</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>89</volume>
          <page-range>101720</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mishra</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chaulya</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasad</surname>
              <given-names>G. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mandal</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Banerjee</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jspr.2020.101720</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design of a low cost, smart and stand-alone PV cold storage system using a domestic split air conditioner</article-title>
          <source>J. Stored Prod. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>60</volume>
          <page-range>105067</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taheri</surname>
              <given-names>Saman</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hosseini</surname>
              <given-names>Paniz</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Razban</surname>
              <given-names>Ali</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jobe.2022.105067</pub-id>
          <article-title>Model predictive control of heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) systems: A state-of-the-art review</article-title>
          <source>J. Build. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>19</volume>
          <page-range>1016</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Asim</surname>
              <given-names>Nilofar</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Badiei</surname>
              <given-names>Marzieh</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohammad</surname>
              <given-names>Masita</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Razali</surname>
              <given-names>Halim</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajabi</surname>
              <given-names>Armin</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chin Haw</surname>
              <given-names>Lim</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jameelah Ghazali</surname>
              <given-names>Mariyam</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19021016</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sustainability of heating, ventilation and air-conditioning (HVAC) systems in buildings-An overview</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>195</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>Bashar Mahmood</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akkaş</surname>
              <given-names>Mehmet</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app14010195</pub-id>
          <article-title>The green cooling factor: Eco-innovative heating, ventilation, and air conditioning solutions in building design</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>262-275</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ikpe</surname>
              <given-names>Aniekan Essienubong</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ekanem</surname>
              <given-names>Imoh Ime</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Udoh</surname>
              <given-names>Victor Etok</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22105/opt.vi.58</pub-id>
          <article-title>The role of mechanical ventilation systems and their applications in contemporary engineering practices</article-title>
          <source>Optimality</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>79-93</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ikpe</surname>
              <given-names>Aniekan Essienubong</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ekanem</surname>
              <given-names>Imoh Ime</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Usungurua</surname>
              <given-names>Enefiok Okon</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thermodynamic analysis and energy balance for environmental sustainability of simple gas turbine inlet cooling system in afam power plant</article-title>
          <source>Comput. Algorithms Numer. Dimens.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>315-334</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Itiat</surname>
              <given-names>Ndifreke Etebom</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ekanem</surname>
              <given-names>Imoh Ime</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ikpe</surname>
              <given-names>Aniekan Essienubong</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31181/sa22202427</pub-id>
          <article-title>A comprehensive review on green energy technologies: An approach for environmental sustainability and eco-friendliness</article-title>
          <source>Syst. Analytics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>62-78</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Devandran</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davis</surname>
              <given-names>F. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sammanasu Joseph</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/XJM-02-2024-0030</pub-id>
          <article-title>Perception of contractors and sub-contractors towards the factors causing delays in heating, ventilation and air conditioning (HVAC) construction projects</article-title>
          <source>Vilakshan-XIMB J. Manage.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gaber</surname>
              <given-names>Ghalia A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohamed</surname>
              <given-names>Lamiaa Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5772/intechopen.1006331</pub-id>
          <article-title>Advancements in materials used in air conditioning technologies</article-title>
          <source>, https://doi.org/10.5772/intechopen.1006331</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>100125</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Darwiche</surname>
              <given-names>Mohamad</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Faraj</surname>
              <given-names>Jalal</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>Samer</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murr</surname>
              <given-names>Rabih</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taher</surname>
              <given-names>Rani</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>El Hage</surname>
              <given-names>Hicham</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khaled</surname>
              <given-names>Mahmoud</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.uncres.2024.100125</pub-id>
          <article-title>Using geothermal energy in enhancing all-air HVAC system performance - Case study, thermal analysis and economic insights</article-title>
          <source>Unconventional Resources</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>67</volume>
          <page-range>625-640</page-range>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ni</surname>
              <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bai</surname>
              <given-names>X. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2016.09.050</pub-id>
          <article-title>A review of air conditioning energy performance in data centers</article-title>
          <source>Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <year>2011</year>
          <publisher-name>7546-7549</publisher-name>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bi</surname>
              <given-names>Guo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>Yinbiao</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>Jing</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>Wei</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>Maojiang</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Xin</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Principles of an in-process monitoring system for precision grinding machine</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>3711</page-range>
          <issue>21</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saidi</surname>
              <given-names>Alireza</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gauvin</surname>
              <given-names>Chantal</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ladhari</surname>
              <given-names>Safa</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen-Tri</surname>
              <given-names>Phuong</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/polym13213711</pub-id>
          <article-title>Advanced functional materials for intelligent thermoregulation in personal protective equipment</article-title>
          <source>Polymers</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>1-25</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ekanem</surname>
              <given-names>Imoh Ime</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Usungurua</surname>
              <given-names>Enefiok Okon</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ikpe</surname>
              <given-names>Aniekan Essienubong</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thermodynamic simulations of exergy efficiency in organic rankine cycle (ORC) based on exergy system</article-title>
          <source>Ann. Process Eng. Manage.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>86-98</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wirawan</surname>
              <given-names>Hendar</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>TK</surname>
              <given-names>B. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Utomo</surname>
              <given-names>M. T. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.47001/IRJIET/2023.704014</pub-id>
          <article-title>Experimental study of retrofit AC inverter performance based on R32 and R410a to R1270</article-title>
          <source>Int. Res. J. Innov. Eng. Technol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>96</volume>
          <page-range>237-249</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saber</surname>
              <given-names>Esmail M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tham</surname>
              <given-names>Kwok Wai</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leibundgut</surname>
              <given-names>Hansjürg</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.buildenv.2015.11.029</pub-id>
          <article-title>A review of high temperature cooling systems in tropical buildings</article-title>
          <source>Build. Environ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>134-147</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Usungurua</surname>
              <given-names>E. O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ekanem</surname>
              <given-names>I. I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ikpe</surname>
              <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-34123-6</pub-id>
          <article-title>Comparative analysis of environmental sustainability and performance indices of different gas turbine inlet cooling systems</article-title>
          <source>J. Adv. Environ. Health Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rizvi</surname>
              <given-names>S. S. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Refrigeration systems</article-title>
          <source>Food Engineering Principles and Practices: A One-Semester Course</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer Cham</publisher-name>
          <year>2024</year>
          <page-range>459-477</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-34123-6</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>326</volume>
          <page-range>115044</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ascione</surname>
              <given-names>Fabrizio</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nižetić</surname>
              <given-names>Sandro</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Fuqiang</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enbuild.2024.115044</pub-id>
          <article-title>Future technologies for building sector to accelerate energy transition</article-title>
          <source>Energy Build.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>292</volume>
          <page-range>113428</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guan</surname>
              <given-names>Yifan</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>Chenxi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meng</surname>
              <given-names>Xi</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.solener.2025.113428</pub-id>
          <article-title>Formation analysis of cooling load from envelopes under air-conditioning intermittent operation</article-title>
          <source>Sol. Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>61</volume>
          <page-range>1-22</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sahai</surname>
              <given-names>R. S. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Momin</surname>
              <given-names>U. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00231-025-03556-6</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enhancing air conditioning performance: Effects of direct evaporative cooling with various pad materials on condensing temperature of R-22 and cycle efficiency</article-title>
          <source>Heat Mass Transfer</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>320</volume>
          <page-range>135146</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Qin</surname>
              <given-names>Yanbin</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Shaojie</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Hua</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
              <given-names>Yuxuan</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>Guozhong</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Baolin</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.energy.2025.135146</pub-id>
          <article-title>Experimental investigation on the performance of a-120°C ultralow temperature refrigeration system based on a three-stage auto-cascade cycle</article-title>
          <source>Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>150</volume>
          <page-range>3201-3223</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yıldırım</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akyüz</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumaş</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tuncer</surname>
              <given-names>A. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gungor</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10973-025-14050-w</pub-id>
          <article-title>A comprehensive overview of refrigerants from the past to the modern day: Energy, exergy, and environmental perspectives</article-title>
          <source>J. Therm. Anal. Calorim.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>253-280</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Patil</surname>
              <given-names>Bhushan</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salunke</surname>
              <given-names>Nilesh</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Diware</surname>
              <given-names>Vijay</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raheman AR</surname>
              <given-names>Shakeelur</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ansari</surname>
              <given-names>Khursheed B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15435075.2024.2413678</pub-id>
          <article-title>Stability assessment of emerging phase change materials for solar thermal storage in absorption refrigeration: A review</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Green Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>327</volume>
          <page-range>115070</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Hui</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Du</surname>
              <given-names>Zhe</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xue</surname>
              <given-names>Tingting</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>Tao</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enbuild.2024.115070</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enhancing smart building performance with waste heat recovery: Supply-side management, demand reduction, and peak shaving via advanced control systems</article-title>
          <source>Energy Build.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>248</volume>
          <page-range>123218</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>CChen</surname>
              <given-names>Xing Ni</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gan</surname>
              <given-names>Wen Tao</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
              <given-names>Zi Qing</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>Bin</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pei</surname>
              <given-names>Gang</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.renene.2025.123218</pub-id>
          <article-title>Thermal performance analysis of a double-channel phase change slurry Trombe wall with seasonal switching, solar energy storage and utilization</article-title>
          <source>Renew. Energy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>100</volume>
          <page-range>31-35</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pham</surname>
              <given-names>Hoang Luong</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tokura</surname>
              <given-names>Shogo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen Viet</surname>
              <given-names>Dung</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>Nguyen An</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lai</surname>
              <given-names>Ngoc Anh</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Study on power consumption and energy performance of split-type Air-Conditioners</article-title>
          <source>J. Sci. Technol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>1611</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alghamdi</surname>
              <given-names>Faisal</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krarti</surname>
              <given-names>Moncef</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en18071611</pub-id>
          <article-title>Review analysis for the energy performance of integrated air-conditioning systems</article-title>
          <source>Energies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>262</volume>
          <page-range>125178</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elsaid</surname>
              <given-names>Ashraf Mimi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wahba</surname>
              <given-names>M A I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharshir</surname>
              <given-names>Swellam W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abd Raboo</surname>
              <given-names>M F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applthermaleng.2024.125178</pub-id>
          <article-title>Energy saving and performance assessment of a split-type air conditioner integrated by an evaporative cooling unit with nanofluids</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Therm. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>