<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JUDM</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Urban Development and Management</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Urban Dev. Manag.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JUDM</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2957-9597</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2957-9589</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-GwHwIsTZnJ3OFJV3zPOL1M4R8sdlQuC5</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/judm010102</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Data Driven Approach to Measure Evolution Trends of City Information Modeling</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1">1</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Guangdong</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2600-0493</contrib-id>
          <email>gd198410@cqu.edu.cn</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1">1</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Handong</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3551-6037</contrib-id>
          <email>20220101010@stu.cqu.edu.cn</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="2,3">2,3</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>Yichuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1492-4370</contrib-id>
          <email>ctycdeng@scut.edu.cn</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="4">4</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Hengqin</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0925-2293</contrib-id>
          <email>hengqin.wu@connect.polyu.hk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="5">5</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Chaoran</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5894-3755</contrib-id>
          <email>linchaoran@hrbeu.edu.cn</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="1">School of Public Policy and Administration, Chongqing University, 400044 Chongqing, China</aff>
        <aff id="2">School of Civil and Transportation Engineering, South China University of Technology, 510641 Guangzhou, China</aff>
        <aff id="3">State Key Laboratory of Subtropical Building Science, South China University of Technology, 510641 Guangzhou, China</aff>
        <aff id="4">College of Civil and Transportation Engineering, Shenzhen University, 518060 Shenzhen, China</aff>
        <aff id="5">School of Economics &amp; Management, Harbin Engineering University, 150001 Harbin, China</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <year>2022</year>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>2</fpage>
      <lpage>16</lpage>
      <page-range>2-16</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <month>06</month>
          <day>17</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <month>08</month>
          <day>08</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="pub">
          <month>10</month>
          <day>31</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2022 by the authors</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <license>. Licensee Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article can be downloaded for free, and reused and quoted with a citation of the original published version, under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 license</ext-link>.</license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>This work aims to reveal the current status of the city information modeling (CIM) from massive patent data, using the latent Dirichlet allocation (LDA) model, and quantify the evolution trends of future topics by the Hidden Markov Model (HMM). The results show that the CIM technologies can be divided into 17 topics. At the present stage, the technologies related to the Internet of things (IOT), big data and data management are the focus of the research and development (R&amp;D) of CIM patents. Compared with the software technology, further development is needed for the hardware technology supporting CIM, particularly in terms of information acquisition (cameras and sensors), storage, and information transmitters. This study deepens the understanding of the CIM-related technical categories, and clarifies the direction of the development and evolution of CIM technology, providing a strong support to decision-makers in urban management.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Smart city</kwd>
        <kwd>City information modeling (CIM)</kwd>
        <kwd>Latent Dirichlet allocation (LDA)</kwd>
        <kwd>Hidden Markov model (HMM)</kwd>
        <kwd>Patented technology</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors">5</count>
        <fig-count>10</fig-count>
        <table-count>1</table-count>
        <ref-count>51</ref-count>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Cities now account for 54% of the world's population, consume 80% of natural resources, and emit 80% of greenhouse gases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. Rising urbanization promotes economic and social development while posing significant challenges to long-term urban development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>]. The topic of smart cities, which are distinguished by smart governance and smart growth, has gradually piqued the interest of researchers seeking to promote sustainable urban development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>].</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">In the last decade, the centralized outbreak of networks, big data, artificial intelligence, modeling, and other technologies, particularly the development of sensors and low-power wide-area network technology, enabled the accurate and real-time representation of the physical world's dynamics in digital format. City Information Modeling (CIM) emerged in response to the concept of digital twins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>].</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">A digital twin is a virtual entity and subsystem that characterizes a physical device in virtual space using the data from the physical device. CIM is a specific application of digital twin technology in urban management that lays the groundwork for smart city construction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. CIM enables data granularity down to a single module within a city building, transforming the traditional static digital city into a perceptible, dynamic, interactive, and intelligent real-world city. As a result, CIM provides critical data support for comprehensive urban management and fine governance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], becoming an essential cornerstone for smart city operations.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">CIM research typically focuses on CIM application scenarios in urban management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>], with few studies of CIM-related technology development and even fewer studies of patent literature research on CIM technology development. Using a scientific analytical framework to efficiently analyze patent documents, gaining technical knowledge, and connecting problems with potential solutions all play important roles in encouraging more effective innovation in this field [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>].</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The ultimate goal of smart cities is to adhere to sustainable urban development principles and accomplish effective urban management (e.g., urban planning, infrastructure, transportation, energy, services, education, health, and public safety) while meeting public needs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. CIM, as a smart city management digital twin system, leverages information and communication technology to make critical components of urban infrastructure and services more interactive, accessible, and effective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]. As a result, in order to support the development of smart cities, it is vital to understand the technological development trends in CIM.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Patent documents are a valuable source of technical information since their contents are accurate, thorough, and cutting-edge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>]. Patent data is increasingly being used by academics to investigate technological development trends. Pellicer et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>] discovered, for example, that basic data gathering, processing, and transmission technologies are required for smart city applications. Furthermore, Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>] discovered that network communication and administration technologies are an important development path in the digital twin area by researching digital twin patent data. </p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">However, due to the limits of research methods, previous studies failed to investigate the distribution of topics and the link between topics from a complete standpoint. The building of CIM by municipal managers, in particular, is not restricted to offering services autonomously. Rather, it necessitates the deployment of a comprehensive infrastructure for urban data collecting, transfer, storage, and analysis in order to provide public services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>]. In this context, this study aims to close the gap by throwing light on the technical scope of CIM and investigating its development trend. This study specifically wants answers to the following research questions:</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">I. What is the most important technology in the field of CIM?</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">II. What are the most essential CIM-related technologies?</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">III. What is the goal and direction of future CIM-related technology development?</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The work classifies patent literature data by using latent Dirichlet allocation (LDA) and the Hidden Markov Model (HMM) to discover the most relevant CIM technologies. From the standpoint of technology change, the changes in content and co-occurrence of technology topics are explored, technology trends are forecasted, and visual displays are developed. CIM-related businesses can shorten the research and development (R&amp;amp;amp;D) cycle, reduce R&amp;amp;amp;D expenses, comprehend the present technological environment, and gain insight into market trends by researching the evolution of CIM technology themes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>]. Additionally, it assists in defining the course of CIM technology development and evolution and directs industries to occupy the next technological highlands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>2. Literature review</title>
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.1. Smart cities</title>
          
          <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The "smart growth" movement of the 1990s is where the idea of a "smart city" first emerged [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. Since then, it has expanded to include nearly every type of cutting-edge technological application for urban planning, construction, operation, and management, including traffic improvement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], environmental sustainability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], and urban governance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>]. Despite the idea of smart cities becoming more and more popular, no consensus exists on what constitutes a smart city. According to studies by Lara et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>] and Mora et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], the most widely used definition of a smart city is a community that systematically promotes the overall well-being of all its members and has sufficient flexibility to adapt and become a better place to live, work, and play in a sustainable manner.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.2. Cim</title>
          
          <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">CIM is a sophisticated synthesis of urban information sources and three-dimensional spatial modeling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]. In a limited sense, it consists of large-scale GIS and BIM data from the development of smart cities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]. Based on the integration of BIM and GIS technologies, CIM enables data granularity precise to a single module inside the city building, creating an intelligent city and providing crucial data support for thorough urban administration and excellent governance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>].</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Unified data standards, urban information models, urban operation data, common supporting platforms, and digital twin applications are just a few of the numerous components that make up a smart city. CIM serves as the key connection in this process by creating a digital twin of a real city model. Digital twin construction emerges as a significant driving force to modernize the capacity of urban governance. It relies on the three-dimensional digital urban backplane of the CIM platform and is highly integrated with real-time perception, simulation, deep learning, and other information technology to carry out omni-dimensional and multi-dimensional smart city application.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">To achieve cross-system application integration and cross-departmental information sharing and support the decision-making analysis of smart cities, CIM's extensibility promotes accessing the information resources of many urban public systems (such as population, housing, household water, electricity and gas information, security police data, traffic information, tourism resource information, and public health care).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.3. Topic extraction of patent documents</title>
          
          <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Traditional techniques evaluate exemplary patents and extract technical topics from patent documents using expert knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>]. The lack of expert resources, the challenge of determining patent representativeness, and the inability to study a large number of patents limit the usefulness of this strategy. Albino et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>] used the categorization properties of patents, such as the International Patent Classification number, as their technical topics to examine the evolution features of a particular field, trying to avoid relying on expert experience.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The limited types of patent features, however, compromise the precision of evolution trend analysis. Researchers used the patent co-occurrence network and citation relationship as a strategy to increase the accuracy of patent topics extraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>]. The timeliness of topic evolution trend analysis cannot be guaranteed by this method due to the delays it produces. Therefore, when mining technical topics from patents and other scientific or technological documents, researchers use the Subject-Action-Object (SAO) structures in semantic similarity recognition, topic modeling, or topic clustering to account for the diversity of technical topics and the timeliness of the analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>].</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">A flexible probabilistic model called LDA was created specifically for topic modeling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]. In order to represent the process of creating documents, this model uses probabilistic latent semantic analysis to introduce Dirichlet prior distribution and maximize word co-occurrence probability to look for word clustering. Consequently, it clusters documents and effectively extracts hidden topics. However, LDA's dimensionality reduction effect and recognition rate are compromised by its inability to keep the local structural information adequately.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">To ensure effective LDA performance, an ideal number of topics must be chosen using a scientific manner. According to a 2012 proposal by Blei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>], the number of themes should be gauged by how perplexing they are. The language probability model's performance can be assessed and its parameters can be improved using perplexity. Perplexity determines the geometric mean of the sentence similarity in the literature set and estimates the information entropy of the probability distribution based on the information theory. Therefore, this work uses perplexity to evaluate and determine the optimal number of topics in the sample literature.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.4. Topic evolution of patent documents</title>
          
          <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Grey prediction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>] and time series analysis are common methods used by researchers to predict the topics' evolution tendency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>]. However, these analysis techniques typically disregard the random characteristics of the innovation process, despite the fact that randomness is a crucial element of innovation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>]. Ignoring randomness in the quantitative forecast of future technological trends causes an overestimation of the endurance of current technical themes and an underestimation of the exponential emergence of new technologies.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The topic evolution may be influenced by two different processes. The first is the motivation that academics gain from reading about past research breakthroughs and the introduction of fresh concepts during literary change. But because there aren't many records, this process is thought to be a secret sequence that can't be seen. Second, motivated by the first step, researchers efficiently document the research findings in scientific literature, producing observable sequences. The latter process serves as the former's micro-foundation, and the former serves as the latter's macro-performance. Therefore, topic evolution can be seen as the superposition of the two processes.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Baum and Petrie's HMM, a probability and statistical model, was developed in 1966 as a method to capture such superposition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>]. The concept was initially employed in language processing before becoming well-known and being adopted in other disciplines.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>3. Methodology</title>
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>3.1. Data sources</title>
          
          <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The frequency approach is employed in this study to choose keywords. To create a trustworthy keyword search list, 48 CIM-related articles from 2018 to 2020 were first chosen, and their topics, titles, abstracts, and keywords were examined. Second, additional data was used to extract keyword synonyms and assess the significance of the keywords (using sources like Wikipedia). Four keywords were selected after screening the frequency of CIM-related terms.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">On February 20, 2021, "Patentscope" was searched the World Intellectual Property Organization (WIPO) patent database for patents relating to CIM using the following search terms: TS="city information model," "urban information model," "urban digital twins," and "digital city." As a result, 2764 CIM-related patents published between April 1992 and February 2021 were found. According to the period of application, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> displays the number of CIM patents that have been registered. As depicted in the image, CIM-related patents began to grow rapidly around 2015 and have continued to do so ever since.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>Number of CIM patents from 1990 to 2020</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_u5UX1WWW4ES4IQ7d.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>3.2. Method design</title>
          
          <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">LDA is used in this study to model the data from the patent literature. In order to avoid the inefficiency and errors associated with human labeling, the model is first trained to create topics. The perplexity and transition matrices between topics in the evolution of CIM topic evolution are then computed using the state transition matrix in HMM and the probability distribution of the initial state. Finally, it is established how CIM topics have evolved over time and what the future evolution trend will be (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>Workflow of the research</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_rRSnpbNqje6G4T3n.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <sec disp-level="level3">
              
                <title>3.2. 1 Document topic extraction module</title>
              
              <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The LDA algorithm's assumptions and requirements are followed in this study. We therefore suppose that each topic follows the hyper parametric Dirichlet prior distribution:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(1)</label>
                  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                    <mi>Dir</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo>∣</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>θ</mi>
                        <mi>d</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <mi>α</mi>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mfrac>
                      <mrow>
                        <mi mathvariant="normal">Γ</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                          <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                          <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                          <munderover>
                            <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                            <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                              <mi>k</mi>
                              <mo>=</mo>
                              <mn>1</mn>
                            </mrow>
                            <mi>k</mi>
                          </munderover>
                          <msub>
                            <mi>α</mi>
                            <mi>k</mi>
                          </msub>
                        </mrow>
                      </mrow>
                      <mrow>
                        <munderover>
                          <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∏</mo>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mi>k</mi>
                            <mo>=</mo>
                            <mn>1</mn>
                          </mrow>
                          <mi>k</mi>
                        </munderover>
                        <mi mathvariant="normal">Γ</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                          <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                          <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                          <msub>
                            <mi>α</mi>
                            <mi>k</mi>
                          </msub>
                        </mrow>
                      </mrow>
                    </mfrac>
                    <munderover>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∏</mo>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>k</mi>
                        <mo>=</mo>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </mrow>
                      <mi>k</mi>
                    </munderover>
                    <msubsup>
                      <mi>θ</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>d</mi>
                        <mi>k</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <msub>
                          <mi>α</mi>
                          <mi>k</mi>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>−</mo>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </mrow>
                    </msubsup>
                  </math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>θ</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>d</mi>
        <mi>k</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula> is the distribution of scientific documents <italic>d</italic> on topic <italic>k; α</italic> is the distribution of subject words.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The topic term distribution <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">∅</mi>
      <mi>k</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>∼</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
    <mi>Dir</mi>
    <mi>β</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula> is generated for each topic <italic>k</italic>, and the topic term distribution <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>θ</mi>
      <mi>d</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>∼</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
    <mi>Dir</mi>
    <mi>α</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula> is generated for each patent document <italic>d</italic>. Furthermore,<italic> </italic>the topic <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>Z</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>d</mi>
        <mi>n</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo>∼</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula> Multinomial <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi mathvariant="normal">∅</mi>
        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
          <msub>
            <mi>Z</mi>
            <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
              <mi>d</mi>
              <mi>n</mi>
            </mrow>
          </msub>
        </mrow>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula> is derived for the <italic>n</italic>-th term in each document. Therefore, the LDA likelihood model can be established as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(2)</label>
                  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                    <mi>p</mi>
                    <mi>W</mi>
                    <mi>α</mi>
                    <mi>β</mi>
                    <mi>p</mi>
                    <mi>p</mi>
                    <mi>p</mi>
                    <mi>d</mi>
                    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                    <mo>∣</mo>
                    <mo>,</mo>
                    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <munderover>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∏</mo>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>d</mi>
                        <mo>=</mo>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </mrow>
                      <mi>D</mi>
                    </munderover>
                    <munderover>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∏</mo>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>n</mi>
                        <mo>=</mo>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </mrow>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <msub>
                          <mi>N</mi>
                          <mi>d</mi>
                        </msub>
                      </mrow>
                    </munderover>
                    <msub>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∫</mo>
                      <mn>0</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>θ</mi>
                      <mi>d</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo>∣</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>θ</mi>
                        <mi>d</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <mi>α</mi>
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo>∣</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>Z</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>d</mi>
                          <mi>n</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>θ</mi>
                        <mi>d</mi>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo>∣</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>w</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>d</mi>
                          <mi>n</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi mathvariant="normal">∅</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <msub>
                            <mi>Z</mi>
                            <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                              <mi>d</mi>
                              <mi>n</mi>
                            </mrow>
                          </msub>
                        </mrow>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <msub>
                          <mi>Z</mi>
                          <mi>d</mi>
                        </msub>
                      </mrow>
                    </munder>
                  </math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Perplexity can be calculated as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(3)</label>
                  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                    <mi>Perplexity</mi>
                    <mi>D</mi>
                    <mi>exp</mi>
                    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo>−</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <mfrac>
                        <mrow>
                          <munderover>
                            <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                            <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                              <mi>d</mi>
                              <mo>=</mo>
                              <mn>1</mn>
                            </mrow>
                            <mi>M</mi>
                          </munderover>
                          <msub>
                            <mi>log</mi>
                            <mi>D</mi>
                          </msub>
                          <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                            <mspace width="1em"/>
                          </mstyle>
                          <mi>p</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                            <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                            <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                            <msub>
                              <mi>w</mi>
                              <mi>d</mi>
                            </msub>
                          </mrow>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                          <munderover>
                            <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                            <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                              <mi>d</mi>
                              <mo>=</mo>
                              <mn>1</mn>
                            </mrow>
                            <mi>M</mi>
                          </munderover>
                          <msub>
                            <mi>N</mi>
                            <mi>d</mi>
                          </msub>
                        </mrow>
                      </mfrac>
                    </mrow>
                  </math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(4)</label>
                  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                    <mi>p</mi>
                    <mi>p</mi>
                    <mi>p</mi>
                    <mi>p</mi>
                    <mi>d</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>w</mi>
                        <mi>d</mi>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo>∣</mo>
                      <mo>=</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>w</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>z</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <mi>j</mi>
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo>=</mo>
                      <mo>∣</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>z</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>w</mi>
                        <mi>d</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <mi>j</mi>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mo>⋅</mo>
                    <mo>⋅</mo>
                    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                      <mi>d</mi>
                    </munder>
                    <munderover>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∏</mo>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>n</mi>
                        <mo>=</mo>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </mrow>
                      <mi>T</mi>
                    </munderover>
                    <munderover>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>j</mi>
                        <mo>=</mo>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </mrow>
                      <mi>T</mi>
                    </munderover>
                  </math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, $D<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mo>;</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>M<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mo>;</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>N_d<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>d<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>;</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>p\left(w_d\right)<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>w_d<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mo>:</mo>
    <mo>;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mo>:</mo>
    <mo>;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo data-mjx-pseudoscript="true">"</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo data-mjx-pseudoscript="true">"</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo data-mjx-pseudoscript="true">"</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo data-mjx-pseudoscript="true">"</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>x</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>x</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>x</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>D</mi>
    <mi>A</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>x</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>F</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>H</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>k</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mn>10.2</mn>
    <mn>10.2</mn>
    <msup>
      <mi>h</mi>
      <mo data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mo>
    </msup>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\alpha=50 / k<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\beta=0.1<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mi>F</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>G</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>S</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>K=\left\{k_1, \ldots, k_h\right\}<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>D_k=$ <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mo>…</mo>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi>j</mi>
        <mn>1</mn>
      </msub>
      <msub>
        <mi>j</mi>
        <mi>n</mi>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula>.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec disp-level="level3">
              
                <title>3.2. 2 Trend analysis module</title>
              
              <p>A complete HMM model can be described as a tuple <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>γ</mi>
    <mi>S</mi>
    <mi>π</mi>
    <mi>A</mi>
    <mi>B</mi>
    <mi>O</mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. The random transition sequence of hidden states can be expressed as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(5)</label>
                  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                    <mi>S</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                      <mo>,</mo>
                      <mo>…</mo>
                      <mo>,</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>s</mi>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>s</mi>
                        <mi>h</mi>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                  </math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>Let <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>Q</mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mo>…</mo>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi>q</mi>
        <mn>1</mn>
      </msub>
      <msub>
        <mi>q</mi>
        <mi>t</mi>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula> denote the randomly generated hidden state sequence, where <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>q</mi>
      <mi>t</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>∈</mo>
    <mi>S</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, and $t<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>Q$ represents the set of all possible topic states.</p>
              <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Then, the initial state of the system follows the probability distribution below:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(6)</label>
                  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                    <mi>π</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                      <mo>,</mo>
                      <mo>≤</mo>
                      <mo>≤</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>π</mi>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                      <mi>N</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>π</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula> is the occurrence probability of state <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>S</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. The probability distribution of transitions of the research topic from state <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>S</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula> to <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>S</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula> can be described as follows:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(7)</label>
                  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                    <mi>A</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>α</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>i</mi>
                          <mi>j</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                  </math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>α</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>i</mi>
        <mi>j</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>≤</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>≤</mo>
    <mi>P</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>j</mi>
    <mi>N</mi>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mo>∣</mo>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
        <msub>
          <mi>q</mi>
          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
            <mi>t</mi>
            <mo>+</mo>
            <mn>1</mn>
          </mrow>
        </msub>
        <msub>
          <mi>S</mi>
          <mi>j</mi>
        </msub>
        <msub>
          <mi>q</mi>
          <mi>t</mi>
        </msub>
        <msub>
          <mi>S</mi>
          <mi>i</mi>
        </msub>
      </mrow>
    </mrow>
    <mn>1</mn>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, and satisfies <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>α</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>i</mi>
        <mi>j</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>α</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>i</mi>
        <mi>j</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo>≥</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mn>0</mn>
    <mn>1</mn>
    <munderover>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>j</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mn>1</mn>
      </mrow>
      <mi>N</mi>
    </munderover>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. For state <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>S</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, the probability distribution of the observed variables can be expressed as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(8)</label>
                  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                    <mi>B</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                      <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                      <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>b</mi>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <mi>v</mi>
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                      <mi>f</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                        <mo>=</mo>
                        <mo>∣</mo>
                        <mo>=</mo>
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>Q</mi>
                          <mi>t</mi>
                        </msub>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>q</mi>
                          <mi>t</mi>
                        </msub>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>S</mi>
                          <mi>i</mi>
                        </msub>
                        <mi>v</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>Q</mi>
      <mi>t</mi>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula> is the $t$-th observed variable. Thus, the observation sequence can be expressed as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(9)</label>
                  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                    <mi>O</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                      <mo>,</mo>
                      <mo>…</mo>
                      <mo>,</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>O</mi>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>O</mi>
                        <mi>t</mi>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                  </math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, the observed state at time $t<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>O_t=(\alpha(t), \beta(t))<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\alpha(t)<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\beta(t)<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>q</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>t<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>q</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>O$. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> shows the relationship between hidden state transition sequence and observation sequence.</p>
              <p>The initial training value of the model is set as <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>O</mi>
    <mi>Q</mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mo>…</mo>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
      <mi>p</mi>
      <mi>p</mi>
      <msub>
        <mi>t</mi>
        <mn>1</mn>
      </msub>
      <msub>
        <mi>t</mi>
        <mn>2</mn>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. Then, the Baum-Welch algorithm is used to estimate the model parameters, yielding a single optimal state sequence. The structure of the research topic after $k<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\hat{O}_{t k}=\sum_{j=1}^N A^K(i, j) E\left(b_j(v)\right)$.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_3">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>Relationship between hidden state transition sequence and observation sequence</caption>
                  <abstract/>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_dhtEpSSsP2JnQV_v.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="results">
      <title>4. Results</title>
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>4.1. Topic extraction of cim patent documents</title>
          
          <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The learning effect of the LDA model, a machine learning technique, is highly correlated with the number of iterations. When there are more than 70 iterations in this study, the new iteration's contribution to the Log-Likelihood increase is almost zero. In order to reduce the cost of operation time, this study sets the number of iterations at 70. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>). The number of topics was also adjusted from six to seventy, and perplexity scores were computed. There is a minimum perplexity of 835.8 when there are 17 topics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref>). Consequently, 17 topics were chosen.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The LDA library (genism) in Python is used in this study to calculate the topic information and provide keywords for each topic. For each topic, 40 keywords are explicitly extracted. The top five keywords with the highest likelihood are chosen to represent the topic after the words are sorted based on the assessed probability. Each topic is labeled and categorized in accordance with the sort of technology it represents to ease learning and ease referencing (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>Topics and their corresponding keywords</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>No.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>KW1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>KW2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>KW3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>KW4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>KW5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>ID</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Category</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Module</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Control</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Communication</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Signal</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wireless</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Communication control module</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Network communication technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Information</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Management</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Monitor</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Terminal</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Server</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Information terminal</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Network communication technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Datum</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Model</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>City</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Information</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Urban</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Datum model</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Heterogeneous application integration technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Network</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Model</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Information</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Prediction</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Invention</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Network model</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Heterogeneous application integration technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Information</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Model</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Accord</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Feature</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Target</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Target recognition</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IOT technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Power</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Electric</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Control</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Circuit</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Energy</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Circuit control</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Network communication technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Layer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Storage</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mechanism</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Plurality</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Computer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Plurality storage</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Big data and data management technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Card</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Camera</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ring</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Utility</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sign</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Camera signal</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IOT technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Plate</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>End</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fix</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rod</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Top</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Plate fixed</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IOT technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Case</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Computing</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Electronic</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Equip</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Utility</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Utility</p><p>Computing</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cloud computing technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Display</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Screen</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Board</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bus</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Information</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>screen board</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IOT technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vehicle</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Traffic</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>City</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Parking</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Road</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Vehicle road</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IOT technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Body</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Machine</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Box</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Equip</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Drive</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Body equip</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IOT technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sensor</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Temperature</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Utility</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Body</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Garbage</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Temperature sensor</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IOT technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Computer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Computing</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Automatic</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Message</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Drive</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Autonomic</p><p>Computing</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cloud computing technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>16</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lamp</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Street</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Light</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>City</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Part</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lamp part</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IOT technology</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>17</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Water</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Pipe</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Gas</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Detection</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Pipeline</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Pipeline detection</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IOT technology</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>Effect of number of iterations on machine learning</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_v1d4Pbejtw7HRRHL.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_5">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>Perplexity scores for different number of topics</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_n8czJvnbLhJf0zqi.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>4.2. Evolution path of cim patent topics</title>
          
          
            <sec disp-level="level3">
              
                <title>4.2. 1 Temporal analysis</title>
              
              <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">A heat map of the topic number and each topic's individual gravity trend is created based on the results that were shown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>b, the annual change trend and initial occurrence time of the topics show how the topics are continually subdivided as the research progresses. The first CIM application dates back to the 1994 Amsterdam experiment De Digitale Stad [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>]. At this point, network communication data utilization and urban data collection have been investigated, thus technological topics like network model, information terminal, and camera signal are developing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>].</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">With the advancement of network communication technologies from wired to wireless and mobile wireless networks, mobile information communication capabilities have been significantly improved. The widespread adoption of 2.5G, 3G, 4G, and 5G technologies, which provide network infrastructure for the quick development of new technologies, has had a significant impact on these advancements. Circuit control, cloud computing, and autonomous computing are topics in network communication.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_6">
                  <label>Figure 6</label>
                  <caption>Evolution charts of the number and proportion of topics</caption>
                  <abstract/>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_Z4t29VAZ2h--j8TP.png"/>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_f-yPiTWCtUwRt67v.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Additionally, the IOT technological topic known as lamp part has been created [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>]. The IOT has enabled the CIM information interaction mode, which primarily relies on human-computer interaction, to progress into the ubiquitous computing stage of multi-source real-time information acquisition and intelligent control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>]. As a result, further discussions evolved on the themes of target recognition, temperature sensors, and communication control module.</p><p>Parallel to this, the growth of the IOT and its applications has created a number of issues, including the administration, processing, fusion, integration, and mining analysis of huge data from several sources, giving rise to the topic of plurality storage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">44</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>]. The storage, administration, processing, sharing, integration, and application of multi-source enormous data present a considerable demand on computer resources with the development of a digital city or smart city. This problem is solved by cloud computing technology, which also gave rise to key topics like utility computing and autonomous computing.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec disp-level="level3">
              
                <title>4.2. 2 Evolution path of cim topics</title>
              
              <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The likelihood of perplexity or transition between topics increases with the similarity of the topics. This paper bases its method of topic word co-occurrence analysis on this idea. We measure and use as a proxy for the degree of similarity across topics the co-occurrences of the first 40 topic words in 17 topics. To this end, the 17 word co-occurrence symmetry matrix was built, and the related heat map is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>. The diagonals are highlighted the most since each topic occurs with itself most frequently, whereas the other parts have varied hues because other topics occur less frequently. The likelihood that a hidden state would be detected as an observable state is displayed in the perplexity matrix. The threshold of transition between patent topics in the evolution process is measured using this probability. The matrix also indicates the likelihood and direction of a topic change at the same time. The perplexity matrix's dark squares correspond to the topics that are subject to change (transition) throughout time. It is apparent from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref> that most CIM topics are straightforward, with a high degree of independence of research content and a high threshold for state transition. In other words, there is a high and clear barrier between most topics.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_7">
                  <label>Figure 7</label>
                  <caption>Heat map of word co-occurrence symmetry matrix</caption>
                  <abstract/>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_t8gZ9P9gtN7y37xe.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Topics having a perplexity probability of more than 10% are shown as a perplexity network diagrams to further the analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>, CIM R&amp;amp;amp;D topics can go more readily from multi-component topics (e.g., drive equipment and information terminal)) to technology topics including multi-scene applications (such as screen board, temperature sensor, and camera signal). Additionally, a number of technology topics serve as crucial links in the development and transformation of other technology topics, serving as significant bridges and intermediaries in the growth of technology. The information terminal, for instance, serves as a node between the control module and the target recognition system and the vehicle road. Information terminal is a vital node in this transition because control module and target recognition are subdivisions of information terminal application, and vehicle road is the integration of information terminal application. A technical transition from target detection and automated drive to vehicle road is also provided by plurality storage. Important machine learning applications include target recognition and automated driving, and plurality storage offers a technical assurance for machine learning. Camera signal, vehicle road, and automatic driving are further topics with comparable functions. The ambiguity feature illuminates the prospective R&amp;amp;amp;D development course of the CIM technology topic, making it simple for the micro R&amp;amp;amp;D department to select the technology path scientifically while planning the scientific research objective.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The chance of switching between topics in the macrohistorical R&amp;amp;amp;D process is represented by the transition matrix. The diagonal in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>d, however, is highlighted, indicating that the majority of topics continue to exhibit consistency in their research trends. The characteristics of the transition in R&amp;amp;amp;D trend among topics vary when seen from the perspective of a single topic. In this study, a relationship feature diagram is plotted using the topics that have a transition probability of more than 15% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref>).</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Datum modeling, target identification, and screen boards are some of the topics with a great ability to retain their R&amp;amp;amp;D direction. The topic with the largest proportion of transition loss throughout evolution is "screen board," which mainly flows to target recognition, control module, information terminal, and body equipment. These topics have consistently maintained a high degree of co-occurrence and are hot technology nodes in the CIM-related R&amp;amp;amp;D. This behavior is brought on by the ongoing diversification of wireless terminal products, the escalating anti-interference standards for circuit boards, the steady decline in R&amp;amp;amp;D for simple-use screen boards, and the rise in R&amp;amp;amp;D and use of specialized equipment.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_8">
                  <label>Figure 8</label>
                  <caption>Perplexity relationship between topics</caption>
                  <abstract/>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_LwrbIkY8tvl6-JSX.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              
                <fig id="fig_9">
                  <label>Figure 9</label>
                  <caption>HMM estimation of transition probabilities between topics</caption>
                  <abstract/>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_1flwavVCO8EH4NAI.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Since the current CIM platform has not yet developed a unified spatiotemporal data underlying framework compatible with heterogeneous information systems, the "datum model" has seen the largest increase in popularity, and its R&amp;amp;amp;D strength mainly comes from "camera signal," "information terminal," and "plurality storage." There are many different standard formats for data collecting or design modeling software, and there exist hurdles to data accommodation between formats. Multi-source data includes vector data, raster data, model data, point cloud data, and other data from several sources. The CIM role is constrained if the interdepartmental business system's data format is uncoordinated, the data authority is unclear, and the data docking mechanism is flawed. As a result, the study of the datum model is always expanding. Additionally important is the rise in the "heat" of target recognition. Target identification, a hot topic in the realm of deep learning, is a crucial way of data collecting and human-computer interaction in the CIM application. The foundational technology of an intelligent city is the road target identification algorithm, which employs deep learning to assess the condition of the road. Finding the target's position and size inside an image, as well as detecting particular target classes, are two of the functions of target recognition. Intelligent security, intelligent medical care, unmanned retail, intelligent hardware, and intelligent robotics are some of the related fields.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec disp-level="level3">
              
                <title>4.2. 3 Prediction and analysis of cim topics</title>
              
              <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The 2021 literature has not yet been released in its whole as of the conclusion of this study. Therefore, this study uses the patents released up until the end of 2020 as the training set to anticipate the CIM evolution trends, and it adds the predicted perplexity matrix and transition matrix to the Matlab HMM module. The outcomes of the HMM prediction of the evolution of the CIM topics from 2018 to 2026 are as a consequence obtained, as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_10">Figure 10</xref>.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_10">
                  <label>Figure 10</label>
                  <caption>Predicted trends of CIM topics from 2019 to 2026</caption>
                  <abstract/>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2022/10/img_OE6y5L0OfWrKCFxu.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The hidden Markov predictions reveal a sharp rise in the proportion of topics related to temperature sensors, camera signals, electrical equipment, and body equipment. Front-end data collection is necessary for the development of CIM. Real-time data acquisition is encouraged by effective front-end data collection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. Artificial intelligence and machine learning technologies provide a better understanding of how cities evolve and cope with drawbacks as sensors, computing cores, and more effective electronic communication systems get installed in urban infrastructure. The Internet of Everything is made possible by the CIM platform [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">47</xref>], and the growth of electrical and body equipment is in line with these developments. Radio frequency identification, infrared sensors, global positioning systems, laser scanners, and other information sensing devices are becoming increasingly embedded in power grids, railways, bridges, tunnels, roads, buildings, water supply systems, dams, oil and gas pipelines, and other objects, thanks to the advancement of front-end data collection systems. Micro-platform integration now replaces fixed technology (plate fixed) requirements for particular platform equipment.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Target recognition is an image recognition technology based on machine learning. The advancement of this technology necessitates increased quantity and quality of visual data as well as the development of more effective algorithms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">48</xref>]. Target recognition hence entered the period of technology accumulation, after quick early development, when the pre-technology such as camera signal failed to progress considerably. As a result, the degree of R&amp;amp;amp;D has somewhat decreased, calling for an upgrade and optimization of the relevant technology (such as machine learning supporting technology). Similar to this, it became challenging to create technical innovation without significant advances in hardware technology, only based on the early development of technologies related to network and datum models. As a result, related technology development is very sluggish.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>5. Discussion</title>
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>5.1. Cim related technology</title>
          
          <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">The examination of the current patent topics in this work leads to the identification of technical CIM-related topics. Data collection, data transmission, data storage, and data application are the four main technological domains that the technologies associated with CIM and Smart City fall under [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>]. CIM views the city as a whole, or as an organic system capable of intelligent and coordinated operation, from a technological perspective. Hence, the city is transformed into an ever-more-powerful digital system. Through the communication control module and the circuit control (nervous system), sensor signals like camera signal and temperature (sensory system) are embedded into the ubiquitous information terminal and datum model (brain), directing automatic drive, pipeline detection, and other data terminals. CIM, which is an essential component of managing smart cities, is the digital twin of urban entities on digital equipment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. However, because management technology is not included in the CIM construction as a concept of digital information technology, it is unable to completely actualize smart management even though it can assist urban intelligence management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. Along with digital information technology, management technologies such as policy-driven management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>] and social restrictions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">50</xref>] should be taken into account when managing smart cities.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">From a technological standpoint, the research of CIM now concentrates on IOT-related technologies (such as camera signals, electrical equipment, body equipment, and temperature sensors), big data, and data management technology (plurality storage). Mobile communication has greatly advanced with the adoption of 4G and 5G technologies, supplying the network infrastructure for the quick development of the IOT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>]. IOT technology advancements have resulted in an increase in data volume and data types in cities. This enhances the usefulness of and active development in associated data scheduling and management technologies (such as effective indexing, databases, and distributed storage).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>5.2. Development trends and focus of cim technology</title>
          
          <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Two tendencies in the advancement of CIM technology were identified by the analysis of the existing patent literature. Namely, software technology progress tends to slack off while hardware technology advances steadily. These trends do not necessarily reflect the relative importance of hardware and software technology, but rather the inadequacies in the current hardware that prevent it from supporting the significant advancement of software technology. For some target recognition applications, high-resolution image technology is necessary. For instance, in autopilot systems, target recognition is crucial, making lidar and camera necessary. The topic transition diagram also demonstrated the flow of target reorganization technology research and development to other technology sectors, including video signal and communication control module research. This highlighted the necessity for additional study on automated driving technology. As a result, municipal administrators must raise their spending on hardware R&amp;amp;amp;D to further the development and promotion of CIM. To encourage the creation of the related follow-up applications, the hardware technology must continuously advance.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>6. Conclusions</title>
      <p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">City managers must transition from traditional urban administration to intelligent city management using high-tech tools as a result of the sharp increase in urban population. The growing demand for intelligent city management among city managers has accelerated the technological advancement of related services and goods, with the development of the associated CIM technology being essential to the creation of the smart city. Therefore, it is urgently needed to reassess CIM technology development. The LDA topic model and HMM are used in this study to offer a fresh approach to mining and forecasting the topics of scientific publications. The technique allows for speedy mining of hidden topic information, collecting the main subject nodes and topic evolution patterns, and enabling efficient and unsupervised (i.e., without expert input) clustering of literature. It also offers a novel approach to text analysis.</p><p style="text-indent: 10.2pt;">Our method divides the associated technologies in the field of CIM into 17 topics, with the R&amp;amp;amp;D of CIM patented technology focused on plurality storage, camera signal, electronic equip, body equipment, and temperature sensor. The three most significant technological advancement directions in the future are front-end collecting technology, terminal application technology, and data management technology. The hardware supporting technology for CIM needs to be developed concurrently, in contrast to the software technology. The technology particularly covers information transmission equipment, storage equipment, and information collecting equipment (cameras, sensors, etc.). As these fields are still in the early stages of research, it is necessary to increase their capacity for innovation. Scientific research institutes from different nations will need to find a solution to the issue of how to conduct additional innovative research on these R&amp;amp;amp;D topics in the future.</p><p>The limitations of this study, however, may serve as a guiding principle for future research. First and foremost, this article exclusively examined the patent information included in the WIPO Patentscope database. Additional patent information from various patent databases should be included in future studies. Second, this study classifies the related topics using the LDA model. Future studies will analyze CIM patent documents using various categorization techniques, such as the BERT model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>]. Finally, the disparities between various locations are not taken into consideration in the examination of technology development trends that has been presented. Future research will therefore compare CIM development trends in other nations.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This study was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No.: 71972018 and 72104064); the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (Grant No.: 2021CDJSKJC02 and 2022CDJSKPY13).</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>Some or all data, models, or code that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Arbolino</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Carlucci</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Cirà</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Ioppolo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Yigitcanlar</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Efficiency of the EU regulation on greenhouse gas emissions in Italy: The hierarchical cluster analysis approach</article-title>
          <source>Ecol. Indic.</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>115-123</page-range>
          <fpage>115</fpage>
          <lpage>123</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolind.2017.05.053</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Arbolino</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Carlucci</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Cirà</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Yigitcanlar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Ioppolo</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mitigating regional disparities through microfinancing: An analysis of microcredit as a sustainability tool for territorial development in Italy</article-title>
          <source>Land. Use. Policy.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>281-288</page-range>
          <fpage>281</fpage>
          <lpage>288</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landusepol.2017.10.042</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Yigitcanlar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Kamruzzaman</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Buys</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Ioppolo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Sabatini-Marques</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>E. M.</given-names>
              <surname>da Costa</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Yun</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Understanding 'smart cities': Intertwining development drivers with desired outcomes in a multidimensional framework</article-title>
          <source>Cities.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>145-160</page-range>
          <fpage>145</fpage>
          <lpage>160</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cities.2018.04.003</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Allwinkle and P</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Creating smart-er cities: An overview</article-title>
          <source>J. Urban Technol.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>1-16</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>16</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1080/10630732.2011.601103</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
              <surname>Griffith</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Smart governance for smart growth: The need for regional governments</article-title>
          <source>Ga. St. UL Rev.</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>1019-1019</page-range>
          <fpage>1019</fpage>
          <lpage>1019</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>R. P.</given-names>
              <surname>Dameri and C</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Governing smart cities: an empirical analysis</article-title>
          <source>Soc. Sci. Comput. Rev.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>693-707</page-range>
          <fpage>693</fpage>
          <lpage>707</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1177/089443931561109</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K. H.</given-names>
              <surname>Soon and V</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Khoo</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CityGML modelling for Singapore 3d national mapping</article-title>
          <source>Int. Arch. Photogramm. Remote Sens-Basel. Spat. Inform. Sci.</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>37-42</page-range>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>42</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>White</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Zink</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Codecá</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A digital twin smart city for citizen feedback</article-title>
          <source>Cities.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cities.2020.103064</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103064</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Selecting optimal combination of data channels for semantic segmentation in city information modelling (CIM)</article-title>
          <source>Remote Sens-Basel.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <page-range>1367-1367</page-range>
          <fpage>1367</fpage>
          <lpage>1367</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/rs13071367</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z. J. M.</given-names>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A systematic review of a digital twin city: A new pattern of urban governance toward smart cities</article-title>
          <source>J. Manag Sci. Eng.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>125-134</page-range>
          <fpage>125</fpage>
          <lpage>134</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmse.2021.03.003</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>El Saddik</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Digital twins: The convergence of multimedia technologies</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Multimedia.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>87-92</page-range>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/MMUL.2018.023121167</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G. Q.</given-names>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Li</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C. Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Li</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A transformer-based deep learning model for recognizing communication-oriented entities from patents of ICT in construction</article-title>
          <source>Automat. Constr.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.autcon.2021.103608</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103608</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Alkandari</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Alnasheet</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>I. F.</given-names>
              <surname>Alshaikhli</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Smart cities: A survey</article-title>
          <source>J. Adv. Comput Sci. Tech Res.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>79-90</page-range>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
              <surname>Albino</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Ardito</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R. M.</given-names>
              <surname>Dangelico</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
              <surname>Petruzzelli</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Understanding the development trends of low-carbon energy technologies: A patent analysis</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Energ.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>135</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>836-854</page-range>
          <fpage>836</fpage>
          <lpage>854</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy.2014.08.012</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Pellicer</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Santa</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. L.</given-names>
              <surname>Bleda</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Maestre</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Jara</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. G.</given-names>
              <surname>Skarmeta</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>A global perspective of smart cities: A survey</article-title>
          <source/>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>
          <conf-name>2013 Seventh International Conference on Innovative Mobile and Internet Services in Ubiquitous Computing, Taichung</conf-name>
          <conf-acronym/>
          <conf-loc>Taiwan</conf-loc>
          <conf-date>03-05 July 2013</conf-date>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>439-444</page-range>
          <fpage>439</fpage>
          <lpage>444</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/IMIS.2013.79.</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T. L.</given-names>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Hsu</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Revolution on digital twin technology-a patent research approach</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Adv Manu Tech.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>107</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>4687-4704</page-range>
          <fpage>4687</fpage>
          <lpage>4704</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00170-020-05314-w</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Samih</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Smart cities and internet of things</article-title>
          <source>J. Inform Tech Case. Appli Res.</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>3-12</page-range>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1080/15228053.2019.1587572</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Wonglimpiyarat</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Technological change of the energy innovation system: From oil-based to bio-based energy</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Energ.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>749-755</page-range>
          <fpage>749</fpage>
          <lpage>755</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy.2009.08.043</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Liu and J</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Strategic planning for technology development with patent analysis</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Technol. Manage.</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>661-680</page-range>
          <fpage>661</fpage>
          <lpage>680</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1504/IJTM.1997.001689</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Menouar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
              <surname>Guvenc</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Akkaya</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Uluagac</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Kadri</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Tuncer</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>UAV-enabled intelligent transportation systems for the smart city: Applications and challenges</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Commun. Mag.</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>22-28</page-range>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/MCOM.2017.1600238CM</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Yigitcanlar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Fabian</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
              <surname>Coiacetto</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Challenges to urban transport sustainability and smart transport in a tourist city: The Gold Coast, Australia</article-title>
          <source>Open Trans. J.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>29-46</page-range>
          <fpage>29</fpage>
          <lpage>46</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.2174/1874447800802010029</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M. D.</given-names>
              <surname>Lytras</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Visvizi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Sarirete</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clustering smart city services: Perceptions, expectations, responses</article-title>
          <source>Sustain.</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>1669-1669</page-range>
          <fpage>1669</fpage>
          <lpage>1669</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/su11061669</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Parra</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Sendra</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Lloret</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
              <surname>Bosch</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of a conductivity sensor for monitoring groundwater resources to optimize water management in smart city environments</article-title>
          <source>Sensors-Basel.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <page-range>20990-21015</page-range>
          <fpage>20990</fpage>
          <lpage>21015</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/s150920990</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A. P.</given-names>
              <surname>Lara</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>E. M.</given-names>
              <surname>Da Costa</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T. Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Furlani</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Yigitcanla</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Smartness that matters: Towards a comprehensive and human-centred characterisation of smart cities</article-title>
          <source>J. Open Innovation. Tech. Market. Complexity.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>8-8</page-range>
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1186/s40852-016-0034-z</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Mora</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Bolici</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Deakin</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The first two decades of smart-city research: A bibliometric analysis</article-title>
          <source>J. Urban Technol.</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>3-27</page-range>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1080/10630732.2017.1285123</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Stojanovski</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>City Information Modelling (CIM) and Urban Design-Morphological Structure, Design Elements and Programming Classes in CIM</article-title>
          <source>eCAADe</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>2018</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>507-516</page-range>
          <fpage>507</fpage>
          <lpage>516</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.52842/conf.ecaade.2018.1.507</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>From building information modeling to city information modeling</article-title>
          <source>J Inf. Technol. Constr.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>292-307</page-range>
          <fpage>292</fpage>
          <lpage>307</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Magrí</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Giovannini</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Connan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Bridoux</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Béline</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nutrient management from biogas digester effluents: a bibliometric-based analysis of publications and patents</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Environ. Sci. Te.</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <page-range>1739-1756</page-range>
          <fpage>1739</fpage>
          <lpage>1756</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s13762-017-1293-3</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>C. G.</given-names>
              <surname>Figuerola</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F. J.</given-names>
              <surname>García Marco</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Pinto</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mapping the evolution of library and information science (1978–2014) using topic modeling on LISA</article-title>
          <source>Scientometrics.</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>1507-1535</page-range>
          <fpage>1507</fpage>
          <lpage>1535</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11192-017-2432-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T. D.</given-names>
              <surname>Bowman</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Milojević</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
              <surname>Larivière</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A lead-lag analysis of the topic evolution patterns for preprints and publications</article-title>
          <source>J. Assoc. Inf. Sci. Tech.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>2643-2656</page-range>
          <fpage>2643</fpage>
          <lpage>2656</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.23347</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Qiang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Finding academic concerns of the Three Gorges Project based on a topic modeling approach</article-title>
          <source>Ecol. Indic.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>693-701</page-range>
          <fpage>693</fpage>
          <lpage>701</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolind.2015.08.007</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
              <surname>Blei</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Ng</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. I.</given-names>
              <surname>Jordan</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Latent dirichlet allocation</article-title>
          <source>J. Mach. Learn. Res.</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>993-1022</page-range>
          <fpage>993</fpage>
          <lpage>1022</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
              <surname>Blei</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Probabilistic topic models</article-title>
          <source>Commun. ACM</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>77-84</page-range>
          <fpage>77</fpage>
          <lpage>84</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1145/2133806.2133826</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
              <surname>Li</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Application of grey prediction theory to forecast technology input within the Chinese High-Tech Industries</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Adv. Compu. Technol.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/ICACC.2011.6016373</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>G. E.</given-names>
              <surname>Heo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K. Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Kang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Song</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analyzing the field of bioinformatics with the multi-faceted topic modeling technique</article-title>
          <source>BMC Bioinformatics.</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <page-range>45-57</page-range>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>57</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12859-017-1640-x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Hargadon and R</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
              <surname>Sutton</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Technology brokering and innovation in a product development firm</article-title>
          <source>Admin. Sci. Quart.</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>716-749</page-range>
          <fpage>716</fpage>
          <lpage>749</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.2307/2393655</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Rogers and M</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title/>
          <source>The definition and measurement of innovation, Parkville</source>
          <publisher-loc>VIC</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research</publisher-name>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>L. E.</given-names>
              <surname>Baum and T</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Statistical inference for probabilistic functions of finite state Markov chains</article-title>
          <source>Ann. Math Stat.</source>
          <year>1966</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>1554-1563</page-range>
          <fpage>1554</fpage>
          <lpage>1563</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Francissen and K</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Tsagarousianou</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Tambini</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>Bryan</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Virtually going places: Square hopping in Amsterdam's digital city</article-title>
          <source>Cyberdemocracy</source>
          <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>18-40</page-range>
          <fpage>18</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Dykes</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Andrienko</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
              <surname>Andrienko</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
              <surname>Paelke</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Schiewe</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Editorial–GeoVisualization and the digital city</article-title>
          <source>Comput. Environ. Urban</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>443-451</page-range>
          <fpage>443</fpage>
          <lpage>451</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compenvurbsys.2010.09.001</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>G. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Yovanof and G</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
              <surname>Hazapis</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An architectural framework and enabling wireless technologies for digital cities &amp; intelligent urban environments</article-title>
          <source>Wireless Pers. Commun.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>445-463</page-range>
          <fpage>445</fpage>
          <lpage>463</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11277-009-9693-4</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Batty</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Big data and the city</article-title>
          <source>Built Enviro.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>321-337</page-range>
          <fpage>321</fpage>
          <lpage>337</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.2148/benv.42.3.321</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Han</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Challenges of big data analysis</article-title>
          <source>Natl. Sci. Rev.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>293-314</page-range>
          <fpage>293</fpage>
          <lpage>314</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1093/nsr/nwt032</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>Lim</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P. P.</given-names>
              <surname>Maglio</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Smart cities with big data: Reference models, challenges, and considerations</article-title>
          <source>Cities.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>86-99</page-range>
          <fpage>86</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cities.2018.04.011</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
              <surname>Tole</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Big data challenges</article-title>
          <source>Database Sys. J.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>31-40</page-range>
          <fpage>31</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S. E.</given-names>
              <surname>Bibri</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The IoT for smart sustainable cities of the future: An analytical framework for sensor-based big data applications for environmental sustainability</article-title>
          <source>Sustain. Cities Soc.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>230-253</page-range>
          <fpage>230</fpage>
          <lpage>253</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scs.2017.12.034</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Neirotti</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>De Marco</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. C.</given-names>
              <surname>Cagliano</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Mangano</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Scorrano</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Current trends in Smart City initiatives: Some stylised facts</article-title>
          <source>Cities.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>25-36</page-range>
          <fpage>25</fpage>
          <lpage>36</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cities.2013.12.010</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Allam and Z</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Dhunny</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On big data, artificial intelligence and smart cities</article-title>
          <source>Cities.</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>80-91</page-range>
          <fpage>80</fpage>
          <lpage>91</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cities.2019.01.032</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Caragliu and C</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Smartness and European urban performance: assessing the local impacts of smart urban attributes</article-title>
          <source>Innovation. Eur. J. Soc Sci. Res.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>97-113</page-range>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <lpage>113</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1080/13511610.2012.660323</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
              <surname>Beretta</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The social effects of eco-innovations in Italian smart cities</article-title>
          <source>Cities.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>115-121</page-range>
          <fpage>115</fpage>
          <lpage>121</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cities.2017.07.010</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Devlin</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. W.</given-names>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Toutanova</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bert: Pre-training of deep bidirectional transformers for language understanding</article-title>
          <source>Comput Sci</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>2018</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.1810.04805</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>