<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CIS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Challenges in Sustainability</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Chall. Sustain.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">CIS</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2297-6477</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print"/>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-cGOV96hROFBsoTqtHjkWQFz4i2ZylYrO</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/cis130403</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Modelling Adaptation to Climate Change among Small-Scale Fishermen in Bengkulu Province in Indonesia</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9324-2652</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mulyasari</surname>
            <given-names>Gita</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>gita.mulyasari@unib.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2811-9391</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Cahyadinata</surname>
            <given-names>Indra</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>cahyadinata@unib.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2609-061X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Irham</surname>
          </name>
          <email>irham@ugm.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0728-8241</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Hadi</surname>
            <given-names>Arif Ismul</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>ismulhadi@unib.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Agricultural Socio-Economics, University of Bengkulu, 38371 Bengkulu, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Department of Agricultural Socio-Economics, Gadjah Mada University, 55281 Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">Department of Geophysics, Faculty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences, University of Bengkulu, 38371 Bengkulu, Indonesia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>508</fpage>
      <lpage>524</lpage>
      <page-range>508-524</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Climate change poses severe challenges to small-scale fisheries, which require critical adaptation strategies. This study developed a model of climate change adaptation among small-scale fishermen in Bengkulu Province, Indonesia, using a framework that links poverty, livelihood vulnerability, and adaptive capacity. This study contributes novel empirical evidence on how these factors interact to shape adaptive behavior in small-scale fisheries within a developing country context. Data was collected from a survey of 700 fishing households selected by quota sampling. The direct and indirect relationships among socioeconomic variables and adaptation strategies were examined using path analysis in Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) and Analysis of Moment Structures (AMOS). The findings revealed that poverty had a significantly adverse effect on the adaptive capacity of fishermen, limiting their capability to respond effectively to climate stressors. Consequently, a majority of fishermen relied on low-cost and easily implemented strategies, such as adjusting fishing times and shifting fishing grounds. Fishing experience, vessel capacity, fishing distance, and the type of fishing gear, in contrast, showed significantly positive effects on adaptation. These results underscore that economic constraints weaken adaptive capacity, while technical assets and practical knowledge enhance resilience. The policy implications highlighted the imperative to strengthen fishermen’s institutions, update fleets, establish cooperatives, diversify fishing gear, and provide accessible digital climate information services. Such governmental interventions are crucial for enhancing adaptive capacity, supporting the sustainable management of fisheries, and improving the economic resilience of coastal communities.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Adaptation</kwd>
        <kwd>Climate change</kwd>
        <kwd>Livelihood vulnerability</kwd>
        <kwd>Poverty</kwd>
        <kwd>Small-scale fishermen</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="4"/>
        <fig-count count="9"/>
        <table-count count="5"/>
        <ref-count count="65"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Global climate change, primarily driven by human activities, has increased the Earth’s surface temperature by approximately 0.85℃ over the last century. Projections indicated that by the end of the twenty-first century, this increase would have reached at least 1.5℃ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">IPCC, 2014</xref>). The trends of recent warming have exacerbated poverty and inequality; these issues are expected to worsen, particularly in vulnerable regions, as global temperatures continue to rise beyond 1.5℃ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">IPCC, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">Kaua et al., 2021</xref>). Coastal areas are particularly susceptible to climate change due to the combined effects of land and sea factors. Climate change has four primary impacts on coastal regions: (1) rising sea levels; (2) shifts in storm patterns and rainfall; (3) increasing temperatures of coastal water; and (4) ocean acidification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">EPA, 2013</xref>). In recent years, fishermen have observed significant disruptions in seasonal patterns, closely aligning with the broader impact of global warming. Uneven seasonal wind patterns have increased the difficulties for fishermen in determining safe and effective fishing times in the sea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">Siregar &amp;amp; Civil Society Forum for Climate Justice, 2011</xref>). Many fishermen misjudge seasonal wind patterns, posing risks to their safety and fish catches. This challenge is particularly pronounced for fishermen operating in waters adjacent to the open ocean, such as those along the western coast of Sumatra, southern Java, Bali, West Nusa Tenggara (NTB), East Nusa Tenggara (NTT), and northern Papua. Miscalculations can lead to hazardous encounters with high waves and strong winds, sometimes resulting in the sinking of fishing vessels.</p><p>Climate change further intensifies the vulnerability of coastal communities, which are already at risk due to erosion and human activities that degrade coastal ecosystems. Increased climate variability disrupts fishing operations, as harsher sea conditions reduce fishing opportunities and catch volumes. This, in turn, negatively impacts the incomes of households, particularly those who rely solely on the fisheries sector for their livelihood. The economic challenges faced by fishermen due to declining fish stocks and unstable marine ecosystems underscore the urgent need for adaptation strategies.</p><p>As the frequency of climate-related disasters has increased and climate projections have gained credibility, adaptation has become a global priority (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">IPCC, 2014</xref>). The primary objectives of climate adaptation include reducing vulnerability, strengthening resilience, and fostering climate-resilient fisheries. This involves modifying fishing practices, resource management, and operational strategies to align with changing climatic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_55">Shaffril et al., 2017</xref>). The crucial component of adaptation, adaptive capacity, refers to a system’s ability to mobilize resources, recover from stressors, and continue functioning despite environmental shocks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Engle, 2011</xref>). Strengthening adaptive capacity helps mitigate socioeconomic and biophysical vulnerabilities linked to climate change.</p><p>Adaptation to climate change can be spontaneous or planned, depending on the urgency of environmental changes and the available resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">Murdiyarso, 2003</xref>). Effective adaptation strategies involve reducing vulnerability, enhancing resilience, and increasing adaptation capacity to determine the success of these actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_57">Smit &amp;amp; Wandel, 2006</xref>). From a sociocultural perspective, adaptation is also a component of cultural evolution, representing the adjustment of individuals and communities to environmental and social changes over time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Helmi &amp;amp; Satria, 2012</xref>). Responsive behaviors, shaped by past experiences, enable individuals to develop coping mechanisms and strategies to navigate changing conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Bennett, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">Ogunbode et al., 2024</xref>). Various factors affect the adaptation to climate change in the fisheries sector. Key determinants include poverty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_63">Yesuph et al., 2023</xref>), access to technology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">Meena et al., 2019</xref>), resource availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">Jha &amp;amp; Amarnath, 2011</xref>), knowledge, infrastructure, financial markets, economic conditions, and overall wealth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">Panda, 2016</xref>). Since adaptation requires logical, practical, and cost-effective solutions, individual fishermen play a crucial role in determining how to respond to fluctuating weather patterns and changing marine conditions.</p><p>Studies on climate change and adaptation have been widely carried out (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Ding et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Fahad &amp;amp; Wang, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">Handayani et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Jamshidi et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">Kim et al., 2024</xref>), and only a few concerns poverty and livelihood vulnerability as variables in adaptation to climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Baptiste &amp;amp; Kinlocke, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Burnham &amp;amp; Ma, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Koehn et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">Oo et al., 2018</xref>). Most studies on adaptation to climate change were partially related to policy and regional vulnerability. Rarely does climate change adaptation analysis fully incorporate an understanding of climate change, poverty, and livelihood vulnerability as determining factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Andrista et al., 2025</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Herreros-Cantis et al., 2025</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">Mensah et al., 2025</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_64">Zeray, 2025</xref>). This study reveals not only the issue of climate change but also its effects on poverty, livelihood vulnerability, and adaptation as perceived by fishermen. Research related to the impact of climate change on fishermen in Indonesia was minimal; those in existence are mainly about adaptation strategies and primarily on the agricultural sector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">Nurhidayah &amp;amp; McIlgorm, 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_58">Susilowardhani, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_62">Yamamoto &amp;amp; Esteban, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_65">Zikra et al., 2015</xref>), particularly on Java Island, the center of economic growth in Indonesia.</p><p>Bengkulu Province, situated on the western coast of Indonesia, is particularly vulnerable to the impacts of climate change. The region, with a coastline of approximately 525 km along the Indian Ocean, features relatively narrow coastal plains highly susceptible to climate-related disasters, including floods, landslides, extreme weather events, tornadoes, and droughts. Notably, North Bengkulu Regency, located on Bangkai Island and Satu Island, is gradually sinking due to rising sea levels, while Enggano Island is experiencing a size reduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_60">Wongke, 2011</xref>). Additionally, coastal erosion poses a severe threat to local communities. According to Nurcholis Sastro, Disaster Coordinator at the Women’s Crisis Center (WCC) Cahaya Perempuan in Bengkulu, at least 20 villages along the Bengkulu coast are expected to be submerged by 2040 due to rapid coastal erosion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">Kupasbengkulu, 2013</xref>). Most fishermen reported growing concerns about unpredictable weather patterns, which have become increasingly chaotic and challenging to forecast. Traditionally, fishermen have relied on inherited knowledge and generational experience to determine the best times for fishing. However, the shifting climate has rendered these time-tested references unreliable, forcing many fishermen to fish under dangerous and uncertain conditions.</p><p>Given the heightened vulnerability of small-scale fishermen, this study developed a model to address climate change adaptation strategies. The research considered multiple factors, including poverty, livelihood vulnerability, vessel size, fishing distance, fishermen’s awareness of the impact of climate change, and other relevant socioeconomic and environmental variables. In this study, understanding these interconnections could provide valuable insights into how small-scale fishermen could build resilience against climate change and sustain their livelihoods in the face of increasing challenges.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Framework of research</title>
      <p>Fishermen constitute one of the most vulnerable groups susceptible to the impact of climate change, particularly in developing countries such as Indonesia, where around 90% of the 16.2 million fishermen live below the poverty line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Acheson, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Emerson, 1980</xref>). Poverty among fishermen is multidimensional, reflected not only by their low income but also by their restricted access to education, health services, technology, and institutional support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">Nurkse, 1953</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">Nurwati, 2008</xref>). These limitations reduce their ability to anticipate, respond to, and recover from climate-related shocks, thus creating a strong link between poverty and livelihood vulnerability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Cutter et al., 2003</xref>).</p><p>Livelihood vulnerability refers to the degree of exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity of fishing households to external and internal stressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Chen &amp;amp; Lopez-Carr, 2015</xref>). In coastal communities, climate change increases vulnerability by reducing fish stocks, damaging ecosystems, and amplifying risks from extreme weather (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">IPCC, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_55">Shaffril et al., 2017</xref>). Vulnerability is further exacerbated when socioeconomic conditions prevent fishermen from accessing adaptive strategies, such as diversifying livelihoods and upgrading fishing gear. Thus, poverty and vulnerability are interrelated factors jointly undermining adaptive capacity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_63">Yesuph et al., 2023</xref>).</p><p>Adaptation is recognized as the primary strategy for minimizing risks and enhancing resilience in the fisheries sector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_57">Smit &amp;amp; Wandel, 2006</xref>). However, empirical studies often remained descriptive, failing to integrate causal relationships among poverty, livelihood vulnerability, and adaptive responses. To address this gap, the present study incorporated the Multidimensional Poverty Index (MPI) and the Livelihood Vulnerability Index (LVI) into a structural model to explain fishermen’s adaptation strategies. Socioeconomic characteristics, including age, education, fishing experience, vessel capacity, fishing distance, and fishing gear, were identified as critical determinants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Abid et al., 2019</xref>). Moreover, fishermen’s awareness of climate change mediated the relationship between vulnerability and adaptation, as higher awareness fostered proactive adjustments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">Piggott-McKellar et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Institutional support also plays a moderating role. Strong fishing cooperatives, access to climate information, and government assistance could strengthen adaptive capacity by enhancing resource availability and collective action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Gupta et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Heydari et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">Olayide &amp;amp; Alabi, 2018</xref>). Without institutional reinforcement, adaptation, such as adjusting fishing times and changing fishing grounds, remains low-cost and reactive, hence insufficiently addressing long-term risks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Helmi &amp;amp; Satria, 2012</xref>).</p><p>The research framework posits that poverty and livelihood vulnerability negatively affect adaptation strategies, while socioeconomic characteristics and awareness positively influence adaptation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>). The novelty of this study lies in empirically demonstrating that multidimensional poverty and livelihood vulnerability jointly shaped adaptive behaviors among small-scale fishermen in Bengkulu Province. Evidence was provided to support policy interventions that combine poverty alleviation, climate information services, and institutional strengthening.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Framework of research on the interrelationship among poverty, livelihood vulnerability, and modelling adaptation to climate change</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_hQ1VEDRVIDj160DH.png"/>
        </fig>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Methodology</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Description of the study area</title>
          
          <p>Bengkulu City, Central Bengkulu Regency, North Bengkulu Regency, Mukomuko Regency, South Bengkulu Regency, and Kaur Regency were coastal regions covered in this study, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>. Bengkulu Province is situated to the west of the Bukit Barisan highlands. Its total area is 19,919.33 square kilometers or 1,991,933 hectares, and its boundary with West Sumatra Province is around 567 km away (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">Mulyasari et al., 2023</xref>).</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Locations of research processed by authors in 2024</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_jvcfmn0uBs7HNSkH.jpeg"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Bengkulu Province has a coastline that stretches approximately 525 km along the Indian Ocean. It is located between latitudes 2°16′ and 3°31′ south and longitudes 101°01′ and 103°41′ east. While the western portion comprises relatively narrow, low-lying lands stretching north to south and dotted with undulating landscapes, the eastern portion features steep terrain and rich highlands. The seas of Bengkulu Province act as a meeting point of four major ocean currents, forming an essential center of climate variability. This interaction produces rain clouds through evaporation processes, which affect seasonal patterns and the world climate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">Mulyasari et al., 2023</xref>). Due to its vulnerability to extreme climate, Bengkulu Province, located on the western coast of Sumatra Island, was specifically chosen for this study.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Sampling and collection of data</title>
          
          <p>The data for this study were collected by a questionnaire survey comprising 700 small-scale fishing households in the coastal districts of Bengkulu Province. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> illustrates the sampling procedure, in which quota sampling was employed to select the respondents. This study examined small-scale fisheries, such as artisanal or traditional fisheries, characterized by fishing households that use relatively small vessels (≤ 10 GT), undertake short fishing trips typically lasting one day, and possess limited resources. The questionnaire consisted of four major components: the first part involved asking respondents about their age, education, level of experience with fishing, size of home, income, and other employment details. The second part examined features of small-scale fisheries, including boat power, number of fishing days, length of journey, fishing distance, catch capacity, membership in fishing associations, availability of loans, and access to climate data. The third part of the questionnaire focuses on multidimensional poverty and livelihood vulnerability, including exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity based on 14 indicators of livelihood vulnerability as defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Chen &amp;amp; Lopez-Carr (2015)</xref>. The last part of the questionnaire is the adaptation of small-scale fishermen to climate change.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Schematic presentation of the sampling procedure</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_eDv6c47fK58SJo3L.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Analysis of data</title>
          
          <p>Path analysis was employed to create models that examined the effects of poverty, fishermen’s awareness of the impact of climate change, and livelihood vulnerability on climate change adaptation. This technique is a multivariate method used to analyze the nature and causal relationships, both direct and indirect or mediated, among several variables. Generally, there are two methods for analyzing route models: (a) estimation using a model selection tool such as Analysis of Moment Structures (AMOS); and (b) multiple regression analysis. The multiple regression strategy was carried out using Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS), which estimates path coefficients using the ordinary least squares method. On the other hand, AMOS often computes path coefficients using maximum likelihood estimation, which helps determine parameter values that maximize the likelihood of the model being correctly specified. In addition to these benefits, AMOS evaluates the indirect and total effects of predictor variables, model fit, and the accuracy with which the model represents the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Etemadi &amp;amp; Karami, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">Meyers et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>Model estimation with the AMOS program is available, using the default maximum likelihood model. Model estimation was conducted using the AMOS program with the maximum likelihood method. To assess the suitability of the model, several goodness-of-fit (GOF) indices were employed. First, the chi-square statistic was used to determine whether the proposed model differed significantly from the observed data. Since chi-square is sensitive to large sample sizes, additional fit indices were used for a more reliable evaluation.</p><p>The Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA) was calculated to assess the degree of approximation in the population, with values below 0.08 indicating an acceptable fit. The Goodness of Fit Index (GFI) and Adjusted Goodness of Fit Index (AGFI) were then used to evaluate the proportion of variance explained by the model, with values above 0.90 considered satisfactory. To account for model parsimony, the chi-square value was divided by the degrees of freedom (CMIN/DF), with a ratio ≤ 2.00 reflecting a good fit.</p><p>Furthermore, the Tucker–Lewis Index (TLI) and the Non-Normed Fit Index (NNFI) were employed to compare the specified model against a null model, where values above 0.90 indicated adequate fit. Together, these indices provided a comprehensive assessment of the overall model suitability, ensuring that the structural relationships tested were well supported by the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Dachlan, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Ferdinand, 2006</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Characteristics of small-scale fishery</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Socioeconomic characteristics</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> illustrates the socioeconomic characteristics of the respondents and their households, including age, formal education, household size, fishing experience, fishing income, and side jobs.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Characteristics of small-scale fishermen</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Characteristics</p></td><td><p>Categories</p></td><td><p>Frequencies</p></td><td><p>Proportion (%)</p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><p>Age (years)</p></td><td><p>17–35</p></td><td><p>230</p></td><td><p>32.86</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>36–54</p></td><td><p>357</p></td><td><p>50.95</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>55–74</p></td><td><p>113</p></td><td><p>16.19</p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5"><p>Formal education</p></td><td><p>None</p></td><td><p>44</p></td><td><p>6.19</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Elementary school</p></td><td><p>460</p></td><td><p>65.71</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Junior high school</p></td><td><p>113</p></td><td><p>16.19</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>High school</p></td><td><p>60</p></td><td><p>8.57</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>University</p></td><td><p>23</p></td><td><p>3.33</p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><p>Household size (person)</p></td><td><p>0–2</p></td><td><p>234</p></td><td><p>33.33</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>3–5</p></td><td><p>443</p></td><td><p>63.33</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>6–7</p></td><td><p>23</p></td><td><p>3.33</p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><p>Fishing experience (years)</p></td><td><p>4–19</p></td><td><p>283</p></td><td><p>40.48</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>20–34</p></td><td><p>294</p></td><td><p>41.90</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>35–50</p></td><td><p>123</p></td><td><p>17.62</p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><p>Fishing income ($/month)</p></td><td><p>31–340</p></td><td><p>553</p></td><td><p>79.05</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>341–650</p></td><td><p>100</p></td><td><p>14.29</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>651–930</p></td><td><p>47</p></td><td><p>6.67</p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><p>Side job</p></td><td><p>Yes</p></td><td><p>153</p></td><td><p>21.90</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>No</p></td><td><p>547</p></td><td><p>78.10</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Characteristics of small-scale fishermen</title>
          
          <p>The characteristics of the respondents and their households, including ship weight, fishing time, fishing distance, fishing gear, use of a crewed ship, ship ownership, catch capacity, group membership, and access to climate information, were collected and presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Characteristics of small-scale fishermen: (a) Ship weight (gross tonnage); (b) Fishing time (hours); (c) Fishing distance (miles); (d) Fishing gear; (e) Use of crew ships; (f) Ship ownership; (g) Catch capacity (kg/trip); (h) Group membership; and (i) Access to climate information</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_WpjlAHd1AXEq3iHB.png"/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_Dyh5IR5rsvj2qZZA.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Results of analysis</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.1. Multidimensional poverty of small-scale fishermen</title>
          
          <p>Poverty is a complex, multidimensional issue that encompasses various aspects of life and is a challenging problem affecting nearly every country worldwide, including Indonesia. Measurement of poverty, with a multidimensional perspective, uses non-monetary approaches to assess deprivation. Poverty extends beyond insufficient income or consumption levels, which are commonly measured against welfare standards, such as minimum calorie requirements or the poverty line. It reflects limited access to essential economic, social, cultural, and political resources, thereby hindering individuals from fully participating in society. </p>
          
            <fig id="fig_5">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Percentages of poverty among small-scale fishermen in the coastal area of Bengkulu</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_iDzVbs6FEUsJUKYF.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_6">
              <label>Figure 6</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Climate change adaptation (a) most frequently, and (b) rarely by poor fishermen</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_QfOp0wma8t2d2CE4.png"/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_aRwDnGQdPm0l1E6j.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Moreover, poverty affects access to fundamental needs, including healthcare, education, clean water, and sanitation. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref>, the average poverty rate among fishers in the Bengkulu coastal area is 29.05%, exposing the problem of poverty in this vulnerable community.</p><p>Poor fishermen on the Bengkulu Coast employ low-cost climate change adaptation strategies that require minimal skills and resources. The typical strategy consists of: (1) adjusting fishing times to align with shifting seasonal patterns; and (2) modifying fishing areas or fishing grounds to follow fish migration patterns caused by varying ocean conditions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>a and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>b.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.2. Livelihood vulnerability of small-scale fishermen</title>
          
          <p>The vulnerability approach analyzes risks within a community and ecosystem, focusing on their exposure and ability to withstand external and internal disturbances. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref> shows that most fishers (68.89%) are highly susceptible to the impacts of climate change, while only 31.11% fall into the non-vulnerable category.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_7">
              <label>Figure 7</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Livelihood vulnerability of small-scale fishermen</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_BNUFmbVmMk2yeYnE.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>In particular, climate change has affected small-scale fishers through declining fish availability, unpredictable weather patterns, increased storm frequency, and higher operational costs. To cope with these impacts, fishers tend to rely on short-term strategies such as adjusting fishing grounds and times, reducing fishing trips during extreme weather, and utilizing basic ecosystem knowledge (e.g., tidal and seasonal patterns). However, their adaptive capacity remains limited due to financial constraints, inadequate access to technology, and weak institutional support, which further exacerbates livelihood vulnerability.</p><p>In the coastal areas of Bengkulu, fishers have experienced a significant decline in catches due to the loss of fishing grounds caused by climate change, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>. </p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Livelihood vulnerability index</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Dimensions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Indicators</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mean</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Status of Vulnerability<sup>*</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Exposure</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Decrease in catch</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.267</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Low</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Sensitivity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishery income</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.899</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Very high</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Number of trips</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.574</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Moderate</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing income for operational costs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.202</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Low</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="10"><p>Adaptive Capacity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishermen who do not share the organization</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.350</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Low</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A poor fishing family</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.179</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Very low</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Income as a fisherman</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.297</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Low</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Number of active fishermen</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Very high</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Average catch price</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.370</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Low</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing experience</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.481</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Moderate</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Age of the fisherman</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.460</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Moderate</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Non-fishery income</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.097</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Very low</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Boat power</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.409</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Moderate</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Catch capacity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.279</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Low</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_8">
              <label>Figure 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Adaptation strategies adopted by vulnerable fishermen (a) most frequently, and (b) rarely</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_wc6AwpnX77Z9L9Yy.png"/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_1qGVJd1b6ZD384Pb.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>To align with their economic and financial capabilities, small-scale fishermen in the Bengkulu coastal area adopt a range of climate change adaptation strategies. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>a, the most common strategies include adjusting fishing times (around 75%), shifting fishing grounds (above 80%), and diversifying fishing gear. These strategies are widely practiced because they are low-cost, rely on existing local knowledge, and can be implemented immediately without requiring institutional support.</p><p>By contrast, the strategies illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>b—such as diversification of economic activities, planting coastal vegetation, mobilizing family members to work, or strengthening fishers’ institutions—are used far less frequently (generally below 30%). These measures demand higher financial resources, longer-term commitment, or institutional coordination, which are often beyond the reach of small-scale fishermen. As a result, although these strategies could potentially enhance resilience, their adoption remains limited compared to the more accessible short-term coping strategies shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref>a.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.3. Modelling adaptation of small-scale fishermen to climate change</title>
          
          <p>Poverty and livelihood vulnerability are two distinct concepts, yet their interrelationship is evident in the key dimension of livelihood vulnerability in poverty assessments. The livelihood vulnerability of fishermen is closely tied to poverty levels and low adaptive capacity. Climate change, which often exacerbates poverty and increases vulnerability, significantly impacts fishers. Therefore, this research aimed to develop a model to analyze the impact of poverty and livelihood vulnerability on the climate change adaptation strategies employed by fishermen in the Bengkulu coastal area.</p><p>The extent of resource ownership by fishermen significantly affects their ability to adopt climate change adaptation measures. It is believed that the degree of poverty and vulnerability experienced by fishermen directly impacts their capacity to implement effective adaptation strategies. Two key processes were conducted to evaluate the structural equation model (SEM) in this research: (a) Assessing the overall model fit, Goodness of Fit, to evaluate the effectiveness of the model in representing the observed data; and (b) Testing hypotheses and analyzing the relationship of variables to determine the extent and significance of their influence on each other.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> demonstrates that the route analysis equation has a satisfactory model fit, meeting the overall criterion. This suggests that there is no substantial disparity between the covariance matrix of the observed variables and that of the proposed model, as indicated by the data. In this context, the model equation used in route analysis could effectively elucidate the relationships and impact between the dependent and independent variables. The structural equation derived from the route analysis results obtained from the fit model in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> can be constructed using the AMOS output in Regression Weights. Specifically, the equation can be generated as follows:</p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myc42tkkpu">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>7</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>7</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Results of goodness-of-fit path analysis</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Goodness of Fit Measure</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fit Value Indicator</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Results of Analysis</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Status</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Chi-square</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Getting smaller</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>24.937</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Probability</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>≥ 0.05</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.204</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CMIN/DF</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>≤ 2.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.247</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>GFI</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>≥ 0.90</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.980</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AGFI</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>≥ 0.90</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.933</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>RMSEA</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>≤ 0.08</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.034</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>TLI</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>≥ 0.90</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.971</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CFI</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>≥ 0.90</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.989</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_4">
              <label>Table 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Estimated values of the influence of each variable on the adaptation of fishermen</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Influence of the Variables</p></td><td><p>Expected Sign</p></td><td><p>Estimated Values</p></td><td><p><italic>P</italic></p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Adaptation (TA) ← Age (X1)</p></td><td><p>-</p></td><td><p>-0.001</p></td><td><p>0.071<sup>*</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Adaptation (TA) ← Formal education (X2)</p></td><td><p>+</p></td><td><p>0.000</p></td><td><p>0.871</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Adaptation (TA) ← Fishing experience (X3)</p></td><td><p>+</p></td><td><p>0.002</p></td><td><p>0.004<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Adaptation (TA) ← Household size (X4)</p></td><td><p>-</p></td><td><p>0.006</p></td><td><p>0.382</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Adaptation (TA) ← Ship weight (X5)</p></td><td><p>+</p></td><td><p>0.004</p></td><td><p>***<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Adaptation (TA) ← Fishing distance (X6)</p></td><td><p>+</p></td><td><p>0.004</p></td><td><p>***<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Adaptation (TA) ← Fishing gear (X7)</p></td><td><p>+</p></td><td><p>0.022</p></td><td><p>0.045<sup>**</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Adaptation (TA) ← Livelihood vulnerability (LVI)</p></td><td><p>-</p></td><td><p>-0.151</p></td><td><p>0.217</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Adaptation (TA) ← Poverty (MPI)</p></td><td><p>-</p></td><td><p>-0.171</p></td><td><p>0.034<sup>**</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Adaptation (TA) ← Climate change understanding (PI)</p></td><td><p>+</p></td><td><p>0.001</p></td><td><p>0.272</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>The estimated values of the influence of each variable and their significance are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>. The results of covariance output in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref> show the loading factor and critical ratio (<italic>C.R.</italic>) values for each indicator that reflects a variable. It is known that the values of the indicators in the path analysis model are valid because they have loading factor values &gt; 0.50 and significant values where the<italic> C.R.</italic> ≥ 2.00 or <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.1, indicated by a *** sign.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_5">
              <label>Table 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Estimated values of the loading factor and the critical ratio relationship between independent variables in path analysis</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Variable Correlation</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Loading Factor (Estimate)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>C.R.</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>P</italic></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Climate change understanding (PI) ↔ Poverty (MPI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.131</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.860</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.063</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Climate change understanding (PI) ↔ Livelihood vulnerability (LVI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.071</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.355</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.175</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Poverty (MPI) ↔ Livelihood vulnerability (LVI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.136</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.892</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing gear (X7) ↔ Climate change understanding (PI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.132</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.637</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing distance (X6) ↔ Livelihood vulnerability (LVI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.062</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.789</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.074</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing distance (X6) ↔ Fishing gear (X7)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.162</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-2.957</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.003</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ship weight (X5) ↔ Livelihood vulnerability (LVI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.254</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.076</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ship weight (X5) ↔ Climate change understanding (PI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>39.927</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.407</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ship weight (X5) ↔ Fishing gear (X7)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.363</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.413</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Age (X1) ↔ Livelihood vulnerability (LVI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.231</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.008</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Age (X1) ↔ Poverty (MPI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.247</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.393</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Age (X1) ↔ Climate change understanding (PI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-15.968</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-2.121</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.034</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Age (X1) ↔ Fishing gear (X7)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.599</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.410</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Formal education (X2) ↔ Poverty (MPI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.110</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-4.710</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Formal education (X2) ↔ Age (X1)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-11.722</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-5.091</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing experience (X3) ↔ Livelihood vulnerability (LVI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.170</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.800</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing experience (X3) ↔ Poverty (MPI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.241</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.191</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.001</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing experience (X3) ↔ Climate change understanding (PI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-25.725</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.395</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing experience (X3) ↔ Fishing gear (X7)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.759</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.676</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing experience (X3) ↔ Ship weight (X5)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-7.956</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.571</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.116</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing experience (X3) ↔ Age (X1)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>87.971</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9.068</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing experience (X3) ↔ Formal education (X2)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-16.587</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-6.504</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Household size (X4) ↔ Poverty (MPI)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.036</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.096</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>***</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Age (X1) ↔ Fishing distance (X6)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-5.223</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.970</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.332</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fishing experience (X3) ↔ Fishing distance (X6)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.430</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.054</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.292</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_9">
              <label>Figure 9</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Model of the influence of poverty, livelihood vulnerability, and understanding of climate change on the level of adaptation of fishermen</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_xw41yvkwGiFhAha3.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The analysis of the path analysis equation model in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref> reveals that the estimated parameter for the impact of fishermen’s poverty level on the level of climate change adaptation is -0.171. The <italic>C.R.</italic> value is 2.125, which exceeds the threshold of 2.00 (&gt; 2.00), indicating statistical significance at a 5% significance level or a <italic>P</italic> value of 0.034. The null hypothesis (H<sub>0</sub>) is rejected, thus indicating that poverty significantly and negatively affects the level of climate change adaptation among fishermen. There is an inverse relationship between poverty levels, as measured by the MPI, and the extent of climate change adaptation practices implemented by the fishermen.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>6. Discussion</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.1. Multidimensional poverty of small-scale fishermen</title>
          
          <p>Small-scale fishermen in Bengkulu Province are among the poorest rural groups, and their poverty is multidimensional rather than purely monetary. Limited education, low access to health services, restricted employment alternatives, and weak access to capital reinforce poverty traps that hinder livelihood improvement. The multidimensional poverty perspective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Alkire &amp;amp; Santos, 2014</xref>) emphasizes that overlapping deprivations exacerbate vulnerability, which explains why fishermen remain poor even when their incomes increase seasonally. Climate change exacerbates poverty by increasing operational costs, reducing fish availability, and creating uncertainty in weather patterns. Under such conditions, fishermen adopt only the most affordable coping strategies, such as adjusting their fishing times and shifting their fishing grounds. These strategies are consistent with findings in other regions, where poverty is a critical factor limiting the capacity of coastal communities to undertake long-term adaptation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Cinner et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_61">Xu et al., 2023</xref>).</p><p>The persistence of poverty among Bengkulu fishermen also reflects the persistence of structural and historical inequalities. For instance, most households rely solely on fishing for subsistence and are unable to accumulate savings to invest in vessel upgrades or alternative livelihoods. Similar findings were reported in small-scale fisheries in Africa and South Asia, where poverty traps are perpetuated by lack of access to credit and weak government support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Cinner et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Daw et al., 2009</xref>). Poverty also intersects with demographic factors: larger household sizes increase dependency ratios, thereby diluting household income and reinforcing vulnerability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">Nurkse, 1953</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">Nurwati, 2008</xref>). Furthermore, low levels of education—where the majority of respondents had only completed elementary school—restrict mobility into other sectors and limit awareness of climate-related risks. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Ananda et al. (2007)</xref> emphasize, low educational attainment directly constrains access to stable employment, health, and food security, thereby perpetuating intergenerational poverty.</p><p>Thus, the multidimensional poverty experienced by fishermen in Bengkulu not only reduces their ability to respond to environmental shocks but also shapes the kinds of adaptation strategies they can realistically adopt. Rather than pursuing transformative measures, they are forced into reactive and low-cost strategies, such as shifting fishing grounds or reducing fishing days. These findings align with those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_61">Xu et al. (2023)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_59">van Noordwijk et al. (2016)</xref>, who note that poverty and resource dependence often lead communities toward short-term responses that maintain survival but do not necessarily enhance long-term resilience.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.2. Livelihood vulnerability of small-scale fishermen</title>
          
          <p>Livelihood vulnerability in Bengkulu emerges from high dependence on fisheries, weak diversification, and limited technical capacity. The vulnerability index indicates that economic and technical aspects—such as income reliance on fishing, small vessel size, and restricted fishing range—contribute most strongly to risk exposure. Socio-cultural constraints, including low educational attainment and reliance on traditional knowledge, further limit adaptive responses. These findings align with studies in other small-scale fisheries, where livelihood vulnerability is exacerbated by ecological shocks combined with weak institutional support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Cinner et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">Pomeroy et al., 2006</xref>). Climate change increases vulnerability by reducing fish stocks, damaging ecosystems, and amplifying risks from extreme weather (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Carron et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">IPCC, 2014</xref>).</p><p>The measurement results of the LVI also reflect varying levels of vulnerability across exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity. Indicators such as fishery income (0.899) and the number of active fishermen (1.000) fall into the very high vulnerability category, indicating that households remain heavily dependent on daily catches for survival. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Cinner et al. (2018)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_61">Xu et al. (2023)</xref> similarly found that dependence on capture fisheries without livelihood diversification greatly amplifies vulnerability during shifts in fishing seasons or declines in catch. This condition is evident in traditional communities in Kaur and Mukomuko Regencies, where limited fleet capacity prevents fishers from venturing further offshore.</p><p>Moderate vulnerability indicators, such as the number of trips (0.574), boat power (0.409), and fishing experience (0.481), illustrate technical and demographic barriers to adaptation. Smaller vessels with limited gross tonnage reduce mobility and safety, particularly during extreme weather events in the Indian Ocean. These constraints align with findings by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">Pomeroy et al. (2006)</xref>, who noted that technological limitations often exacerbate climate risks for small-scale fishermen. Conversely, indicators such as non-fishery income (0.097) and fishing income for operational costs (0.202) fall into the low or very low categories, suggesting some opportunities for diversification. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Cinner et al. (2018)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Daw et al. (2009)</xref> argue that household-level diversification into fish processing, trade, or even non-fisheries work is a key pathway for reducing vulnerability.</p><p>Geophysical factors also intensify vulnerability. Coastal erosion in South and North Bengkulu, with rates of 2–3 meters per year, has resulted in the loss of fishing grounds and the intrusion of saltwater into coastal agricultural land (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_52">Pandu, 2020</xref>). This environmental degradation not only reduces catch but also undermines household food security. Fishermen report withered coastal vegetation, which further accelerates erosion and limits ecosystem-based adaptation options. Combined with low institutional support, these ecological pressures create a situation in which fishers remain highly vulnerable but are unable to mobilize the necessary resources for effective adaptation.</p><p>The gender dimension of vulnerability is equally significant. Women, though central in post-harvest processing and marketing, face limited access to credit, training, and decision-making spaces. This reduces household resilience and constrains families' capacity to diversify income sources. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Atteridge &amp;amp; Remling (2018)</xref> emphasize that including women in adaptation planning strengthens livelihood outcomes and ensures more equitable resilience. In Bengkulu, empowering women through access to cooperatives and microfinance could therefore play a critical role in reducing overall vulnerability.</p><p>Overall, the situation of small-scale fishermen in Bengkulu illustrates that livelihood vulnerability is concentrated in economic dependence, technological limitations, and institutional weaknesses. Without substantial intervention in these areas, fishermen will remain trapped in cycles of poverty and vulnerability, with climate change further intensifying their precarious livelihoods.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.3. Modelling adaptation of small-scale fishermen to climate change</title>
          
          <p>The structural equation model highlights the interrelationship between poverty, livelihood vulnerability, and adaptation among small-scale fishermen in Bengkulu. The results indicate that poverty and vulnerability negatively affect adaptation, while vessel capacity, fishing distance, and gear diversity significantly improve adaptive capacity. Interestingly, fishing experience was found to correlate with higher poverty, indicating that long-term dependence on traditional fishing methods may reinforce vulnerability rather than reduce it. This finding resonates with the concept of “poverty traps” in climate-sensitive communities, where accumulated experience does not automatically translate into resilience without adequate assets or institutional support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">Milman &amp;amp; Warner, 2016</xref>).</p><p>These results suggest that adaptation is shaped not only by ecological and technical conditions but also by socioeconomic and institutional contexts. Fishermen with better assets—larger vessels, diversified gear, and greater access to capital—were more likely to adopt proactive strategies, while poorer households relied on reactive, short-term coping mechanisms. This reflects broader patterns identified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Cinner et al. (2018)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_61">Xu et al. (2023)</xref>, who argue that poverty directly constrains the capacity of small-scale fishers to shift from coping to adaptation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Cinner et al. (2018)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">Pomeroy et al. (2006)</xref> similarly observed that resource-poor fishing communities tend to remain dependent on familiar practices, even when such practices may become maladaptive under changing climate conditions.</p><p>The model also confirms the role of education and generational differences in shaping adaptation. Fishermen with higher levels of education were more likely to access information, engage with cooperatives, and diversify livelihoods, thereby reducing their dependence on capture fisheries. By contrast, older fishermen with decades of experience tended to persist with traditional methods, often due to cultural attachment and lack of alternative skills. This duality reflects the argument of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Daw et al. (2009)</xref>, who emphasize that both social capital and human capital are critical in determining adaptation pathways. In the Bengkulu context, education serves not only as a protective factor but also as a bridge toward more innovative and resilient adaptation practices.</p><p>From a methodological perspective, integrating MPI and LVI into the SEM framework provides a holistic understanding of how socioeconomic and ecological pressures interact to shape adaptation. This approach adds empirical depth to the literature by simultaneously capturing both structural constraints and adaptive responses. While previous studies often assessed poverty, vulnerability, or adaptation separately, this study demonstrates that they must be analyzed in relation to one another to understand the dynamics of resilience in small-scale fisheries.</p><p>From a policy perspective, the results highlight that adaptation among Bengkulu fishermen remains reactive mainly. Adjusting fishing grounds or times may help households cope in the short term, but these strategies do not address the underlying causes of poverty and vulnerability. Without institutional support—such as cooperatives, access to credit, modernized fleets, or extension services—fishermen risk being locked into cycles of reactive adaptation that may eventually become maladaptive. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Antwi-Agyei et al. (2018)</xref> caution that maladaptation can arise when short-term strategies reduce vulnerability in the present but increase risks in the future, for example, by overexploiting nearshore resources or reinforcing dependence on unstable fisheries.</p><p>Overall, the modelling results confirm that poverty alleviation, livelihood diversification, and institutional strengthening are essential to move fishermen from coping to genuine adaptation. In line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">Pomeroy et al. (2006)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_61">Xu et al. (2023)</xref>, this study underscores that adaptation cannot be viewed solely as an individual or technical process but must be supported by broader social, economic, and governance interventions. Strong cooperatives and government assistance could strengthen adaptive capacity by enhancing resource availability and collective action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Béné et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Gupta et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">Nti et al., 2021</xref>). Thus, integrating poverty reduction into adaptation planning is not only a welfare concern but also a prerequisite for building resilience in climate-vulnerable coastal communities.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>7. Conclusions and policy implications</title>
      <p>This study contributed to the theoretical and methodological development of research on climate change adaptation by integrating poverty and livelihood vulnerability into the analysis of fishermen’s adaptive capacity. Unlike numerous previous studies that focused solely on exposure and sensitivity, the approach in this paper highlighted how socioeconomic constraints, particularly poverty and dependence on fishing income, directly shaped adaptation strategies. This article advanced the methodological tools, LVI, and their linkage with the outcomes of adaptation, to assess the resilience of small-scale fisheries in the context of developing countries.</p><p>The current study illustrated that fishermen in Bengkulu Province mainly relied on reactive strategies, such as changing fishing areas and adjusting fishing times. These responses, while common, remain insufficient in the absence of institutional and financial support. It was discovered that poverty was a significant limiting factor, whereas vessel capacity and fishing distance were positively associated with greater adaptation. This demonstrates the importance of combining socioeconomic and technical variables in explaining adaptation behavior.</p><p>From the policy perspective, strengthening resilience requires participatory and locally grounded interventions. First, empowering local economic institutions, such as fishermen cooperatives, savings and loan groups, and microfinance organizations, could improve access to credit, reduce individual risks, and enable investments in vessel modernization and diversified livelihoods. Second, strengthening social capital through fishermen’s associations and community-based organizations could facilitate collective action, knowledge sharing, and the integration of local ecological knowledge into adaptation planning. Finally, government programs should adopt a more participatory approach by involving fishermen in decision-making processes to ensure that policies align with local realities, cultural practices, and the actual needs of coastal communities.</p><p>By emphasizing the interaction between poverty, vulnerability, and adaptation, this article not only extended theoretical insights into climate change adaptation but also provided practical guidance for participatory and context-specific policy design in small-scale fisheries. Strengthening both economic and social institutions at the community level is crucial for ensuring that fishermen in Bengkulu and other similar regions can develop sustainable resilience against the impacts of climate change.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>Conceptualization, G.M. and I.C.; methodology, G.M., I.C. and I.; software, G.M.; validation, G.M., I.C., I. and A.I.H.; formal analysis, G.M. and I.C.; investigation, A.I.H.; resources, G.M., I.C. and I.; data curation, I.C and I.; writing—original draft preparation, G.M., I.C., I. and A.I.H.; writing—review and editing, G.M., I.C. and I.; visualization, G.M. and A.I.H.; supervision, I.; project administration, G.M.; funding acquisition, G.M. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work is funded by the Ministry of Education, Culture, Research, and Technology in Indonesia (Grant No.: 3939/UN30.15/PT/2024).</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>63</volume>
          <page-range>110-123</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abid</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scheffran</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schneider</surname>
              <given-names>U. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elahi</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00267-018-1113-7</pub-id>
          <article-title>Farmer perceptions of climate change, observed trends and adaptation of agriculture in Pakistan</article-title>
          <source>Environmental Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>275–316</page-range>
          <year>1981</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Acheson</surname>
              <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anthropology of fishing</article-title>
          <source>Annu. Rev. Anthropol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>59</volume>
          <page-range>251-274</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alkire</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>M. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2014.01.026</pub-id>
          <article-title>Measuring acute poverty in the developing world: Robustness and scope of the multidimensional poverty index</article-title>
          <source>World Development</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ananda</surname>
              <given-names>C. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Resosudarmo</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nazara</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Empowering Regional Economic Development Toward Sustainable Poverty Alleviation (1st ed.)</source>
          <publisher-name>Indonesian Regional Science Association</publisher-name>
          <year>2007</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>377</volume>
          <page-range>124593</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andrista</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Utami</surname>
              <given-names>N. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hukom</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2025.124593</pub-id>
          <article-title>Responses to climate change: Perceptions and adaptation among small-scale farmers in Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Environmental Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>1296-1312</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Antwi-Agyei</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dougill</surname>
              <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Agyekum</surname>
              <given-names>T. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stringer</surname>
              <given-names>L. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14693062.2018.1431199</pub-id>
          <article-title>Alignment between nationally determined contributions and the sustainable development goals for West Africa</article-title>
          <source>Climate Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>e500</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Atteridge</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Remling</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wcc.500</pub-id>
          <article-title>Is adaptation reducing vulnerability or redistributing it?</article-title>
          <source>WIREs Climate Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>73</volume>
          <page-range>47-59</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baptiste</surname>
              <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kinlocke</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoforum.2015.05.006</pub-id>
          <article-title>“We are not all the same!”: Comparative climate change vulnerabilities among fishers in Old Harbour Bay, Jamaica</article-title>
          <source>Geoforum</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>261-274</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Béné</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barange</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Subasinghe</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pinstrup-Andersen</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Merino</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hemre</surname>
              <given-names>G. I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12571-015-0427-z</pub-id>
          <article-title>Feeding 9 billion by 2050 – Putting fish back on the menu</article-title>
          <source>Food Security</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>J.n W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The Ecological Transition: Cultural Anthropology and Human Adaptation (1st ed.)</source>
          <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>
          <year>2005</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>289-311</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Burnham</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17565529.2015.1067180</pub-id>
          <article-title>Linking smallholder farmer climate change adaptation decisions to development</article-title>
          <source>Climate and Development</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>28-44</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carron</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muys</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Orshoven</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leinfelder</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12924/cis2021.09010028</pub-id>
          <article-title>Landscape design to meet the societal demand for ecosystem services: A perspective</article-title>
          <source>Challenges in Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>59</volume>
          <page-range>88-97</page-range>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lopez-Carr</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apgeog.2014.10.015</pub-id>
          <article-title>The importance of place: Unraveling the vulnerability of fisherman livelihoods to the impact of marine protected areas</article-title>
          <source>Applied Geography</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>117-123</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cinner</surname>
              <given-names>J. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adger</surname>
              <given-names>W. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allison</surname>
              <given-names>E. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnes</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cohen</surname>
              <given-names>P. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gelcich</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hicks</surname>
              <given-names>C. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hughes</surname>
              <given-names>T. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lau</surname>
              <given-names>J. et al.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41558-017-0065-x</pub-id>
          <article-title>Building adaptive capacity to climate change in tropical coastal communities</article-title>
          <source>Nature Climate Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>84</volume>
          <page-range>242-261</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2003</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cutter</surname>
              <given-names>S. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boruff</surname>
              <given-names>B. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shirley</surname>
              <given-names>W. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1540-6237.8402002</pub-id>
          <article-title>Social vulnerability to environmental hazards</article-title>
          <source>Social Science Quarterly</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dachlan</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Complete Guide to Structural Equation Modelling</source>
          <publisher-name>Lentera Ilmu</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Daw</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adger</surname>
              <given-names>W. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Badjeck</surname>
              <given-names>M. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Climate change and capture fisheries: Potential impacts, adaptation and mitigation</article-title>
          <source>Climate Change Implications for Fisheries and Aquaculture: Overview of Current Scientific Knowledge</source>
          <publisher-name>FAO Fisheries and Aquaculture Technical Paper No. 530. Rome, FAO</publisher-name>
          <year>2009</year>
          <page-range>107–150</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>20</volume>
          <page-range>434-446</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Widhalm</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/09653561111161752</pub-id>
          <article-title>Measuring economic impacts of drought: A review and discussion</article-title>
          <source>Disaster Prevention and Management: An International Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Rethinking Artisanal Fisheries Development: Western Concepts, Asian Experiences</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.cabidigitallibrary.org/doi/full/10.5555/19841809017</source>
          <year>1980</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>647-656</page-range>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Engle</surname>
              <given-names>N. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2011.01.019</pub-id>
          <article-title>Adaptive capacity and its assessment</article-title>
          <source>Global Environmental Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Composting at Home</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.epa.gov/recycle/composting-home</source>
          <year>2013</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>124</volume>
          <page-range>142-149</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Etemadi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karami</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaridenv.2015.08.003</pub-id>
          <article-title>Organic fig growers' adaptation and vulnerability to drought</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Arid Environments</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>79</volume>
          <page-range>301-309</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fahad</surname>
              <given-names>Shah</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Jianling</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.landusepol.2018.08.018</pub-id>
          <article-title>Farmers’ risk perception, vulnerability, and adaptation to climate change in rural Pakistan</article-title>
          <source>Land Use Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferdinand</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Structural Equation Modeling Dalam Penelitian Manajemen (4th ed)</source>
          <publisher-name>Semarang: Badan Penerbit Universitas Diponegoro</publisher-name>
          <year>2006</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>459-471</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Termeer</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klostermann</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meijerink</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van den Brink</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jong</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nooteboom</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bergsma</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envsci.2010.05.006</pub-id>
          <article-title>The adaptive capacity wheel: A method to assess the inherent characteristics of institutions to enable the adaptive capacity of society</article-title>
          <source>Environmental Science &amp;amp; Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>35</volume>
          <page-range>101073</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Handayani</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fisher</surname>
              <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rudiarto</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Setyono</surname>
              <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foley</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijdrr.2019.101073</pub-id>
          <article-title>Operationalizing resilience: A content analysis of flood disaster planning in two coastal cities in Central Java, Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Disaster Risk Reduction</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>68-78</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2012</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Helmi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Satria</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7454/mssh.v16i1.1494</pub-id>
          <article-title>Strategi adaptasi nelayan terhadap perubahan ekologis</article-title>
          <source>Makara Human Behavior Studies in Asia</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>124</volume>
          <page-range>105550</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Herreros-Cantis</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khromova</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Olazabal</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McPhearson</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Langemeyer</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neumann</surname>
              <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijdrr.2025.105550</pub-id>
          <article-title>Knowledge diversity for climate change adaptation: A social-ecological-technological systems (SETS) approach to mental models</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Disaster Risk Reduction</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>16-27</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heydari</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Solhi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Janani</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farzadkia</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12924/cis2021.09010016</pub-id>
          <article-title>Determinants of sustainability in recycling of municipal solid waste: Application of community-based social marketing (CBSM)</article-title>
          <source>Challenges in Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Climate Change 2014 Impacts, Adaptation, and Vulnerability Part A: Global and Sectoral Aspects</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.ipcc.ch/site/assets/uploads/2018/02/WGIIAR5-FrontMatterA_FINAL.pdf</source>
          <year>2014</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>IPCC</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Annex I: Glossary</article-title>
          <source>Global Warming of 1.5°C</source>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
          <year>2018</year>
          <page-range>541–562</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/9781009157940.008</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>23</volume>
          <page-range>146-159</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jamshidi</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asadi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalantari</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azadi</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scheffran</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crm.2018.06.002</pub-id>
          <article-title>Vulnerability to climate change of smallholder farmers in the Hamadan province, Iran</article-title>
          <source>Climate Risk Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>66</volume>
          <page-range>353–360</page-range>
          <issue>33</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jha</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amarnath</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isn't climate change affecting wheat productivity in India?</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Agric. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>1-15</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kaua</surname>
              <given-names>C. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thenya</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mutheu</surname>
              <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12924/cis2021.09010001</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analyzing effects of climate variability in the nexus of informal microfinance institutions: A case study of Tharaka South Subcounty, Kenya</article-title>
          <source>Challenges in Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>177</volume>
          <page-range>93</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>M.-J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>I.-S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>J.-S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>D.-H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10584-024-03758-7</pub-id>
          <article-title>A climate change risk assessment in aquaculture in Korea</article-title>
          <source>Climatic Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>e0272120</page-range>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koehn</surname>
              <given-names>Laura E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>Laura K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samhouri</surname>
              <given-names>Jameal F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Norman</surname>
              <given-names>Karma C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacox</surname>
              <given-names>Michael G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cullen</surname>
              <given-names>Alison C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fiechter</surname>
              <given-names>Jerome</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pozo Buil</surname>
              <given-names>Mercedes</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levin</surname>
              <given-names>Phillip S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0272120</pub-id>
          <article-title>Social-ecological vulnerability of fishing communities to climate change: A U.S. West Coast case study</article-title>
          <source>PLOS ONE</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>erubahan iklim semakin nyata di Bengkulu</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.kupasbengkulu.com/perubahan-iklim-semakin-nyata-di-bengkulu</source>
          <year>2013</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>58–67</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Meena</surname>
              <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vikas</surname>
              <given-names>T. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verma</surname>
              <given-names>R. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yadav</surname>
              <given-names>R. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahapatra</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surya</surname>
              <given-names>J. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Local perceptions and adaptation of Indigenous communities to climate change: Evidence from high mountain Pangi Valley of Indian Himalayas</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Tradit. Knowl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>384</volume>
          <page-range>125598</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mensah</surname>
              <given-names>S. O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Osei-Acheampong</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacobs</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cunningham</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akoto</surname>
              <given-names>A. B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2025.125598</pub-id>
          <article-title>Smallholder farmers’ climate change adaptation in Ghana: A systematic literature review and future directions</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Environmental Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Meyers</surname>
              <given-names>L. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gamst</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guarino</surname>
              <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Applied Multivariate Research: Design and Interpretation</source>
          <publisher-name>London: Sage</publisher-name>
          <year>2006</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>36</volume>
          <page-range>46-55</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Milman</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warner</surname>
              <given-names>B. P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2015.11.007</pub-id>
          <article-title>The interfaces of public and private adaptation: Lessons from flooding in the Deerfield River Watershed</article-title>
          <source>Global Environmental Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2023</volume>
          <page-range>8770267</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mulyasari</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trisusilo</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Windirah</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Djarot</surname>
              <given-names>I. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Putra</surname>
              <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2023/8770267</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessing perceptions and adaptation responses to climate change among small-scale fishery on the northern coastal of Bengkulu, Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>The Scientific World Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Murdiyarso</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Sepuluh Tahun Perjalanan Negosiasi Konvensi Perubahan Iklim</source>
          <publisher-name>Penerbit Buku Kompas</publisher-name>
          <year>2003</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>45-58</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nti</surname>
              <given-names>E. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wongnaa</surname>
              <given-names>C. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edusah</surname>
              <given-names>Nana Sampson E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Awunyo-Vitor</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kyei</surname>
              <given-names>V. B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12924/cis2021.09010045</pub-id>
          <article-title>Towards financial sustainability: Beneficiaries’ perception and performance of community water supply services in Ghana</article-title>
          <source>Challenges in Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>171</volume>
          <page-range>11-18</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nurhidayah</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McIlgorm</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2019.01.011</pub-id>
          <article-title>Coastal adaptation laws and the social justice of policies to address sea level rise: An Indonesian insight</article-title>
          <source>Ocean &amp;amp; Coastal Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nurkse</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Problems of Capital Formation in Underdeveloped Countries</source>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
          <year>1953</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>1–11</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nurwati</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Kemiskinan: Model pengukuran, permasalahan, dan alternatif kebijakan</article-title>
          <source>Jurnal Kependudukan Padjadjaran</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>1144-1150</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ogunbode</surname>
              <given-names>C. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doran</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ayanian</surname>
              <given-names>A. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Utsugi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van den Broek</surname>
              <given-names>K. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghorayeb</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aquino</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lins</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aruta</surname>
              <given-names>J. J. B. R. et al.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41558-024-02168-y</pub-id>
          <article-title>Climate justice beliefs related to climate action and policy support around the world</article-title>
          <source>Nature Climate Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>198</volume>
          <page-range>1-10</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Olayide</surname>
              <given-names>O. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alabi</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2018.06.221</pub-id>
          <article-title>Between rainfall and food poverty: Assessing vulnerability to climate change in an agricultural economy</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Cleaner Production</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>28</volume>
          <page-range>10-21</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oo</surname>
              <given-names>A. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Huylenbroeck</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Speelman</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijdrr.2018.02.012</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessment of climate change vulnerability of farm households in Pyapon District, a delta region in Myanmar</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Disaster Risk Reduction</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>84</volume>
          <page-range>777-796</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Panda</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11069-016-2456-0</pub-id>
          <article-title>Exploring climate change perceptions, rainfall trends and perceived barriers to adaptation in a drought affected region in India</article-title>
          <source>Natural Hazards</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Ekspansi Perkebunan Sawit Ancam Kelestarian Pesisir</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.kompas.id/artikel/ekspansi-perkebunan-sawit-ancam-kelestarian-pesisir</source>
          <year>2020</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>24</volume>
          <page-range>374-390</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Piggott-McKellar</surname>
              <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McNamara</surname>
              <given-names>K. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nunn</surname>
              <given-names>P. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watson</surname>
              <given-names>J. E. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13549839.2019.1580688</pub-id>
          <article-title>What are the barriers to successful community-based climate change adaptation? A review of grey literature</article-title>
          <source>Local Environment</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>30</volume>
          <page-range>786-793</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2006</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pomeroy</surname>
              <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ratner</surname>
              <given-names>B. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hall</surname>
              <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pimoljinda</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vivekanandan</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpol.2006.02.003</pub-id>
          <article-title>Coping with disaster: Rehabilitating coastal livelihoods and communities</article-title>
          <source>Marine Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>81</volume>
          <page-range>256-261</page-range>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shaffril</surname>
              <given-names>H. A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abu Samah</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D'Silva</surname>
              <given-names>J. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpol.2017.03.031</pub-id>
          <article-title>Climate change: Social adaptation strategies for fishermen</article-title>
          <source>Marine Policy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_56">
        <label>56.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Nelayan Dan Ketidakpastian Iklim: Tanggapan Nelayan Atas Informasi Prakiraan Cuaca Dan Potensi Ikan. Civil Society Forum for Climate Justice</article-title>
          <source>, https://catalogue.nla.gov.au/catalog/6183561</source>
          <year>2011</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_57">
        <label>57.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>282-292</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2006</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smit</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wandel</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2006.03.008</pub-id>
          <article-title>Adaptation, adaptive capacity and vulnerability</article-title>
          <source>Global Environmental Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_58">
        <label>58.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>135</volume>
          <page-range>3-9</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Susilowardhani</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sbspro.2014.07.317</pub-id>
          <article-title>The potential of strategic environmental assessment to address the challenges of climate change to reduce the risks of disasters: a case study from Semarang, Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Procedia - Social and Behavioral Sciences</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_59">
        <label>59.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>1-8</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>van Noordwijk</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>Y.-S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leimona</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hairiah</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fisher</surname>
              <given-names>L. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cosust.2016.10.004</pub-id>
          <article-title>Metrics of water security, adaptive capacity, and agroforestry in Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Current Opinion in Environmental Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_60">
        <label>60.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wongke</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Mencari Solusi Atas Perubahan Iklim</source>
          <publisher-name>Jakarta: Jakarta.BPK</publisher-name>
          <year>2011</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_61">
        <label>61.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>e22549</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qayum</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Afzal</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aslam</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e22549</pub-id>
          <article-title>vailability and access to Livelihood capital assets for development of sustainable Livelihood strategies of fishermen: A case study of Manchar Lake Pakistan</article-title>
          <source>Heliyon</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_62">
        <label>62.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Esteban</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Atoll Island States and International Law: Climate Change Displacement and Sovereignty</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_63">
        <label>63.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>100158</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yesuph</surname>
              <given-names>D. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bedeke</surname>
              <given-names>S. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Didana</surname>
              <given-names>H. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resglo.2023.100158</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessing climate change-induced poverty of mixed crop-livestock smallholders in Wolaita zone</article-title>
          <source>Research in Globalization</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_64">
        <label>64.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>38</volume>
          <page-range>100567</page-range>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zeray</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cliser.2025.100567</pub-id>
          <article-title>Smallholder Farmers’ perceptions of climate change and adaptation strategies in Southern Ethiopia: Mixed method approach</article-title>
          <source>Climate Services</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_65">
        <label>65.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>57-63</page-range>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zikra</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suntoyo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lukijanto</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.proeps.2015.07.085</pub-id>
          <article-title>Climate change impacts on Indonesian coastal areas</article-title>
          <source>Procedia Earth and Planetary Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>