<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OCS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Opportunities and Challenges in Sustainability</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Oppor Chall. Sustain.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">OCS</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2957-9643</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2957-7217</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-DeHV3lBs_A90VOVpbNPywtKrzZd7RuK-</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/ocs050101</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Systemic Drivers of Eutrophication: Agricultural Runoff, Waste Discharge, and the Degradation of Aquatic Ecosystems</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-1695-6054</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Basu</surname>
            <given-names>Anushka</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>anushkabasu10@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Science, Dayanand Anglo Vedic International School, 380051 Ahmedabad, India</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>01</month>
        <year>2026</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>9</lpage>
      <page-range>1-9</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>01</month>
          <year>2026</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2026 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2026</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Eutrophication, defined as excessive nutrient enrichment in aquatic ecosystems, has been increasingly recognized as one of the most critical drivers of freshwater and coastal ecosystem degradation worldwide. A qualitative research framework based on systematic literature synthesis, statistical data interpretation, and comparative regional case analysis was employed to examine the systemic drivers and socio-ecological consequences of nutrient pollution. Case studies from India and the United States were comparatively analyzed in order to identify recurring patterns of nutrient loading and ecological outcomes. It is demonstrated that excessive nutrient inputs substantially increase the frequency and severity of harmful algal blooms, which subsequently contribute to hypoxic or anoxic conditions, biodiversity loss, and the structural destabilization of aquatic food webs. These ecological transformations are shown to generate cascading socio-economic impacts, particularly for fishing-dependent and agrarian communities whose livelihoods are directly linked to aquatic ecosystem services. The analysis further indicates that climate change amplifies nutrient cycling dynamics and accelerates eutrophication processes. To address these challenges, integrated mitigation strategies emphasizing watershed-scale nutrient management, improved wastewater treatment infrastructure, and strengthened environmental governance were critically evaluated. Community-based resource management and participatory water governance mechanisms were identified as essential components for enhancing ecological resilience and long-term sustainability. The findings highlight the necessity of systemic policy reforms that prioritize nutrient pollution control, sustainable agricultural practices, and coordinated water governance frameworks in order to mitigate the escalating environmental and socio-economic consequences of eutrophication.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Eutrophication</kwd>
        <kwd>Nutrient pollution</kwd>
        <kwd>Agricultural runoff</kwd>
        <kwd>Aquatic ecosystem degradation</kwd>
        <kwd>Algal blooms</kwd>
        <kwd>Water governance</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="1"/>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="18"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Eutrophication is a process wherein water bodies become excessively enriched with nutrients, notably phosphates and nitrates, often as a result of agricultural runoff, industrial discharge, and improper waste management. This nutrient overloading promotes abnormal growth of phytoplankton and algal blooms, leading to oxygen depletion, biodiversity loss, and the eventual ecological collapse of aquatic ecosystems. Although eutrophication has been a subject of scientific inquiry for decades, the public and policy response remains disproportionately muted—particularly in developing nations where environmental degradation intersects with deep socio-economic fragility. Existing literature tends to examine eutrophication primarily from an ecological or chemical perspective. However, there is a critical need to understand its systemic consequences on vulnerable human populations who depend on these ecosystems for survival—especially small-scale fishers, tribal communities, and rural cultivators. These groups, already marginalized by climate change, market inequality, and infrastructural neglect, are further burdened by the cascading effects of polluted and dying water bodies.</p><p>This study aims to bridge this analytical gap by synthesizing interdisciplinary findings on the causes and impacts of eutrophication. It focuses on its socio-economic dimensions, using case studies from India and the United States, while proposing integrated solutions that combine ecological restoration with equity-centered environmental governance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Smith et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Smith &amp;amp; Schindler, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Vollenweider, 1976</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Literature review</title>
      <p>The phenomenon of eutrophication has been widely studied in ecological and environmental sciences. Early foundational work focused on nutrient cycles in freshwater lakes, highlighting the relationship between phosphorus inputs and algal bloom formation. More recent studies have expanded the scope to include marine ecosystems and the compounded effects of climate change on eutrophication intensity and frequency. Notably, recent investigations have examined how eutrophication interacts with microplastic pollution and sediment resuspension in shallow lakes, suggesting a feedback loop where nutrient enrichment accelerates pollutant retention and ecological collapse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>). Similarly, some reports have emphasized the silent, cumulative nature of artificial nutrient inflows—often exacerbated by climate-induced hydrological volatility. Previous studies have demonstrated that excessive nitrogen and phosphorus loading from agricultural runoff is one of the primary drivers of eutrophication in both freshwater and marine ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Carpenter et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Conley et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Smith et al., 1999</xref>). It illustrates the growing public attention toward eutrophication and marine pollution, reflecting increasing awareness of nutrient-driven ecological degradation in aquatic environments.</p><p>In terms of public health, peer-reviewed articles have linked eutrophic conditions to pathogen proliferation and increased disease burdens in low-income communities. Some studies have also modeled the economic ramifications of declining fish stocks, particularly in coastal zones dependent on artisanal and small-scale fisheries. However, there remains a relative dearth of scholarship that integrates ecological, socio-economic, and political dimensions of eutrophication—particularly in developing countries. Most analyses prioritize technical mitigation strategies over community resilience or environmental justice frameworks. In addition, much of the existing literature tends to treat ecological degradation and socio-economic consequences as separate analytical domains. While scientific research has extensively examined nutrient cycles, algal bloom formation, and water chemistry, fewer studies have integrated these ecological dynamics with the socio-economic vulnerabilities of communities dependent on aquatic ecosystems. This study contributes to the literature by synthesizing ecological research with socio-economic analysis, highlighting how eutrophication functions simultaneously as an environmental, economic, and governance challenge.</p><p>This study addresses that gap by drawing from both scientific and socio-political literature to present eutrophication not only as a water-quality issue but also as a systemic threat to livelihoods, food security, and equitable development.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Methodology</title>
      <p>This study employs a qualitative, interdisciplinary methodology rooted in environmental systems analysis and socio-political contextualization. Rather than conducting primary field research, the study synthesizes secondary data from peer-reviewed scientific literature, institutional reports, and credible media documentation. Data was selected based on its relevance to three key dimensions of eutrophication: (a) ecological degradation, (b) socio-economic displacement, and (c) governance failures. Case studies from the United States (e.g., Florida’s Gulf Coast and Lake Erie) and India (e.g., Bihar’s makhana-producing regions and Dal Lake in Kashmir) were examined to illustrate how eutrophication manifests across distinct geographies and governance regimes.</p><p>The study also integrates global datasets on fishery employment, plastic waste generation, and water quality indices to analyze broader patterns. Sources were cross-validated where possible, with emphasis on reports published after 2018 to ensure current relevance. The findings are interpreted through a lens of environmental justice and systemic inequality, emphasizing how ecological degradation exacerbates existing socio-economic vulnerabilities. This framework allows for a more nuanced understanding of eutrophication—not only as a scientific problem but also as a deeply human one.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Problems faced</title>
      <p>Eutrophication is not merely an environmental issue—it is a deeply systemic threat that cuts across ecological integrity, human health, economic survival, and social equity. While it manifests biologically through nutrient overload and algal blooms, its consequences ripple outward into the fabric of communities and economies. Crucially, these impacts are not evenly distributed. Those who bear the brunt are often the most marginalized: fishing communities, agrarian families, informal laborers, and rural populations with minimal access to policy protection or infrastructural support.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Collapse of aquatic ecosystems</title>
          
          <p>At its core, eutrophication initiates a process of ecosystem suffocation. The over-enrichment of water bodies with nutrients—mainly nitrogen and phosphorus from agricultural runoff, untreated sewage, and industrial effluents—triggers explosive algal growth. These algae deplete dissolved oxygen when they die and decay, creating hypoxic or anoxic zones commonly referred to as “dead zones.” In these zones, fish and other aerobic aquatic life either flee or perish, leading to sharp declines in biodiversity and the collapse of once-stable aquatic ecosystems. In severe cases, such as the Gulf of Mexico’s seasonal hypoxic zone or Lake Erie’s recurrent blooms, entire food chains are disrupted. Organisms at the base of the food web, such as zooplankton, are outcompeted by toxic or invasive species like cyanobacteria and jellyfish. The result is a destabilized aquatic ecosystem that can no longer support sustainable life or harvest. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Diaz &amp;amp; Rosenberg, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Paerl &amp;amp; Otten, 2013</xref>)</p><p>Decreased production of fish is intricately correlated with the lives of people of fishing communities. It is directly proportional to their standard of living. Communities all around the globe depend on the fishing industry for food and income. It is estimated that approximately 3.2 billion people get at least 20% of their daily animal protein intake from fish; 33 million people are directly employed in the wild capture fisheries sector; 7.3% of the global population relies on fisheries for their livelihoods; and 37% of the world’s population lives in coastal communities, where whole families are engaged in fishing. In addition, women account for most of the workforce in secondary marine-related activities.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Socio-economic vulnerability of fishing communities</title>
          
          <p>The economic ramifications are devastating for communities reliant on fisheries. Globally, 33 million individuals are directly employed in wild-capture fisheries, with an additional 60 million engaged in associated sectors such as processing, distribution, and equipment maintenance. For coastal and riparian communities—especially in Asia, Africa, and Latin America—fish is not only a commodity but also a subsistence resource, a cultural staple, and a foundation of local identity.</p><p>Eutrophication-induced fish mortality leads to steep income volatility, threatening already precarious livelihoods. In many parts of South and Southeast Asia, fishing communities operate in highly informal, subsistence-oriented economies with limited access to insurance, state subsidies, or alternative employment. Women in particular—who dominate post-harvest sectors like fish drying, net repair, and local sale—are disproportionately affected by every link in the supply chain that eutrophication disrupts. These vulnerabilities are compounded by rising competition from industrialized trawler fleets and coastal tourism, further marginalizing artisanal fishers who often lack political capital or organizational strength to defend their rights or access mitigation funds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Rabalais et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Turner &amp;amp; Rabalais, 2003</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.3. Ecological and economic disruption in agriculture</title>
          
          <p>Beyond fisheries, eutrophication affects freshwater agrarian systems that rely on balanced aquatic ecology for crop productivity. The state of Bihar in India offers a striking case. It is home to makhana (fox nut) cultivation, a traditional and culturally significant agricultural activity rooted in wetland ecosystems. The proliferation of algal blooms—fueled by both climate-induced rainfall shifts and runoff from synthetic fertilizers—has choked the ponds and oxbow lakes essential for makhana growth. Reduced light penetration and altered water chemistry have led to declining yields, increasing labor demands, and widespread dissatisfaction among producers, most of whom belong to economically backward classes with limited bargaining power in agricultural markets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Carpenter et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Smith et al., 1999</xref>).</p><p>Similar challenges are being observed among lotus farmers in Kashmir, where eutrophication has severely affected the ecology of iconic lakes such as Dal and Wular. The deterioration of these water bodies has undermined not only livelihoods but also cultural practices and tourism-dependent economies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Conley et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Dodds, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Jeppesen et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.4. Public health emergencies</title>
          
          <p>Eutrophic water bodies are fertile breeding grounds for waterborne pathogens. Warm, stagnant, nutrient-rich environments facilitate the spread of diseases such as cholera, typhoid, dysentery, and gastroenteritis. Microbial contaminants like Escherichia coli, Shigella, Vibrio cholerae, Salmonella, and rotaviruses become persistent threats, especially in low-income regions lacking access to treated water.</p><p>In many underdeveloped and conflict-affected areas—such as parts of sub-Saharan Africa or war-affected regions in the Middle East—communities depend directly on rivers, lakes, and ponds for drinking and washing. As these water sources become toxic, the result is not only an uptick in disease outbreaks but also long-term impacts on child mortality, maternal health, and public sanitation. The situation is worsened by the fragility of healthcare infrastructure in these regions. Even in rapidly urbanizing slums in cities like Lagos, Dhaka, or Delhi, contaminated surface water from atrophied rivers mixes with urban drainage systems, exacerbating the cycle of disease and poverty.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.5. Tourism, cultural loss, and urban blight</title>
          
          <p>Eutrophication also has aesthetic and reputational consequences that translate into measurable economic loss—particularly in the tourism and recreation sectors. Beaches covered in dead fish, lakes choked with green slime, and foul-smelling shorelines have led to the closure of entire tourism economies. Florida’s Gulf Coast experienced a historic red tide in 2018, leading to hotel cancellations, mass fish die-offs, and losses exceeding $90 million. In India, Dal Lake’s progressive ecological decline has reduced tourism inflows and raised alarms about cultural degradation, as the lake has long been a symbol of Kashmiri heritage.</p><p>Urban water bodies like Bengaluru’s Bellandur Lake—infamous for catching fire due to eutrophic sludge—represent the dark edge of environmental neglect where eutrophication meets toxic urbanism. These events carry not only economic consequences but also symbolic weight, reflecting a civilization’s declining relationship with its ecosystems.</p><p>The example of Dal Lake demonstrates how eutrophication is not confined to a single region but represents a global environmental challenge. Rapid urbanization, untreated sewage discharge, and nutrient loading have significantly contributed to the deterioration of water quality in this freshwater ecosystem.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.6. Systemic inequity and political invisibility</title>
          
          <p>A critical but often overlooked dimension of eutrophication is political invisibility. The communities most affected—indigenous groups, informal laborers, and subsistence farmers—rarely have the platform to voice their concerns or demand systemic redress. They often reside in geographically isolated or politically underrepresented regions where environmental degradation is normalized or ignored. Furthermore, mitigation responses often prioritize techno-centric interventions—like dredging, geoengineering, or bio-treatment—that are expensive and inaccessible to low-income stakeholders. This deepens the gap between those who produce pollution and those who pay the price. In many cases, local populations are blamed for the degradation of water bodies, when in fact the source lies upstream: in industrial farming, regulatory neglect, and unaccountable waste disposal by corporate actors.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Causes</title>
      <p>Eutrophication is not the product of isolated incidents or accidental mismanagement—it is the predictable consequence of human systems designed around short-term gains, extractive industrialization, and infrastructural neglect. The intensification of this process globally reflects deeper systemic failures: the agricultural systems are optimized for yield rather than ecological sustainability; the urban waste infrastructures are outdated and underregulated; and the political and economic incentives continue to reward polluters while sidelining vulnerable populations and ecosystems.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.1. Agricultural runoff and chemical dependency</title>
          
          <p>The most significant and widespread driver of eutrophication is the uncontrolled runoff of chemical fertilizers from agricultural fields. Modern agriculture, especially in the post-Green Revolution era, has created an unsustainable dependency on nitrogen- and phosphorus-based fertilizers. While intended to boost food productivity, these chemicals are often overapplied or poorly managed, with excess nutrients leaching into adjacent water bodies through surface runoff or subsurface drainage. The situation is exacerbated in monsoon-dependent regions like South Asia, where seasonal rainfall events carry massive loads of unabsorbed nutrients directly into rivers and lakes. Studies have shown that in countries like India, China, and Brazil, more than 50% of applied nitrogen is lost to the environment, entering aquatic systems and initiating eutrophic conditions. The absence of mandatory buffer zones, contour farming, or cover cropping—practices designed to reduce runoff—only accelerates the flow of these pollutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Elser et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Yang et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>Moreover, subsidies on chemical fertilizers in many countries incentivize overuse, with little accountability or education for farmers about long-term ecological damage. Traditional, sustainable farming practices—such as composting, intercropping, and rotational grazing—have been largely displaced by monocultures and agro-industrial practices that prioritize output over resilience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Carpenter et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Tilman et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Vitousek et al., 1997</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.2. Urban waste and untreated sewage</title>
          
          <p>Urbanization has rapidly outpaced infrastructure in much of the Global South. As cities expand, the volume of domestic and industrial waste they generate overwhelms their existing treatment capacities. In many metropolitan areas, including Dhaka, Nairobi, and New Delhi, sewage treatment plants operate at less than 50% of required capacity. The remainder—often containing high concentrations of organic waste, detergents, nitrates, phosphates, and heavy metals—is discharged untreated into nearby rivers, lakes, and estuaries. Compounding the issue is the informal nature of waste disposal in peri-urban slums and informal settlements. Greywater and blackwater from unregulated housing often find their way into open drains that connect directly to water bodies. These water bodies become not only nutrient-rich but also breeding grounds for bacteria, viruses, and parasites.</p><p>Industrial discharge is an even graver issue. Polluting industries—tanneries, dye factories, pulp and paper mills, pharmaceuticals, and food processing plants—often bypass regulation through corruption or policy loopholes. In India’s Ganga basin or China’s Yangtze River delta, for instance, the pollution load from industries routinely exceeds safe limits, with minimal enforcement of environmental impact assessments or penalties.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.3. Landfills, leachates, and plastic-driven pollution</title>
          
          <p>The global solid waste crisis is a silent, yet potent, contributor to eutrophication. Landfills, particularly those situated near rivers and wetlands, leak toxic leachates rich in nitrates, ammonia, and phosphates. These substances seep through the soil, contaminating both surface and groundwater sources. The problem is particularly acute in tropical countries with high rainfall, where leachates travel faster and in larger volumes during monsoon seasons. An emerging facet of this crisis is plastic pollution, especially microplastics. Once in the aquatic system, microplastics act as substrates for biofilms and algae, creating artificial surfaces where nutrient concentrations become even more intense. They also alter sedimentation patterns and may indirectly facilitate eutrophic conditions by enhancing nutrient retention in lakebeds and ocean floors. Even biodegradable waste—such as food scraps—can worsen eutrophication if dumped into water bodies. As this organic matter decays, it adds to the biochemical oxygen demand, further tipping the ecosystem toward hypoxia or anoxia.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.4. Climate-driven amplification</title>
          
          <p>Climate change is not just a parallel environmental crisis—it is an amplifier of eutrophication. Warmer water temperatures enhance metabolic rates in algae and cyanobacteria, accelerating bloom formation. Shifting precipitation patterns lead to more intense and erratic runoff events, washing larger volumes of nutrients into aquatic systems in shorter periods. In coastal areas, rising sea temperatures coupled with ocean acidification disturb nutrient cycling and salinity balances, weakening the natural resistance of ecosystems to eutrophic shifts. Case studies from Lake Erie in the United States and the Baltic Sea in Europe show how climate variability directly correlates with algal bloom frequency, intensity, and toxicity.</p><p>Moreover, extreme weather events such as hurricanes and typhoons—now more frequent due to climate change—serve as nutrient delivery mechanisms. Hurricane Irma, for example, flushed enormous quantities of nutrients and waste from Florida’s terrestrial ecosystems into coastal waters, leading to a catastrophic bloom that killed thousands of marine animals and devastated tourism-dependent communities. Eutrophication also releases potent greenhouse gases—methane and nitrous oxide—from decomposing biomass in anoxic zones. This creates a feedback loop where eutrophication contributes to climate change, which in turn fuels further eutrophication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Scavia et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.5. Policy paralysis and governance failure</title>
          
          <p>While the technical causes of eutrophication are well understood, the real driver behind its persistence is a global failure of environmental governance. In many countries, environmental regulations exist only on paper—underenforced, underfunded, and politically compromised. Regulatory agencies are often captured by the very industries they are meant to oversee, resulting in a lack of accountability for polluters. Wastewater discharge standards are either outdated or riddled with exemptions. Environmental impact assessments are routinely diluted or ignored in the name of economic development. In large democracies like India, Indonesia, or Brazil, river rejuvenation schemes are launched with great fanfare but often lack monitoring, scientific rigor, or long-term funding.</p><p>Internationally, there is little coordination or enforcement on transboundary water pollution. Upstream nutrient discharges can destroy downstream ecosystems, yet there are few legal instruments holding countries accountable. The lack of strong multilateral agreements on freshwater pollution mirrors the global paralysis around climate change. Public participation in water governance remains extremely limited, especially among the marginalized communities most affected by eutrophication. Women, indigenous peoples, and fishing castes are rarely consulted in environmental policymaking, and their traditional ecological knowledge is often dismissed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Howarth et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Smith &amp;amp; Schindler, 2009</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Proposed solutions</title>
      <p>Addressing eutrophication requires more than technocratic interventions—it demands a structural rethinking of how societies manage land, water, and waste. The solutions must span policy reform, community empowerment, infrastructural redesign, and global coordination. What follows is a synthesis of multi-layered solutions, each tied directly to the systemic drivers identified in the preceding section.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.1. Transforming agricultural practices</title>
          
          <p>Agriculture must move away from chemical dependency and toward ecologically intelligent systems. Governments should:</p><p>Phase out blanket subsidies on synthetic fertilizers and instead incentivize organic alternatives, composting, and regenerative farming methods such as crop rotation, agroforestry, and no-till farming.</p><p>Mandate and enforce buffer zones between agricultural land and nearby water bodies using vegetative strips, constructed wetlands, or sedimentation ponds that absorb excess nutrients before they reach aquatic systems.</p><p>Promote precision agriculture technologies that optimize fertilizer application to prevent overuse, particularly in countries with large-scale monoculture systems.</p><p>Educate and train farmers in nutrient budgeting and sustainable land management practices, with special focus on smallholders and indigenous cultivators.</p><p>These reforms are not merely ecological—they are socio-economic. Reducing dependence on costly chemical inputs helps stabilize rural economies, improve soil health, and ensure long-term food security.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.2. Overhauling wastewater infrastructure</title>
          
          <p>Waste management must be treated as a critical public health and ecological service, not an afterthought.</p><p>Governments must invest in decentralized, modular wastewater treatment systems, especially in rural and peri-urban areas that are often bypassed by central planning.</p><p>Urban areas require upgraded sewage treatment plants with phosphorus and nitrogen removal capabilities, especially in fast-growing cities across the Global South.</p><p>Zero-liquid discharge mandates should be enforced for all major polluting industries, particularly in industrial belts near water bodies.</p><p>Cities must adopt circular waste economy principles, where nutrients are recovered and reused as biofertilizers rather than being dumped into ecosystems.</p><p>In parallel, public-private partnerships and local cooperatives can be mobilized to manage greywater recycling and small-scale treatment plants in informal settlements and tribal zones.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.3. Integrated plastic and solid waste management</title>
          
          <p>Eutrophication cannot be solved without confronting the global waste crisis. All nations must:</p><p>Ban the siting of landfills near water bodies and enforce strict leachate management protocols.</p><p>Develop and scale waste segregation at the source and community composting hubs to reduce the volume of organic waste entering water systems.</p><p>Introduce plastic stewardship laws, making manufacturers responsible for post-consumer waste (Extended Producer Responsibility).</p><p>Invest in microplastic interception technologies at wastewater outlets and regulate the disposal of synthetic textiles and tire dust that contribute to aquatic plastic pollution.</p><p>Waste governance reforms must also address labor justice—particularly the conditions of informal waste pickers who are essential but invisibilized players in urban waste ecosystems.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.4. Climate-resilient water system design</title>
          
          <p>To counter climate-amplified eutrophication, water systems must be redesigned with flexibility and redundancy.</p><p>Build nutrient sinks like man-made wetlands, which trap runoff during extreme rainfall events and naturally filter pollutants before they enter rivers or lakes.</p><p>Promote urban green infrastructure (bioswales, rain gardens, and green roofs) that reduces runoff and increases nutrient absorption capacity.</p><p>Incorporate early-warning systems using satellite data and predictive models to track nutrient flux and bloom formation, allowing timely intervention.</p><p>Restore degraded catchment areas with native vegetation, enhancing the water retention and filtering capacity of terrestrial ecosystems.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.5. Governance reform and accountability mechanisms</title>
          
          <p>No technical solution can outpace political apathy. Structural reform in governance is critical. Environmental regulatory bodies must:</p><p>Be independent, well-funded, and legally empowered to enforce discharge standards, levy penalties, and shut down repeat offenders.</p><p>Introduce citizen science initiatives and community monitoring systems to create grassroots pressure and localized data collection, as well as equip local bodies—especially panchayats, tribal councils, and cooperatives—with legal authority to enforce water protection norms.</p><p>Make environmental impact assessments genuinely consultative and science-driven, especially for projects near vulnerable ecosystems.</p><p>Develop transboundary water governance treaties to regulate upstream-downstream nutrient flows across national borders—particularly in major river basins like the Mekong, Ganga-Brahmaputra, and Nile.</p><p>At the global level, eutrophication should be elevated within the climate justice framework, recognizing that its impacts are disproportionately borne by low-emission, low-income communities.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.6. Educational and cultural reorientation</title>
          
          <p>Ultimately, the fight against eutrophication is also a cultural project. Societies must begin to value water not just as a resource but as a living system.</p><p>Introduce ecological literacy curricula in schools, emphasizing nutrient cycles, aquatic ecosystems, and community water stewardship.</p><p>Promote place-based storytelling and traditional knowledge systems around water bodies—especially those of indigenous and fishing communities.</p><p>Support artistic, literary, and media initiatives that reframe eutrophication from a technical issue to a human and moral crisis.</p><p>Changing the narrative is crucial—from algae to accountability and from pollution to power structures.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>7. Discussion and conclusion</title>
      <p>Eutrophication has emerged as one of the most significant environmental challenges affecting freshwater and marine ecosystems worldwide. The findings of this study indicate that eutrophication is not solely the result of natural nutrient enrichment processes but is strongly associated with anthropogenic activities, including intensive agricultural practices and untreated domestic and industrial wastewater discharge. These factors contribute to oxygen-depleted waters, dead aquatic zones, collapsed fisheries, and poisoned communities. The results further highlight that the impacts of eutrophication extend beyond ecological degradation and also have substantial socioeconomic consequences. Communities that depend directly on aquatic resources for their livelihoods—such as fishing communities, small-scale farmers, and residents in densely populated urban areas—are particularly vulnerable to declining water quality and ecosystem deterioration.</p><p>From an ecological perspective, the study confirms that excessive nutrient enrichment significantly disrupts aquatic ecosystem dynamics. Large-scale algal blooms, the decline of aquatic biodiversity, and alterations in food web structures have been observed in many eutrophic water bodies. In addition, the interaction between eutrophication and climate change may further intensify these impacts. Specifically, as climate change intensifies, warmer waters, erratic rainfall, and extreme weather will act as nutrient catalysts, amplifying eutrophication in both freshwater and marine systems. Despite growing scientific evidence regarding the severity of eutrophication, management responses in many regions remain limited or fragmented. In several cases, mitigation strategies focus primarily on short-term remediation measures, such as top-down cleanup schemes or technological “solutions”. While such approaches may temporarily alleviate symptoms, they do not adequately address the underlying drivers of nutrient pollution. Effective long-term management requires integrated approaches that combine environmental regulation, sustainable agricultural practices, improved wastewater treatment systems, and coordinated watershed management strategies.</p><p>Based on the findings of this study, several policy and management implications can be identified. First, decentralized water governance and the involvement of local communities in water resource management may improve the effectiveness and sustainability of conservation efforts. Second, strengthening regulatory mechanisms is necessary to ensure that industries are held financially and legally accountable for pollutant discharge into aquatic systems. Third, the promotion of sustainable and regenerative agricultural practices should be encouraged in order to reduce excessive fertilizer use and nutrient runoff from agricultural land. Fourth, investments in wastewater treatment and waste management infrastructure are essential, particularly in rapidly urbanizing regions where untreated domestic and industrial waste frequently enters nearby water bodies. Finally, environmental justice considerations should be incorporated into climate adaptation and water management policies.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The author declares no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>559–568</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>1998</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carpenter</surname>
              <given-names>S. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caraco</surname>
              <given-names>N. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Correll</surname>
              <given-names>D. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howarth</surname>
              <given-names>R. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharpley</surname>
              <given-names>A. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>V. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/1051-0761(1998)008</pub-id>
          <article-title>Nonpoint pollution of surface waters with phosphorus and nitrogen</article-title>
          <source>Ecol. Appl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>323</volume>
          <page-range>1014-1015</page-range>
          <issue>5917</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Conley</surname>
              <given-names>Daniel J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paerl</surname>
              <given-names>Hans W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howarth</surname>
              <given-names>Robert W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boesch</surname>
              <given-names>Donald F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seitzinger</surname>
              <given-names>Sybil P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Havens</surname>
              <given-names>Karl E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lancelot</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Likens</surname>
              <given-names>Gene E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1167755</pub-id>
          <article-title>Controlling eutrophication: Nitrogen and phosphorus</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>321</volume>
          <page-range>926-929</page-range>
          <issue>5891</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Diaz</surname>
              <given-names>Robert J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenberg</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1156401</pub-id>
          <article-title>Spreading dead zones and consequences for marine ecosystems</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>51</volume>
          <page-range>671-680</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2006</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dodds</surname>
              <given-names>Walter K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4319/lo.2006.51.1_part_2.0671</pub-id>
          <article-title>Eutrophication and trophic state in rivers and streams</article-title>
          <source>Limnology and Oceanography</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>1135-1142</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2007</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elser</surname>
              <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bracken</surname>
              <given-names>M. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cleland</surname>
              <given-names>E. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gruner</surname>
              <given-names>D. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harpole</surname>
              <given-names>W. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hillebrand</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ngai</surname>
              <given-names>J. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seabloom</surname>
              <given-names>E. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shurin</surname>
              <given-names>J. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>J. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2007.01113.x</pub-id>
          <article-title>Global analysis of nitrogen and phosphorus limitation of primary producers in freshwater, marine and terrestrial ecosystems</article-title>
          <source>Ecology Letters</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>18–26</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Howarth</surname>
              <given-names>R. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Swaney</surname>
              <given-names>D. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Billen</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garnier</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Humborg</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnes</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mörth</surname>
              <given-names>C. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marino</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/100178</pub-id>
          <article-title>Nitrogen fluxes from the landscape are controlled by net anthropogenic nitrogen inputs and by climate</article-title>
          <source>Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>50</volume>
          <page-range>1747-1771</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2005</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jeppesen</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Søndergaard</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>J. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Havens</surname>
              <given-names>K. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anneville</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carvalho</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coveney</surname>
              <given-names>M. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deneke</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dokulil</surname>
              <given-names>M. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foy</surname>
              <given-names>B. et al.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2427.2005.01415.x</pub-id>
          <article-title>Lake responses to reduced nutrient loading—An analysis of contemporary long-term data from 35 case studies</article-title>
          <source>Freshwater Biology</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>65</volume>
          <page-range>995-1010</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paerl</surname>
              <given-names>H. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Otten</surname>
              <given-names>T. G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-012-0159-y</pub-id>
          <article-title>Harmful cyanobacterial blooms: Causes, consequences, and controls</article-title>
          <source>Microbial Ecology</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>33</volume>
          <page-range>235-263</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2002</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rabalais</surname>
              <given-names>N. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>R. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiseman Jr.</surname>
              <given-names>W. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.33.010802.150513</pub-id>
          <article-title>Gulf of Mexico hypoxia, A. K. A. “The dead zone”</article-title>
          <source>Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>25</volume>
          <page-range>149-164</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2002</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scavia</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Field</surname>
              <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boesch</surname>
              <given-names>D. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buddemeier</surname>
              <given-names>R. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burkett</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cayan</surname>
              <given-names>D. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fogarty</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harwell</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howarth</surname>
              <given-names>R. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mason</surname>
              <given-names>C. et al.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf02691304</pub-id>
          <article-title>Climate change impacts on US coastal and marine ecosystems</article-title>
          <source>Estuaries</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>24</volume>
          <page-range>201-207</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>V. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schindler</surname>
              <given-names>D. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2008.11.009</pub-id>
          <article-title>Eutrophication science: Where do we go from here?</article-title>
          <source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>100</volume>
          <page-range>179-196</page-range>
          <issue>1-3</issue>
          <year>1999</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tilman</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nekola</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0269-7491(99)00091-3</pub-id>
          <article-title>Eutrophication: Impacts of excess nutrient inputs on freshwater, marine, and terrestrial ecosystems</article-title>
          <source>Environmental Pollution</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>292</volume>
          <page-range>281-284</page-range>
          <issue>5515</issue>
          <year>2001</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tilman</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fargione</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolff</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D’Antonio</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dobson</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howarth</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schindler</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schlesinger</surname>
              <given-names>W. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simberloff</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Swackhamer</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1057544</pub-id>
          <article-title>Forecasting agriculturally driven global environmental change</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>53</volume>
          <page-range>563–572</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2003</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>R. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rabalais</surname>
              <given-names>N. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1641/0006-3568(2003)053</pub-id>
          <article-title>Linking landscape and water quality in the Mississippi river basin for 200 years</article-title>
          <source>BioScience</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>737–750</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>1997</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vitousek</surname>
              <given-names>P. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aber</surname>
              <given-names>J. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howarth</surname>
              <given-names>R. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Likens</surname>
              <given-names>G. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matson</surname>
              <given-names>P. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schindler</surname>
              <given-names>D. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schlesinger</surname>
              <given-names>W. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tilman</surname>
              <given-names>D. G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/1051-0761(1997)007</pub-id>
          <article-title>Human alteration of the global nitrogen cycle: Sources and consequences</article-title>
          <source>Ecol. Appl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>33</volume>
          <page-range>53–83</page-range>
          <year>1976</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vollenweider</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Advances in defining critical loading levels for phosphorus in lake eutrophication</article-title>
          <source>Mem. Ist. Ital. Idrobiol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>197-209</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>X. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>H. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>Z. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1631/jzus.b0710626</pub-id>
          <article-title>Mechanisms and assessment of water eutrophication</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Zhejiang University SCIENCE B</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>705</volume>
          <page-range>135979</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zeng</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xing</surname>
              <given-names>W. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>X. et al.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.135979</pub-id>
          <article-title>How climate change and eutrophication interact with microplastic pollution and sediment resuspension in shallow lakes: A review</article-title>
          <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>