<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IDA</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Information Dynamics and Applications</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Inf. Dyn. Appl.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IDA</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2958-1494</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-1486</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-G3LpM0Jue74do6nUd764ehfjl1I-TRKz</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/ida030104</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Enhancing 5G LTE Communications: A Novel LDPC Decoder for Next-Generation Systems</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5056-6342</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Venkatesh</surname>
            <given-names>Divyashree Yamadur</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>divyapatel.gowda@gmail.com</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff_1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2362-0152</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mallikarjunaiah</surname>
            <given-names>Komala</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>mkomala@sjbit.edu.in</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff_1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1106-5515</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Srikantaswamy</surname>
            <given-names>Mallikarjunaswamy</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>fund.impfile@gmail.com</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff_2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1206-5317</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>Ke</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>Hk125cn@wzu.edu.cn</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff_3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Electronics and Communication Engg, SJB Institute of Technology, 560060 Bengaluru, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Department of Electronics and Communication Engg, JSS Academy of Technical Education, 560060 Bengaluru, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">Wenzhou University, 325000 Wenzhou, China</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>03</month>
        <year>2024</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>47</fpage>
      <lpage>63</lpage>
      <page-range>47-63</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2024 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>The advent of fifth-generation (5G) long-term evolution (LTE) technology represents a critical leap forward in telecommunications, enabling unprecedented high-speed data transfer essential for today’s digital society. Despite the advantages, the transition introduces significant challenges, including elevated bit error rate (BER), diminished signal-to-noise ratio (SNR), and the risk of jitter, undermining network reliability and efficiency. In response, a novel low-density parity check (LDPC) decoder optimized for 5G LTE applications has been developed. This decoder is tailored to significantly reduce BER and improve SNR, thereby enhancing the performance and reliability of 5G communications networks. Its design accommodates advanced switching and parallel processing capabilities, crucial for handling complex data flows inherent in contemporary telecommunications systems. A distinctive feature of this decoder is its dynamic adaptability in adjusting message sizes and code rates, coupled with the augmentation of throughput via reconfigurable switching operations. These innovations allow for a versatile approach to optimizing 5G networks. Comparative analyses demonstrate the decoder’s superior performance relative to the quasi-cyclic low-density check code (QCLDC) method, evidencing marked improvements in communication quality and system efficiency. The introduction of this LDPC decoder thus marks a significant contribution to the evolution of 5G networks, offering a robust solution to the pressing challenges faced by next-generation communication systems and establishing a new standard for high-speed wireless connectivity.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Low-density parity check</kwd>
        <kwd>Quasi-cyclic low-density check code</kwd>
        <kwd>Bit error rate</kwd>
        <kwd>Signal-to-noise ratio</kwd>
        <kwd>5G long-term evolution</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="4"/>
        <fig-count count="12"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <ref-count count="66"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>The method of delivering and receiving signals by channel is known as communication. Mistakes may occur within the acquired signal during the transportation of a signal from a source to a destination in a communication system due to a variety of impediments. As a result, in order to retrieve the original message, error repair is required. Robert Gallagher invented LDPC codes in 1963. The researcher looked at the codes and discovered that LDPC codes effectively increased the Shannon capacity of an energy harvesting transmitter communicating over additive white Gaussian noise (AWGN) and binary erasure channels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>]. Transmission mistakes can be repaired using error-correcting codes and clever mathematical procedures. Channel coding is the term for this. Codes can also be used to reduce the number of bits required to provide legitimate data, a process known as source coding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. This study deals with channel coding schemes for two critical communication systems, which shows that, by employing effective channel coding schemes in these systems, their overall performance may be improved in a variety of ways, bringing them to practical applications in the real world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. In the literature, authors have proposed a hybrid decoding algorithm by applying linear approximation with non-linear functions to the Belief Propagation (BP) algorithm, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>.</p><p>The main aim of the present research work is to develop a high-performance and area-efficient 5G LDPC decoder. In the conventional method to construct the 5G LDPC codes, a low-density generator matrix (LDGM) code and a high-rate LDPC code are concatenated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. The variable nodes (VNs) in LDGM are 1-degree VNs, which receive the message from one check-to-variable (CTV) in each iteration and are reliable for the CTV messages received. Therefore, a fixed point with low quantization and a limited correction component was implemented. The degradation of overall performance is effected by the Optimized Min-Sum (OMS) decoder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>]. In recent years, several algorithms have been proposed to improve the performance of error correction for 5G LDPC codes. In much research work, generalized approximate-min algorithms are proposed by considering the approximate-min algorithm. Due to the implementation complexity, they suffer enormously, just like the BP decoding with concerned non-linear capabilities.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Block diagram for decoding</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_OwhrcNlYjySGpfu8.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.1. Background on 5g lte</title>
          
          <p>In modern communication systems, particularly in the context of 5G LTE technology, the significance of error-correcting codes cannot be overstated. 5G LTE represents a leap forward in telecommunications, offering vastly improved data rates, reduced latency, and increased connectivity for a myriad of devices. However, the very features that empower 5G LTE, such as higher frequency bands and dense network environments, also make it more susceptible to various types of transmission errors. These errors can stem from factors like signal fading due to longer distances or obstacles, interference from the increased number of devices and base stations, and the inherent vulnerabilities of moving at high speeds, which are especially relevant for mobile communications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>]. Error-correcting codes are integral to mitigating these challenges. They enhance the reliability of data transmission across the 5G network by identifying and correcting errors that occur during signal transmission. This is critical to maintaining the high-speed, high-quality communication expected of 5G LTE. The types of errors that can impact 5G LTE include bit errors, where individual bits are flipped from 0 to 1 or vice versa; burst errors, which affect a string of consecutive bits; and packet errors, where entire blocks of data are lost or corrupted. These errors can degrade the quality of service, causing video streams to buffer, voice calls to drop, and critical data transmissions to fail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. Error-correcting codes in 5G LTE, such as Turbo codes, LDPC codes, and Polar codes, are designed to address these issues efficiently. They enable the system to detect and correct errors without needing to retransmit data, thus saving bandwidth and reducing latency. This is particularly important for applications requiring real-time communication, such as autonomous driving, remote surgery, and interactive virtual reality, where even minimal delays or data inaccuracies could lead to significant consequences. By ensuring data integrity and reliability, error-correcting codes play a pivotal role in fulfilling the promise of 5G LTE as a cornerstone of modern digital infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.2. Research gap</title>
          
          <p>Despite the rapid advancements in 5G LTE technologies, a critical challenge persists in the form of signal errors that compromise data transmission reliability and efficiency. Current literature offers extensive insights into error correction methods, yet there's a notable gap in the targeted evaluation of these methods within the 5G LTE framework. The unique challenges posed by 5G LTE, such as higher susceptibility to interference, signal fading, and the demands of supporting high data rates with minimal latency, necessitate a nuanced approach to error correction. This gap underscores the need for an in-depth investigation into the types of errors that predominantly affect 5G LTE and the effectiveness of existing error-correcting codes in this specific context [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.3. Aim and contribution</title>
          
          <p>This research aims to bridge this research gap by conducting a comprehensive analysis of error types in 5G LTE and assessing the performance of current error-correcting codes against these challenges. The objectives are threefold: firstly, to catalog and analyze the prevalent errors in 5G LTE systems; secondly, to evaluate the efficacy of existing error correction strategies within this context; and thirdly, to propose refinements or new error-correcting approaches tailored to enhance 5G LTE reliability and efficiency. By addressing these aims, the proposed work contributes significantly to the telecommunications field. It not only deepens the understanding of error correction needs in 5G LTE but also introduces practical solutions that could pave the way for more robust and efficient 5G communication systems. Through this focused approach, the paper endeavors to fill the identified research gap, thereby facilitating improvements in 5G LTE technology that are essential for its broader adoption and success in various applications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.4. Hybrid decoding algorithm</title>
          
          <p>The hybrid decoding algorithm emerges as a pivotal innovation in the landscape of 5G communication, specifically designed to enhance the performance of LDPC decoders. This algorithm ingeniously synthesizes the strengths of two well-established decoding techniques, namely, the BP and the Min-Sum (MS) algorithms, to address the twin imperatives of decoding efficacy and computational efficiency that are critical for the next generation of wireless networks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>].</p><p>At its core, the BP algorithm is celebrated for its exceptional error-correcting performance, utilizing probabilistic message passing to accurately predict and correct bit errors within transmitted data. However, this accuracy comes at a cost, necessitating substantial computational resources and power, which can be a limiting factor in resource-constrained environments typical of mobile and embedded systems. Conversely, the MS algorithm offers a streamlined alternative that, while slightly less precise in error correction, significantly reduces the computational burden and hardware footprint, making it an attractive option for systems where efficiency is paramount [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>].</p><p>The hybrid decoding algorithm operates by dynamically assessing the error landscape of each LDPC code block received, leveraging real-time analysis to determine the most appropriate decoding strategy. For code segments where the error probability is high or in scenarios demanding the utmost in reliability, such as critical communications infrastructure or high-speed mobile connections, the algorithm opts for the BP approach to maximize error correction. In contrast, for segments with lower error probabilities or when optimizing for power and hardware efficiency, it switches to the MS algorithm. This dual-strategy approach allows the algorithm to adaptively optimize its decoding process, ensuring that it maintains a high level of decoding accuracy without unduly taxing the system's computational and hardware resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>].</p><p>The significance of the hybrid decoding algorithm within the 5G LDPC decoding context cannot be overstated. By harmonizing the error-correcting power of the BP algorithm with the computational elegance of the MS algorithm, it addresses one of the most pressing challenges in 5G communication: how to achieve ultra-reliable, high-speed data transmission in an environment that is inherently resource-constrained and variable. This algorithm not only enhances the robustness and efficiency of 5G LDPC decoders but also contributes to the broader goal of making 5G technology a viable, scalable solution for an array of applications, ranging from Internet of Things (IoT) deployments to ultra-reliable, low-latency communications and beyond. In doing so, the hybrid decoding algorithm stands as a testament to the ongoing evolution of communication technology, driving forward the capabilities of 5G networks to meet the demands of the digital age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>].</p><p>Recent advancements in 5G LDPC code enhancement have introduced notable algorithms like the Layered BP (LBP) and OMS algorithms. The LBP algorithm accelerates error correction by processing codes in layers, leading to faster convergence and improved throughput, although it may falter in highly noisy conditions. On the other hand, the OMS algorithm refines error correction with dynamically adjusted scaling factors for a better balance between performance and complexity, requiring precise tuning under varying network conditions. Both algorithms aim to boost the reliability and efficiency of 5G communications, each with unique strengths and limitations that contribute to the evolving landscape of 5G technology.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.5. Qcldc</title>
          
          <p>The QCLDC method serves as a benchmark for evaluating the performance of a newly proposed LDPC decoder optimized for 5G LTE communications. The abstract outlines a scenario where the advent of 5G technology, despite offering high-speed communication capabilities, introduces challenges such as increased BER, reduced SNR, and the potential for jitter. These issues necessitate advanced error-correcting mechanisms to ensure reliable data transmission [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>].</p><p>The proposed LDPC decoder is presented as a solution specifically designed to address these challenges within 5G networks. It aims to lower the BER, improve the SNR, and enhance both switching and parallel operations, crucial for the efficient handling of the massive data flows characteristic of 5G technology. The decoder's capability to dynamically adjust message size and code rate, along with its improved throughput via reconfigurable switching operations, signifies a significant advancement over traditional methods, such as the QCLDC.</p><p>By comparing the performance of this new LDPC decoder against the QCLDC method, the abstract highlights the former's superior performance through simulation results. This comparison underscores the innovative decoder's effectiveness in enhancing communication quality and system efficiency within 5G networks. The advancements outlined suggest that the LDPC decoder not only addresses the immediate challenges posed by 5G technology but also sets a new benchmark for future developments in wireless communication systems, offering a more reliable and efficient solution for managing the complexities of next-generation networks.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Relative work</title>
      <p>A comprehensive survey on the LDPC decoder for 5G LTE technology has been carried out in order to carry out the work that has been recommended. This survey was based on the challenges of deterioration in noisy environments, balancing error correction and efficiency, SNR, and other factors. A comparison of the work that has been done in the field of LDPC is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison of studies in LDPC</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>No.</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Title</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Authors</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technology</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Drawbacks</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Year</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>F. S. Sheela et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5G LDPC codes</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High computational complexity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2021</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>S. Jyothi et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Layered BP</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Performance degradation in noisy environments</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2014</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>J. Shrinidhi et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Optimized MS</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Demand for precise scaling factor tuning</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2020</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A. Muskan et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hybrid algorithms</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Balance between error correction and efficiency</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2023</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A. Pramanik et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5G LDPC codes</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Susceptibility to error floors</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2018</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>V. L. Petrović</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Focus on achieving high data processing speeds</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Possible increase in error rates in scenarios with low SNR</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2022</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>K. H. Lin et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Design of codes that scale efficiently across networks</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Complexity challenges in large-scale deployments</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2011</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>A. Jemima and G. Manoj</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Reduction of decoding time to meet 5G's low-latency requirements</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Potential compromises on decoding accuracy for speed</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2023</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>L. Chen et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Optimization of power consumption for IoT devices</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Possible consequences of lower decoding performance to save energy</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2020</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>H. Li et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhancement of resilience against a wide range of errors</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Complex implementation and optimization</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2005</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Y. Wang and S. Che</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Adaptation of decoding strategies dynamically</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Introduction of overhead from dynamic adaptation mechanisms</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2024</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>M. Zhang et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Aim for superior processing speeds in communication</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Synchronization challenges in high-speed contexts</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2024</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>B. M. Kavya et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Adaptation of LDPC codes for 5G New Radio (NR) specifics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Demand for sophisticated design efforts and custom hardware</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2024</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>P. S. Wulandari et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Preparations for future quantum computing threats</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Challenges in decoding time and complexity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2023</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>M. Elkadi et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Utilization of artificial intelligence (AI) to refine LDPC code performance</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Heavy dependence on extensive datasets for effective training</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2021</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>16</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Y. Lyu et al.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Implementation of LDPC decoders on the Field-Programmable Gate Array (FPGA) for flexibility and speed</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Possible limitations in scalability and higher power consumption</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2023</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Methodology</title>
      <p>LDPC codes are widely used in modern communication systems, including 5G LTE, due to their excellent error-correcting capabilities. Designing an LDPC decoder for a next-generation communication system like 5G LTE requires a well-structured methodology. This section presents a high-level outline of the methodology for developing an LDPC decoder with the 5G LTE algorithm.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Shannon channel coding theorem</title>
          
          <p>The Shannon channel coding theorem in information theory is understood to have endorsed the development of error control codes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]. It states that all the data rates much less than the channel capacity may be done with an arbitrarily small chance of error, which is given by the Shannon-Hartley Eq. (1).</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>C</mi>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>∗</mo>
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                <msub>
                  <mi>T</mi>
                  <mi>p</mi>
                </msub>
                <msub>
                  <mi>log</mi>
                  <mn>2</mn>
                </msub>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                  <mfrac>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>p</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mrow>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>N</mi>
                        <mi>p</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>T</mi>
                        <mi>p</mi>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                  </mfrac>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, $C<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>T_p<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>S_p<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>N_p$ is the spectral density of noise power [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>].</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Block diagram of the designed LDPC decoder</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_aGJnpxPJHYpNYvS8.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> shows the block diagram of the designed LDPC decoder, which consists of synchronous reset inputs and a global clock. Based on the provided value at the MaxIter input, the iteration’s permissible range is decided between 0 and 15. The value of MaxIter is read by setting the “configure” to high. Through the control signal of the load, the log-likelihood ratios (LLRs) are fed into the decoder. The start signal is used to initiate the decoding process. After the completion of the decoding process, the decoded data is collected through the signal “data out ready.” For the confirmation of data receipt, the decoded bit “Data Out Ack” is used. The “used Iter” port is used to acquire the iteration range. The progress of the decoder is shown by the port “decoder status,” which shows the active and idle states.</p><p>The LLR input is loaded one after another serially to the decoder, and the decoded data is also latched serially bit by bit through the “decoded data” port. This process of decoding is used because of the FPGA input/ output ports available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Top-level architecture</title>
          
          <p>The quantization version is predicted using LLR messages and decoded in the input port. Quantization and LLR messages are important components in the context of LDPC decoding. The LLR messages represent the likelihood of bits being either 0 or 1, and quantization is a process of mapping these continuous LLR values to discrete symbols (0 or 1) for further processing. This is commonly done in LDPC decoding to facilitate the message-passing algorithm, such as BP. The CTV messages compressed are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Compressed format of CTV messages</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_zMmx6FRd0c0UEbTG.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The base matrix <italic>HB</italic>, corresponding to a QC-LDPC with dimensions <italic>Mb</italic>×<italic>Nb</italic> and a decoding layer range L, is observed to typically equal <italic>Mb</italic>. This equality suggests that the expansion factor Z directly correlates with the parallelism degree of the decoder. It is noted that the values of a posteriori probability (APP) q-bits are subjected to quantization, ensuring that the messages exchanged are represented with q-bit precision. All control signals are generated. All control signals are generated by the controller. The CTV and APP messages are stored in blocks of two memories, CTV memory and APP memory, respectively. The dual-port random access memory (DP-RAM) aids simultaneous write and read operations. The operations of read, write, and begin are performed in parallel with the APP memory, which uses registers. The memory of APP is classified into three portions in the suggested architecture, and the memory of CTV is divided into two parts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>].</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Top-level architecture of the proposed 5G LTE-based LDPC decoder</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_hQ14RxdnHQ7t7JyP.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> shows the top-level architecture of the proposed 5G LTE-based LDPC decoder. During the decoding process, the APP messages are taken from APP memory, and then they forward into the read network, where they rearrange to choose the message for the processing layer in accordance with the VN units (VNUs) and left barrel shifters (LBSs). In the same manner, APP messages are organized to update the write network; hence, they can be stored in the APP memory addresses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">44</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>]. The code of the maximum is represented by <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msup>
      <mi>C</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
      </mrow>
    </msup>
  </math>
</inline-formula> of VNUs and LBSs adopted in the proposed architecture. The read network message is turned left through LBSs in line with the shift factors to calculate VTC messages. The barrel shifter data write-back may be avoided by using the approach given to produce the shift factor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">47</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">48</xref>].</p><p>CNU's architecture is separated into subunits, as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref>. The VTC message units are applied to the $1^{\text {st }}<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>C</mi>
    <mi>N</mi>
    <mi>U</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>2^{\text {nd }}<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>C</mi>
    <mi>N</mi>
    <mi>U</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>C</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>S</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>C</mi>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>V</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>C</mi>
    <mi>N</mi>
    <mi>U</mi>
    <mi>I</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>c$ be the greatest row degree. The width of CTV memory is set to 512 bytes in order to store sets of CTV messages at the same address, and the CTV memory process has been done using Eq. (2).</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_5">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Architecture of the CNU</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_cLNgRRYq44upo2WL.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(2)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN" fence="true" stretchy="true" symmetric="true"/>
                  <mo>=</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
                  <mo>,</mo>
                  <mo>∗</mo>
                  <mo>∗</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                  <mi>w</mi>
                  <mi>p</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                    <mo>∗</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <mi>p</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo>+</mo>
                      <mo>.</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <msup>
                        <mi>c</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </msup>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                        <mo>−</mo>
                        <mo>+</mo>
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">]</mo>
                        <mi>q</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>log</mi>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <msup>
                          <mi>c</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
                          </mrow>
                        </msup>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo>+</mo>
                    <mo>.</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msup>
                      <mi>c</mi>
                      <mi>d</mi>
                    </msup>
                    <mn>2</mn>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo>−</mo>
                      <mo>+</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <mi>q</mi>
                      <mi>s</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>log</mi>
                        <mn>2</mn>
                      </msub>
                      <msup>
                        <mi>c</mi>
                        <mi>d</mi>
                      </msup>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>2</mn>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>The memories of CTV are divided into parts. The orthogonal components, and the maximum row degree of layers except the core, <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mn>1</mn>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
      <mspace width="0.167em"/>
    </mstyle>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
      <mo>+</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi>n</mi>
        <mi>d</mi>
      </msub>
      <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
        <mspace width="0.167em"/>
      </mstyle>
      <mi>c</mi>
      <mn>2</mn>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
        <mo>−</mo>
        <mo>+</mo>
        <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
        <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
        <mi>q</mi>
        <mi>c</mi>
        <mn>1</mn>
        <msub>
          <mi>log</mi>
          <mn>2</mn>
        </msub>
        <msub>
          <mi>n</mi>
          <mi>d</mi>
        </msub>
        <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
          <mspace width="0.167em"/>
        </mstyle>
      </mrow>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula> denote the detailed structure of those submemories. The initial segments <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mn>1</mn>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula> of CTV messages are generated within the core. Orthogonal components are stored in CTV memory 1, and the rest are stored in memory 2 of CTV, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_6">
              <label>Figure 6</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Detailed structure of the CTV memory</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_hu3JIGXm_MhAd4iY.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The messages of CTV are absolutely saved in memory CTV 1 for distinct levels. CTV memory 2's depth L0 is substantially shorter than L since it is only used for the layers in the centre and orthogonal regions. In addition, the scale of memory CTV is reduced by 16.6% for codes BFI and by 18.4% for codes BG2. In sum, of CTV RAM, 39.6% is saved for BG1, and 29.8% of BG2 is used in the layer merging method. Because the CTV memory consumes such a large portion of the decoder's area, these solutions have a considerable impact on overall area reduction. The interconnection block, which determines the overall hardware overhead, is another important component of the memory block [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">50</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_52">52</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">53</xref>].</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_7">
              <label>Figure 7</label>
              <caption>
                <title>APP memory for the structure of extension bits</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_0voJBStvGw4lepj4.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>During the decoding process, the APP messages are taken from APP memory. Then it forwards into the read network, and rearranges to choose the message for the processing layer in accordance with the VNUs and LBSs. In the same manner, APP messages are organized to update the write network; hence, they can be stored in the APP memory addresses as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>.</p><p>This algorithm, which is also employed in the AI field, is found in Gallagher's work. It is characterized by the probabilistic model governing the transmission of messages from a message node c to check nodes. This model takes into account the value v observed at the node as well as the value communicated to v in the preceding round. The transfer of messages from c to v is likely to have certain values from the last round. Under a particular assumption known as the assumption of independence, it is simple to construct formulas for these probabilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">54</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_55">55</xref>].</p><p>Working with log-likelihoods and likelihoods rather than probabilities is occasionally helpful. The likelihood probability is given in Eq. (3), which articulates the formulation of the likelihood probability x for a binary random variable.</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(3)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mtext> Let </mtext>
                <mi>L</mi>
                <mi>X</mi>
                <mi>x</mi>
                <mi>x</mi>
                <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo fence="false" stretchy="false">⌈</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo fence="false" stretchy="false">⌉</mo>
                <mo fence="false" stretchy="false">⌈</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo fence="false" stretchy="false">⌉</mo>
                <msub>
                  <mi>P</mi>
                  <mi>r</mi>
                </msub>
                <msub>
                  <mi>P</mi>
                  <mi>r</mi>
                </msub>
                <mn>0</mn>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mo>/</mo>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>By Baye's rule, if $x<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>q</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>L\left(\frac{x}{y}\right)=L\left(\frac{y}{x}\right)<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>A</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\left[y_1, y_2, y_3, y_4 \ldots \ldots y_d\right]$ are random variables that are independent of one another, as shown in Eqs.</p><p>(4) and (5), then:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(4)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>ln</mi>
                <mi>L</mi>
                <mi>x</mi>
                <mi>y</mi>
                <mi>y</mi>
                <mi>d</mi>
                <mi>ln</mi>
                <mi>L</mi>
                <mi>x</mi>
                <mi>y</mi>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                <mo>∣</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                <mo>∣</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <munderover>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>d</mi>
                </munderover>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(5)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>ln</mi>
                <mi>L</mi>
                <mi>x</mi>
                <mi>x</mi>
                <mi>l</mi>
                <mi>y</mi>
                <mi>y</mi>
                <mi>l</mi>
                <mi>ln</mi>
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                <mo>⊕</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>⊕</mo>
                <mo>∣</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mfrac>
                  <mrow>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                    <mo>+</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <munderover>
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∏</mo>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>i</mi>
                          <mo>=</mo>
                          <mn>1</mn>
                        </mrow>
                        <mi>l</mi>
                      </munderover>
                      <mi>tanh</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                        <mfrac>
                          <mrow>
                            <mi>l</mi>
                            <mi>i</mi>
                          </mrow>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </mfrac>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <munderover>
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∏</mo>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>i</mi>
                          <mo>=</mo>
                          <mn>1</mn>
                        </mrow>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                      </munderover>
                      <mi>tanh</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                        <mfrac>
                          <mrow>
                            <mi>l</mi>
                            <mi>i</mi>
                          </mrow>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </mfrac>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mfrac>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, $I<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>q</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\ln x_i / y_i$.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Check node processing</title>
          
          <p>In LDPC decoding, check node processing is a crucial step in the BP, or sum-product algorithm (SPA), used to correct errors in received data. Check node processing occurs in the second phase of the BP algorithm and is responsible for updating the information about parity checks in the LDPC code. The check node values are computed using the second step of the logarithmic message. The check node values are computed using the second step of the logarithmic message forwarding technique. As seen below, the check node values <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi>r</mi>
        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
          <mi>j</mi>
          <mi>i</mi>
        </mrow>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula> are generated from the VN values <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>L</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>q</mi>
        <mi>i</mi>
        <mi>j</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. Check node processing has been conducted using Eq. (6). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref> represents the output generation of its input by adding all <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>r</mi>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula> inputs to the output of check nodes.</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(6)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>L</mi>
                <mi mathvariant="normal">∅</mi>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>r</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>j</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∮</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <munder>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>i</mi>
                      <mo>∈</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>R</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>i</mi>
                          <mi>i</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                  </munder>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>β</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>.</mo>
                <munder>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∏</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mo>∈</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>R</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </munder>
                <msub>
                  <mo>∝</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mi>j</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </msub>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>α</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>i</mi>
        <mi>j</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>β</mi>
      <mi>q</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
      <mi>L</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
        <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
        <msub>
          <mi>q</mi>
          <mi>s</mi>
        </msub>
      </mrow>
    </mrow>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">|</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">|</mo>
      <mi>L</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
        <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
        <msub>
          <mi>q</mi>
          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
            <mi>i</mi>
            <mi>j</mi>
          </mrow>
        </msub>
      </mrow>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, and <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi mathvariant="normal">∅</mi>
    <mi>z</mi>
    <mi>log</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
    <mfrac>
      <mrow>
        <msup>
          <mi>e</mi>
          <mi>z</mi>
        </msup>
        <mo>+</mo>
        <mn>1</mn>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
        <msup>
          <mi>e</mi>
          <mi>z</mi>
        </msup>
        <mo>−</mo>
        <mn>1</mn>
      </mrow>
    </mfrac>
  </math>
</inline-formula>.</p><p>The magnitude of the check nodes is computed according to Eq. (7).</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(7)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">|</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">|</mo>
                  <mi>L</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>r</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>j</mi>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <munder>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>i</mi>
                      <mo>∈</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>R</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>j</mi>
                          <mi>i</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                  </munder>
                  <mi>φ</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>β</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mi>φ</mi>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_8">
              <label>Figure 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Check node values for magnitude computation</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_wGKhfjgXPYFSrVqJ.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The LDPC decoding process starts with the initialization of VNs and check nodes. VNs represent bits, and check nodes represent parity checks in the LDPC code. The received LLRs are associated with VNs. Message passing uses the BP algorithm, and it occurs iteratively between VNs and check nodes. VNs send messages to connected check nodes, and check nodes send messages back to VNs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">56</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_57">57</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_58">58</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.4. Check node processing</title>
          
          <p>During the check node processing step, check nodes calculate and send updated messages to VNs.</p><p>The message sent from a check node to a VN contains information about the parity constraints associated with that check node. The check node checks whether the parity constraints are satisfied based on the LLRs received from the connected VNs.</p><p>The messages typically represent soft information and are updated using the SPA. The SPA involves the following steps:</p><p> ·Message calculation: The check node calculates a message for each connected VN by summing or combining the LLRs from the connected VNs.</p><p> ·Message update: The calculated messages are sent to the respective VNs. These messages can be thought of as “soft constraints" based on the parity checks.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.5. Flow chart</title>
          
          <p>Binary Phase Shift Keying (BPSK) modulation is used in this example, which transforms a code in sequence <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>C</mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>…</mo>
    <mo>…</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <msub>
      <mi>C</mi>
      <mn>1</mn>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>C</mi>
      <mn>2</mn>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>C</mi>
      <mi>n</mi>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. Then <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mi mathvariant="normal">S</mi>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula> is sent over an AWGN channel. Following demodulation, the obtained value for <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>S</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula> is <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>Y</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>S</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>n</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo>+</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. Then <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi>P</mi>
        <mi>i</mi>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula> is calculated from the received value <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>Y</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. Bit $i<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>k</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>V</mi>
    <mi>N</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>I<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>R</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>L\left(q_{i j}\right)<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>i<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>V</mi>
    <mi>N</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>I<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>k</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mi>A</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>L\left(Q_i\right)<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>R</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>i$.</p><p>The flow chart of the BP decoding algorithm is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref>.</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(8)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN" fence="true" stretchy="true" symmetric="true"/>
                  <mo>=</mo>
                  <mo>…</mo>
                  <mo>…</mo>
                  <mo>,</mo>
                  <mo>∼</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <mi>L</mi>
                  <mi>E</mi>
                  <mi>n</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>r</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>j</mi>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo>&gt;</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <mi>π</mi>
                    <mi>c</mi>
                    <mi>j</mi>
                    <msup>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msup>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <mi>t</mi>
                  <mi>J</mi>
                  <mi>j</mi>
                  <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                    <mspace width="0.167em"/>
                  </mstyle>
                  <msup>
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msup>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>For ease of reference in subsequent discussions, the following notations are introduced:</p><p><inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>R</mi>
    <mi>j</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula> : Check node $j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>V</mi>
    <mi>N</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>x</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\mathrm{VN} i<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;</mo>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>C(i) j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>:</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\mathrm{VN} i<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>k</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>x</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>k</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;</mo>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>L\left(P_i\right):<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>R</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;</mo>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula>L\left(r_{j i}\right)<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>:</mo>
    <mi>B</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>i<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\mathrm{VN} i<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>k</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>R</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>i<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;</mo>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>L\left(q_{i j}\right)<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>:</mo>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>R</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>i<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\mathrm{VN} i<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>k</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;</mo>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>L\left(Q_i\right):<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>L</mi>
    <mi>R</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>i$.</p><p>The BP decoding technique is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref> as a flow chart. The process goes back to step 1 if the number of repetitions is the maximum and if it is not a valid code word [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_59">59</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_60">60</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_61">61</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_62">62</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_63">63</xref>]. The BP algorithm works well for codes such as LDPC, but the tanh and tanh-1 operations are too difficult to implement in hardware. Otherwise, the minsum technique makes updating messages in check nodes faster to calculate by using a clever approximation of the conventional BP algorithm, as given in Eq. (9).</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(9)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>L</mi>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>r</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>j</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <munder>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∏</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <msup>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msup>
                      <mo>∈</mo>
                      <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                      <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                      <mi>R</mi>
                      <mi>j</mi>
                      <mi mathvariant="normal">∖</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </munder>
                  <msub>
                    <mi mathvariant="normal">∅</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <msup>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msup>
                      <mi>j</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">min</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE" fence="true" stretchy="true" symmetric="true"/>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>β</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <msup>
                          <mi>i</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                          </mrow>
                        </msup>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
                <mo>=</mo>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_9">
              <label>Figure 9</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Flow chart of the BP algorithm</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_eqplLg0Z7fLLyXJM.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The computed values for a particular pair of <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>I</mi>
    <mi>j</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula> are denoted by <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>L</mi>
      <mn>1</mn>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>L</mi>
      <mn>2</mn>
    </msub>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, which have the same sign, and <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>I</mi>
    <msub>
      <mi>L</mi>
      <mn>2</mn>
    </msub>
    <mo>&amp;gt;</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula> <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>I</mi>
    <msub>
      <mi>L</mi>
      <mn>1</mn>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. The performance is approximated based on the offset BP-based algorithm while containing only adds and comparisons, making it appropriate for hardware implementation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_64">64</xref>]. To compensate for the min-sum hardware implementation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_64">64</xref>]. To compensate for the min-sum approximation's performance loss, it was calculated using Eq. (10). </p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(10)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>L</mi>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>r</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>j</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <munder>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∏</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <msup>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msup>
                      <mo>∈</mo>
                      <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                      <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                      <mi>R</mi>
                      <mi>j</mi>
                      <mi mathvariant="normal">∖</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </munder>
                  <msub>
                    <mi mathvariant="normal">∅</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <msup>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msup>
                      <mi>j</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">min</mo>
                  <mo>−</mo>
                  <mo>,</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE" fence="true" stretchy="true" symmetric="true"/>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>β</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <msup>
                          <mi>i</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                          </mrow>
                        </msup>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>ρ</mi>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mrow>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>.</mo>
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.6. Decoder for an awgn channel</title>
          
          <p>For an LDPC code, a tanner graph is a bipartite graph in which one class of nodes corresponds to n bits in the code word and the other class corresponds to VNs. The second sort of node is the check node, which corresponds to m parity check equations. An edge connects a VN to the check node if and only if that particular bit is included in the parity check equation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_65">65</xref>]. The bit nodes in the Tanner graph are known as repetition nodes, whereas the check nodes are known as zero-sum nodes. The incoming data at each bit node corresponds to a single variable only, similar to how a repetition code works. The parity check constraint, often known as the zero-sum constraint, relates to the incoming data at each check node [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_66">66</xref>]. As a result, the belief propagation decoder is divided into two parts: a Soft Input Soft Output (SISO) decoder for a repetition code and a SISO decoder for a Single Parity Check (SPC) code. The i-th zero-sum node is represented in Eq. (11), where the i-th repetition node <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">mi</mi>
    </mrow>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">ri</mi>
    </mrow>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">Li</mi>
    </mrow>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <munderover>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>j</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mn>1</mn>
      </mrow>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>w</mi>
        <mi>c</mi>
        <mo>−</mo>
        <mn>1</mn>
      </mrow>
    </munderover>
  </math>
</inline-formula>.</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(11)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">Li</mi>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">Si</mi>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mo stretchy="false">|</mo>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mo stretchy="false">|</mo>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">mi</mi>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mo>/</mo>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mo stretchy="false">|</mo>
                </mrow>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>×</mo>
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">|</mo>
                <munderover>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>j</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>w</mi>
                    <mi>r</mi>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                </munderover>
                <mi>log</mi>
                <mi>tanh</mi>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Results and discussion</title>
      <p>In this section, the performance analysis has been done between the proposed algorithm and conventional methods with an Nb= 672 block code. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_10">Figure 10</xref> shows the performance analysis between the proposed method and conventional methods for R=1/2. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_11">Figure 11</xref> shows the performance analysis between the proposed method and conventional methods for R=13/16. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_12">Figure 12</xref> shows the SNR performance analysis between the proposed method and conventional methods for R=9/10.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_10">
          <label>Figure 10</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Performance analysis between the proposed method and conventional methods with respect to the code rate of 1/2</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_b4YX9bvKTUM-4mDO.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>This analysis is predicated upon the variable <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mfrac>
      <msub>
        <mi>E</mi>
        <mi>b</mi>
      </msub>
      <msub>
        <mi>N</mi>
        <mn>0</mn>
      </msub>
    </mfrac>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, representing the energy per bit to noise power spectral density ratio, articulated in decibels (dB). The delineation of BER performance as a function showcases the efficacy of the proposed method in contrast to conventional methodologies. The BER is plotted on a logarithmic scale which is common for such analyses, allowing for a wide range of error rates to be displayed clearly. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_11">Figure 11</xref> shows the <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mfrac>
      <msub>
        <mi>E</mi>
        <mi>b</mi>
      </msub>
      <msub>
        <mi>N</mi>
        <mn>0</mn>
      </msub>
    </mfrac>
  </math>
</inline-formula> ratio on the x-axis, which represents the quality of the communication channel, with higher values indicating better channel conditions (less noise). The BER on the y-axis measures the rate at which errors occur in the received data stream. The lower the BER for a given <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mfrac>
      <msub>
        <mi>E</mi>
        <mi>b</mi>
      </msub>
      <msub>
        <mi>N</mi>
        <mn>0</mn>
      </msub>
    </mfrac>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, the better the performance of the decoding algorithm.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_11">
          <label>Figure 11</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Performance analysis between the proposed method and conventional methods with respect to the code rate of 13/16</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_iujxbg6f4s_UANe5.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_11">Figure 11</xref> shows the BER performance of various decoding schemes, including a proposed 5G-LTE algorithm, which is plotted against the <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mfrac>
      <msub>
        <mi>E</mi>
        <mi>b</mi>
      </msub>
      <msub>
        <mi>N</mi>
        <mn>0</mn>
      </msub>
    </mfrac>
  </math>
</inline-formula> ratio in <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">dB</mi>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. The uncoded BPSK/Quadrature Phase Shift Keying (QPSK) curve serves as the baseline, showing error rates without correction. The Quadrature Convolutional-Viterbi (QC-Viterbi) and QCLDC curves represent traditional and LDPC codes, respectively, both of which are standard in communications for error correction. Notably, the 5G-LTE algorithm's curve is expected to demonstrate enhanced performance, characterized by a lower BER across the <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mfrac>
      <msub>
        <mi>E</mi>
        <mi>b</mi>
      </msub>
      <msub>
        <mi>N</mi>
        <mn>0</mn>
      </msub>
    </mfrac>
  </math>
</inline-formula> spectrum, indicating superior error-correcting capabilities tailored for the 5G environment. Analyzing this graph involves assessing how each curve descends with increasing <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mfrac>
      <msub>
        <mi>E</mi>
        <mi>b</mi>
      </msub>
      <msub>
        <mi>N</mi>
        <mn>0</mn>
      </msub>
    </mfrac>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, as a steeper descent indicates more effective error correction.</p><p>The proposed 5G-LTE algorithm's performance is of particular interest; if it maintains lower BER values at higher <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mfrac>
      <msub>
        <mi>E</mi>
        <mi>b</mi>
      </msub>
      <msub>
        <mi>N</mi>
        <mn>0</mn>
      </msub>
    </mfrac>
  </math>
</inline-formula> levels compared to the QC-Viterbi and QCLDC methods, it suggests a significant improvement in maintaining data integrity under typical 5G network conditions. This comparative analysis underscores the potential of the proposed algorithm to enhance the reliability of 5G communications, a key factor in supporting the network's high-speed and low-latency objectives.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_12">
          <label>Figure 12</label>
          <caption>
            <title>SNR performance analysis between the proposed method and conventional methods for R=9/10</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/2/img_Ra4Y6a2NvtxBxWJM.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_12">Figure 12</xref> shows the BER performance of several decoding schemes plotted against SNR in dB, which is a standard way to evaluate the efficacy of error correction in communication systems. The uncoded BPSK/QPSK curve establishes a baseline by showing the error rate without error correction, while the QC-Viterbi and QCLDC curves represent the performance of quasi-cyclic and LDPC codes, respectively. The 5G-LTE algorithm curve is included to illustrate the performance of the proposed method tailored for 5G networks. The steepness of the curve for the 5G-LTE algorithm, as compared to the QC-Viterbi and QCLDC, and its position relative to the uncoded BPSK/QPSK baseline, provide insight into its error-correcting performance. If the 5G-LTE algorithm's curve falls below the other curves at the same SNR levels, this would indicate a lower BER, signifying that the algorithm is more robust in correcting errors over the communication channel, especially in the noisy environments typical of 5G networks. </p><p>The 5G-LTE algorithm performs across different SNR values, particularly focusing on the lower end of the SNR spectrum, which is challenging for error correction algorithms. Superior performance at lower SNR values would mean that the 5G-LTE algorithm can maintain data integrity even in poor signal conditions, which is critical for the reliability of 5G communications. Additionally, the graph would be scrutinized for the SNR value at which each algorithm begins to flatten out, indicating the point at which further increases in SNR provide diminishing returns in error correction. This analysis would be crucial for understanding the practical applications and limitations of the 5G-LTE algorithm in real-world scenarios.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>5. Conclusions</title>
      <p>This study makes a significant contribution to the field of wireless communication by proposing a technique that enhances switching operations, facilitating the simultaneous control of multiple devices within a 5G communication infrastructure. The technique's ability to manage 64-bit operations with improved efficiency underlines its potential to handle complex tasks that are likely to be commonplace in the emerging IoT ecosystem.</p><p>The simulation results underscore the method's efficacy, demonstrating a notable reduction in the BER, namely, 2.5% over uncoded BPSK/QPSK, 1.6% over QC-Viterbi, and 0.5% over QCLDPC for a code rate (r) of 1/2. These improvements in BER directly translate to more reliable communication, with fewer errors and corrections needed, which is particularly valuable in applications requiring high data integrity. Moreover, the proposed method's enhancement of the SNR by 3.6%, 2.5%, and 1.3%, respectively, for the same methods and code rate further attests to its superior performance, offering clearer signal transmission and better overall network efficiency. For the higher code rate of 13/16, the BER improvements are 2.2% over uncoded BPSK/QPSK, 1.3% over QC-Viterbi, and 0.2% over QCLDPC, indicating that the method maintains its effectiveness even as the redundancy in the transmitted data is reduced. This aspect is crucial for high-throughput systems where bandwidth efficiency is paramount.</p><p>The future scope of this research is ambitious, aiming to expand the operational capability to 128-bit operations. This scale-up is in direct response to the anticipated growth in the number of devices connecting to 5G networks, which will demand faster switching speeds and more robust error correction algorithms. The intention to improve upon the current research will likely focus on further optimizing the switching speed and reliability, ensuring that the 5G LTE network can keep pace with the rapid expansion of connected devices and the data-heavy demands of modern communication systems. This forward-looking approach highlights the ongoing need for innovation in 5G technology to support the burgeoning network of smart devices, industrial automation, and other emerging technologies that will define the digital landscape of the future.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors would like to thank SJB Institute of Technology, JSS Academy of Technical Education, Bengaluru, JSS Science and Technology, Mysore, KS Institute of Technology, Bengaluru, Visvesvaraya Technological University (VTU), Belagavi and Vision Group on Science and Technology (VGST) Karnataka Fund for Infrastructure strengthening in Science &amp;amp; Technology Level – 2 sponsored “Establishment of Renewable Smart Grid Laboratory" for all the support and encouragement provided by them to take up this research work and publish this paper.</p>
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>152 960–152 971</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Papatheofanous</surname>
              <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reisis</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nikitopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.20213127039</pub-id>
          <article-title>LDPC hardware acceleration in 5G open radio access network platforms</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Access</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>98-101</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Su</surname>
              <given-names>B. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>C. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiueh</surname>
              <given-names>T. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/lssc.2022.3167423</pub-id>
          <article-title>A 58.6/91.3 pj/b dual-mode belief-propagation decoder for LDPC and polar codes in the 5G communications standard</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Solid State Circuits Lett.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>469-478</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sathyanarayana</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srikantaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11591/ijece.v14i1.pp469-478</pub-id>
          <article-title>An efficient unused integrated circuits detection algorithm for parallel scan architecture</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Electr. Comput. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sampath</surname>
              <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeswanth</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Snehith</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anooja</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An efficient channel coding architecture for 5G wireless using high-level synthesis</article-title>
          <source>2021 5th International Conference on Trends in Electronics and Informatics (ICOEI)</source>
          <publisher-name>Tirunelveli, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2021</year>
          <page-range>674-680</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icoei51242.2021.9453001</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Belhadj</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abdelmounaim</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On error correction performance of LDPC and polar codes for the 5G machine type communications</article-title>
          <source>2021 IEEE International IOT, Electronics and Mechatronics Conference (IEMTRONICS)</source>
          <publisher-name>Toronto, Canada</publisher-name>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>2021</volume>
          <page-range>1-4</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/iemtronics52119.2021.9422665</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>N. I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>J. U.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Early termination scheme for 5G NR LDPC code</article-title>
          <source>2021 International Conference on Information and Communication Technology Convergence (ICTC)</source>
          <publisher-name>Jeju Island, Republic of Korea</publisher-name>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>2021</volume>
          <page-range>933-935</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ictc52510.2021.9621117</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Petrović</surname>
              <given-names>V. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>El Mezeni</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reduced-complexity offset min-sum based layered decoding for 5G LDPC codes</article-title>
          <source>2020 28th Telecommunications Forum (TELFOR)</source>
          <publisher-name>Belgrade, Serbia</publisher-name>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>2020</volume>
          <page-range>1–4</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/telfor51502.2020.9306590</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ren</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kristensen</surname>
              <given-names>A. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>You</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burg</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Improved belief propagation decoding of turbo codes</article-title>
          <source>ICASSP 2023 - 2023 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP)</source>
          <publisher-name>Rhodes Island, Greece</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <page-range>1-5</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icassp49357.2023.10097058</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>305-314</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sukumar</surname>
              <given-names>P. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krishnaiah</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Velluri</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Satish</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Puttaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>N. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srikantaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11591/ijece.v14i1.pp305-314</pub-id>
          <article-title>An efficient adaptive reconfigurable routing protocol for optimized data packet distribution in network on chips</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Electr. Comput. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>2501-2510</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manjunath</surname>
              <given-names>T. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11591/ijpeds.v12i4.pp2501-2510</pub-id>
          <article-title>An efficient hybrid reconfigurable wind gas turbine power management system using MPPT algorithm</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Power Electron. Drive Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>56</volume>
          <page-range>1003-1017</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pandith</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srikantaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/jesa.560611</pub-id>
          <article-title>Efficient geographic routing for highspeed data in wireless multimedia sensor networks</article-title>
          <source>J. Eur. Syst. Autom.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>14-25</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pandith</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srikantaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/ida010103</pub-id>
          <article-title>A comprehensive review of geographic routing protocols in wireless sensor network</article-title>
          <source>Inf. Dyn. Appl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>195</volume>
          <page-range>526</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Subramoniam</surname>
              <given-names>S. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-023-11140-w</pub-id>
          <article-title>An assessment of vegetation cover of Mysuru City, Karnataka State, India, using deep convolutional neural networks</article-title>
          <source>Environ. Monit. Assess.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kang</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xing</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/tcomm.2023.3261380</pub-id>
          <article-title>Parity-check matrix partitioning for efficient layered decoding of QC-LDPC codes</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Trans. Commun.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>H. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
              <given-names>C. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>J. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Low-complexity LDPC decoder for 5G URLLC</article-title>
          <source>2018 IEEE Asia Pacific Conference on Postgraduate Research in Microelectronics and Electronics (PrimeAsia)</source>
          <publisher-name>Chengdu, China</publisher-name>
          <year>2018</year>
          <page-range>43–46</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/primeasia.2018.8597812</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>C. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>H. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>H. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ueng</surname>
              <given-names>Y. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hardware-friendly LDPC decoding scheduling for 5G HARQ applications</article-title>
          <source>ICASSP 2019 - 2019 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP)</source>
          <publisher-name>Brighton, UK</publisher-name>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>2019</volume>
          <page-range>1418–1422</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icassp.2019.8682481</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Katyushnyj</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krylov</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rashich</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peng</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>FPGA implementation of LDPC decoder for 5G NR with parallel layered architecture and adaptive normalization</article-title>
          <source>2020 IEEE International Conference on Electrical Engineering and Photonics (EExPolytech)</source>
          <publisher-name>St. Petersburg, Russia</publisher-name>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>2020</volume>
          <page-range>34-37</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/eexpolytech50912.2020.9243997</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>C. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>L. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liao</surname>
              <given-names>Y. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>H. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A 33.2 gbps/iter. reconfigurable LDPC decoder fully compliant with 5G NR applications</article-title>
          <source>2021 IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS)</source>
          <publisher-name>Daegu, Korea</publisher-name>
          <year>2021</year>
          <page-range>1-5</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/iscas51556.2021.9401329</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ortega-Ortega</surname>
              <given-names>A. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bravo-Torres</surname>
              <given-names>J. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Combining LDPC codes, M-QAM modulations, and IFDMA multiple access to achieve 5G requirements</article-title>
          <source>2017 International Conference on Electronics, Communications and Computers (CONIELECOMP)</source>
          <publisher-name>Cholula, Mexico</publisher-name>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume>2017</volume>
          <page-range>1–5</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/conielecomp.2017.7891828</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nga</surname>
              <given-names>N. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khanh</surname>
              <given-names>C. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tho</surname>
              <given-names>N. Q.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An investigation of the 5G LDPC and polar decoding performance in spatial correlated MIMO-OFDMA system</article-title>
          <source>2022 16th International Conference on Ubiquitous Information Management and Communication (IMCOM)</source>
          <publisher-name>Seoul, Korea</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>2022</volume>
          <page-range>1-7</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/imcom53663.2022.9721755</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Papatheofanous</surname>
              <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reisis</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nikitopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The LDPC challenge in software based 5G new radio physical layer processing</article-title>
          <source>2021 IEEE International Mediterranean Conference on Communications and Networking (MeditCom)</source>
          <publisher-name>Athens, Greece</publisher-name>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>2021</volume>
          <page-range>312–317</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/meditcom49071.2021.9647697</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sheela</surname>
              <given-names>F. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naveen</surname>
              <given-names>K. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Basavaraju</surname>
              <given-names>N. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krishnaiah</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An efficient vehicle to vehicle communication system using intelligent transportation system</article-title>
          <source>2023 International Conference on Recent Advances in Science and Engineering Technology (ICRASET)</source>
          <publisher-name>B G Nagara, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>2023</volume>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icraset59632.2023.10420043</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jyothi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kavitha</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kavya</surname>
              <given-names>B. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A machine learning based power load prediction system for smart grid energy management</article-title>
          <source>2023 International Conference on Recent Advances in Science and Engineering Technology (ICRASET)</source>
          <publisher-name>B G Nagara, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>2023</volume>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icraset59632.2023.10420183</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>171</volume>
          <page-range>2128–2136</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shrinidhi</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krishna</surname>
              <given-names>P. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamuna</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pargunarajan</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procs.2020.04.230</pub-id>
          <article-title>Mcodified min sum decoding algorithm for LDPC codes</article-title>
          <source>Procedia Comput. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Muskan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raj</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nisar</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abbas</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naz</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Various channel coding schemes for 5G</article-title>
          <source>2023 IEEE International Students’ Conference on Electrical, Electronics and Computer Science</source>
          <publisher-name>Bhopal, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>2023</volume>
          <page-range>1-13</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/sceecs57921.2023.10062998</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>72</volume>
          <page-range>553-565</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pramanik</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maity</surname>
              <given-names>S. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarkar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compeleceng.2018.01.014</pub-id>
          <article-title>Compressed sensing image reconstruction by LDPC codes and soft decoding of space time block codes</article-title>
          <source>Comput. Electr. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Petrović</surname>
              <given-names>V. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Flexible encoder and decoder of low-density parity-check codes</article-title>
          <source>2022 30th Telecommunications Forum</source>
          <publisher-name>Belgrade, Serbia</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>2022</volume>
          <page-range>1-2</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/telfor56187.2022.9983744</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>K. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>M. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tseng</surname>
              <given-names>J. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Low-complexity architecture design for modified WiMAX low density parity check codes</article-title>
          <source>2011 8th International Conference on Information, Communications &amp; Signal Processing</source>
          <publisher-name>Singapore</publisher-name>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>2011</volume>
          <page-range>1-4</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icics.2011.6174313</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jemima</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manoj</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Post and pre-layout analysis of LDPC decoder using 120nm technology cadence encounter tool</article-title>
          <source>2015 2nd International Conference on Electronics and Communication Systems</source>
          <publisher-name>Coimbatore, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>2015</volume>
          <page-range>342–349</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ecs.2015.7124921</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xue</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guan</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Implementation of multi rate quasi cyclic low density parity check codes</article-title>
          <source>The 9th International Conference on Advanced Communication Technology</source>
          <publisher-name>Gangwon, Korea (South)</publisher-name>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>2007</volume>
          <page-range>1066–1070</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icact.2007.358542</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bai</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/lcomm.2024.3360450</pub-id>
          <article-title>Efficient construction of quasi-cyclic LDPC codes with multiple lifting sizes</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Commun. Lett.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Che</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/lcomm.2024.3359856</pub-id>
          <article-title>Blind recognition of 5G LDPC codes over a candidate set</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Commun. Lett.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jadagerimath</surname>
              <given-names>A. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sheela</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prakash</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tevaramani</surname>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A machine learning based consumer power management system using smart grid</article-title>
          <source>2023 International Conference on Recent Advances in Science and Engineering Technology (ICRASET)</source>
          <publisher-name>B G NAGARA, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>2023</volume>
          <page-range>1-5</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icraset59632.2023.10419979</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kavya</surname>
              <given-names>B. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naveen</surname>
              <given-names>K. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manu</surname>
              <given-names>K. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manjunatha</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A machine learning based smart grid for home power management using cloud-edge computing system</article-title>
          <source>2023 International Conference on Recent Advances in Science and Engineering Technology (ICRASET)</source>
          <publisher-name>B G NAGARA, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>2023</volume>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icraset59632.2023.10419952</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wulandari</surname>
              <given-names>P. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Utami</surname>
              <given-names>E. Y. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Timotius</surname>
              <given-names>I. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ber performance comparison of low-density parity-check code and polar code</article-title>
          <source>2023 29th International Conference on Telecommunications (ICT)</source>
          <publisher-name>Toba, Indonesia</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>2023</volume>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ict60153.2023.10374061</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elkadi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sadeghi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Russell</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ryu</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Open source-based over-the-air 5G new radio sidelink testbed</article-title>
          <source>MILCOM 2023 - 2023 IEEE Military Communications Conference (MILCOM)</source>
          <publisher-name>Boston, MA, USA</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>2023</volume>
          <page-range>63–70</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/milcom58377.2023.10356257</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lyu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/lcomm.2023.3341081</pub-id>
          <article-title>Optimized non-surjective FAIDs for 5G LDPC codes with learnable quantization</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Commun. Lett.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design of high-speed reconfigurable coprocessor for next-generation communication platform</article-title>
          <source>Emerging Research in Electronics, Computer Science and Technology: Proceedings of International Conference, ICERECT 2012</source>
          <publisher-name>New Delhi</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>2014</volume>
          <page-range>57–67</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-81-322-1157-0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Selvarathinam</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tiling parity-check matrix for reduced complexity high throughput low-density parity-check decoders</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Workshop on Signal Processing Systems Design and Implementation</source>
          <publisher-name>Athens, Greece</publisher-name>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>2005</volume>
          <page-range>744–749</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/sips.2005.1579964</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>40</volume>
          <page-range>3566-3571</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Todd</surname>
              <given-names>R. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cruz</surname>
              <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/tmag.2004.835673</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enforcing maximum-transition-run code constraints and low-density parity-check decoding</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Trans. Magn.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>C. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ueng</surname>
              <given-names>Y. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>M. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>M. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adaptive quantization for low-density-parity-check decoders</article-title>
          <source>2010 International Symposium On Information Theory &amp; Its Applications</source>
          <publisher-name>Taichung, Taiwan</publisher-name>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>2010</volume>
          <page-range>13-18</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/isita.2010.5649830</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>19</volume>
          <page-range>913-916</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jiao</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mu</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/lcomm.2015.2421445</pub-id>
          <article-title>Improved ADMM penalized decoder for irregular low-density paritycheck codes</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Commun. Lett.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ratnayake</surname>
              <given-names>R. N. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haratsch</surname>
              <given-names>E. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A bit-node centric architecture for low-density parity-check decoders</article-title>
          <source>IEEE GLOBECOM2007 - IEEE Global Telecommunications Conference</source>
          <publisher-name>Washington, DC, USA</publisher-name>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>2007</volume>
          <page-range>265-270</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/glocom.2007.57</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Duangthong</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phakphisut</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design of lookup-table (LUT) decoder for protograph-based low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes</article-title>
          <source>2022 37th International Technical Conference on Circuits/Systems, Computers and Communications (ITC-CSCC)</source>
          <publisher-name>Phuket, Thailand</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>844–847</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/itc-cscc55581.2022.9895041</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>24</volume>
          <page-range>100-116</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thazeen</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31436/iiumej.v24i2.2730</pub-id>
          <article-title>The effectiveness of 6T beamformer algorithm in smart antenna systems for convergence analysis</article-title>
          <source>IIUM Eng. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nooli</surname>
              <given-names>C. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hrishikesh</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kruthik</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vakkalanka</surname>
              <given-names>H. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cloud based centralized smart cart and contactless billing system</article-title>
          <source>7th International Conference on Communication and Electronics Systems (ICCES)</source>
          <publisher-name>Coimbatore, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>2022</volume>
          <page-range>820–826</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/icces54183.2022.9835856</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>141-147</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pooja</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.35940/ijeat.f2998.0810621</pub-id>
          <article-title>Hybrid Regularization Algorithm for Efficient Image Deblurring</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Eng. Adv. Technol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>68</volume>
          <page-range>609-617</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24425/ijet.2022.141280</pub-id>
          <article-title>An efficient classification of hyperspectral remotely sensed data using support vector machine</article-title>
          <source>Inter. J. Electro. Telecom.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>3860-3866</page-range>
          <issue>9-10</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Umashankar</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramakrishna</surname>
              <given-names>M. V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1166/jctn.2020.8975</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design of high speed reconfigurable distributed life time efficient routing algorithm in wireless sensor network</article-title>
          <source>J. Comput. Theor. Nanosci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of IoT for vehicle to promote electric vehicles large-scale demonstration application in Chinese cities</article-title>
          <source>Second International Conference on Mechanic Automation and Control Engineering</source>
          <publisher-name>Inner Mongolia, China</publisher-name>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>2011</volume>
          <page-range>5723–5726</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/mace.2011.5988330</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>6239-6247</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rathod</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11591/ijece.v12i6</pub-id>
          <article-title>An efficient reconfigurable peak cancellation model for peak to average power ratio reduction in orthogonal frequency division multiplexing communication system</article-title>
          <source>Inter. J. Electrical Comput. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>69-73</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shebin</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9790/0661-16296973</pub-id>
          <article-title>A software tool that provides relevant information for diabetic patients to help prevent diabetic foot</article-title>
          <source>IOSR J. Comput. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Umashankar</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A survey on IoT protocol in real-time applications and its architectures</article-title>
          <source>ICDSMLA 2021. Lecture Notes in Electrical Engineering</source>
          <publisher-name>Singapore: Springer</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-19-5936-3</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siddesh</surname>
              <given-names>G. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Komala</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel architecture for cluster based false data injection attack detection and location identification in smart grid</article-title>
          <source>Advances in Thermofluids and Renewable Energy</source>
          <publisher-name>Singapore: Springer</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-16-3497-0_48</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>2733-2746</page-range>
          <issue>27</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maheshkumar</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Komala</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17485/ijst/v13i27.982</pub-id>
          <article-title>Implementation of an effective hybrid model for islanded microgrid energy management</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Sci. Tech.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_56">
        <label>56.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>3612-3629</page-range>
          <issue>35</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Madhu</surname>
              <given-names>T. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Komala</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pooja</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17485/ijst/v13i35.1510</pub-id>
          <article-title>Design of fuzzy logic controlled hybrid model for the control of voltage and frequency in microgrid</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Sci. Tech.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_57">
        <label>57.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thazeen</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saqhib</surname>
              <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>DOA method with reduced bias and side lobe suppression</article-title>
          <source>International Conference on Communication, Computing and IoT (IC3IoT)</source>
          <publisher-name>Chennai, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ic3iot53935.2022.9767996</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_58">
        <label>58.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>417–420</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shebin</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17577/ijertv7is020103</pub-id>
          <article-title>A review on clinical decision support system and its scope in medical field</article-title>
          <source>Inter. J. Engi. Res. Tech.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_59">
        <label>59.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pooja</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11042-023-14335-y</pub-id>
          <article-title>Image region driven prior selection for image deblurring</article-title>
          <source>Multimed. Tools Appl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_60">
        <label>60.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>199-210</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumari</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kashyap</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fulwani</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.46488/nept.2023.v22i01.018</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessment and prediction of air quality level using ARIMA model: A case study of Surat City, Gujarat State, India</article-title>
          <source>Nature Environ. Pollut. Tech.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_61">
        <label>61.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thazeen</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saqhib</surname>
              <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Septennial adaptive beamforming algorithm</article-title>
          <source>International Conference on Smart Information Systems and Technologies (SIST)</source>
          <publisher-name>Nur-Sultan, Kazakhstan</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1–4</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/sist54437.2022.9945753</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_62">
        <label>62.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>3270-3279</page-range>
          <issue>44</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rekha</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17485/ijst/v14i44.1790</pub-id>
          <article-title>Comprehensive review of optimal utilization of clock and power resources in multi bit flip flop techniques</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Sci. Tech.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_63">
        <label>63.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>169–190</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sheela</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nataraj</surname>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/mits020305</pub-id>
          <article-title>A comprehensive exploration of resource allocation strategies within vehicle Ad-Hoc Networks</article-title>
          <source>Mechatron. Intell. Transp. Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_64">
        <label>64.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>26</volume>
          <page-range>173-188</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1504/ijetm.2023.130787</pub-id>
          <article-title>An assessment of built-up cover using geospatial techniques – A case study on Mysuru District, Karnataka State, India</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Environ. Tech. Manage.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_65">
        <label>65.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Basavaraju</surname>
              <given-names>N. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharmila</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pooja</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deepak</surname>
              <given-names>B. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An efficient big data gathering in wireless sensor network using reconfigurable node distribution algorithm</article-title>
          <source>Fourth International Conference on Cognitive Computing and Information Processing (CCIP)</source>
          <publisher-name>Bengaluru, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ccip57447.2022.10058620</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_66">
        <label>66.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahendra</surname>
              <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallikarjunaswamy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Basavaraju</surname>
              <given-names>N. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poojary</surname>
              <given-names>P. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gowda</surname>
              <given-names>P. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mukunda</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Navya</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pushpalatha</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Deep learning models for inventory of agriculture crops and yield production using satellite images</article-title>
          <source>IEEE 2nd Mysore Sub Section International Conference (MysuruCon)</source>
          <publisher-name>Mysuru, India</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <page-range>1–7</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/mysurucon55714.2022.9972523</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>