<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJTDI</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Transport Development and Integration</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Int. J. Transp. Dev. Integr.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IJTDI</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2058-8313</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2058-8305</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-Wyl5UcH_GnvcbWvI_tnG1kzBcJ0KTQZs</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/ijtdi090420</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Purchasing Power of Water Transportation Pioneer Services in the Archipelago Region of North Sulawesi</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1,2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-3741-5056</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Hardianto</surname>
            <given-names>Sri</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>sri_hardianto@dephub.go.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9002-402X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Jinca</surname>
            <given-names>Muhammad Yamin</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>yaminjinca@unhas.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_4">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9740-333X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Jompa</surname>
            <given-names>Jamaluddin</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>j.jompa@unhas.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9886-7451</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Saud</surname>
            <given-names>Muhammad Yamin</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>firman23e@student.unhas.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Development Studies Program, Graduate School, Hasanuddin University, 90245 Makassar, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Directorate General of Land Transportation, Ministry of Transportation, 10110 Jakarta, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">Transportation Engineering, Graduate School, Hasanuddin University, 90245 Makassar, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_4">Department of Marine and Fisheries Science, Hasanuddin University, 90245 Makassar, Indonesia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>986</fpage>
      <lpage>1001</lpage>
      <page-range>986-1001</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>07</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>North Sulawesi’s geography includes both its mainland and the island regencies of Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro (Siau Tagulandang Biaro). This study examines the economic and service disparities between the island regencies of Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro and mainland North Sulawesi. In 2023, the Human Development Index (HDI) and Gini ratio for these island regencies were below the averages for both Indonesia and North Sulawesi. To address these gaps, the Ministry of Transportation implemented subsidized sea and ferry transport programs. Using a mixed-methods approach, the research combines a quantitative analysis of purchasing power with a qualitative review of relevant regulations. The study surveyed residents in the island regencies who utilize these subsidized services to assess their Ability to Pay (ATP) and Willingness to Pay (WTP). The findings reveal a significant gap: ATP for both passengers and freight is consistently lower than WTP, indicating a willingness to pay more than they can currently afford. Further analysis shows a disconnect between these ATP-WTP values and government-regulated fares, creating inconsistencies that influence consumer travel choices. This lack of alignment between bottom-up demand for affordable transport and top-down regulatory frameworks has led to inefficient service integration. While multimodal transshipment could offer a potential solution, its implementation is currently hindered by significant geographic and regulatory challenges, perpetuating the economic and service disparities faced by the island regencies.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Water transportation</kwd>
        <kwd>Archipelago</kwd>
        <kwd>Purchasing power</kwd>
        <kwd>Regional development</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="4"/>
        <fig-count count="7"/>
        <table-count count="6"/>
        <ref-count count="62"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.1. Background</title>
          
          <p>North Sulawesi Province is renowned for its marine features, which are reflected in its culture, tourism, and geography. The geography of North Sulawesi includes both the mainland and the island districts of Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro (Siau Tagulandang Biaro) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. In 2023, the Human Development Index (HDI) and Gini ratio for these island districts were below the averages for both Indonesia and North Sulawesi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>].</p><p>To address these disparities, the Government of Indonesia, through the Ministry of Transportation, provides subsidized water transportation services in North Sulawesi via pioneering sea transportation programs, sea tolls, and ferry services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. Private companies operate commercial passenger transportation from mainland North Sulawesi to the islands, while crossing services that transport passengers, vehicles, and cargo are managed by PT ASDP Indonesia Ferry Bitung Branch.</p><p>Fare subsidies for water transportation in archipelagic regions are likely to have significant effects on community travel frequency. By decreasing the cost burden of transportation, these subsidies can promote increased mobility and accessibility among residents of islands and coastal communities, which may be isolated geographically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.2. Problem statement</title>
          
          <p>The geographical distance from mainland North Sulawesi, coupled with extreme water conditions and limited ship capabilities, increases travel time and transportation costs for island communities. This situation requires attention as poverty remains a significant economic challenge in the archipelago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>]. This research aims to identify the purchasing power of water transportation services among communities in the Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro Islands Regencies by analyzing socio-economic factors that influence their travel destinations.</p><p>Studies emphasize the essential nature of transport subsidies, particularly where alternative modes of transport are limited. In the context of maritime connectivity, ferry services act as critical mediators of access to education, healthcare, and economic opportunities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]. Subsidies, by easing financial barriers, can increase the frequency of travel and foster stronger socio-economic connections throughout the archipelago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.3. Research objectives</title>
          
          <p>The initial stage of this research involved a literature review of previous studies to identify similarities in perspective between the research topic and the analysis stage. The literature review was conducted to highlight research gaps in prior studies and to identify differences that contribute to the novelty of this research. Previous studies have shown that sea toll programs are among the government’s flagship initiatives aimed at supporting the maritime axis by distributing basic and essential commodities from economic centres to underdeveloped, remote, outermost, and border areas (referred to as “3TP”). These programs aim to reduce economic inequality, address price disparities, and support sustainable and equitable economic development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>].</p><p>Moreover, effective implementation of subsidies can lead to communities expressing a higher Willingness to Pay (WTP) for continued access to vital travel routes, reflecting a perceived fairness and essential utility derived from subsidized transport options [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.4. Significance of the study</title>
          
          <p>Water transportation plays a critical role in supporting inter-island connectivity within the 3TP region of North Sulawesi. This includes the provision of infrastructure, such as ports in Bitung, Manado, Likupang, and Amurang [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>], as well as the establishment of water transportation networks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>].</p><p>The measurement of people’s purchasing power for transportation services is conducted to assess their Ability to Pay (ATP) and WTP. This serves as a basis for making strategic decisions, such as determining water transportation tariffs and setting the amount of government subsidies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>]. Previous research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>], has substantial relevance to this study, though key differences exist. For example, research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>] focuses on the performance of Bitung Port and its connectivity to the hinterland, primarily analyzing land transportation aspects, while this study focuses on the island districts of Sangihe and Sitaro to evaluate service availability.</p><p>The analysis method in research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>] measures purchasing power using the Composite Performance Index method, producing index values categorized by specific proportions. In contrast, this study employs the Travel Cost Method to generate financial values. The research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>] uses the same method as this study but differs in its research object. While previous studies primarily analyse crossing transport rates for passengers, this study examines passenger and vehicle fares, along with cargo from various groups. Additionally, earlier research does not cover the island regencies of Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro. Research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>] discusses purchasing power normatively as a recommendation for further investigation. This study advances the analysis by examining purchasing power from a quantitative perspective and comparing it with regulatory frameworks. The novelty of this research lies in its focus on location, object, and method of analysis.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Research methods</title>
      <p>This research employs a mixed-methods approach, integrating quantitative and qualitative analyses. Primary data were collected through a survey using a questionnaire instrument, employing a random purposive sampling method. The respondents were individuals from the Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro regencies who use water transportation, with a total of 100 participants. The survey was conducted at three port locations Amurang, Bitung, and Likupang in May 2024, as well as at the ports of Bitung, Pananaru, Melonguane, and Minangga between November and December 2024. The sample size was determined using the Slovin formula with a 10\% margin of error, balancing the feasibility of the study with the need for representative data given the geographically dispersed population of 3TP water transportation users.</p><p>Additional primary data were obtained through focus group discussions (FGDs) with relevant stakeholders. Respondents for the FGDs were selected using purposive sampling, targeting representatives from the Ministry of Transportation, local governments, and ship operators with managerial and operational authority [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>]. This approach reduces potential bias while recognizing the limitations inherent in fieldwork in remote areas. From the survey results, the Ability-to-Pay/Willingness-to-Pay (ATP-WTP) calculation will be based on the Travel Cost Method. This analytical option is particularly relevant for assessing purchasing power in this context as it links actual travel behaviour to spending patterns, avoiding the hypothetical bias common in stated-preference methods.</p><p>Secondary data included information on transportation production, hinterland connectivity, water transportation routes, tariffs, and related regulations. These data were sourced from official entities such as regulators, operators, and statistical agencies.</p><p>The analysis began by identifying hinterland aspects with connectivity as the main indicator—measured by the availability of routes and vessels linking respondents' trip origins and destinations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>]. Port and hinterland selection focused on representativeness of capital islands and outermost islands in each district: Tahuna Sea Port and Pananaru Ferry Port for Sangihe Regency’s capital island; Kawaluso Port and Marore Port for its outermost islands; Melonguane Sea Port and Ferry Port for Talaud Regency’s capital island; Marampit and Miangas Ports for its outermost islands; Siau Port for Sitaro Regency’s capital island; and Makalehi Port for its outermost island.</p><p>Two parallel analyses were conducted:</p><p><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m0d4uq2l7j">
    <mml:mo>∙</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> A qualitative review of regulations comparing the Minister of Transportation Regulations PM 55/2019 (pioneer sea tariffs) and PM 66/2019 (pioneer ferry tariffs), supplemented by FGD findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>].</p><p><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m2io2syjuo">
    <mml:mo>∙</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> An ATP-WTP analysis using the Travel Cost Method to assess purchasing power for water transportation services. Indicators included travel purpose, income, expenditure, and travel frequency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>]. The integration of these analyses provides a comprehensive understanding of community purchasing power for water transportation services, which can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Research framework</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_RYg19ccJ2rHYe4OI.png"/>
        </fig>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Analysis and discussion</title>
      <p>The Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro Island Regencies are among Indonesia’s outermost, and most remote border areas. Their geographical features, population demographics, and the potential for plantation production are detailed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>. These regions include 12 small outer islands in North Sulawesi: Bongkil, Mantehage, Makalehi, Kawaluso, Kawio, Marore, Batuwaikang, Miangas, Marampit, Intata, Kakorotan, Kabaruan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>].</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Regional geography, population GRDP of plantation products</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Regency</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="2" colwidth="135"><p>Islands</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Area</p><p>(km<mml:math id="myqfgyukcm">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math>)</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Road</p><p>(km)</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>District:</p><p>Village</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Population</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>GRDP</p></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1" colwidth="115,98,106"><p>Plantation Production (Ton)</p></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(Billions)</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>Coconut</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="98"><p>Cloves</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="106"><p>Nutmeg</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sangihe</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="135"><p>137:28</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>597.260</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>779.750</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15:22:145</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>141,980</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.559</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>24,081.43</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="98"><p>668.05</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="106"><p>1,104.42</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Talaut</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="135"><p>16:8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1,012.140</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>447.475</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>19:11:142</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>97,310</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.843</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>19,575.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="98"><p>24.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="106"><p>4,318.00</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sitaro</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="135"><p>55:10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>217.287</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>281.099</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10:10:83</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>73,400</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.862</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="115"><p>2,975.16</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="98"><p>-</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="106"><p>3,126.85</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Within the Sangihe Islands Regency, the districts of Tahuna, Tahuna Timur, and Tahuna Barat (Outside Lokpri) have been designated as National Strategic Activity Centers (NSAC) for maritime activities. These locations are part of priority growth corridors outlined in Indonesia's National Medium-Term Development Plan for 2020–2024. Specific priority areas include six locations in the Sangihe Islands (North Tabukan, Nusa Tabukan, Kendahe, Tahuna, East Tahuna, and Marore Islands), five locations in the Talaud Islands (Nanusa, Kabaruan, Melonguane, Damau, and Miangas), and one location in the Sitaro Islands (West Siau) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>].</p><p>In 2023, the HDI and the Gini Ratio (a measure of economic inequality) for the Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro regions were below Indonesia’s national averages. The HDI scores were as follows: Indonesia (74.39), North Sulawesi (75.04), Sangihe (73.94), Talaud (72.22), and Sitaro (70.81). The Gini Ratios were: Indonesia (0.313), North Sulawesi (0.345), Sangihe (0.356), Talaud (0.339), and Sitaro (0.366) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>].</p><p>Water transportation is the primary mode of transport between islands and the mainland in North Sulawesi for these regions. According to the National Port Master Plan (2017–2032), 70 seaports and ferry ports are planned for development by 2032. Currently, operational ports include: Sangihe (sea port 12, ferry port 3), Talaut (sea port 11, ferry port 3), Sitaro (sea port 6, ferry port 3), Port development plans: Sangihe (sea port 9, ferry port 7), Talaut (sea port 3, ferry port 5), Sitaro (sea port 3, ferry port 30) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">44</xref>].</p><p>In 2014, the government launched pioneering and sea toll services to enhance connectivity for the Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro Islands. These services included five pioneer ships with base ports in Bitung (R-35, R-36) and Tahuna (R-37, R-38). Direct routes from mainland Sulawesi were established, such as Likupang-Tagulandang (R-35) and Likupang-Biaro (R-36), with plans for 12 trips annually.</p><p>Additionally, six Ro-Ro (Roll-on/Roll-off) passenger pioneer ships were introduced to serve the following routes: Amurang-Pananaru, Bitung-Tagulandang, Likupang-Biaro, Likupang-Pananaru, Likupang-Melonguane, Tanjung Perak-Makasar-Tahuna-Tanjung Perak Sea Toll. For remote and outermost areas served by sea pioneers and Ro-Ro passengers: Makalehi, Kawaluso, Marore, Marampit, and Miangas. Details of the provision of pioneer subsidies by the Ministry of Transportation, commercial transportation, and island services can be seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref>.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_2">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Subsidy provision of pioneer sea transportation</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Home Base</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Route</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bitung R-35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 917,47; Round Voy: 12 days; Target/year: 30 freq; Vessel: KM. Sabuk Nusantara 69;</p><p>Bitung-(55)-Likupang-(55)-Tagulandang-(59)-Para-(26)-Ngalipaeng-(33,8)-Petta-(95)-Damau-(15)-Lirung-(51)-Gemeh-(27)-Kakorotan-(7,67)-Karatung-(3)-Dampulis-(64)-Miangas-(108)-Melonguane-(19)-Damau-(120)-Tahuna-(28)-Kalama-(41)-Makalehi-(110)-Bitung</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bitung R-36</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 383,18; Round Voy: 8 days; Target/year: 45 freq; Vessel: KM. Sabuk Nusantara 70;</p><p>Bitung-(55)-Likupang-38)-Biaro-(19)-Tagulandang-(32)-Buhias-(4)-Sawang-(4)-UluSiau-(32)-Makalehi-(14,8)-Pehe-(25)-Para(29)-UluSiau-(4,78)-Buhias-(32)-Tagulandang-(19)-Biaro-(74)-Bitung</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tahuna R-37</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 241,78; Round Voy: 7 days; Target/year: 52 freq; Vessel: KM. Sabuk Nusantara 95;</p><p>Tahuna-(26,)-Peta-(9.5)-Bukide-(16,2)-Lipang-(19,4)-Kawaluso-(26)-Matutuang-(21)-Kawio-(5,14)-Marore-(5,14)-Kawio-(21)-Matutuang(-26)-Kawaluso-(19,4)-Lipang-(21)-Petta-(26)-Tahuna</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tahuna R-38</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 840,98; Round Voy: 11 days; Target/year: 33 freq; Vessel: KM. Sabuk Nusantara 109;</p><p>Tahuna-(119)-Mangaran-(8,32)-Lirung(4)-Melonguane-(41)-Dapalan-(25,30)-Kakorotan(7,67)-Karatung-(3)-Marampit-(69,6)-Miangas-(69,6)-Marampit-(3)-Karatung-(7,67)-Kakorotan-(40)-Esang-(23)-Beo-(19,5)-Melonguane-(4)-Lirung(8,32)-Mangaran-(212)-Bitung-(176)-Tahuna</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tahuna R-39</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 551,08; Round Voy: 8 days; Target/year: 45 freq; Vessel: KM. Kanon Moon;</p><p>Tahuna-(28)-Lipang-(19,4)-Kawaluso-(26)-Matutuang-(21)-Kawio-(5,17)-Marore-(5,14)-Kawio-(21)-Matutuang-(26)-Kawaluso-(19,4)-Lipang-(28)-Tahuna-(176)-Bitung-(176)-Tahuna</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tanjung Perak H-1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 2286; Round Voy: 30 days; Target/year: 12 freq; Vessel: KM logistik nusantara 2;</p><p>TanjungPerak-(438)-Makasar-(766)-Tahuna-(1082)-TanjungPerak</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_3">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Subsidy provision of pioneer crossing transportation</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Home Base</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cross</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Bitung P-01</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 264; Round Trip: 3 days; Target/year: 22 freq; Vessel: KMP. Lokong Banua;</p><p>Bitung-(60)-Tagulandang-(36)-Buhias-(6)-Siau-(60)-Pananaru-(60)-Siau-(6)-Buhias-(36)-Bitung</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 204; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 88 freq; Vessel: KMP. Lokong Banua;</p><p>Bitung-(60)-Tagulandang-(36)-Buhias-(6)-Siau-(6)-Buhias-(36)-Tagulandang-(60)-Bitung</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bitung P-02</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 472; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 88 freq; Vessel: KMP. Bawal;</p><p>Bitung-(212)-Mangaran-(20)-Musi-(4)-Melonguane(4)-Musi-(20)-Mangaran-(212)-Bitung</p><p>Note: Bitung-Mangaran (layanan komersial), Mangaran-Musi dan Musi-Melonguane (Perintis)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Likupang P-03</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 705; Round Trip: 3 days; Target/year: 22 freq; Vessel: KMP. Watunapato;</p><p>Likupang-(209)-Melonguane-(67,5)-Marampit-(62,1)-Miangas-(62,1)-Marampit-(67,5)-Melonguane-(209)-Likupang</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 418; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 88 freq; Vessel: KMP. Watunapato;</p><p>Likupang-(209)-Melonguane-(209)-Likupang</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Likupang P-04</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 418; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 18 freq; Vessel: KMP. Tarusi;</p><p>Likupang-(117)-Pananaru-(92)-Melonguane-(92)-Pananaru-(117)-Likupang</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 314; Round Trip: 1 day; Target/year: 83 freq; Vessel: KMP. Tarusi;</p><p>Likupang-(117)-Pananaru-(117)-Likupang</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Likupang P-05</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 209; Round Trip: 3 days; Target/year: 83 freq; Vessel: KMP. Lohoraung;</p><p>Likupang-(43)-Biaro-(25)-Tagulandang-(24)-Makalehi-(22)-UluSiau-(22)-Makalehi-(24)-Tagulandang-(24)-Biaro(25)-Likupang</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Amurang P-06</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 520; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 22 freq; Vessel: KMP. Porodisa;</p><p>Amurang-(160)-Pananaru-(60)-Kawaluso-(40)-Marore-(40)-Kawaluso-(60)-Pananaru-(160)-Amurang</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_4">
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Commercial sea and crossing transportation</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Home Base</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cross</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Manado M-01</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 276; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 145 freq; Vessel: KM. Mercy Teratai;</p><p>Mile: 276; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 47 freq; Vessel: KM. Saint Mary;</p><p>Manado-(138)-Tahuna-(138)-Manado</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Manado M-02</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 260,8; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 39 freq; Vessel: KM. Saint Mary;</p><p>Manado-(85,4)-Siau-(55)-Tahuna-(55)-Siau(85,4)-Manado</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Manado M-03</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 177,8; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 116 freq; Vessel: KM. Glory Mary;</p><p>Mile: 177,8; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 52 freq; Vessel: KM. Marina Bay I;</p><p>Manado-(62,9)-Tagulandang-(26)-Siau-(26)-Tagulandang-(62,9)-Manado</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Manado M-04</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 420,74; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 76 freq; Vessel: KM. Gregorius;</p><p>Mile: 420,74; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 78 freq; Vessel: KM. Barcelona VA;</p><p>Manado-(190,8)-Lirung-(2,8)-Melonguane-(16,77)-Beo-(16,77)-Melonguane-(2,8)-Lirung-(190,8)-Manado</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Manado M-05</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 188,8; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 82 freq; Vessel: KM. Marina Bay I;</p><p>Manado-(52,9)-Biaro-(15,5)-Tagulandang-(26)-Siau-(26)-Tagulandang-(15,5)-Biaro-(52,9)-Manado</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Manado M-06</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 267,8; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 112 freq; Vessel: KM. Espress Bahari 2E;</p><p>Manado-(52,9)-Tagulandang-(26)-Siau-(55)-Tahuna-(55)-Siau-(26)-Tagulandang-(52,9)-Manado</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bitung P-02</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 212; Round Trip: 2 days; Target/year: 88 freg; Vessel: KMP. Bawal;</p><p>Bitung-(188)-Mangaran-(20)-Musi-(4)-Melonguane-(4)-Musi-(20)-Mangaran-(188)-Bitung</p><p>Note: Bitung-Mangaran (Commercial services), Mangaran-Musi and Musi-Melonguane (Pionerers)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bitung P-07</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mile: 212; Round Trip: 3 days; Target/year: freg; Vessel: KMP. Labuhan Haji;</p><p>Bitung-(212)-Melonguane-(212)-Bitung</p><p>Note; Serving January to June 2024</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_5">
          <label>Table 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Commercial sea and crossing transportation</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>District/Island</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Area</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Population</p></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1"><p>Port</p></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1"><p>Freq (2024)</p></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(Km<mml:math id="mmfofp8t2m">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math>)</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(2023)</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>RoRo</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sea</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sum</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>RoRo</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sea</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sum</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="9" rowspan="1"><p>Sangihe</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kalama</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8.67</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>886</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>30</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>30</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kawaluso</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>670</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>44</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>194</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>238</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kawio</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.41</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>504</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>194</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>194</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lipang</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>357</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>194</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>194</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Nusa</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8.66</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.445</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>52</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>52</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Marore</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.50</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>716</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>97</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>119</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Matutuang</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.31</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>443</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>194</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>194</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Para</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.37</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.338</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>75</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>75</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sangihe</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>na</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>185</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>499</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>684</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" rowspan="1"><p>Sitaro</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Biaro</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>19.19</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.388</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>166</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>90</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>256</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Gunatin</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.38</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.232</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>90</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>90</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Makalehi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9.75</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.185</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>166</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>75</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>241</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Siau</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>140.11</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>30.420</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>215</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>180</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>395</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tagulandang</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>53.22</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>20.986</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>364</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>120</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>484</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" rowspan="1"><p>Talaud</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kabaruan</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>94.63</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10.847</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>176</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>126</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>302</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kakorotan</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.71</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>666</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>96</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>96</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Karalelang</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>801.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>60.544</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>220</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>195</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>415</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Karatung</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7.43</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.221</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>96</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>96</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Marampit</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12.75</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.605</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>44</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>96</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>140</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Miangas</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.39</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>811</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>63</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>85</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Salibabu</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>99.36</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>20.431</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>194</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>96</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>290</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Main Sulawesi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>514</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>303</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>817</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>R-35 connects mainland Sulawesi: 3 islands in Sitaro, Sangihe island, 7 islands in Talaut, R-36 connects mainland Sulawesi: 6 islands in Sitaro, R-37 specifically serves 7 islands in Sangihe, R-37 connects Tahuna on Sangihe island with 9 islands in Talaut and with mainland Sulawesi, R-39 connects mainland Sulawesi with 6 islands in Sangihe. P-01 connects mainland Sulawesi: 4 islands in Sitaro, P-02 serves mainland Sulawesi: to 2 islands in Talaut, P-03 serves mainland Sulawesi to 5 islands in Talaut, P-04 serves mainland Sulawesi to Sangihe Island and Karakelang Island, P-05 serves mainland Sulawesi: 4 islands in Sitaro, P-06 serves Sulawesi mainland to 3 islands in Sangihe.</p><p>R-36, P-01 and P-05 serve mainland Sulawesi to the Sitaro islands, R-35, R-38, P-02 and P-03 serve mainland Sulawesi to the Talaut islands, R-39 and P-06 serve mainland Sulawesi to the Sangihe islands.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>, there are similar services on the island for the region: Sangihe (Sangihe, Kalawaluso, Marore), Sitaro (Biaro, Gunatin, Makalehi, Siau, Tagulandang), Talaut (Kabaruan, Karakelang, Marampit, Miangas, Salibabu). This condition is interesting if discussed from different perspectives: bottom-up and top-down.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_2">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Route network of (a) sea transportation pioneer and (b) ferry crossing pioneer</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_RP15i_cQhc0wyzA3.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_Vwf8EVOeZII-LHkx.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>This research adopts a top-down perspective, employing a series of quantitative and qualitative analysis processes to examine the government's role as a regulator responsible for providing transportation services in the island districts of Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro. Quantitative analysis was conducted to calculate the connectivity ratio of sea, and inland waterway transportation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>]. The analysis revealed that the overall connectivity value for Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro is 69.16, indicating that transportation in this region is predominantly reliant on water-based systems. In contrast, land transportation connectivity remains very limited. Public land transport services, such as liner routes, are sparse and concentrated mainly in regency capitals like Tahuna (Sangihe), Melonguane (Talaud), and Ulu Siau (Sitaro). These services cater only to internal island needs, with no land transport routes connecting islands via ferry crossings.</p><p>Sea transportation and ferry crossings are the primary contributors to the connectivity ratio. These networks not only facilitate intra-island connections within each district but also link the three districts Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro with mainland North Sulawesi (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>). Supporting research highlights the critical role of port connectivity in eastern Indonesia, including North Sulawesi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>]. A key node in this connectivity network is Bitung Port, which serves as a bridge between western Indonesia (the national economic hub) and eastern Indonesia, which includes underdeveloped areas classified as 3TP (frontier, outermost, and underdeveloped regions). Bitung Port's potential is underscored by its designation as a sea port capable of supporting both commercial and pioneer routes, as outlined in the National Port Master Plan (RIPN). Additionally, Likupang and Amurang Ports connect mainland North Sulawesi with Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_3">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison of passenger productivity</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_eOoTpT-Zwzg2cScb.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>Bitung Port has an extensive network linking North Sulawesi trade to regions like Jakarta, East Java, and North Maluku. This trade connectivity is further bolstered by government initiatives such as the Sea Toll Program, which uses ports like Bitung (mainland North Sulawesi), Tahuna (Sangihe), Melonguane (Talaud), and Ulu Siau (Sitaro) as hubs or sub-hubs. These hubs feed into other 3TP areas through pioneering sea transportation and crossings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]. The provision of similar services such as sea transportation, ferry crossings, and commercial operations at ports directly impacts the market share for passenger transport. Pioneer sea vessels typically utilize coaster-type ships for transporting passengers and general cargo, while pioneer ferry vessels employ Ro-Ro ferries designed to carry passengers, vehicles, and cargo. The overlap in functionality between these two types of vessels, both serving the same geographic areas, leads to direct competition between the government’s two water transportation programs. This competition is evaluated using performance indicators such as passenger transport production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">47</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">48</xref>].</p><p>A comparison of passenger transport production between sea pioneer and ferry crossing pioneer (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>) shows that cumulatively sea pioneer transport carries more passengers than ferry crossing with the greatest productivity on the capital island in Tahuna and Melonguane, for access to the outermost island in Sangihe and Talaud is also still dominant using sea pioneer. On the other hand, in Sitaro regency, ferry crossing pioneer transportation has the highest passenger transportation productivity compared to sea pioneer, including when compared to the other two regencies.</p><p>The government and local governments play a crucial role in the pioneer transportation sector, not only by providing facilities, infrastructure, and route networks but also by determining service tariffs. Although both sea pioneer services and ferry crossing pioneer services fall under the category of water transportation, their tariff formulations are governed by distinct regulations.</p><p>The tariff for sea pioneer services is determined based on PM 55/2019 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>], while the tariff for ferry crossing pioneer services is regulated under PM 66/2019 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">50</xref>]. Both frameworks share a general similarity in that tariffs are calculated based on ship operating cost components. However, specific differences in these regulations influence operational characteristics and result in varying tariffs applicable to each route. Comparison of regulations can be seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref>. The bottom-up perspective discusses the utilization of water transport based on the consumer perspective. The analysis phase begins with identifying the travel patterns of the community, based on the water transportation production data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> can be made tables and origin-destination matrix images that identify inter-regional travel patterns between Sangihe, Talaud, Sitaro, and Mainland North Sulawesi.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_6">
          <label>Table 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison of regulation</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>No.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Primary Aspect</p></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Manager</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PM 55 2019, Sea Pioneer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PM 66 2019, Ferry Crossing Pioneer</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Tariff type</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article 3, paragraph 1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article 2</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Passengers and Goods</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Passengers (Infants, Adults), Passenger Vehicles, Goods Vehicles and their cargo based on vehicle dimensions (Vehicle Classes)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article 4, paragraph 1</p><p>Menteri</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article 3, paragraph 2</p><p>Tariff Determination: Minister, Governor, Mayor/Regent</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="6"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="6"><p>Cost and income components</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article 3, paragraph 1 and Annex point 3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article 17, outlined in Annex II</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The cost component is based on the operating costs of the ship and continued by considering the aspects of achieving the performance of each route as measured by the level of occupancy of the use of passenger space and loading of goods (cluster load factor in a range of varying values) in the previous year and given public service compensation with a fixed value of 10% of the cost.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The cost components are based</p><p>on vessel operating costs and combined with Unit Production (UP) at a 60% load factor, which is fixed. Not taking into account compensation for public service costs in the form of profit margins</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article 4, paragraph 2, 3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article 16, described by type and unit in Annex I</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The units for calculating passengers and cargo use the number of passengers and the weight/volume of cargo (kg, tons and m3). The stowage factor on pioneer sea vessels does not take into account the type of vehicle cargo.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tariffs for passengers, passenger vehicles and goods vehicles and their loads are calculated based on fix production units, pioneer ferry ships do not yet take into account the type of tariff for general cargo loads (not loaded in vehicles)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article 2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Article 6</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Taking into account the cost of cargo safety insurance</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cargo safety insurance costs, placed separately outside the tariff</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>The analysis results indicate that people's travel destinations are generally motivated by family matters, business (trade), tourism, education, and health purposes. Similar patterns have been observed in previous research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_52">52</xref>]. Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro are administrative regions that form distinct service clusters, each with its own economic centers, government services, education facilities, and healthcare infrastructure. The population in these districts, spread across numerous small islands, predominantly travels to their respective district capitals to meet these needs. This is evident from the high volume of passenger, goods, and vehicle transportation at key ports such as Tahuna and Pananaru in Sangihe, Melonguane in Talaud, and Ulu Siau in Sitaro.</p><p>However, the increasingly complex community needs for goods and services cannot be fully met within the district capitals. The economic disparities and differences in service quality between the district capitals of Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro and the mainland of North Sulawesi (the provincial capital) drive additional travel from these island regions to the mainland. The mainland offers a broader range of goods, services, and public amenities. Consequently, travel volumes to the mainland surpass internal movements between these three districts (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>).</p><p>Sangihe holds a strategic position within this travel pattern. Beyond serving as an economic and public service hub for its local population, it also functions as a transshipment point for economic activities in Talaud. This strategic role is reinforced by historical factors: the three districts were once unified as the Sangihe-Talaud district. Initially, transportation accessibility and development activities such as economic infrastructure and public services were concentrated in Tahuna (Sangihe Island). As a result, community movemHistorical factors reinforce this strategic roleents were predominantly centered around this area. Following administrative divisions in 2002 (separating Talaud) and 2007 (establishing Sitaro), new patterns emerged.</p><p>Talaud Regency has direct connectivity with the mainland; however, limited vessel capacity and frequency result in lower trip volumes. In contrast, Sitaro's proximity to the mainland makes it a primary destination for its residents. Few residents of Sitaro travel to Sangihe or Talaud except for short trips related to family matters. The phrase “trade follows the ship” aptly describes travel patterns in this region. Pioneer water transportation remains crucial but heavily depends on government-regulated shipping schedules. Despite this dependence, the availability of alternative water transport options allows communities to choose their travel activities based on factors such as mode type or cost.</p><p>The ATP-WTP analysis that provides this overview is then combined with the origin-destination movement patterns with the following results (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_4">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>ATP-WTP passengers (a) and vehicles (b)</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_xeXSrAA4vJZ-vhP7.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_rdkDkGo48FYghBcy.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>The analysis of ATP and WTP, considering community income, travel frequency, and the allocation of maritime transportation costs, reveals two distinct characteristics (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>). Trucks are transported using Ro-Ro vessels exclusively served by pioneer ferry crossings, while passengers are served by two types of vessels: Ro-Ro vessels on pioneer ferry crossings and coaster ships on sea pioneer services.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_5">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>ATP-WTP based on origin-destination for (a) passengers and (b) vehicles</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_cQ0WyRm94fRv77Qg.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_p5mIsJnLyaMMQvzY.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <fig id="fig_6">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison between passenger tariff and ATP-WTP</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_Yc022jut0947qshS.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>The ATP-WTP analysis for logistic truck cargo indicates that ATP is lower than WTP, suggesting that consumers in this cluster are willing to pay more for improved services. Survey results identify a general need for faster Ro-Ro vessel services compared to the current average speed of 7–9 knots. This speed is considered slow by users transporting fishery products from islands to the mainland. The demand for faster vessels aligns with cold supply chain support, such as providing electrical plugs for reefer trucks.</p><p>Limited vessel facilities affect the marketing of fishery products, requiring users to wait for direct route schedules to ports like Amurang, Bitung, and Likupang on the mainland. This issue is compounded by inadequate fish product packaging, which relies on ice cubes for voyages lasting 6–15 hours. To avoid transshipment routes involving multiple ports, users prefer direct routes.</p><p>Currently, the Nusantara Logistics ship under the Sea Toll program operates on H-1 and T-5 routes but has limited capacity, carrying only five TEUs of reefer containers per trip. These containers must serve multiple ports, leaving only 1–2 TEUs available per port per trip. This aligns with previous research indicating that Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro are major fishery producers in North Sulawesi but face marketing challenges in other regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">53</xref>]. For truck cargo (categories 5 and 6), ATP-WTP values cannot fully justify public purchasing power for Ro-Ro services as most cargo belongs to private companies. However, the analysis shows respondents in this cluster are willing to pay more than current fares for better services. This scientifically demonstrates a general trend where WTP exceeds ATP.</p><p>ATP-WTP analysis on passengers also shows that ATP is lower than WTP. This indicates that passengers are also willing to pay more than the available ticket, in the hope of improving facilities such as speed, safety, comfort and other facilities such as those that already exist in coaster ships on sea pioneer services.</p><p>The comparison of ATP and WTP with passenger transportation fares was conducted by selecting routes considered geographically representative of each district and connecting them to the mainland (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>). The available route network primarily facilitates access through direct routes from the mainland to the capital, while outermost regions must rely on multiport route patterns. Limited direct accessibility impacts transportation costs per trip. For round trips, fares are assumed to double, but ATP-WTP values remain constant.</p><p>The fare regulation (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref>) results in different outputs for applicable tariffs. Maritime pioneer fares follow a round multiport pattern, where vessels rotate through several ports and either return directly to their home base or minimize stopovers on the return journey (e.g., A–B–C–D–E–A or A–B–C–D–E–C–A). This regulation uses a fixed distance matrix between ports to determine fares, resulting in consistent pricing. On the other hand, the fare formulation for ferry crossing pioneers also uses fixed crossing distances. However, due to limited vessel availability, ferries often serve multiple connected crossings sequentially (e.g., AB–BC–CD–DE–ED–DC–CB–BA).</p><p>This sequential route structure means passengers pay based on the number of crossings traveled. For origin-destination trips requiring only one trajectory (e.g., mainland-capital island), fares remain reasonable for both one-way and round trips. However, as the number of crossings increases, cumulative fares become costly, particularly for outermost regions.</p><p>The direct consequence of the applicable fares on ATP and WTP is the frequency of passenger trips. Residents on the capital island, with access to similarly priced ferry crossing pioneer and sea pioneer services, can typically afford two round trips per month. In contrast, residents of outermost islands can only afford an average of one round trip per month using ferry crossings. Despite the lower cost of sea pioneer services, which are preferred for up to two round trips per month, residents in outermost areas primarily opt for sea pioneer services.</p><p>This analysis aligns with other studies indicating that travel frequency occurs within the limits of affordable pricing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">54</xref>]. Geographically, high costs relative to ATP-WTP are most prevalent among passengers from the outermost clusters in Sangihe and Talaud. Sitaro, being closer to the mainland, offers more transportation options. For trips originating from the mainland, Sitaro islands are often the first stop for ferry crossings and sea pioneer ships serving Talaud. Consequently, fares for residents in Sitaro remain low. Conversely, when traveling from Sitaro to the mainland, passengers can choose between ferry crossing and sea pioneer services returning from the capital and outermost areas like Talaud to their home ports in Bitung and Likupang (mainland).</p><p>Cumulatively, this scenario reflects passenger transportation productivity data showing a preference for sea pioneer services in Sangihe and Talaud, while ferry crossing pioneers are favored in Sitaro (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>). Regarding logistics distribution, local conditions mirror comparisons with other countries. Sea transportation using Lo-Lo (lift-on/lift-off) systems is more cost-efficient than Ro-Ro systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_55">55</xref>]. Inter-island trade logistics are predominantly handled by MSMEs (micro, small, and medium enterprises) across Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro. These MSMEs typically transport mixed general cargo from the mainland to the outermost islands in relatively small quantities (less than 1 ton per month), favoring sea pioneer services with fixed rates based on origin-destination distances between ports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">56</xref>]. However, maritime transport data also show general cargo exceeding one-ton capacity, particularly for construction materials.</p><p>On the other hand, Ro-Ro ferry crossings lack a formulated tariff system for cargo. In logistics scenarios involving trucks on Ro-Ro vessels traveling between multiple ports from the mainland to outermost regions or vice versa, cumulative costs are significantly higher than Lo-Lo systems. Overall, Sea Pioneer services offer cheaper passenger fares but entail longer round-trip durations due to routes serving 13–20 ports per voyage. This makes them less suitable for urgent travel needs, such as transporting perishable goods like fishery products or emergency healthcare travel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_57">57</xref>]. Meanwhile, ferry crossing pioneers provide shorter round-trip durations serving up to five ports per route but at higher cumulative costs.</p><p>Cost efficiency is the primary preference for water transportation services in 3TP (Frontier, Outermost, and Underdeveloped) regions and must be balanced with effective route selection. For route effectiveness, residents in the outermost areas of Sangihe and Talaud typically choose intermodal transshipment routes. From smaller islands, they prioritize sea pioneer ship schedules heading to Tahuna and Melonguane (the capitals), where they then switch to ferry crossing pioneer services that connect directly to the mainland via alternative ports such as Bitung, Likupang, and Amurang, or vice versa.</p><p>The direct connectivity between sea pioneer and ferry crossing pioneer routes in Sangihe and Talaud remains partial. The differing locations of maritime ports and ferry terminals result in additional movement and transshipment costs. For example, the distance between Tahuna's maritime port and Pananaru ferry terminal in Sangihe is approximately 38 km by land, while Melonguane’s maritime port and ferry terminal in Talaud are relatively close at just 1 km apart. These transshipment journeys can incur extra accommodation costs if sea pioneer and ferry crossing schedules are not synchronized. Transshipment costs for passenger and cargo movements are an additional finding of this research that has not yet been comprehensively analyzed.</p><p>The development of ports across Indonesia, including on the islands of Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro, remains partial and fragmented within the bureaucracy of government agencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_58">58</xref>]. Port infrastructure development is managed by two separate units within the Ministry of Transportation: seaports are developed by the Directorate General of Sea Transportation (DJPL), while ferry ports are developed by the Directorate General of Land Transportation (DJPD). A regulatory framework is needed to bridge this bureaucratic gap. As stated in the RIPN, many ports are classified as "seaports serving ferry transportation." In this study, such ports include Amurang, Melonguane, Pananaru, Marore, Likupang, Bitung, Marampit, Miangas, Kawaluso, and Siau. Tahuna Port is classified solely as a seaport under this regulation.</p><p>The designation of "seaports serving ferry transportation" aims not only to integrate Lo-Lo (lift-on/lift-off) and Ro-Ro systems within a single port area but also to optimize government budgets for port development. Currently, inefficiencies arise because seaports and ferry ports are often constructed in close proximity on the same small islands and serve the same hinterland market (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>). These inefficiencies are particularly evident when comparing the construction of main facilities like wharves and supporting facilities like yards, which are nearly identical. The only significant difference is the addition of mooring dolphins and/or breasting dolphins as berthing facilities at ferry ports.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_7">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Sea port and ferry port in Miangas, Marore, and Kawaluso island</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_1iO02dBWNOPZ-u5K.png"/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/0/img_A2daIZvEj3UjS4xe.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>The overall conditions described indicate that seamless multimodal transshipment is not fully implemented in this region. The ATP-WTP analysis and data interpretation in this study align with several previous research aspects. ATP-WTP serves as an indicator influencing passenger movement and logistics distribution, impacting efforts to provide effective and efficient transportation services in the North Sulawesi archipelago. However, numerous challenges and barriers remain, including aspects of delivery characteristics, interoperability, multimodal freight transport terminals, multimodal freight transport networks, management, regulations, and subsidies.</p><p>The identification of travel characteristics analyzed in the previous section provides a lot of information that can be used as a consideration in government programs for regional development and development. The results of the analysis also show compatibility with some general theories of regional development. In the Sangihe, Talaud and Sitaro districts, which are archipelagic regions, it can be identified that the center of economic growth is on the capital island, which is in accordance with the conditions described in the growth pole theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_59">59</xref>].</p><p>The prioritization of the development of government service facilities, business and economic areas is only on the islands of Tahuna (Sangihe), Melonguenae (Talaud), and Ulu Siau (Sitaro) while facilities on the outer islands are still relatively minimal.</p><p>On the other hand, in the context of regional interaction theory, the gravity model adapted by Reilly states that inter-regional interactions are influenced by factors such as socioeconomic conditions, education levels, livelihoods, and transportation infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_60">60</xref>].</p><p>Although Sangihe, Talaud and Sitaro are island districts that have their own development centers but still have a large dependency on the mainland, the survey results show that the dominant movement of island communities still leads to the mainland for trade, education and health services. This condition shows that there is still a gap in the availability of services, quality of services, or completeness of facilities between the islands and the mainland. This gap causes a reciprocal regional dependency between the islands and the mainland, especially in the fields of industry and trade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_61">61</xref>].</p><p>Manado city in the mainland is the center of trade in North Sulawesi which has connections and interactions with other regions such as Java which is the center of the national economy including in cargo distribution so that it can become a transhipment point that bridges trade from the archipelago with the national economic center [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_62">62</xref>].</p><p>Regional development can also arise in the form of regional expansion, looking at the recent discourse on the formation of Nusa Raya province which will separate the districts of Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro from the administrative area of North Sulawesi province.</p><p>Although political in nature, this policy needs to pay attention to the results of academic studies, and based on transportation patterns, the connectivity of the islands and mainland areas is still dominant using water transportation so that in the future the route pattern is expected to remain the same as the existing conditions, including travel motives and mode selection. The ideal regional development option carried out by the current government is the construction of adequate health and education service facilities on the outer island.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Conclusion and recommendation</title>
      <p>The archipelagic regions of Sangihe, Talaud, and Sitaro continue to face economic disparities compared to mainland North Sulawesi. Subsidized sea transport and ferry services play a crucial role in improving accessibility, but challenges remain in cost efficiency, route integration, and service schedules.</p><p>This study quantitatively analyzed ATP and WTP for water transportation services. Findings indicate that ATP is lower than WTP for passengers and freight transport. A comparison of ATP-WTP values with government-regulated fares highlights inconsistencies affecting consumer travel preferences. The lack of synchronization between bottom-up demand for cost-efficient transport and top-down regulatory frameworks has resulted in suboptimal service integration. Multimodal transshipment could be a solution, but faces geographic and regulatory barriers.</p><p>To overcome these challenges, fare regulations need to be harmonized, transport routes and schedules optimized, and integrated ports developed to streamline sea and ferry services. Enhancing infrastructure and public services, particularly healthcare, would reduce dependency on mainland travel.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors would like to thank the Director General of Sea Transportation, Director General of Land Transportation, local government, port authorities, ship operators, respondents, Pusaran Team, and all parties who help us in data collection, analysis, and some warm discussion.</p>
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>Conceptualization: S.H., M.Y.J., J.J., and M.Y.S.; methodology: S.H., M.Y.J., J.J., and M.Y.S.; software: S.H., data curation; S.H., writing—original draft preparation; S.H., writing—review and editing: M.Y.J., J.J., and M.Y.S., visualization: S.H, supervision: M.Y.J., J.J., and M.Y.S., project administration, S.H. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>165-181</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rianawati</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Darmasetiawan</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hadi</surname>
              <given-names>F. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oktavianus</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Utama</surname>
              <given-names>C. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21511/ppm.22(2).2024.14</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enhancement of Indonesia's blue economy sector through innovation and competitive advantage based on resource-based view theory</article-title>
          <source>Probl. Perspect. Manage.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>57-74</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sandy</surname>
              <given-names>D. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhanwani</surname>
              <given-names>N. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arma</surname>
              <given-names>A. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yusuf</surname>
              <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anshori</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bagagasyah</surname>
              <given-names>S. K. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Destrianto</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rachmadiena</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Budiansyah</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khoir et al.</surname>
              <given-names>M. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Potensi tinggalan arkeologi dan pariwisata di Kepulauan Sangihe, Provinsi Sulawesi Utara</article-title>
          <source>Nadit. Widya</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Limpele</surname>
              <given-names>P. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawung</surname>
              <given-names>G. M. V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tumangkeng</surname>
              <given-names>S. Y. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pengembangan potensi ekonomi dan penetapan sektor unggulan di Provinsi Sulawesi Utara</article-title>
          <source>J. Berk. Ilm. Efisiensi</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>759</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mananeke</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Machmud</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijsdp.16041</pub-id>
          <article-title>Factors influencing tourist visit in North Sulawesi, Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Sustain. Dev. Plan.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>129-136</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Syafrie</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.53676/jism.v3i2.52</pub-id>
          <article-title>Kajian ekologis dalam kaitannya dengan aktifitas pariwisata di Taman Nasional Laut Bunaken, Provinsi Sulawesi Utara</article-title>
          <source>J. Ilm. Satya Minabahari</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Riyanti</surname>
              <given-names>Agustina</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32630/sukowati.v2i1.51</pub-id>
          <article-title>Clustering of regions in North Sulawesi Province based on socioeconomic characteristics in 2017</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Indeks Pembangunan Manusia Provinsi Sulawesi Utara 2023</article-title>
          <source>, https://sulut.bps.go.id/id/publication/2024/05/27/a024e609634ce80ebf5b40e3/indeks-pembangunan-manusia-provinsi-sulawesi-utara-2023.html</source>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Gini Ratio Menurut Kabupaten/Kota, 2025</article-title>
          <source>, https://sulut.bps.go.id/id/statistics-table/2/MjgwIzI=/gini-ratio-menurut-kabupaten-kota.html</source>
          <year>2025</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>1067-1074</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kolinung</surname>
              <given-names>F. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rompas</surname>
              <given-names>J. J. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Betrix</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.53494/jira.v10i2.719</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analisis pengeluaran pemerintah bidang kesehatan dan pendidikan terhadap Indeks Pembangunan Manusia di Provinsi Sulawesi Utara</article-title>
          <source>J. Ilm. Raflesia Akunt.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>23</volume>
          <page-range>398-415</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rorong</surname>
              <given-names>I. P. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analisis pengaruh Indeks Pembangunan Manusia terhadap pertumbuhan ekonomi dan kemiskinan di Provinsi Sulawesi Utara</article-title>
          <source>J. Pemb. Ekonom. Keu. D.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>24</volume>
          <page-range>37-48</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lahengke</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Masninambow</surname>
              <given-names>V. A. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sumual</surname>
              <given-names>J. I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analisis ketimpangan pendapatan antar kabupaten di Provinsi Sulawesi Utara</article-title>
          <source>J. Berk. Ilm. Efisiensi</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>129-138</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Halamury</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patty</surname>
              <given-names>H. W. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Delsen</surname>
              <given-names>M. S. Noya</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30598/parameterv1i2pp129-138</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analisis indeks pembangunan manusia (IPM) dengan menggunakan analisis regresi kuantil (studi Kasus Indonesia bagian timur: Maluku, Maluku Utara, Papua Barat, Papua)</article-title>
          <source>Parameter: J. Mat. Stat. Appl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>220-227</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tehupeiory</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sianipar</surname>
              <given-names>I. M. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sari</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Septiariva</surname>
              <given-names>I. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suhardono</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suryawan</surname>
              <given-names>I. W. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14710/jil.21.1.220-227</pub-id>
          <article-title>Estimasi karakteristik sosial-ekonomi wilayah dalam capaian pembangunan berkelanjutan untuk 100% akses sanitasi di Provinsi Kepulauan Riau</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>KP-DJPL 160: Amendment to the Decision of the Director General of Sea Transportation Number KP-DJPL 729 of 2023 concerning the Determination of the Route Network for the Provision of Public Services for Pioneer Sea Transportation in the 2024 Fiscal Year</article-title>
          <source>, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1t9jh0K0KveFzgvOGPwETRvogfywejqef/view?usp=sharing</source>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>KP-DJPL 639: Determination of the Route Network for the Implementation of Public Service Obligations for Maritime Freight Transportation In the 2024 Fiscal Year</article-title>
          <source>, https://legalcentric.com/content/view/190934</source>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>KP-DRJD 7330: Determination of Pioneer Crossings for Fiscal Year 2024</article-title>
          <source>, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Ex-C8aybtJ3mADZJrd5v4Tn7HaGAEej8/view?usp=sharing</source>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>4307</page-range>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lara-Pulido</surname>
              <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mojica</surname>
              <given-names>Á.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bruner</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guevara-Sanginés</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simón</surname>
              <given-names>C. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vásquez-Lavin</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>González-Baca</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Infanzón</surname>
              <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su13084307</pub-id>
          <article-title>A Business case for marine protected areas: Economic valuation of the reef attributes of Cozumel Island</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>70</volume>
          <page-range>388-399</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Valido</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Socorro</surname>
              <given-names>M. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hernández</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Betancor</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tre.2014.08.001</pub-id>
          <article-title>Air transport subsidies for resident passengers when carriers have market power</article-title>
          <source>Transp. Res. Part E: Logist. Transp. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>283-299</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Febriandika</surname>
              <given-names>N. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rahayu</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15294/jejak.v15i2.36675</pub-id>
          <article-title>The determinant factors of poverty in Eastern Indonesia: Evidence from 12 provinces</article-title>
          <source>J. Ekon. Kebij.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <page-range>268911</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baig</surname>
              <given-names>M. Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lagdami</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mejia</surname>
              <given-names>M. Q.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33175/mtr.2024.268911</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enhancing maritime safety: A comprehensive review of challenges and opportunities in the domestic ferry sector</article-title>
          <source>Marit. Technol. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>701-711</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rizaldi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muzwardi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santoso</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iffan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fera</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15549/jeecar.v10i4.1378</pub-id>
          <article-title>The strategic development of maritime connectivity in the border area in Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>J. East. Eur. Cent. Asia Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>193-197</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kelwulan</surname>
              <given-names>L. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soumokil</surname>
              <given-names>R. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manuputty</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30598/ale.6.2023.193-197</pub-id>
          <article-title>Identifikasi kendala-kendala konektivitas transportasi laut di wilayah kepulauan (studi Kasus Provinsi Maluku)</article-title>
          <source>Archipel. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>548</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Džupka</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dráb</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gróf</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Štofa</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su16020548</pub-id>
          <article-title>Exploring willingness to pay across different passenger traits</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>3475</page-range>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eichhorn</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meixner</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su12083475</pub-id>
          <article-title>Factors influencing the willingness to pay for aquaponic products in a developed food market: A structural equation modeling approach</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>12830</page-range>
          <issue>19</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Son</surname>
              <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su141912830</pub-id>
          <article-title>Willingness to pay for the public electric bus in Nepal: A contingent valuation method approach</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>70</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aversa</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adamashvili</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fiore</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spada</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su15010070</pub-id>
          <article-title>Scoping review (SR) via text data mining on water scarcity and climate change</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>2300</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
              <given-names>D. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gong</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siri</surname>
              <given-names>J. G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su9122300</pub-id>
          <article-title>The impact of subsidies on the prevalence of climate-sensitive residential buildings in Malaysia</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <page-range>394-405</page-range>
          <publisher-place>Malang, Indonesia</publisher-place>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manti</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kusuma</surname>
              <given-names>L. T. W. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramadhani</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Majid</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2991/icoemis-19.2019.54</pub-id>
          <article-title>Indonesia sea toll strategy framework directive: Innovative and participatory decision-making methods towards the world maritime axis</article-title>
          <source>2019 1st International Conference on Engineering and Management in Industrial System (ICOEMIS 2019)</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3145</volume>
          <page-range>020040</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fauzi</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Airawati</surname>
              <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cholishoh</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murtiaji</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/5.0214511</pub-id>
          <article-title>The development and challenges of sea tolls in supporting Indonesia's vision 2045</article-title>
          <source>AIP Conf. Proc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>131</volume>
          <page-range>91-106</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guidon</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wicki</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bernauer</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Axhausen</surname>
              <given-names>K. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tra.2019.09.023</pub-id>
          <article-title>Transportation service bundling—For whose benefit? Consumer valuation of pure bundling in the passenger transportation market</article-title>
          <source>Transp. Res. Part A: Policy Pract.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>1690</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pronello</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duboz</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rappazzo</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su9101690</pub-id>
          <article-title>Towards smarter urban mobility: Willingness to pay for an advanced traveller information system in Lyon</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>260</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miwa</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su11010260</pub-id>
          <article-title>A comparative analysis on residents' reservation willingness for bus service based on option price</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fahmiasari</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Developing inland logistics hub in North Sulawesi to reduce transport cost to/from Bitung Port</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <publisher-name>Delft University of Technology</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>744-751</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mappangara</surname>
              <given-names>A. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adisasmita</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samang</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sitepu</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17577/IJERTV4IS110489</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sea transportation network order of sulawesi corridor for supporting connectivity of region</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Eng. Res. Technol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>147-157</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Junyu</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Victoria</surname>
              <given-names>O. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arifani</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18502/kss.v5i1.8277</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sea transportation system policy</article-title>
          <source>KnE Soc. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raga</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aksa</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herdian</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samosir</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ponto</surname>
              <given-names>K. N. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pengukuran indeks daya beli jasa transportasi laut dan penyeberangan pada wilayah tertinggal</article-title>
          <source>J. Sistem Transportasi Logistik</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>172-181</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rohani</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasyim</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ainuddin</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Feasibility evaluation of freight rates (Traditional shipping) in the tourist area of Pemenang in Northern Lombok</article-title>
          <source>Spektrum Sipil</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>762-768</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Makwana</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Engineer</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dabhi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chudasama</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sampling methods in research: A review</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Trend Sci. Res. Dev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>106</volume>
          <page-range>102031</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rhoads</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rames</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Solé-Ribalta</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>González</surname>
              <given-names>M. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szell</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borge-Holthoefer</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compenvurbsys.2023.102031</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sidewalk networks: Review and outlook</article-title>
          <source>Comput. Environ. Urban Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van Hoecke</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5553/REM/.000010</pub-id>
          <article-title>Methodology of comparative legal research</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parson</surname>
              <given-names>G. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The travel cost model</article-title>
          <source>A Primer on Nonmarket Valuation</source>
          <publisher-name>Dordrecht: Springer</publisher-name>
          <year>2003</year>
          <page-range>269-329</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-007-0826-6_9</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Keppres 6 Determination of Outermost Small Islands</article-title>
          <source>, https://peraturan.bpk.go.id/Download/46855/Keppres%20No%206%20Tahun%202017.pdf</source>
          <year>2017</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Perpres 118 Master Plan for the Management of State Borders and Border Areas for 2020-2024</article-title>
          <source>, https://peraturan.go.id/files/1.+Salinan+Perpres+Nomor+118+Tahun+2022.pdf</source>
          <year>2022</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>KP 432 National Port Master Plan</article-title>
          <source>, https://legalcentric.com/content/view/148350/kp-432-tahun-2017-governmental-affairs-organization-transportation</source>
          <year>2017</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>118-127</page-range>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zaman</surname>
              <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vanany</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Awaluddin</surname>
              <given-names>K. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.proeps.2015.07.092</pub-id>
          <article-title>Connectivity analysis of port in Eastern Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Procedia Earth Planet. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1423</volume>
          <page-range>012015</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kurniawan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kharisma</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasadi</surname>
              <given-names>K. I. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bahri</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wirawan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1755-1315/1423/1/012015</pub-id>
          <article-title>Evaluation of tol laut in Tahuna and Natuna as underdeveloped, remote, outermost, and border areas</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Optimization of sea toll route with hub and spoke concept</article-title>
          <source>, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1NevuW_rE3LJM9uh_XJjW372MHmBCWYJs/view?usp=sharing</source>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Performance of Pioneer Transportation Services in North Sulawesi, Case Studies of Sea Pioneers and Ferry Pioneers</article-title>
          <source>, https://drive.google.com/file/d/13_RyefvqW160_3FzAgM-L8PHqiRTd3OJ/view?usp=sharing</source>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>PM 55 Cost and revenue components taken into account in public service activities of pioneer ships</article-title>
          <source>, https://peraturan.bpk.go.id/Download/141262/PM_55_TAHUN_2019.pdf</source>
          <year>2019</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>PM 66 mechanism of determination and formulation of tariff calculation for crossing transportation</article-title>
          <source>, https://peraturan.bpk.go.id/Download/141296/PM_66_TAHUN_2019_rev.pdf</source>
          <year>2019</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>630</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kurniawan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hutapea</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hardianto</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suhartana</surname>
              <given-names>I. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yuliani</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Putra</surname>
              <given-names>T. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siahaan</surname>
              <given-names>W. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hidayat</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Humang</surname>
              <given-names>W. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paotonan</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>others</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su15010630</pub-id>
          <article-title>Finding a new home: Rerouting of ferry ships from Merak-Bakauheni to east Indonesian trajectories</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <page-range>100149</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Önden</surname>
              <given-names>İ.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deveci</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Çancı</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Çal</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Önden</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dajour.2022.100149</pub-id>
          <article-title>A spatial analytics decision support system for analyzing the role of sea transport in public transportation</article-title>
          <source>Decis. Anal. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>37</volume>
          <page-range>102-114</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nasution</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wicaksono</surname>
              <given-names>V. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Putri</surname>
              <given-names>I. A. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Irewati</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prakoso</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33997/j.afs.2024.37.2.003</pub-id>
          <article-title>Opportunity to export fish directly from the outermost islands of Indonesia: Exploring value chain and power dynamics in Fisheries</article-title>
          <source>Asian Fish. Soc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <page-range>tdad008</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/tse/tdad008</pub-id>
          <article-title>How does trip frequency distort time value to impact congestion charging schemes?</article-title>
          <source>Transp. Saf. Environ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>1340</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>X. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>Y. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>Y. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jmse9121340</pub-id>
          <article-title>Cost effectiveness analysis in short sea shipping: Evidence from Northeast Asian routes</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_56">
        <label>56.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Regulation Number 7 2023, Pioneer Sea Transportation Tariff</article-title>
          <source>, https://jdih.maritim.go.id/cfind/source/files/permenhub/permenhub-no.-pm-7-tahun-2023.pdf</source>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_57">
        <label>57.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>43</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karam</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>A. J. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hussein</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12544-023-00614-0</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analysis of the barriers to multimodal freight transport and their mitigation strategies</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_58">
        <label>58.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Duffield</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hui</surname>
              <given-names>F. K. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Infrastructure Investment in Indonesia: A Focus on Ports</source>
          <publisher-name>Open Book Publishers</publisher-name>
          <year>2019</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_59">
        <label>59.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roth</surname>
              <given-names>B. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20935/AcadBiol6081</pub-id>
          <article-title>A mathematical model of mechanotransduction</article-title>
          <source>Acad. Biol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_60">
        <label>60.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>937-950</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wijaya</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Darma</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Darma</surname>
              <given-names>D. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijsdp.150618</pub-id>
          <article-title>Spatial interaction between regions: Study of the East Kalimantan Province, Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Sustain. Dev. Plan.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_61">
        <label>61.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>130</volume>
          <page-range>1-15</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sarkis</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>Q.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lai</surname>
              <given-names>K. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpe.2010.11.010</pub-id>
          <article-title>An organizational theoretic review of green supply chain management literature</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Prod. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_62">
        <label>62.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>627-634</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Humang</surname>
              <given-names>W. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aspar</surname>
              <given-names>W. A. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Upahita</surname>
              <given-names>D.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muharam</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bowo</surname>
              <given-names>L. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Puriningsih</surname>
              <given-names>F. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/IJSDP.180233</pub-id>
          <article-title>Competitiveness of traditional shipping in sea transportation systems based on transport costs: Evidence from Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Sustain. Dev. Plan.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>