<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJCMEM</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Computational Methods and Experimental Measurements</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Int. J. Comput. Methods Exp. Meas.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IJCMEM</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2046-0554</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2046-0546</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-RutOYGW0zMYyA86zJPXJ3tui5ocFdgT3</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/ijcmem140107</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>RB-BERT: A Hybrid Framework of Rule-Based Weak Supervision and BERT for Aspect-Level Sentiment Analysis of Tourist Attractions</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7494-3472</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Imamah</surname>
          </name>
          <email>i2m@trunojoyo.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-4287-6241</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Rachman</surname>
            <given-names>Fika Hastarita</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>fika.rachman@trunojoyo.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1919-0540</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Satoto</surname>
            <given-names>Budi Dwi</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>budids@trunojoyo.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9248-461X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Herawati</surname>
            <given-names>Sri</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>sriherawati@trunojoyo.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-4628-3252</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Damayanti</surname>
            <given-names>Fitri</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>fitrid@trunojoyo.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7324-1380</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Rochman</surname>
            <given-names>Eka Mala Sari</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>em_sari@trunojoyo.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0005-8827-1917</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Fatoni</surname>
            <given-names>Danar</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>danarnurfatoni@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1488-7696</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Dewi</surname>
            <given-names>Deshinta Arrova</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>deshinta.ad@newinti.edu.my</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Information Systems, University of Trunodjoyo Madura, 69112 Bangkalan, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Department of Informatics Engineering, University of Trunodjoyo Madura, 69112 Bangkalan, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">Faculty of Data Science and Information Technology, INTI International University, 71800 Nilai, Malaysia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>03</month>
        <year>2026</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>112</fpage>
      <lpage>124</lpage>
      <page-range>112-124</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>01</month>
          <year>2026</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2026</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2026 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2026</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Multi-aspect sentiment analysis aims to identify different aspects and associated sentiments within user-generated reviews. In recent years, bidirectional encoder representations from transformer (BERT) have been widely used for sentiment analysis due to its strong ability to capture contextual information. However, BERT has limitations in explicitly identifying aspect boundaries and aligning sentiments, especially when multiple aspects with different sentiments appear in the same review. To address this issue, we propose a combination of rule-based and bidirectional encoder representations from transformer (RB-BERT). The main idea of RB-BERT is to utilize domain-specific linguistic rules to automatically generate weak labels for aspect and sentiment pairs, which are then used to fine-tune the pretrained BERT model. A key contribution of this study is addressing BERT’s limitations in aspect-based sentiment analysis (ABSA) by enhancing aspect identification and sentiment assignment. The dataset consists of 3811 user reviews about Sarangan Lake, a popular tourist attraction in East Java, Indonesia. We collected the dataset from Google Maps. The aspects used in this study are scenery view, price, and local environment. The sentiment polarities are positive and negative. We applied four rule levels to enhance the BERT model. The first rule handles aspect extraction, the second addresses sentiment extraction, and the third determines the dominant sentiment based on the frequency of positive and negative words. The fourth rule combines aspects and sentiment in each review to produce a label. BERT tokenization and BERT embeddings are used for feature extraction, with a fully connected linear layer serving as the classification head. RB-BERT performs best with a precision value of 0.9218, a recall of 0.9748, a Micro-F1 of 0.9476, and a Hamming Loss value of 0.0132. Thus, RB-BERT can be used as an approach to perform automatic labeling in multilabel classification by offering speed, low cost, and good performance.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Text mining</kwd>
        <kwd>Transformer</kwd>
        <kwd>Deep learning</kwd>
        <kwd>Creativity and innovation</kwd>
        <kwd>Process innovation</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="8"/>
        <fig-count count="6"/>
        <table-count count="6"/>
        <ref-count count="27"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Sentiment analysis is an automated text extraction process that aims to identify the polarity of opinions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]. However, this approach struggles to capture an opinion’s aspect. For example, someone might say the hotel service is good. However, the location is far from the tourist area. Sentiment analysis would classify this as a negative review. This happens because an annotator will highlight consumer disappointment at the location, possibly missing the positive aspect of good service. Yet, good service enhances the hotel’s value. The distant location cannot be easily changed, but aspects like service can be improved. To address this issue, the multi-label sentiment approach evolved into a more detailed method: aspect-based sentiment analysis (ABSA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. ABSA categorizes reviews by aspect and sentiment. For example, in the previous case, it would classify: aspect: service; sentiment polarity: positive and aspect: location; sentiment polarity: negative.</p><p>To achieve this detail, ABSA uses a multi-stage extraction process. The first stage identifies aspects in the user’s review, such as service, location, or price. The second stage extracts sentiment. The third stage determines the target opinion from the detected aspects and sentiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>]. For example, the target opinion could be “service_positive” and “location_negative”. These tasks commonly addressed within natural language processing (NLP), which enables machines to interpret human language. Recently, pretrained models have become popular and effective for complex NLP tasks. This includes sentiment analysis and ABSA. One widely used pretrained model is bidirectional encoder representations from transformer (BERT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. BERT is trained on Wikipedia and BookCorpus by Google. It performs tasks like masked language modeling and next-sentence prediction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. Although BERT captures sentence structure and context, it cannot classify text on its own [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>]. Adding a classification head, such as a fully connected linear layer, allows BERT to perform text classification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. However, just adding a classification head does not enable BERT to classify text without supervision. The new layer’s parameters must be trained on labeled data. Thus, BERT’s ability to perform classification tasks, including ABSA, depends on the availability of labeled datasets. For ABSA, required labels include sentiment polarity and aspect information at the word or phrase level. This makes labeling more complex than in conventional sentiment analysis.</p><p>The labeling process for the ABSA dataset relies on manual annotation and weak labeling. Manual annotation by linguists provides high accuracy. However, it is time-consuming, costly, and hard to scale across domains or languages with limited resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>]. This need for scalability highlights the importance of weak labeling to generate supervision data at a lower cost.</p><p>Weak labeling methods include unsupervised approaches like topic modeling (e.g., Latent Dirichlet Allocation) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>] and clustering [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. These methods extract “topics” as aspect sentiment from a large corpus. However, they are limited to ABSA. First, they produce document- or sentence-level topics but do not extract explicit aspect terms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>]. Second, performance drops on short texts due to data sparsity and rare word co-occurrence. This makes it difficult to perform aspect extraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>]. Third, clusters or topics need manual labeling or human interpretation to generate meaningful categories. This reduces the benefits of automation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. Thus, topic modeling and clustering do not provide the necessary label granularity for training ABSA models. These models require annotation at the token or phrase level. Large language model (LLM)-based weak labeling is another option, but it also has constraints. LLMs can produce inconsistent outputs and suffer from reproducibility issues. They also require significant computational resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>]. These issues highlight the need for weak labeling methods that use explicit linguistic knowledge, such as dependency relations between aspect and opinion words. This helps label aspects and polarities for ABSA more consistently, reproducibly, and efficiently.</p><p>This study proposes a hybrid weakly supervised framework for aspect-level sentiment analysis of tourist attraction reviews. It combines rule-based pseudo-label generation with BERT-based classification. The approach aims to reduce dependency on extensive manual annotation. It also improves classification performance using contextual semantic learning. In addition, this study aims to demonstrate that rule-based supervision can serve as an effective bridge between traditional interpretable methods and modern deep contextual language models. The main contributions of this study are as follows:</p><p>1. To develop a rule-based weak supervision mechanism for automatically generating aspect-level sentiment pseudo-labels from unlabeled tourism reviews.</p><p>2. To fine-tune a BERT-based classifier using pseudo-labeled data in order to improve contextual understanding and generalization beyond rules.</p><p>3. To evaluate the effectiveness of the proposed hybrid framework in supporting annotation-efficient aspect-level sentiment analysis in the tourism domain.</p><p>4. To provide empirical evidence that integrating rule-based supervision with contextual language modeling can offer a practical alternative for low-resource sentiment classification tasks.</p><p>This paper is organized as follows: Section 2 contains the details of materials and methods; Section 3 presents results and discussions; and Section 4 presents the conclusion and the following work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Methodology</title>
      <p>This section describes the research architecture as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>. The figure illustrates data collection, data labelling, and performance evaluation. The following section explains these stages in more detail.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Architecture of rule-based and bidirectional encoder representations from transformer (RB-BERT)</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/3/img_mT8V0sR8cKZjvUg1.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Dataset</title>
          
          <p>This study used a dataset obtained with the Instant Data Scraper extension. This tool automates data retrieval from Google Maps. The scraping process collected usernames and user reviews for Sarangan Lake, a popular tourist spot in East Java, Indonesia. In total, 3,811 reviews were collected.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.1.1 Aspect definition and annotation strategy</title>
              
              <p>The primary objective of this labeling process is to categorize user reviews by aspect and sentiment polarity. In this study, we used three aspects: scenery view, price, and local environment. Each aspect is classified into two sentiment polarities: positive and negative. Combining aspect and sentiment results in six classification labels: LP (Positive Environment), LN (Negative Environment), HP (Positive Price), HN (Negative Price), PP (Positive View), and PN (Negative View).</p><p>Each labeled dataset is transformed into a binary relevance format [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>. This enables effective handling of multilabel classification. Each label is represented as a binary value: 1 means the label is present in a review; 0 means it is absent. This approach is widely used in multilabel modeling. It allows a single review to have multiple labels and enables independent prediction for each label.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_1">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Example of dataset aspect-based sentiment analysis (ABSA)</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>User Reviews (Indonesian)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>User Reviews (English)</p></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>View</p></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Price</p></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Local Environment</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PP</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PN</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>HP</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>HN</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LP</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LN</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Pemandangannya indah di pagi hari, cuacanya juga dingin. Cocok untuk wisata dengan keluarga dan juga teman.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The scenery is beautiful in the morning, and the weather is also cold. Suitable for tours with family and friends.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.1.2 Rule based for automatic annotations</title>
              
              <p>There are four rules required to create the target opinion or the final label for ABSA. A detailed explanation of the four rules is as follows.</p><p>• Rule 1 for aspect detection</p><p>Sentence as a sequence of tokens: <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myds6t33yx">
    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and a predefined set of aspects <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mwygwk7y0f">
    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, each aspect <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m15ta4y60w">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is associated with a keyword set <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mr99v6mmiu">
    <mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. An aspect is considered active in sentence $S<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mpvnlikqxt">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>W_i<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7vulrh270">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>S<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m0pdx7ndvu">
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>K\left(a_j\right)$. The matching token positions are defined as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(1)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mbhlkgcy8t">
                    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="false">{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="false">}</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∣</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>The aspect activation function is then defined as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(2)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mda3ag4tt4">
                    <mml:mi>AspectActive</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="true"/>
                      <mml:mtable columnalign="left right" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>∅</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> otherwise </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                      </mml:mtable>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>The final detected aspect set is:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(3)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mqn2hmz5fx">
                    <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∣</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∧</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mtext> spectActive </mml:mtext>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>• Rule 2 for sentiment detection</p><p>After aspect detection, sentiment-bearing words are identified using a contextual polarity function. Given a sentence <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mdm9rjo5az">
    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, each token <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mm7ryi8ev8">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is assigned a base polarity:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(4)</label>
                  <mml:math id="m79lu5q8f3">
                    <mml:mi>BasePol</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="true"/>
                      <mml:mtable columnalign="left left" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing=".2em">
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                            <mml:msup>
                              <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msup>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                            <mml:msup>
                              <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msup>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> otherwise </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                      </mml:mtable>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p> where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mz8bptaict">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mxv7qemf54">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>denote the positive and negative sentiment lexicons, respectively. To capture contextual modification, the polarity is adjusted using negation and intensifier cues:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(5)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mdwqb7psbx">
                    <mml:mi>Neg</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>Adj</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="true"/>
                      <mml:mtable columnalign="right center" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mtext> and </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mtext> </mml:mtext>
                              <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> otherwise </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                      </mml:mtable>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(6)</label>
                  <mml:math id="m5xbukmr3z">
                    <mml:mi>IntAdj</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="true"/>
                      <mml:mtable columnalign="center center" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mtext> and </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> otherwise </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                      </mml:mtable>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>Thus, the contextual polarity of token <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m6uyf9ylkj">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is defined as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(7)</label>
                  <mml:math id="m9o7hnqa95">
                    <mml:mi>CP</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>BasePol</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>NegAdj</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>IntAdj</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>For each detected aspect <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m51jnn0xph">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, sentiment cues are associated using a nearest-window heuristic. Let <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mq0jl5bupy">
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denote the set of positions of aspect keywords in sentence $S<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m93qnn0alu">
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>W<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m3ijmjt4sx">
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>w_i<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mtm3r9hhgg">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>a_j$ if:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(8)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mhj7azn2zt">
                    <mml:mi>CP</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>∃</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>∧</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>The sentiment cue set for aspect <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m8h3oagw0v">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is therefore defined as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(9)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mqajte7zrw">
                    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="true"/>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>CP</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msub>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mi>∃</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>CP</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msub>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>The corresponding sentiment score collection is:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(10)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mlj16ifsy8">
                    <mml:mi>Score</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∣</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>• Rule 3 for dominant sentiment with contextual word polarity</p><p>For each sentence <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="msjq0msy66">
    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> each token <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="miso6vnfnk">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is assigned a contextual polarity <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mxw46mm8nf">
    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> as defined in Rule 2. Let $C$ denote the set of contrastive conjunctions (e.g., but, however, although). The positions of contrastive words are defined as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(11)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mvubg4fv9t">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="false">{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="false">}</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∣</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>If a contrastive conjunction exists, only the clause after the first contrastive word is prioritized:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(12)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mtnkwgpgvb">
                    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="true"/>
                      <mml:mtable columnalign="left left" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing=".2em">
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>∣</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                              <mml:msup>
                                <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
                              </mml:msup>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>∅</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mo fence="false">{</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>∣</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo fence="false">}</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> otherwise </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                      </mml:mtable>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p> where,</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(13)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mzp0hp9002">
                    <mml:msup>
                      <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
                    </mml:msup>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>min</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>The positive and negative sentiment scores are then computed as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(14)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mxcqspp2td">
                    <mml:mi>PosScore</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>max</mml:mo>
                    <mml:munder>
                      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:munder>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CP</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(15)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mgdo50lmk1">
                    <mml:mi>NegScore</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>max</mml:mo>
                    <mml:munder>
                      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:munder>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CP</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>The dominant sentence sentiment is defined as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(16)</label>
                  <mml:math id="m1gh7817gl">
                    <mml:mtext> DomSent </mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="true"/>
                      <mml:mtable columnalign="left left" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing=".2em">
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> Positive, </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if PosScore </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mtext> NegScore </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> Negative, </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if NegScore </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mtext> PosScore </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> LastPolarity </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> otherwise </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                      </mml:mtable>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>In case of equal sentiment scores, the polarity of the last sentiment-bearing word in the sentence is used:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(17)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mzdjq32xtx">
                    <mml:msup>
                      <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
                    </mml:msup>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>max</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="false">{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="false">}</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∣</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CP</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(18)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mwzdugdtno">
                    <mml:mtext> LastPolarity </mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="true"/>
                      <mml:mtable columnalign="left left" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing=".2em">
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> positive, </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CP</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
                                </mml:mrow>
                              </mml:msub>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> negative, </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CP</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
                                </mml:mrow>
                              </mml:msub>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> positive, </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mi>∀</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CP</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                      </mml:mtable>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>• Rule 4 for final aspect sentiment annotations</p><p>For each detected aspect <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mu5i49lrqb">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, the final sentiment label is assigned by aggregating all aspect-related sentiment cues obtained from Rule 2. Let: Score <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mwia9t73pg">
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denote the set of contextual sentiment scores associated with aspect <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mybbc29gn6">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> in sentence $S$. The total aspect sentiment score is computed as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(19)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mrzgu00p20">
                    <mml:mi>AspScore</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:munder>
                      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>Score</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:munder>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>The final aspect label is then assigned as:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(20)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mqivnhi86u">
                    <mml:mi>Label</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo fence="true"/>
                      <mml:mtable columnalign="left left" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing=".2em">
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> Positive, </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if AspScore </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> Negative, </mml:mtext>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if AspScore </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                        <mml:mtr>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> Domsent </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mtd>
                          <mml:mtd>
                            <mml:mtext> if AspScore </mml:mtext>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mtd>
                        </mml:mtr>
                      </mml:mtable>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>When aspect-specific polarity is not identified (i.e., <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="merl3nd94f">
    <mml:mi>AspScore</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>), the dominant sentence-level sentiment from Rule 3 is used as the fallback polarity. Thus, the final output of the rule-based labeling process for sentence $S$ is:</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(21)</label>
                  <mml:math id="m2pwmgu0w4">
                    <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∣</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mtext> Label </mml:mtext>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mrmonphc8f">
    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes the set of detected aspects in sentence $S$. For example, we use the dataset shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> to generate ABSA labels according to predefined rules. The results are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>. Rule 1 detects the aspect [scenic view], and Rule 2 detects the sentiment terms [indah] and [dingin]. Rule 3 counts the number of positive terms appearing in the sentence. Because there are two positive terms, the sentiment label is determined as [positive]. Rule 4 combines the detected aspect and sentiment; therefore, the final labels are [PP] and [LP].</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_2">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>The sentence labeling process using rule-based aspect-based sentiment analysis (ABSA)</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/3/img_EPtPFUCeTcQE82IC.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Bidirectional encoder representations from transformers</title>
          
          <p>BERT is a pre-trained NLP model developed by Google in 2018. It is built on the Transformer encoder architecture and is designed to capture bidirectional context. This allows the model to consider both the left and right contexts of a word simultaneously. This capability enables a deeper understanding of word meaning within sentences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>]. BERT consists of multiple stacked encoder layers, enabling it to learn complex language representations. Through this deep architecture, BERT can effectively model semantic relationships in text. As a result, it has been widely applied in various NLP tasks such as sentiment analysis, information retrieval, and machine translation. Numerous studies have shown that BERT improves both accuracy and efficiency across a range of language tasks, making it one of the most widely used approaches in modern NLP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>].</p><p>In the BERT model, input text is converted into a sequence of tokens. These tokens include the [CLS] token, which indicates the sentence start, and the [SEP] token, which separates sentences. The [PAD] token adds padding, ensuring each sentence matches the model’s fixed length [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. The PAD token is essential for batch processing, as it ensures all sentences have a consistent length. This allows the model to work efficiently and accurately. Such a transformation improves contextual understanding during learning, enabling BERT to capture a sentence’s semantic details more effectively. The process for representing the dataset in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>. Input sentences are tokenized with the BERT tokenizer, embedded, and processed into BERT outputs. The architecture used in this research is detailed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Bidirectional encoder representations from transformer (BERT) representation</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/3/img_VUNJ01w_DDHXDr-P.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Architecture of bidirectional encoder representations from transformer (BERT)</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Layer (Type)</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Shape Output (seq_len=128)</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Param (<mml:math id="mek9393lps">
  <mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
</mml:math>)</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Input_ids</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(None, 128)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Attention_mask</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(None, 128)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Embeddings (token + position)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(B, 128, 768)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mvqtlqwye6">
  <mml:mo>∼</mml:mo>
</mml:math>V <mml:math id="mzqckscb4w">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math> 768</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Encoder <mml:math id="mb0dfuqyx6">
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math>12 (Transformer)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(B, 128, 768)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mjrq6zzyne">
  <mml:mo>∼</mml:mo>
</mml:math>124 M</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Pooling (CLS)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(B, 768)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Dense 768 <mml:math id="m9xkkrxr7v">
  <mml:mo>→</mml:mo>
</mml:math> 256</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(B, 256)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>196,864</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Batch Normalization</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(B, 256)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1,024</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Dropout</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(B, 256)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Dense 256 <mml:math id="mk3hst0td8">
  <mml:mo>→</mml:mo>
</mml:math> 128</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(B, 128)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>32,896</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Dropout</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(B, 128)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Output Dense 128 <mml:math id="mfmh7bjhss">
  <mml:mo>→</mml:mo>
</mml:math> 6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(B, 6)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>774</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Deal with imbalance dataset</title>
          
          <p>One challenge in conducting research with multi-aspect datasets is obtaining a balanced distribution. This is because applying balancing techniques, such as synthetic minority over-sampling technique (SMOTE), across multiple aspects can unintentionally increase instances of other labels, making it harder to achieve proper balance. To address this issue, this study applied a text augmentation method specifically to words that influence class formation, following the approach proposed by Santoso et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], with the following steps:</p><p>1. Identify the distribution of classes in the dataset and define minority classes.</p><p>2. Furthermore, each sentence in a minority class is analyzed at the word level to determine its contribution to the sentiment label. This process uses two main approaches, analytical correlation and semantic similarity. Analytical correlation is calculated using Pointwise Mutual Information (PMI), which measures the statistical association between a word and a particular label in the corpus. Meanwhile, semantic similarity is computed using word-embedding-based cosine similarity (Word2Vec) to capture the proximity of meaning between a word and a sentiment label representation. These values are then normalized and used to group words into four categories: meaningful, necessity, reward, and irrelevant. The meaningful category includes words that strongly define the sentiment and should not be altered, while the other categories allow greater flexibility for augmentation.</p><p>3. The augmentation process uses these word categories to selectively modify sentences in three sequential steps: selective replacement, selective insertion, and selective deletion. In selective replacement, synonyms of words not categorized as meaningful replace the originals, preserving the term aspect. In selective insertion, synonyms of selected words are added to the sentence to strengthen context without changing meaning. In selective deletion, words identified as irrelevant are removed to reduce noise and better focus on sentiment. These three operations are applied to ensure that, while the wording may vary, the sentence’s sentiment remains consistent.</p><p>4. The amount of new data generated from each sentence depends on the augmentation strength (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mwzion0c40">
    <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>) parameter. This parameter controls how much each sentence is modified. The process is repeated for all minority-class data, producing synthetic datasets with high variation but the same sentiment label. Augmented data is combined with the original dataset to increase the number of minority-class samples.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Evaluation metrics</title>
          
          <p>Since ABSA involves assigning multiple aspect–sentiment labels to a single instance, its evaluation protocol is aligned with multi-label classification, where metrics such as Hamming Loss, Precision, Recall, and Micro-averaged F1 score are commonly used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Result and discussion</title>
      <p>This study aims to compare rule-based weak supervision with human labeling and evaluate the performance of several deep learning methods. Furthermore, the best-performing model will be examined in more detail through hyperparameter tuning.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Rule based annotation</title>
          
          <p>In this study, we used 100 reviews to check the validity of rule-based labeling compared to human labeling. The reviews were randomly selected from a total of 3,811 reviews. We used Cohen’s Kappa to assess agreement between the two labeling methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]. Cohen’s Kappa is a widely used statistical measure for evaluating the consistency between two annotators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]. A higher Cohen’s Kappa score indicates a stronger agreement between rule-based and manual labeling. The results show that the distribution of positive labels generated by the rule-based approach is generally close to that of human labeling, as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>. This indicates that rule-based approaches have captured labeling patterns that are relatively similar to human annotations, although some labels still cannot be detected.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Number of positive assignments per label</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/3/img_di4ugYdTkvRfUDh0.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>According to the quantitative results, the rule-based method achieved an overall Cohen’s Kappa of 0.90, indicating almost perfect agreement with manual labeling. In addition, an Exact Match Ratio of 0.89 shows that 89% of the data shares the same label combination between the rule-based and human labeling results. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> shows that most labels achieve good agreement rates. In the review sample, the HP and HN labels achieved a Cohen’s Kappa score of 1.00. It indicates that rule-based and human labeling yielded identical labels. The PP label also showed strong performance, with a Cohen’s Kappa of 0.97, while the LP label achieved 0.81.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Comparison annotation using Cohen Kappa</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><th >Label</th><th >Cohen Kappa</th><th >Agreement Count</th><th >Total</th></tr><tr><td >LP</td><td >0.81</td><td >91</td><td >100</td></tr><tr><td >LN</td><td >0.39</td><td >97</td><td >100</td></tr><tr><td >HP</td><td >1.00</td><td >100</td><td >100</td></tr><tr><td >HN</td><td >1.00</td><td >100</td><td >100</td></tr><tr><td >PP</td><td >0.97</td><td >99</td><td >100</td></tr><tr><td >PN</td><td >0.00</td><td >99</td><td >100</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>However, rule-based doesn’t perform well across all labels. The LN label produced a Cohen’s Kappa of 0.39, even though 97 of 100 data points agreed. This shows that rule-based approaches are weak in recognizing LN labels. It is similar to the PN label, which earned a Cohen’s Kappa score of 0.00 despite agreement at 99 out of 100 data points. This value indicates that the rule-based approach failed to detect PN labels, as did human labeling. In other words, the rule-based method tends to agree with human labeling only when PN labels are absent, rather than consistently identifying their presence</p><p>Overall, these results show that the rule-based approach has good validity and is feasible to use as a weak supervision or pseudo-label generator. A rule-based approach has proven particularly effective for labels with more explicit linguistic patterns, such as HP, HN, PP, and LP. However, this approach couldn’t detect labels that appear infrequently, are ambiguous, or are context-dependent, such as LN and PN. Therefore, these findings strengthen the rationale for employing deep learning models in later stages. While rule-based approaches can produce high-quality pseudo-labels, deep learning models can improve generalization, capture complex semantic relationships, and overcome the limitations of rule-based methods, particularly in handling minority or implicit labels.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Comparison of deep learning performance</title>
          
          <p>In text classification research, several deep learning methods are commonly used. These include sequential and bidirectional models. In this study, the most frequently used methods are compared: convolutional neural networks (CNN) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], recurrent neural networks (RNN) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], long short-term memory (LSTM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], bidirectional long short-term memory (Bi-LSTM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], and bidirectional gated recurrent units (Bi-GRU) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>]. Their performance is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>. CNN and BERT models achieved the highest precision, both reaching 0.91. This means the model made a few false-positive predictions. In contrast, the RNN had the lowest precision at 0.39. This is due to the RNN’s limitations in capturing long-term word dependencies. As a result, there are more false positives.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_4">
              <label>Table 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Comparison of deep learning</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Model</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Precision</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Recall</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Micro-F1</p></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hamming Loss</p></th></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CNNs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.91</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.83</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.87</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.04</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>RNNs</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.39</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.84</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.53</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.23</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LSTM</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.77</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.78</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.78</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.06</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bi-LSTM</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.87</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.77</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.81</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.53</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bi-GRU</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.85</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.89</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.87</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.04</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>BERT</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.91</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.95</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.93</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.02</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>BERT also achieved the highest recall (0.95). This shows it is effective at identifying most positive instances. On the other hand, Bi-LSTM had the lowest recall at 0.77. The lower recall of the Bi-LSTM model can be attributed to its more selective prediction behavior. It is causing some relevant labels to be overlooked and leading to a higher number of false negatives. For the Micro-F1 score, BERT achieved the highest value at 0.93. CNN and Bi-GRU also performed well, with scores of 0.87, while RNN had the lowest score at 0.53. This shows that BERT has the best balance of precision and recall. In terms of Hamming Loss, BERT also gets the best score of 0.02. Both CNN and Bi-GRU had Hamming Loss values of 0.04. RNN had a high error rate, as indicated by the highest Hamming Loss of 0.23. A higher error rate corresponds to higher label prediction errors.</p><p>Based on this study, we conclude that RNN performed the lowest due to its limited ability to capture long-term word dependencies. LSTM performed better than RNN because it captures long-term dependencies. CNN performed well, particularly in precision, which is comparable to BERT. It is because CNN can extract local patterns correctly. Bidirectional models such as Bi-LSTM and Bi-GRU generally outperformed unidirectional models. However, BERT still performed best, leading most evaluation metrics, especially recall, Micro-F1, and Hamming Loss. This shows that BERT is the best deep learning model in this study.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Bidirectional encoder representations from transformers hyperparameter tuning</title>
          
          <p>In this study, BERT appeared as the highest-performing model compared to sequential and bidirectional models. As mentioned, the best model will be tuned to identify the optimal parameter that maximizes BERT performance. The parameter tuning for BERT used in this study is the epoch and batch size. The two epoch settings are 5 and 10. We selected these parameters following Devlin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], who recommended 3–4 epochs for fine-tuning. However, prior studies by Dodge et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>] and Mosbach et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>] indicated that increasing the number of epochs may improve performance on small datasets. To optimize the control of update weight, we used batch sizes of 16, 32, and 64. The range of batch sizes is standardized to maximize performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]. The learning rate was varied among four values (2e-5, 3e-5, 4e-5, 5e-5). These learning rate parameters were selected because, according to Devlin et al., they have a significant impact on model performance in classification tasks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>].</p>
          <p>After evaluating combinations of epoch, batch size, and learning rate, we observed differences in BERT’s performance, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref>. In parameter epoch 5, the best performance was achieved with a batch size of 32 and a learning rate of 2e-5. This configuration achieved a precision of 0.9355, a recall of 0.9388, Micro-F1 of 0.9372, and a Hamming Loss of 0.0154. However, at epoch 10, the best performance was achieved with a batch size of 64 and a learning rate of 2e-5, producing a precision of 0.9218, a recall of 0.9748, a Micro-F1 of 0.9476, and a Hamming Loss of 0.0132. Increasing the number of epochs from 5 to 10 allows BERT to better understand contextual relationships in the data. As a result, the model becomes better at capturing relevant patterns and identifying true positive labels, and improves overall performance.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.1 Analysis of epoch variation</title>
              
              <p>Based on the results in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref>, increasing the number of epochs from 5 to 10 can improve Micro-F1, Hamming Loss, and recall. In epoch 5, the best Micro-F1 is 0.9372, which increases to 0.9476 when using epoch 10. The best Hamming Loss in epoch 5 is 0.0154 and drops to 0.0132. These improvements indicate that increasing the epoch length allows a model to learn the patterns of relationships between labels and text contexts more effectively.</p>
              
                <table-wrap id="table_5">
                  <label>Table 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Rule-based and bidirectional encoder representations from transformer (RB-BERT) with epoch = 5</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Epoch</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Batch Size</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Learning Rate</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Precision</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Recall</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Micro-F1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hamming Loss</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="12"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>16</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9234</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9101</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9167</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0203</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8963</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9640</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9289</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0181</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8654</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9712</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9153</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0220</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9190</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9388</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9288</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0176</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>32</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9355</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9388</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9372</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0154</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9144</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9604</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9368</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0159</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9196</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9460</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9326</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0168</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9214</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9281</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9247</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0185</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>64</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9326</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8957</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9138</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0207</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9164</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9460</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9310</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0172</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8851</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9424</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9129</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0220</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9228</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9460</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9343</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0163</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
              
                <table-wrap id="table_6">
                  <label>Table 6</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Rule-based and bidirectional encoder representations from transformer (RB-BERT) with epoch = 10</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Epoch</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Batch Size</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Learning Rate</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Precision</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Recall</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Micro-F1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hamming Loss</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="12"><p>10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>16</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9138</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9532</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9331</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0168</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9146</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9245</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9195</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0198</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9027</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9676</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9340</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0168</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8935</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9353</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9139</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0216</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>32</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9135</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9496</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9312</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0172</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9281</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9281</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9281</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0176</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9296</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9496</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9395</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0150</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9345</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9245</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9295</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0172</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>64</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9218</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9748</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9476</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0132</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9412</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9209</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9309</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0168</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9091</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9353</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9220</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0194</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5e-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9097</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9424</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9258</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0185</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
                </table-wrap>
              
              <p>In addition, epoch also affected recall. In epoch 5, the best recall reached 0.9388, and in epoch 10, it reached 0.9748. This means that models could detect labels more accurately and reduce false negatives. In other words, more epochs allow the model to better adjust its weights, leading to a more precise semantic representation. However, increasing the number of epochs does not always guarantee improved performance of BERT. In some configurations, precision decreases when we increase the length of the epoch. It means that the highest epochs can lead to higher recall, but precision may drop. Therefore, the number of epochs must be carefully chosen to help the model capture more labels while maintaining prediction accuracy.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.2 Analysis of learning rate variation</title>
              
              <p>Based on the two tables, the learning rate affects the quality of BERT’s learning. In general, smaller learning rates, such as 2e-5, can yield better results than larger ones, such as 3e-5, 4e-5, and 5e-5. In epoch 5, the best configuration was obtained at a learning rate of 2e-5 and a batch size of 32, which gave the best result in a Micro-F1 of 0.9372 and a Hamming Loss of 0.0154. In epoch 10, the best performance was achieved with a learning rate of 2e-5 and a batch size of 64, resulting in a Micro-F1 of 0.9476 and a Hamming Loss of 0.0132. This indicates that a smaller learning rate allows the BERT fine-tuning process to be more stable. However, if the learning rate is too large, the weight updates are too fast, which risks the model missing important representations learned during pre-training. As a result, model performance decreases, and Hamming Loss tends to increase.</p><p>We also observed that learning rates of 4e-5 or 5e-5 can lead to high recall, but are not always accompanied by good precision and low Hamming Loss. For example, in epoch 5, with a batch size of 16 and a learning rate of 4e-5, recall reached 0.9712, but precision dropped to 0.8654, and Hamming Loss increased to 0.0220. This condition shows that a too-large learning rate can make the model assign labels faster, but leads to more false positives.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.3 Analysis of batch size variation</title>
              
              <p>Besides the epoch and learning rate, batch size also affects model performance. The larger batch sizes can lead to lower Hamming Loss and higher Micro-F1 scores. Increasing the batch size from 16 to 32 could improve BERT’s performance. For example, in epoch 5, when we used a batch size of 16, the Hamming Loss was 0.0203 and dropped to 0.0154 when we increased the batch size to 32. While the Micro-F1 also increased from 0.9167 to 0.9372. In epoch 10, the best performance was also achieved with a maximum batch size of 64, with a Micro-F1 of 0.9476 and a Hamming Loss of 0.0132. The larger batch sizes make the learning process more stable, as gradient estimates are derived from a larger set of samples at each iteration, thereby reducing variance. Larger batch sizes can improve training stability, but not always improve the precision. In our experiments, increasing batch size improved recall but sometimes reduced precision. This suggests that batch size influences the balance between detecting labels and maintaining prediction accuracy.</p><p>The results of this study show that rule-based and BERT (RB-BERT)’s best performance is not determined by a single parameter, but by the optimal combination of hyperparameters. Detailed results of BERT’s best performance in Hamming Loss are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>. The combination of epoch 10, batch size 64, and learning rate 2e-5 yielded the best overall results. It means that epoch 10 provides sufficient training time, that a learning rate of 2E-5 maintains fine-tuning stability, and that a batch size of 64 helps produce more stable gradient updates. In other words, the optimal performance of the RB-BERT is achieved when the model is given sufficient training time, less aggressive weight updates, and a large enough batch size to stabilize the learning process. in contrast, a combination of improper parameters, such as too large of a learning rate or too small of a batch size, tends to result in less stable performance and higher Hamming Loss. Therefore, hyperparameter tuning is a crucial step in optimizing the performance of the BERT model for multi-label classification tasks.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_5">
                  <label>Figure 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Best Hamming Loss comparison: epoch 5 and 10</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/3/img_8bNY5Ptvox2gegb3.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              
                <fig id="fig_6">
                  <label>Figure 6</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Best Micro-F1-score comparison: epoch 5 and 10</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/3/img_4WA240wZKL83TrVT.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Conclusion</title>
      <p>Based on the evaluation results, RB-BERT achieved the highest performance, with a precision of 0.9218, a recall of 0.9748, a micro F1 score of 0.9476, and a Hamming loss of 0.0132. These findings confirm that rule-based labeling can be effectively used for automatic annotation for ABSA. This approach can address individual interpretation biases in human labeling, particularly when identifying ABSA. Further studies are needed to integrate semi-supervised learning methods that combine a small set of high-quality human-labeled data with larger rule-based annotations. Additionally, involving multiple annotators and calculating inter-annotator agreement would help validate the quality of manual labeling. Another promising direction is the use of adaptive rule-based systems that incorporate linguistic variations or domain-specific terms, particularly for languages with rich morphology, such as Indonesian, to enhance annotation accuracy and robustness.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>Conceptualization, I. and F.H.R.; methodology, I. and F.H.R.; validation, I.; formal analysis, I.; investigation, I.; resources, B.D.S. and D.F.; data curation, D.F.; writing—original draft preparation, I.; writing—review and editing, S.H., F.D., E.M.S.R., and D.A.D.; project administration, D.F. All authors were actively involved in discussing the findings and refining the final manuscript.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work is funded by Universitas Trunojoyo Madura (UTM), National Collaboration Grant 2023 (Contract No.: 5906/UN46.4.1/PT.01.03/2023).</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <page-range>23–27</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rachman</surname>
              <given-names>F. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imamah</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rintyarna</surname>
              <given-names>B. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ISMODE53584.2022.9742894</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sentiment analysis of Madura tourism in new normal era using Text Blob and KNN with hyperparameter tuning</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of International Seminar on Machine Learning, Optimization, and Data Science (ISMODE), Jakarta, Indonesia</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <volume>2021</volume>
          <page-range>923–934</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wahid</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-16-3246-4</pub-id>
          <article-title>Social media analysis for sentiment classification using gradient boosting machines</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of International Conference on Communication and Computational Technologies: ICCCT 2021. Springer, Singapore</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>1</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tao</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fang</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40537-019-0278-0</pub-id>
          <article-title>Toward multi-label sentiment analysis: A transfer learning based approach</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <volume>2020</volume>
          <page-range>546–557</page-range>
          <publisher-place>Zhengzhou, China</publisher-place>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ying</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dai</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-60457-8_45</pub-id>
          <article-title>Transformer-based multi-aspect modeling for multi-aspect multi-sentiment analysis</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of Natural Language Processing and Chinese Computing (NLPCC 2020)</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>139</volume>
          <page-range>107503</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kabir</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasan</surname>
              <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laskar</surname>
              <given-names>M. T. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joarder</surname>
              <given-names>T. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahmud</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasan</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chb.2022.107503</pub-id>
          <article-title>DEPTWEET: A typology for social media texts to detect depression severities</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <volume>2019</volume>
          <page-range>194–206</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qiu</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-32381-3_16</pub-id>
          <article-title>How to fine-tune BERT for text classification</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of Chinese Computational Linguistics: 18th China National Conference, Kunming, China</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <volume>2022</volume>
          <page-range>7576–7586</page-range>
          <publisher-place>Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates</publisher-place>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lv</surname>
              <given-names>Q.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18653/v1/2022.emnlp-main.514</pub-id>
          <article-title>Parameter-efficient tuning makes a good classification head</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 2022 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing,</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2022</volume>
          <page-range>3498123</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Qasim</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bangyal</surname>
              <given-names>W. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alqarni</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali Almazroi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2022/3498123</pub-id>
          <article-title>A fine-tuned BERT-based transfer learning approach for text classification</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <volume>2020</volume>
          <page-range>3051–3062</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kratzwald</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feuerriegel</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18653/v1/2020.emnlp-main.246</pub-id>
          <article-title>Learning a cost-effective annotation policy for question answering</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 2020 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>168</volume>
          <page-range>114231</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ozyurt</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akcayol</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eswa.2020.114231</pub-id>
          <article-title>A new topic modeling based approach for aspect extraction in aspect based sentiment analysis: SS-LDA</article-title>
          <source>Expert Syst. Appl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>57</volume>
          <page-range>296</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hua</surname>
              <given-names>Y. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Denny</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wicker</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taskova</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10462-024-10906-z</pub-id>
          <article-title>A systematic review of aspect-based sentiment analysis: Domains, methods, and trends</article-title>
          <source>Artif. Intell. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>58</volume>
          <page-range>383</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>K. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duong</surname>
              <given-names>T. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10462-025-11398-1</pub-id>
          <article-title>A systematic review of multi-modal large language models on domain-specific applications</article-title>
          <source>Artif. Intell. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>284</volume>
          <page-range>111286</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Emmert-Streib</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.knosys.2023.111286</pub-id>
          <article-title>Optimal performance of binary relevance CNN in targeted multi-label text classification</article-title>
          <source>Knowl.-Based Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>165</volume>
          <page-range>113898</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moirangthem</surname>
              <given-names>D. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eswa.2020.113898</pub-id>
          <article-title>Hierarchical and lateral multiple timescales gated recurrent units with pre–trained encoder for long text classification</article-title>
          <source>Expert Syst. Appl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>825-835</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taj</surname>
              <given-names>N. M. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shivappa</surname>
              <given-names>G. G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22266/ijies2024.1031.62</pub-id>
          <article-title>Aspect based sentiment analysis using modified latent dirichlet allocation and optimized BERT with LSTM classification</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Intell. Eng. Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>79</volume>
          <page-range>11452-11477</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wankhade</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Annavarapu</surname>
              <given-names>C. S. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abraham</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11227-023-05112-7</pub-id>
          <article-title>MAPA BiLSTM-BERT: Multi-aspects position aware attention for aspect level sentiment analysis</article-title>
          <source>J. Supercomput.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>8738</page-range>
          <issue>19</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Santoso</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mendonça</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aritsugi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app14198738</pub-id>
          <article-title>TAWC: Text augmentation with word contributions for imbalance aspect-based sentiment classification</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <volume>2023</volume>
          <page-range>202–218</page-range>
          <publisher-place>Ingolstadt, Germany</publisher-place>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fehle</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Munster</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolff</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aspect-based sentiment analysis as a multi-label classification task on the domain of german hotel reviews</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 19th Conference on Natural Language Processing (KONVENS 2023)</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2026</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bucarelli</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Purificato</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bacciu</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cassano</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siciliano</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nelakanti</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mantrach</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silvestri</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TAI.2026.3666527</pub-id>
          <article-title>When annotators disagree: A principled approach to learning with noisy labels</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Trans. Artif. Intell.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>65</volume>
          <page-range>112604</page-range>
          <year>2026</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Siam</surname>
              <given-names>M. F. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wafa</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dib.2026.112604</pub-id>
          <article-title>BABSA: A large scale bangla aspect based sentiment analysis dataset</article-title>
          <source>Data Br.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>84</volume>
          <page-range>9257-9286</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ji</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
              <given-names>Q.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Long</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11042-024-18806-8</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enhancing patent text classification with Bi-LSTM technique and alpine skiing optimization for improved diagnostic accuracy</article-title>
          <source>Multimedia Tools Appl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>1893-1913</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>R. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yuosif</surname>
              <given-names>N. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohammed</surname>
              <given-names>A. B. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.51519/journalisi.v7i2.1140</pub-id>
          <article-title>Comparison of RNN and LSTM classifiers for sentiment analysis of airline tweets</article-title>
          <source>J. Inf. Syst. Informatics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>76-85</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>First</surname>
              <given-names>B. A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shanmugavadive</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sathishkumar</surname>
              <given-names>V. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maruthappa</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Subramanian</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thinakaran</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14569/IJACSA.2024.0151010</pub-id>
          <article-title>Attention mechanism-based CNN-LSTM for abusive comments detection and classification in social media text</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Adv. Comput. Sci. Appl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>1-26</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nourmohammadi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-01516-y</pub-id>
          <article-title>A novel framework for sentiment classification employing Bi-GRU optimized by enhanced human evolutionary optimization algorithm</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <page-range>4171–4186</page-range>
          <publisher-place>Minneapolis, Minnesota</publisher-place>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Devlin</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>M. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toutanova</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18653/v1/N19-1423</pub-id>
          <article-title>BERT: Pre-training of deep bidirectional transformers for language understanding</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 2019 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies, Volume 1 (Long and Short Papers),</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dodge</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ilharco</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schwartz</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farhadi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajishirzi</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2002.06305</pub-id>
          <article-title>Fine-tuning pretrained language models: Weight initializations, data orders, and early stopping</article-title>
          <source>arXiv Prepr. arXiv2002.06305</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mosbach</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andriushchenko</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klakow</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2006.04884</pub-id>
          <article-title>On the stability of fine-tuning BERT: Misconceptions, explanations, and strong baselines</article-title>
          <source>arXiv Prepr. arXiv2006.04884</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>