<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJKIS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Knowledge and Innovation Studies</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Int J. Knowl. Innov Stud.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IJKIS</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">3005-6101</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">3005-6098</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-jbx61cHQGQPcHE2a15OzCd8H2zqmxQ_k</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/ijkis010101</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Utilizing Edge Cloud Computing and Deep Learning for Enhanced Risk Assessment in China’s International Trade and Investment</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1">1</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Abid</surname>
            <given-names>Muhammad</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0006-8619-6666</contrib-id>
          <email>mabid@ncsu.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="2">2</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Saqlain</surname>
            <given-names>Muhammad</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3617-6043</contrib-id>
          <email>muhammad.saql@kmutt.ac.th</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="1">Department of Mathematics, North Carolina State University, 27695 Raleigh, USA</aff>
        <aff id="2">Department of Mathematics, Faculty of Science, King Mongkut’s University of Technology Thonburi (KMUTT), 10140 Bangkok, Thailand</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <year>2023</year>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>9</lpage>
      <page-range>1-9</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <month>07</month>
          <day>31</day>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <month>09</month>
          <day>09</day>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="pub">
          <month>09</month>
          <day>29</day>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2023 by the authors</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <license>. Licensee Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article can be downloaded for free, and reused and quoted with a citation of the original published version, under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 license</ext-link>.</license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Amidst a transformative economic milieu in China, domestic enterprises are venturing into the global market, exposing them to intensified perils in international trade and investment. This research elucidates the international trade and investment (ITI) context within China, establishing criteria for ITI risk evaluation through an analytical exploration of international trade interactions. A methodology has been developed to quantify ITI risk, employing deep neural networks (DNNs), with a particular focus on the potential impact of edge cloud computing on China's trading economy. Through the utilization of convolutional neural networks (CNN), risks in China's trade and investment are appraised across various dimensions, exhibiting a noteworthy accuracy rate of 90.38%. It is identified that while CNN exhibits exemplary performance in estimating severe and high-risk scenarios, its efficacy diminishes when discerning general investment perils. The analysis underscores that a substantial portion of investments, constituting 14.8%, emanates from The Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) and China, with market dynamics and macroeconomic conditions markedly influencing the risk associated with Chinese investments. By extending the utilization of deep learning (DL) in financial investments and integrating edge cloud computing, this investigation augments the capabilities for assessing China's ITI risk, providing a valuable resource for comprehending the ITI landscape within China.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Convolutional neural network</kwd>
        <kwd>Advanced machine learning</kwd>
        <kwd>International trade and investment</kwd>
        <kwd>Risk analysis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors">2</count>
        <fig-count>7</fig-count>
        <table-count>0</table-count>
        <ref-count>35</ref-count>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Amidst the burgeoning evolution of the global digital economy, activities anchored in digital technology, such as online R&amp;amp;D, design, production, and trading, have been catapulted into popularity. An enhancement in the dominance of digital trade on the global stage is witnessed, with the rise of global digital service trade by 3.8% in 2019 to attain a zenith of \$3,192.6 billion, eclipsing the growth rates of both service and products trade and constituting 12.9% of all commerce and 52.0% of service trade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]. Subsequent to its accession to the WTO, regulatory enhancements governing digital trade have been fortified by China to more effectively cater to its national interests, evidenced by the ratification of over 20 trade agreements and active negotiation on an additional ten free trade accords [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>]. However, the pandemic-induced uncertainties loom, bearing the potential to amplify trade-restrictive measures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>].</p><p>A fluctuation in China's foreign investment has been observed, with a decrement of actual foreign capital utilization by 1.3% YoY in the initial half of 2020, conversely elevating by 7.1% YoY in June [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>]. The influence of enigmatic elements in a sophisticated global economic environment on foreign investment has been noted, rendering the attainment of stable foreign investment a persisting challenge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>]. Emphasis by China on high-performance computing has been elucidated through policies spearheading the advancement of supercomputing facilities and initiatives such as “East-West Computing”. A consequential amplification in advancements in digital technology and the economy is foreseen through cloud-edge collaboration, signaling a pivotal developmental trajectory forward [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>].</p><p>Historical examinations of the risks entwined with global trade and investment have been extensive. Recognizing risks and proffering solutions pertinent to corporate finance, investment climates, governmental management, and decision-making, Buckley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>] have charted these perils. Additional research has dissected the risks engulfing Chinese foreign investment, spanning political, economic, cultural, and M&amp;amp;A dimensions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], while a spotlight has also been cast upon risks affiliated with China's “Belt and Road” (B&amp;amp;R) initiative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]. Despite numerous academics delving into the quantitative assessment of trade and investment risks, a comprehensive evaluation, encapsulating manifold risk constituents, remains elusive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>]. Employment of DL in this research endeavors to evaluate China's ITI risk has been articulated, offering a synopsis of the contemporary ITI landscape within China, formulating risk evaluation criteria grounded in international trade relations, and architecting a risk assessment system underpinned by DNNs. Cognizance has been taken of the results yielded from ITI risk training, in conjunction with trade and investment volumes and ratios, as well as the risk pertaining to foreign investments, subject to varied influential variables. Furthermore, a DL-supported ITI risk assessment system has been developed, illuminating the applicability of DL in research concerning financial investments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>].</p><p>In summation, the exploration delineates challenges entwined with foreign investment, delineates the metamorphosis of digital trade, and elucidates China's standing within the global economy. An exposition of the capabilities of DL in the evaluation of ITI risk is spotlighted, alongside a detailed analysis of China's entanglement in global trade dynamics.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>2. Methodology</title>
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.1. Chinese trade's exemplary adaptations</title>
          
          <p>Initiation of modified import tax rate applications was witnessed in China, with reductions enacted for upwards of 700 items starting January 2019, an additional 850 items from January 1, 2020, and a further 298 information technology products as of July 1. The mitigation of these tariffs is perceived to enhance the procurement of high-calibre global commodities, thereby ameliorating the domestic supply chain, and accommodating production requisites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]. Consequently, diversification in the import market's structure was identified. Trade transactions between China and nations affiliated with the (B&amp;amp;R) initiative was reported to aggregate 4.2 trillion yuan during the first half of 2020, constituting 29.5% of total trade and manifesting a 0.7% increment relative to the preceding year.</p><p>This expansion in imports, which ostensibly underscores China's fidelity to international responsibilities, concomitantly fosters global economic growth. By refining the business environment, a simplification in trade processes has been introduced in China. Reforms have culminated in a reduction of obligatory documentation for customs declarations and clearances from 86 to 44, thus streamlining transactional activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]. Between the years 2017 and 2019, implementation of automated online verifications was correlated with a 42% and 65.3% decline in export and import compliance costs respectively.</p><p>The establishment of free trade zones and cross-border e-commerce pilot zones has been associated with enhancements in trade quality. In H1 2020, the emergence of new pilot zones, inclusive of those dedicated to cross-border e-commerce, was linked with a 28.7% surge in exports and a 33.4% amplification in market procurement, thereby rejuvenating the transmutation and development of international trade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>]. Despite a contraction in global Information Technology and Investment (ITI), an escalation in China's ITI has been discerned, bolstering an open global economy. During the first half of 2020, a 0.5% ascent in foreign capital utilisation was observed, whilst international trade witnessed a year-over-year (YOY) augmentation of 6.5%, with exports and imports expanding by 10.4% and 1.6% respectively, highlighting China's proliferating influence within the international market [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.2. Implications of chinese exports through edge cloud computing</title>
          
          <p>In the conceptual expansion of cloud computing, edge cloud computing has emerged, where computational capacity is strategically positioned at the network's edge, thereby facilitating reduced processing times for proximal requirements. Typically utilised for local decision-making, real-time data processing, and the deployment of time-sensitive services, this approach has been adopted with an aim to enhance collaborative efforts amidst the completion of cloud computing. Categorically, edge computing mirrors cloud computing, bifurcating into Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS), Platform as a Service (PaaS), and Software as a Service (SaaS) tiers, encompassing technologies such as edge gateways, integrated computers, and computational platforms.</p><p>Such technologies, wherein GPUs and various computational tools are employed, are designed to expediently access edge devices, facilitate data acquisition, and integrate protocols, tailoring their functionalities to specific circumstances. Analogous to cloud-native technology, edge cloud systems incorporate lightweight virtualization, a strategy that has been implemented by manufacturers, including but not limited to Huawei, Kingsoft, and Baidu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>]. These platforms are often instituted across varied locations to accommodate the prerequisites of edge intelligence and Artificial Intelligence (AI) deployment. In parallel with the evolution of China's cloud service market, which witnessed a 57.10% YoY proliferation in 2019 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>], edge cloud computing has demonstrated congruent growth. Notably, in the realm of edge applications, the burgeoning popularity of cloud-native solutions, underscored by scalable and uniform design, addresses challenges pertinent to application distribution delivery and maintenance by proffering integrated application distribution support.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.3. The determination of risk indicators</title>
          
          <p>Global trade, facilitated by the division of labour and encompassing the exchange of goods and services between nations, is posited as an indispensable avenue for international integration. Such interactions underline the economic interdependence amongst countries, giving due regard to their cumulative bilateral transactions. The delineation of factors influencing the inherent risks of China's ITI can be observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>Influential determinants of China's ITI risks</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/9/img_RhOHy_RjbpWWZrY3.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>As depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>, the determinants of risks in China's ITI have been compartmentalized into five predominant clusters. The interplay amongst these clusters mirrors the tension between global market dynamics and China's commercial and investment paradigms. In economies driven by commodities, the symbiotic relationship between product supply and market demand is manifested, thereby highlighting the consonance between production processes and market consumption patterns. Policy milieu, in this context, pertains to the gamut of regulatory interventions that bolster China's transnational trade and investment trajectories. Furthermore, the technological milieu encompasses salient sociological and technological facets directly pertinent to the ITI landscape in China. Embedded within this are the national technical blueprint, technological governance, degrees of technological advancement, and patterns of technological evolution.</p><p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> then elucidates commonly employed techniques for risk assessment.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>Prevalent methodologies for risk evaluation</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/9/img_QxP_PeWHbxLk9lBU.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Within the precincts of China's ITI, nations are categorized grounded on the congruence of their investment risk profiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]. Additionally, methods for gauging attributes and for hierarchically ranking alternatives have been profusely applied within the theoretical frameworks of fuzzy set and its amalgamated paradigms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]. It is noteworthy that such methodologies find versatile applicability, spanning sectors from economics to healthcare.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.4. Dnn model optimisation process</title>
          
          <p>DL is recognised for synthesising lower-level features to create intricate, high-level features, thereby revealing sparse feature representations within data, elucidating attribute categories, or features. The merits of identifying risks pertinent to China's trade and investment through the adoption of DL methodologies are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>Merits of constructing China's trade and investment risks through DL methodologies</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/9/img_ogQ4mwttfO2I7VzA.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>DL algorithms, capable of leveraging exceedingly complex and abstract data features for prediction or classification tasks, afford the autonomous extraction of features from unsupervised data. The fundamental construct within DL is a DNN, utilised in the formation of DL models. An understanding of the perceptron model emerges as paramount prior to delving into the intricacies of the DNN. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> illustrates the perceptron model, which, in its configuration, harbours numerous inputs and outputs, representing input values as <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>x</mi>
      <mn>1</mn>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>x</mi>
      <mn>2</mn>
    </msub>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, and <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>x</mi>
      <mn>3</mn>
    </msub>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, whilst the activation function is denoted by $f<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">[</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">]</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>q</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>G</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>E</mi>
    <mi>q</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>k</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>x</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mn>28</mn>
    <mn>1</mn>
    <mn>1</mn>
    <mn>1.</mn>
    <msup>
      <mi>l</mi>
      <mo data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mo>
    </msup>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\operatorname{sign}(z)$, albeit simple, suffers from restricted processing capacity. Alternative activation functions, commonly employed in neural networks (NNs), such as the Sigmoid function utilised in logistic regression, are denoted in Eq. (1):</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>f</mi>
                <mi>z</mi>
                <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mfrac>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                  <mrow>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                    <mo>+</mo>
                    <msup>
                      <mi>e</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mo>−</mo>
                        <mi>z</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msup>
                  </mrow>
                </mfrac>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>The evolution of the perceptron concept precipitated the inception of NNs. A variant of NN, incorporating several hidden layers, is categorized as a DNN. Both multi-layer NN and DNN typically allude to an analogous concept. At times, DNN is alternatively termed a Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> elucidates the foundational structure of the DNN.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>Fundamental structure of DNN</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/9/img_o8gMM4oTORLfb0Tu.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>DNN segmentation, based on the locations of its constituent layers, is displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref>. DNN incorporates three variants of layers: input, hidden, and output layers. Every neuron in the i-th layer necessitates connectivity to neurons in the <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mo>+</mo>
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mn>1</mn>
  </math>
</inline-formula> layer, ensuring comprehensive connectivity across these layers. Despite DNN’s apparent complexity, smaller, localized models exhibit perceptible similarities to the perceptron, indicating a linear relationship [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>]. Assuming the chosen activation function is <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>σ</mi>
    <mi>z</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula> and the output value of both the hidden layer and the output layer is denoted as $a$, Eq. (2) elucidates the model expression:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(2)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msubsup>
                  <mi>a</mi>
                  <mi>j</mi>
                  <mi>l</mi>
                </msubsup>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mi>σ</mi>
                <mi>σ</mi>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <msubsup>
                    <mi>z</mi>
                    <mi>j</mi>
                    <mi>l</mi>
                  </msubsup>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <munderover>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>k</mi>
                      <mo>=</mo>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </mrow>
                    <mi>m</mi>
                  </munderover>
                  <msubsup>
                    <mi>w</mi>
                    <mi>l</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>j</mi>
                      <mi>k</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msubsup>
                  <msubsup>
                    <mi>a</mi>
                    <mi>k</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>l</mi>
                      <mo>−</mo>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </mrow>
                  </msubsup>
                  <msubsup>
                    <mi>b</mi>
                    <mi>j</mi>
                    <mi>l</mi>
                  </msubsup>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>In Eq. (2), <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msubsup>
      <mi>a</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
      <mi>l</mi>
    </msubsup>
  </math>
</inline-formula> signifies the output value of the $j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>l<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>z_j^l<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mn>1</mn>
  </math>
</inline-formula>l-1<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>F</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>b_j^l<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>w_{j k}^l<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>z</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>k<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>l-1<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>l<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>T</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>a_k^{l-1}<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>k<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </math>
</inline-formula>l-1$ th layer.</p><p>NNs can incorporate numerous hidden layers, facilitating the evolution of novel abstractions in higher hidden layers based upon preceding ones. However, an escalation in the number of hidden layers often engenders two prominent challenges: overfitting and the vanishing gradient problem. The vanishing gradient issue pertains to the gradual attenuation of the gradient, as information permeates through layers, thereby exerting a diminished influence on the network's weights. Overfitting transpires when a model becomes excessively intricate, manifesting exceptionally elevated recognition performance on training data yet potentially performing poorly on unseen data. To navigate these challenges, DNN methodologies traditionally employ the stochastic gradient descent approach for optimization.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.5. Assessment of china's iti risk utilising dnn-based system</title>
          
          <p>The utilisation of NN Technology within the realm of DL has facilitated the attainment of intelligent decision-making in China's ITI. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> elucidates the ITI Risk Assessment System, developed via DNN methodologies.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_5">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>A DNN-based risk assessment system for China's ITI</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/9/img_-SVbGFZam0X6hOyI.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Primary data, extracted from digital platforms, undergoes a process of vectorised feature extraction, as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref>. Subsequent analysis of the acquired data is executed in MATLAB for DNN training purposes. The z-score function, applied for the data normalisation, is employed in the context of studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>], and is expressed as follows:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(3)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>z</mi>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mfrac>
                  <mrow>
                    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                    <mi>x</mi>
                    <mi>μ</mi>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>σ</mi>
                </mfrac>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>In Eq. (3), the function $z<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>u</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\mu<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>b</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\sigma<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>x$ indicates the input data pertaining to foreign trade investment. Upon extraction of feature vectors from the data related to China's foreign trade investments, a DNN model is constructed computationally. A model for investment risk assessment is consequently formulated, utilising pivotal feature vectors related to China's foreign trade investments. Ultimately, the developed model enables the forecasting of investment risks, thereby facilitating the formulation of informed investment decisions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>3. Results and discussion</title>
      <p>Data for most of the report were derived from diverse databases, the Ministry of Commerce, and national statistical data, with a focal point on utilizing DNN to evaluate the financial risk of listed firms. This was achieved by leveraging the broad spectrum of variables embedded within China's foreign trade and investment data, necessitating the implementation of parameter transfer learning. The dataset tailored for the risk assessment of listed firms is denoted as “Finance,” whilst the dataset employed for gauging the financial risk of foreign trade investments by China is termed “Invest”. The juxtaposition of training results between parameter transfer learning and DNN-based risk assessment pertaining to China's ITI is elucidated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_6">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>The comparative analysis of training outcomes between DNN risk training for China's foreign trade investment and parameter transfer learning</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/9/img_QcA929RSc2eYutcV.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref> illustrates a decrement in training errors as the iteration number augments, enhancing judgement accuracy. The precision of the pre-trained Invest model is heightened during the Finance fine-tuning evaluation by the parameter-driven CNN, amplifying the model's convergence effect. This discovery underscores the robust generalization capability of CNN while formulating the risk associated with China's foreign trade investments. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>, derived from CNN, delineates the proficient prediction of China's ITI risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>].</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_7">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>Predictive accuracy of China's ITI risk as analysed by CNN</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/9/img_jc6tjm_FxpX9b3KA.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>As depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref>, the prediction of risk levels is compartmentalised into five discrete strata. A multitude of samples from China's foreign trade investment are examined across these risk levels utilising CNN for risk evaluation. The results intimate that CNN manifests a remarkable average accuracy of 90.38% in predicting China's foreign trade investment risk, exemplifying its formidable predictive capacity. Remarkably, CNN achieves an unblemished accuracy of 100% when evaluating severe, higher, and lower risks linked to China's foreign trade investment. Its acumen in ascertaining overall investment risk, nonetheless, languishes at a considerably reduced 68.18%. Predictive errors generally tend towards higher investment risks in scenarios involving general investment risk, albeit they remain manageable and customarily do not transgress one risk category. In summary, CNN's risk assessment concerning China's ITI proffers a comparatively comprehensive and nuanced appraisal of risk tiers.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>4. Conclusion</title>
      <p>In this investigation, CNN were utilised to examine the outcomes of risk training pertinent to China's ITI, alongside a scrutiny into the magnitude and dispersion of investments enacted by China and its ITI collaborators. The inclusion of risk pertaining to China's foreign investments under various risk determinants was also encompassed in the analysis. Results have demonstrated that during Finance fine-tuning examinations, the accuracy of the Invest pre-trained model was enhanced by the parameter-based CNN, culminating in superior model convergence effects. A thorough risk analysis of China's ITI by CNN has been discerned.</p><p>Distinctively, 14.8% of the total investment was channelled into trade and investment relations with the ASEAN. Subsequent investments into the European Union, the United States, and Japan witnessed augmentations of 14.0%, 12.4%, and 6.6% respectively, whilst the countries aligned with the B&amp;amp;R initiative experienced a 24.8% enhancement. Market supply and demand, coupled with the overarching economic climate, were identified as exerting a substantial influence on the risk of Chinese investments abroad. It was discerned that the classification of investment risk levels was substantially impacted by risk-affecting elements.</p><p>This exploration underscores the economic pertinence embedded within DL, whilst concurrently extending deeper into the domain of DL, furnishing a rigorous examination and research on China's ITI risk assessment and thereby constituting a valuable reference. The array of variables impacting China's trade and investment risk has been identified as comprehensive, yet imperfectly honed, introducing a degree of subjectivity into the analytical outcomes. For a more pinpointed analysis, subsequent research endeavours are recommended to enhance the variables determining China’s ITI risk. The synthesis of DL theory with finance and an embrace of the evolution of DL theory for ITI risk assessment may pave the way towards the establishment of a robust trade and investment risk assessment model.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>MN: conceptualization, methodology, data analysis, and writing-original draft, MZ: resources, and writing-review and editing.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p></p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>671-692</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Azmeh</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>Foster</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Echavarri</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/isr/viz033</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>The international trade regime and the quest for free digital trade</article-title>
          <source>Int. Stud. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>343-359</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Sahana</given-names>
              <surname>Udupa</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Shobha</given-names>
              <surname>Venkatraman</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Azam</given-names>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1527476419870516</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Millennial India: Global digital politics in context</article-title>
          <source>Telev. New Media</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>23</volume>
          <page-range>187-220</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Mira</given-names>
              <surname>Burri</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Rodrigo</given-names>
              <surname>Polanco</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jiel/jgz044</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Digital trade provisions in preferential trade agreements: Introducing a new dataset</article-title>
          <source>J. Int. Econ. Law</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>30</volume>
          <page-range>2038-2060</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Usama</given-names>
              <surname>Awan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Robert</given-names>
              <surname>Sroufe</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Muhammad</given-names>
              <surname>Shahbaz</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bse.2731</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Industry 4.0 and the circular economy: A literature review and recommendations for future research</article-title>
          <source>Bus. Strateg. Environ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>32</volume>
          <page-range>1535-1557</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Giovanni</given-names>
              <surname>Valensisi</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1057/s41287-020-00314-8</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>COVID-19 and global poverty: Are LDCs being left behind?</article-title>
          <source>Eur. J. Dev. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>56</volume>
          <page-range>2198-2212</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>He</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Li</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1540496X.2020.1785865</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>COVID-19's impact on stock prices across different sectors—An event study based on the Chinese stock market</article-title>
          <source>Emerg. Mark. Financ. Trade</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>56</volume>
          <page-range>2408-2421</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>Vidya</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Prabheesh</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1540496X.2020.1785426</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Implications of COVID-19 pandemic on the global trade networks</article-title>
          <source>Emerg. Mark. Financ. Trade</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>47</volume>
          <page-range>841-858</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
              <surname>Atherton</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
              <surname>Grijalva</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Roberts</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Robins</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0146167220949362</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Stability and change in personality traits and major life goals from college to midlife</article-title>
          <source>Pers. Soc. Psychol. Bull.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>1961-1975</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
              <surname>Sabirov</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Berdiyarov</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Yusupov</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Absalamov</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Berdibekov</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.47059/revistageintec.v11i2.1811</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Improving ways to increase the attitude of the investment environment</article-title>
          <source>Rev. Geintec-Gest. Inov. Tecnol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>55</volume>
          <page-range>101044</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Sardana</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jwb.2019.101044</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Multinational enterprises' risk mitigation strategies in emerging markets: A political coalition perspective</article-title>
          <source>J. World Bus.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>55</volume>
          <page-range>101040</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Buckley</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Clegg</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Voss</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jwb.2019.101040</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>The role of endogenous and exogenous risk in FDI entry choices</article-title>
          <source>J. World Bus.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>42</volume>
          <page-range>570-587</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Bashir</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Shahzad</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Q.</given-names>
              <surname>Ruan</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mde.3255</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>China's quest for economic dominance and energy consumption: Can Asian economies provide natural resources for the success of One Belt One Road?</article-title>
          <source>Managerial Decis. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>e000692</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Ashish</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Unsworth</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Martindale</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Sundar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Kavuri</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Sedda</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Farrier</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2020-000692</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>CPAP management of COVID-19 respiratory failure: A first quantitative analysis from an inpatient service evaluation</article-title>
          <source>BMJ Open Respir. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <page-range>1765703</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>An</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Gu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/20964129.2020.176570</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Flood risk assessment using the CV-TOPSIS method for the Belt and Road Initiative: An empirical study of Southeast Asia</article-title>
          <source>Ecosyst. Health Sustain.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>8375</page-range>
          <issue>20</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Khudyakova</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhuravlyov</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
              <surname>Varkova</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Aliukov</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Shmidt</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhuravlyov</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su12208375</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Improving approaches to strategic enterprise management in the context of sustainable development</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>27</volume>
          <page-range>469-481</page-range>
          <issue/>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
              <surname>Li</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Miao</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Kong</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-019-06517-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Risk grade assessment of sudden water pollution based on analytic hierarchy process and fuzzy comprehensive evaluation</article-title>
          <source>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>39</volume>
          <page-range>379-395</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Peng</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Shi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14615517.2019.1706386</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Social stability risk assessment: Status, trends and prospects—a case of land acquisition and resettlement in the hydropower sector</article-title>
          <source>Impact Assess. Proj. Apprais.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>337-342</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Gruszczynski</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/err.2020.29</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>The COVID-19 pandemic and international trade: Temporary turbulence or paradigm shift?</article-title>
          <source>Eur. J. Risk Regul.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>China will lower import tariffs on over 850 products from January 1, Finance Ministry Says</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.cnbc.com/2019/12/23/china-will-lower-import-tariffs-on-over-850-products-from-january-1.html</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <uri/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Governance in the 21st century</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.oecd.org/futures/17394484.pdf</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <uri/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>13876</page-range>
          <issue>18</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su151813876</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Impacts of the sustainable development of cross-border e-commerce pilot zones on regional economic growth</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume/>
          <page-range/>
          <issue/>
          <year>2010</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Heshmati</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.1667775</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>International trade and its effects on economic growth in China</article-title>
          <source>SSRN Electronic Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>1-26</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Periyasamy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Periyasami</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s44265-023-00016-z</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Rise of digital fashion and metaverse: Influence on sustainability</article-title>
          <source>Digit. Econ. Sustain. Dev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Baidu tops China’s AI public cloud services market</article-title>
          <source>, according to IDC Report. https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/baidu-tops-chinas-ai-public-cloud-services-market-according-to-idc-report-301094072.html</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <uri/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>141-159</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Urata</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/aepr.12279</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>US–Japan trade frictions: The past, the present, and implications for the US–China trade war</article-title>
          <source>Asian Econ. Policy Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>53</volume>
          <page-range>158-176</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10971475.2019.1688003</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>China's policy response to the China US trade war: An initial assessment</article-title>
          <source>Chin. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>56-68</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Goulard</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0974910119896642</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>The impact of the US–China trade war on the European Union</article-title>
          <source>Glob. J. Emerg. Mark. Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume/>
          <page-range>66-77</page-range>
          <issue/>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>de Salles</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20885/ejem.vol13.iss1.art6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Similarity evidence between the country risk and the idiosyncratic risk: An empirical study of the Brazilian case</article-title>
          <source>Econ. J. Emerg. Mark.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume/>
          <page-range/>
          <issue/>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Saqlain</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumam</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumam</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Phiangsungnoen</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2023.3292273</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Proportional distribution based pythagorean fuzzy fairly aggregation operators with multi-criteria decision-making</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Access</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>6880-6899</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Saqlain</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Riaz</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Imran</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Jarad</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3934/math.202334</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Distance and similarity measures of intuitionistic fuzzy hypersoft sets with application: Evaluation of air pollution in cities based on air quality index</article-title>
          <source>AIMS Math.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>55</volume>
          <page-range>5</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Saqlain</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Riaz</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
              <surname>Kiran</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumam</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Water quality evaluation using generalized correlation coefficient for m-polar neutrosophic hypersoft sets</article-title>
          <source>Neutrosophic Sets Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>2919-2930</page-range>
          <issue/>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Cao</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.H.</given-names>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10346-020-01473-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Landslide susceptibility prediction based on a semi-supervised multiple-layer perceptron model</article-title>
          <source>Landslides</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>117</volume>
          <page-range>30071-30078</page-range>
          <issue>48</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Bau</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Strobelt</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Lapedriza</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Torralba</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1907375117</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Understanding the role of individual units in a deep neural network</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>3572-3595</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Doan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>Barnes</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
              <surname>McQuin</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Caicedo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Goodman</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Carpenter</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Rees</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41596-021-00549-7</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Deepometry, a framework for applying supervised and weakly supervised deep learning to imaging cytometry</article-title>
          <source>Nat. Protoc.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>7518</page-range>
          <issue>22</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Latif</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Driss</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
              <surname>Boulila</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Huma</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Jamal</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Idrees</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Ahmad</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s21227518</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher"/>
          <article-title>Deep learning for the Industrial Internet of Things (IIoT): A comprehensive survey of techniques, implementation frameworks, potential applications, and future directions</article-title>
          <source>Sensors</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>