<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCGIRM</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Corporate Governance, Insurance, and Risk Management</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Corp. Gov. Insur. Risk Manag.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JCGIRM</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2757-0983</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-1923</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-okhT3vA_SvYDjjynkOVc9BO9uCXJ6Sgh</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jcgirm110202</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Adoption of Green Marketing Strategies and Challenges in Sustainable Business Practices: Insights from Indian Companies</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0005-5436-594X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Rawat</surname>
            <given-names>Gautam</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>rawatgautam75@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0002-1860-1114</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Pande</surname>
            <given-names>Mohan Chandra</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>pandemc2000@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Commerce, Dev Singh Bisht College (DSB Campus), 263002 Nainital, Uttarakhand, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">P.N.G. Government Post Graduate College, 244715 Ramnagar, Uttarakhand, India</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2024</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>98</fpage>
      <lpage>112</lpage>
      <page-range>98-112</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2024 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>The increasing global awareness of environmental issues has driven consumers toward eco-friendly products, making green marketing an essential aspect of contemporary business strategy. Originating in the 1980s, the concept of "going green" has significantly evolved, positioning sustainability at the forefront of corporate agendas. Indian companies, in particular, are increasingly adopting green marketing strategies to appeal to environmentally conscious consumers and maintain competitiveness in an eco-aware marketplace. However, significant challenges persist, primarily concerning perceived costs and the effectiveness of these strategies. This study aims to critically examine the landscape of green marketing in India, exploring the concept’s evolution, its strategic importance, and the challenges faced by businesses in this domain. By analyzing secondary data from academic literature and credible sources, the study provides a comprehensive overview of the current state of green marketing in India. The findings highlight that the integration of green marketing practices not only enhances corporate competitiveness but also contributes to broader environmental goals. Nevertheless, the successful adoption of these strategies requires overcoming substantial barriers, including misconceptions about financial implications and the need for greater governmental support. The paper concludes that every incremental effort towards environmental sustainability can significantly impact the resolution of contemporary ecological challenges. As such, the incorporation of green marketing strategies represents a logical and necessary progression for companies aiming to achieve long-term sustainability and societal benefits. The promotion of green marketing, supported by governmental incentives, is essential for fostering a greener future for current and future generations.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Green marketing</kwd>
        <kwd>Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR)</kwd>
        <kwd>Indian companies</kwd>
        <kwd>Sustainability</kwd>
        <kwd>Green incentives</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="2"/>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="39"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>In the wake of escalating environmental concerns and the pressing need for sustainable development, the global business landscape has undergone a profound transformation in recent years. This shift has given rise to the concept of green marketing, a strategic approach that involves the development, promotion, and distribution of products and services that are environmentally friendly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Polonsky, 2011</xref>). As one of the world's fastest-growing economies and a significant contributor to global carbon emissions, India finds itself at a critical juncture, facing both unique challenges and unprecedented opportunities in adopting green marketing strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Kumar &amp;amp; Ghodeswar, 2015</xref>).</p><p>The Indian business environment is characterized by a complex interplay of rapid industrialization, a burgeoning middle class with increasing purchasing power, and growing environmental awareness. These factors have created a multifaceted ecosystem where companies must navigate the delicate balance between economic growth and environmental responsibility. In this context, green marketing has emerged as a potential solution to this challenge, offering businesses the opportunity to differentiate themselves in a crowded marketplace, reduce their environmental footprint, and cater to the expanding segment of environmentally conscious consumers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Jain &amp;amp; Kaur, 2004</xref>).</p><p>However, the adoption of green marketing strategies in India is not without its challenges. Companies face a myriad of obstacles, including higher costs associated with eco-friendly products, a lack of consumer awareness and willingness to pay premium prices for green products, and regulatory uncertainties that can hinder long-term planning and investment in sustainable practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Mathur &amp;amp; Mathur, 2000</xref>). Understanding these challenges and the strategies employed by Indian companies to overcome them is crucial for developing effective green marketing initiatives and fostering a more sustainable business environment.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.1. The emergence of green marketing</title>
          
          <p>The concept of green marketing, also known as environmental marketing or ecological marketing, has its roots in the environmental movement of the 1970s and gained significant traction in the 1980s and 1990s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Peattie &amp;amp; Crane, 2005</xref>). It represents a holistic approach to marketing that considers the ecological and social impacts of products and services throughout their lifecycle, from production to disposal. Green marketing goes beyond mere promotional tactics; it encompasses product design, manufacturing processes, packaging, and distribution, all aimed at minimizing environmental harm while meeting consumer needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Fuller, 1999</xref>).</p><p>In the Indian context, the evolution of green marketing has been closely linked to the country's economic liberalization in the early 1990s and its subsequent rapid industrialization. As India opened its markets to global competition, it also became increasingly exposed to international environmental standards and sustainability practices. This exposure, coupled with growing domestic environmental concerns, has gradually shifted the focus of Indian businesses towards more sustainable practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Manaktola &amp;amp; Jauhari, 2007</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.2. The indian green marketing landscape</title>
          
          <p>India's green marketing landscape is characterized by a unique set of factors that both drive and hinder its adoption. On one hand, the country's rich cultural heritage, which emphasizes harmony with nature, provides a fertile ground for environmental consciousness. Traditional practices such as using natural materials and minimizing waste have been part of Indian society for centuries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Jain &amp;amp; Kaur, 2006</xref>). On the other hand, the pressing need for economic development and poverty alleviation often takes precedence over environmental concerns in policy-making and business decisions.</p><p>The Indian government has taken steps to promote sustainable development and environmental protection through various initiatives and regulations. The National Environment Policy of 2006, for instance, provides a framework for integrating environmental considerations into development planning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Ministry of Environment &amp;amp; Forests, 2006</xref>). Additionally, programs like the National Mission for a Green India aim to increase forest cover and enhance ecosystem services (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Ministry of Environment Forest &amp;amp; Climate Change, 2014</xref>).</p><p>These government initiatives, coupled with increasing global pressure to address climate change, have created a more conducive environment for green marketing in India. Many Indian companies, particularly in sectors such as fast-moving consumer goods (FMCG), automobiles, and information technology, have begun to incorporate sustainability into their business strategies and marketing efforts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Saxena &amp;amp; Khandelwal, 2010</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.3. Consumer perspectives on green marketing in india</title>
          
          <p>Understanding consumer attitudes and behaviors towards green products is crucial for the success of green marketing strategies. In India, consumer perspectives on green products are complex and multifaceted. While there is growing awareness of environmental issues, this awareness does not always translate into purchasing behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Jain &amp;amp; Kaur, 2004</xref>).</p><p>Several studies have explored the factors influencing green product purchase decisions among Indian consumers. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Bhatia &amp;amp; Jain (2013)</xref> found that environmental consciousness, product price, and quality were significant determinants of green purchase intentions. However, they also noted a significant gap between intentions and actual behavior, with many consumers expressing a willingness to buy green products but failing to do so in practice.</p><p>The price sensitivity of Indian consumers presents a particular challenge for green marketing. Many consumers are unwilling to pay premium prices for eco-friendly products, perceiving them as luxury items rather than necessities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Manaktola &amp;amp; Jauhari, 2007</xref>). This perception is compounded by the fact that many green products are indeed priced higher than their conventional counterparts due to increased production costs and smaller economies of scale.</p><p>Moreover, the lack of consumer trust in green claims made by companies is another significant barrier. Greenwashing, the practice of making misleading or false environmental claims, has eroded consumer confidence in green marketing messages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Nyilasy et al., 2014</xref>). This skepticism highlights the need for transparent and credible communication of environmental benefits by companies engaging in green marketing.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.4. Challenges in adopting green marketing strategies</title>
          
          <p>Indian companies face numerous challenges in adopting and implementing green marketing strategies. These challenges can be broadly categorized into economic, regulatory, and cultural factors.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>1.4.1 Economic challenges</title>
              
              <p>• Higher costs: Developing and producing eco-friendly products often involves higher costs due to the use of sustainable materials, the implementation of cleaner technologies, and smaller production scales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Ginsberg &amp;amp; Bloom, 2004</xref>).</p><p>• Limited access to green technologies: Many Indian companies, particularly small and medium enterprises (SMEs), struggle to access and afford the latest green technologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Nair &amp;amp; Menon, 2008</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>1.4.2 Regulatory challenges</title>
              
              <p>• Lack of clear and consistent regulations: The regulatory environment for green products and practices in India is often unclear and subject to frequent changes, creating uncertainty for businesses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Jain &amp;amp; Kaur, 2004</xref>).</p><p>• Inadequate enforcement: Even where environmental regulations exist, their enforcement is often inconsistent or lacking, which can discourage companies from investing in compliance.</p><p>• Limited incentives: The absence of strong government incentives for green initiatives, such as tax breaks or subsidies, can make it difficult for companies to justify the additional costs associated with green marketing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Kumar, 2016</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>1.4.3 Cultural challenges</title>
              
              <p>• Low environmental awareness: Despite growing concern, overall environmental awareness among Indian consumers remains relatively low, particularly in rural areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Maheshwari &amp;amp; Malhotra, 2011</xref>).</p><p>• Resistance to change: Traditional consumption patterns and a preference for familiar products can make it challenging to introduce new, eco-friendly alternatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Jain &amp;amp; Kaur, 2006</xref>).</p><p>• Diverse market: India's vast and diverse market, with significant variations in income levels, education, and cultural practices, makes it difficult to implement a one-size-fits-all green marketing strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Kumar &amp;amp; Ghodeswar, 2015</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.5. Strategies for overcoming challenges</title>
          
          <p>Despite these challenges, many Indian companies have successfully implemented green marketing strategies. Some key strategies employed include:</p><p>• Education and awareness: Companies are investing in consumer education programs to raise awareness about environmental issues and the benefits of green products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Maheshwari &amp;amp; Malhotra, 2011</xref>).</p><p>• Innovation in product design: Developing eco-friendly products that offer additional benefits, such as cost savings or improved performance, can help overcome price sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Saxena &amp;amp; Khandelwal, 2010</xref>).</p><p>• Strategic partnerships: Collaborating with NGOs, government agencies, and other businesses can help companies access resources, share costs, and increase the credibility of their green initiatives.</p><p>• Transparent communication: Providing clear, verifiable information about the environmental benefits of products can help build consumer trust and combat skepticism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Nyilasy et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>• Localization of strategies: Adapting green marketing approaches to suit local cultural contexts and consumer preferences can increase their effectiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Kumar &amp;amp; Ghodeswar, 2015</xref>).</p><p>The adoption of green marketing strategies by Indian companies represents a critical step towards a more sustainable business environment. While significant challenges persist, including cost concerns, a lack of consumer awareness, and regulatory hurdles, there are also promising signs of progress. By understanding these challenges and developing strategies to overcome them, Indian businesses can position themselves at the forefront of the global shift towards sustainability.</p><p>This research paper aims to contribute to this understanding by exploring the current state of green marketing adoption among Indian companies, identifying key challenges, and examining the strategies employed to overcome these obstacles. By doing so, this study seeks to provide valuable insights for businesses, policymakers, and researchers working towards a more sustainable future for India's economy.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Literature review</title>
      <p>The adoption of green marketing strategies in India has been the subject of numerous studies over the past few decades. This literature review synthesizes key findings from these studies, focusing on the evolution of green marketing in India, consumer behavior, challenges faced by companies, and successful strategies implemented by Indian companies.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Evolution of green marketing in india</title>
          
          <p>The evolution of green marketing in India has been closely tied to the country's economic liberalization and growing environmental awareness. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Prakash (2002)</xref> traced this evolution, noting that while environmental concerns began to influence Indian business practices in the 1990s, it wasn't until the early 2000s that green marketing gained significant traction.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Mishra &amp;amp; Sharma (2010)</xref> further elaborated on this timeline, identifying three distinct phases in the development of green marketing in India:</p><p>The Ecological Phase (1960s-1970s): Characterized by initial awareness of environmental issues and their relation to marketing activities.</p><p>The Environmental Phase (1980s-1990s): Marked by the emergence of cleaner technologies and a focus on designing innovative products to reduce environmental impact.</p><p>The Sustainable Phase (2000s-present): Defined by a more holistic approach to green marketing, integrating environmental considerations into all aspects of business strategy.</p><p>This evolution reflects a broader global trend towards sustainability, but with unique characteristics shaped by India's economic, social, and cultural context.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Consumer behavior and green marketing in india</title>
          
          <p>Understanding consumer attitudes and behaviors towards green products is crucial for effective green marketing strategies. Several studies have explored this aspect in the Indian context.</p><p>Building on this work, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">Yadav &amp;amp; Pathak (2017)</xref> examined the factors influencing green purchase intentions among Indian consumers. Their study revealed that environmental consciousness, product price, and quality were the most significant determinants of green purchase intentions. However, they also noted a significant gap between intentions and actual behavior, highlighting the complex nature of consumer decision-making in this area.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Jaiswal &amp;amp; Kant (2018)</xref> focused specifically on the attitudes of Indian youth towards green marketing. Their research indicated a growing environmental consciousness among younger consumers, suggesting the potential for increased demand for green products in the future. However, they also found that this awareness did not always translate into a willingness to pay premium prices for green products.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">Paul et al. (2016)</xref> delved deeper into the factors affecting green product purchase decisions. Their study identified five key factors: social appeal, environmental concern, environmental appeal of products, green product experience, and environmental friendliness of companies. This multifaceted approach to understanding consumer behavior provides valuable insights for companies developing green marketing strategies.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Challenges in adopting green marketing strategies</title>
          
          <p>The adoption of green marketing strategies by Indian companies faces several challenges, as highlighted by various researchers.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Rawat &amp;amp; Garga (2012)</xref> conducted an early analysis of the financial implications of green marketing strategies. They found that while some green initiatives led to positive market reactions, others resulted in negative returns, highlighting the economic risks associated with green marketing.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">Singh &amp;amp; Pandey (2012)</xref> identified several barriers to green marketing adoption in India, including:</p><p>• Lack of awareness among consumers</p><p>• High costs associated with developing and marketing green products</p><p>• Lack of appropriate infrastructure for recycling and waste management</p><p>• Absence of clear government policies and support</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Maheshwari (2014)</xref> expanded on these challenges, emphasizing the role of regulatory uncertainty and the difficulty of balancing short-term profitability with long-term sustainability goals. They argued that these challenges were particularly acute for small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) with limited resources.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Successful green marketing strategies in india</title>
          
          <p>Despite these challenges, several studies have documented successful green marketing initiatives by Indian companies.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Mishra &amp;amp; Sharma (2010)</xref> analyzed case studies of successful green marketing campaigns in India. They found that companies that integrated environmental considerations into their core business strategy, rather than treating them as add-ons, were more likely to succeed. They also emphasized the importance of clear and credible communication of environmental benefits to consumers.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Cherian &amp;amp; Jacob (2012)</xref>, while not focusing exclusively on India, provided insights applicable to the Indian context. They identified three successful approaches to developing sustainable products:</p><p>• Accentuate: Emphasizing existing green attributes of products</p><p>• Acquire: Buying or partnering with companies that already have green credentials</p><p>• Architect: Developing new green products or technologies from scratch</p><p>In the Indian context, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Vernekar &amp;amp; Wadhwa (2011)</xref> examined successful green marketing strategies in the automotive sector. The study highlighted the importance of technological innovation, government support, and effective communication in driving the adoption of eco-friendly vehicles.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.5. Research gap</title>
          
          <p>While the existing literature provides valuable insights into green marketing in India, several key areas remain underexplored or require further investigation. This study aims to address these research gaps:</p><p>While numerous studies have identified individual challenges in implementing green marketing strategies in India (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Maheshwari, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">Singh &amp;amp; Pandey, 2012</xref>), there is a lack of research that provides a comprehensive, integrated analysis of these challenges. This study aims to fill this gap by examining the interplay between various obstacles and their cumulative impact on green marketing adoption.</p><p>Much of the existing research on green marketing in India has focused on general consumer attitudes or broad business strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">Paul et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">Verma &amp;amp; Tanwar, 2019</xref>). However, there is a dearth of studies examining industry-specific green marketing strategies and their effectiveness. This research seeks to address this gap by investigating green marketing approaches across different sectors, providing more nuanced and actionable insights for businesses.</p><p>The majority of studies on green marketing in India have focused on short-term outcomes or consumer intentions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Jaiswal &amp;amp; Kant, 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">Yadav &amp;amp; Pathak, 2017</xref>). There is a notable lack of longitudinal research examining the long-term impact of green marketing strategies on both business performance and environmental outcomes. This study aims to contribute to filling this gap by incorporating a temporal dimension into the analysis of green marketing effectiveness.</p><p>Much of the existing research treats green marketing as a standalone strategy. However, there is a lack of studies examining how green marketing integrates with broader corporate sustainability initiatives in the Indian context. This research aims to explore the synergies and tensions between green marketing and other aspects of corporate sustainability.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Research methodology</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Research questions</title>
          
          <p>This study investigates green marketing, exploring its various opportunities and challenges within the Indian context. Additionally, the paper delves into the steps taken by Indian organizations to implement eco-friendly marketing strategies.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Structure of the paper</title>
          
          <p>This study is based on secondary data from scholarly articles and websites. The first part examines India's green marketing landscape. The second section reviews literature, analyzing the green marketing concept as explained by various scholars. The third segment highlights green marketing strategies, their limitations, advantages, and consumer acceptance in India thus far.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Scope of the study</title>
          
          <p>This study is specifically focused on the field of marketing, delving into the importance of green marketing principles within the Indian market. The research's scope is limited to this particular region, and a similar investigation could be carried out in other geographical areas beyond India or even in a global context. The concept of environmentally friendly marketing practices holds great significance for businesses aiming to achieve sustainability and meet consumer demands for eco-conscious products and services. By understanding the unique challenges and opportunities presented in the Indian market, companies can better tailor their strategies for success within this rapidly evolving landscape. Future research can expand upon these findings by examining green marketing trends and practices in other regions across the globe, identifying key similarities and differences that contribute to effective, eco-friendly marketing initiatives.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.4. Objectives of the study</title>
          
          <p>a. To understand the concept and benefits of green marketing.</p><p>b. To study and implementation of green marketing by Indian companies.</p><p>c. To know the challenges faced by the organization in the context of green marketing.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.5. Methodology</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.5.1 Research paradigm and philosophical underpinnings</title>
              
              <p>This study adopts a pragmatic research paradigm, acknowledging the complex and multifaceted nature of green marketing in the Indian context. The pragmatic approach allows for the integration of both interpretive and positivist elements, enabling a holistic understanding of the phenomenon under investigation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Creswell &amp;amp; Creswell, 2018</xref>). This philosophical stance aligns with the study's objectives of exploring both the quantifiable aspects of green marketing implementation and the nuanced challenges and opportunities within the Indian business ecosystem.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.5.2 Research design</title>
              
              <p>The research employs a qualitative, multiple case study design, drawing on the methodological frameworks proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">Yin (2018)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Eisenhardt (1989)</xref>. This approach facilitates an in-depth exploration of green marketing practices within their real-world context, allowing for the identification of patterns and theoretical constructs across diverse organizational settings.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.5.3 Data collection and sampling</title>
              
              <p>1. Secondary data sources</p><p>The study utilizes a comprehensive range of secondary data sources, including:</p><p>Peer-reviewed scholarly articles from high-impact journals in marketing, sustainability, and business management; Industry reports and white papers, government publications and policy documents, corporate sustainability reports, and official company websites. A systematic literature review methodology, as outlined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">Tranfield et al. (2003)</xref>, was employed to ensure a rigorous and replicable approach to data collection and synthesis.</p><p>2. Case selection</p><p>Twelve case studies of Indian corporations were selected using a purposive sampling strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Patton, 2014</xref>). The selection criteria included: Engagement in significant CSR activities, implementation of green marketing initiatives, representation of diverse industry sectors, availability of rich, detailed information on green marketing practices.</p><p>This sampling approach allows for theoretical replication and literal replication, enhancing the robustness of the findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">Yin, 2018</xref>).</p><p>Additionally, a cross-case analysis technique (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Miles &amp;amp; Huberman, 1994</xref>) is utilized to compare and contrast findings across the twelve case studies, facilitating the development of more robust and generalizable insights.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.5.4 Reliability and validity</title>
              
              <p>To ensure the reliability and validity of the research, several strategies are employed: Triangulation of data sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Denzin, 1978</xref>), peer debriefing and expert consultation, thick description of cases and contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Geertz, 1973</xref>), maintenance of a clear audit trail throughout the research process.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.5.5 Five ethical considerations</title>
              
              <p>Although the study primarily relies on publicly available secondary data, ethical considerations are still paramount. The research adheres to principles of academic integrity, ensuring proper citation and attribution of all sources. Care is taken to present findings objectively, without misrepresentation or undue criticism of the organizations studied.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.5.6 Limitations of this study</title>
              
              <p>The study acknowledges its limitations, including the reliance on secondary data and the focus on a limited number of cases within the Indian context. Future research could address these limitations by incorporating primary data collection methods and expanding the geographical scope to enable cross-cultural comparisons.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Understanding the concept of green marketing</title>
      <p>Green marketing, a widely popular concept in recent times, focuses on promoting products and services that are environmentally friendly. It involves employing sustainable business practices to benefit both the company and the environment. As more people become aware of the importance of safeguarding our planet for future generations, businesses have started to recognize the impact of their operations on the environment.</p><p>Incorporating green marketing strategies allows businesses to meet consumer demands for eco-conscious goods and services. This has led to the creation of an entirely new market segment consisting of environmentally-conscious consumers. Moreover, incorporating these practices into a company's operations often garners a positive reputation and boosts its brand image.</p><p>One primary aspect of green marketing is attributing value to environmental conservation through sustainable product manufacturing. This can encompass anything from sourcing raw materials in an environmentally friendly manner to minimizing waste during production. Another critical component is eco-friendly packaging, which emphasizes reduced plastic usage and recyclable materials.</p><p>Moreover, tapping into green marketing helps businesses connect with ethically-minded clientele who actively search for socially responsible products. When combined with transparent communication about their sustainable efforts, companies can foster trust and long-lasting customer loyalty while making a difference in reducing their carbon footprint.</p><p>Through effective advertising and promotion campaigns, green marketing can position a brand as environmentally conscious and responsible. It demonstrates to consumers the company's commitment to sustainability, creating a significant competitive advantage over other market players not engaging in eco-friendly practices.</p><p>However, it is crucial to uphold honesty and integrity within green marketing initiatives as customers are increasingly aware of “greenwashing,” a deceptive tactics some businesses use to promote false environmental concerns for profit. Therefore, maintaining genuine intent is key to ensuring long-term success with green marketing efforts.</p><p>In conclusion, the concept of green marketing is transforming the way businesses approach environmental stewardship by placing value on sustainable actions while meeting consumer demands for eco-friendly products and services. By striving for authentic initiative implementation across multiple aspects, such as sourcing, packaging, and promotional efforts, companies can cultivate a strong bond with environmentally conscious customers and create a positive brand image. Going green is no longer just an option but has become essential to gain a competitive edge in today's marketplace.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Advantages of adopting green marketing practices</title>
      <p>In today's world, humans grapple with innumerable desires while the resources remain regrettably insufficient, fostering a responsibility to maximize their usage. Green marketing is at the forefront of this movement, rapidly attaining popularity and receiving government endorsement for its sustainable actions. This approach encompasses the following key elements that contribute to its growing significance:</p><p>a. A crucial aspect of any business's social responsibility agenda is safeguarding the environment. By incorporating eco-friendly practices into their operations, companies can successfully combine environmental stewardship with strategic planning, ensuring that these two aspects mutually reinforce each other.</p><p>b. Environmental protection has prompted government agencies worldwide to implement regulations aimed at mitigating the hazardous waste produced by industries. These laws serve as a barrier between harmful industrial practices and the delicate balance of nature, ensuring that negative impacts on our surroundings are minimized.</p><p>c. Green marketing has emerged as an alluring prospect for environmentally conscious consumers, providing them with the satisfaction that comes from choosing products that align with their values. As awareness regarding environmental issues increases, so does the public’s proclivity for patronizing enterprises that endorse green initiatives.</p><p>d. Contrary to popular belief, green marketing methods also exhibit cost-effectiveness due to their reliance on recycling. By reusing certain materials rather than opting for entirely new ones, companies can reduce production costs significantly since recycled items are generally cheaper than those made from scratch.</p><p>e. Lastly, businesses that actively engage in environmentally-friendly practices maintain a distinct competitive advantage over those that do not prioritize sustainability. Through their socially responsible and ecologically sound policies, these trailblazing enterprises can foster customer loyalty and effectively set themselves apart from their less eco-minded counterparts.</p><p>Moreover, consumer behavior has been steadily evolving in response to global ecological crises such as climate change and resource depletion. Consequently, more and more individuals are demonstrating a preference for environmentally-sustainable products—a trend that is unlikely to wane anytime soon.</p><p>Governments across the globe have also begun imposing stricter regulations on industries to mitigate the adverse effects of their operations on the environment. By enforcing laws that promote responsible waste management and limit pollution, they have made it apparent that businesses can no longer neglect their role in preserving nature.</p><p>Furthermore, corporate organizations worldwide have started recognizing their responsibility towards conserving the environment and have begun adopting green marketing strategies. These organizations are working tirelessly to minimize waste, produce eco-friendly products, and adopt production processes with a lower environmental impact.</p><p>Some enterprises have even transcended merely adopting sustainable business practices by extending their commitment to educate customers about the importance of environmental conservation. By empowering consumers with knowledge concerning the benefits of eco-friendly choices, these companies actively participate in fostering long-term change—a step that ultimately reflects positively on their brand reputation and credibility.</p><p>In conclusion, green marketing's rising significance can be attributed not only to societal expectations but also to its inherent cost-saving potential and competitive edge for environmentally-conscious companies.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Green marketing practices uses by the indian companies</title>
      <p>TCS</p><p>• Tackle Pollution and CSR</p><p>In an effort to address climate change and its effects, TCS APAC has implemented a variety of eco-friendly initiatives throughout the region. These endeavors include tree planting efforts in countries such as the Philippines, Malaysia, Thailand, and China, as well as cleanup drives for beaches, rivers, and communal spaces in locations like Singapore, Japan, and Hong Kong. The TCS team actively contributes to environmental preservation on a global scale.</p><p>One notable highlight from their environmental endeavors is TCS Thailand's inaugural CSR event dedicated to coral reef conservation at the country level. This event further solidifies TCS's commitment to fighting against the negative impact of climate change.</p><p>Moreover, the theme of reducing plastic pollution is at the forefront of TCS's initiatives. As a result, plastic items such as straws, cutlery, and glasses have been eliminated across their operations. Additionally, all remaining forms of plastic waste are carefully sorted and sent for recycling when possible, minimizing the environmental footprint left behind by the organization.</p><p>Through these diverse efforts spanning different countries and cultures in the Asia Pacific region, TCS demonstrates genuine dedication to its environmental responsibility. By remaining steadfast in its commitment to sustainable practices and engaging in significant green initiatives throughout its geographical reach, TCS continues to do its part in combating climate change and supporting a healthy planet.</p><p>Dabur</p><p>• Using effluent treatment system (ETP)</p><p>Dabur HD, a highly reputed healthcare organization in India, has commenced its mission to cooperate with the government in realizing their objective of an open defecation-free (ODF) nation. To contribute to this initiative, Dabur HD plans to construct 1,200 rural household toilets across 28 villages by the close of this fiscal year. This project aims to drastically improve the quality of life for residents in rural regions while also promoting better sanitation and health standards.</p><p>In addition to their ODF efforts, Dabur India Limited has recently commissioned a new manufacturing facility situated in Tezpur, Assam. This state-of-the-art plant is equipped with an advanced effluent treatment system (ETP), which is designed to recycle the entirety of treated wastewater for utilization within the factory premises. Such innovative technology demonstrates Dabur India's commitment to adopting sustainable business practices and reducing their ecological footprint for the greater good.</p><p>In summary, Dabur HD's most recent endeavors showcase their dedication not only to trusted healthcare but also to social welfare and environmental conservation. Their work positively influences both the government's overall vision of an open defecation-free India and endorses resourceful solutions for a greener future. As they continue on this path, Dabur HD establishes itself as a true leader in the realm of healthcare and community development.</p><p>Hindustan Unilever</p><p>• Reduce water consumption(5R)</p><p>Hindustan Unilever Limited (HUL) stands as India's most prominent FMCG company, boasting a rich legacy exceeding eight decades. With over 35 diverse brands under its umbrella, covering 20 unique categories, HUL impacts the daily lives of millions of Indian consumers nationwide.</p><p>In their commitment to environmental sustainability, HUL has embarked on an ambitious project focused on barren land revitalization and water conservation and harvesting. This initiative pursues two primary objectives.</p><p>Firstly, HUL aims to significantly reduce water consumption within its own operations by adhering to the 5R principle – Reduce, Reuse, Recycle, Recover, and Renew. Through this approach, the company seeks to regenerate subsoil water tables at its facilities, thus lessening the strain on natural resources.</p><p>Secondly, HUL strives to aid neighboring villages in establishing suitable watershed development models. This enables communities to better manage water resources and promotes an eco-friendly approach to utilizing available water supplies.</p><p>Reliance industries limited</p><p>• Post-consumer waste</p><p>RIL specializes in refining, producing refined petroleum products, and petrochemicals such as basic chemicals, fertilizers, nitrogen compounds, plastic, and synthetic rubber in their primary forms. RECRON GREEN emerges from transforming post-consumer waste into new, eco-friendly products to mitigate material and resource waste. Reliance has pioneered a technology that repurposes post-consumer P.E.T. bottles into high-quality polyester.</p><p>RECRON FEEL FRESH textiles address the need for modern fabrics that combat sweat-induced bacterial growth, odor, microbial infestations, fading colors, and compromised performance. Recron's innovative solution incorporates silver—a long-admired antimicrobial element capable of deterring or even destroying various bacteria and fungi—into textiles. This results in RECRON FEEL FRESH products containing silver ions, granting permanent antimicrobial and antifungal properties to items made using these fibers.</p><p>Avenue Super-Marts Limited</p><p>• Green building</p><p>Green building encompasses both the design and implementation of environmentally conscious strategies throughout a structure's life cycle. Avenue Super-Marts Limited recently earned gold certificates for green building certification at 23 additional stores, bringing their total to 50 environmentally friendly establishments. The company actively advocates for the utilization of autoclaved aerated concrete (AAC) blocks in construction, which comprise up to 65% of recycled materials. This not only demonstrates their commitment to sustainable practices but also sets a positive example for other businesses in the industry. By prioritizing green building concepts in both design and construction, Avenue Super-Marts Limited helps pave the way for a more ecologically responsible future while maintaining their dedication to reducing their environmental impact over the life span of their structures.</p><p>Larsen and Toubro</p><p>• Water Conservation</p><p>Larsen and Toubro (L&amp;amp;T) Company, a reputable organization that prioritizes environmental conservation, has implemented several initiatives to protect the ecosystem. This includes establishing 24 water-positive campuses and a duo of carbon-neutral sites. A significant amount of rainfall - specifically, over 2400 million liters - is harvested each year through their state-of-the-art water harvesting structures. This innovative approach allows L&amp;amp;T to efficiently manage water resources and contribute to ecological balance.</p><p>In addition, a considerable portion of the company's revenue – 22% to be precise – is generated through the marketing of environmentally friendly products and services. By doing so, L&amp;amp;T not only bolsters its commitment to safeguarding the environment but also demonstrates its dedication to fostering sustainable practices in the industry.</p><p>Through these impressive measures, L&amp;amp;T Company leads by example in showcasing how effective environmental initiatives can have a direct impact on preserving valuable resources for future generations while maintaining profitability and progress in the corporate landscape.</p><p>ONGC</p><p>• Solar power system</p><p>The ONGC group is committed to promoting clean fuel usage in both its operations and transportation aspects. In March 2019, the first set of five electric vehicles was introduced to the offices of ONGC Videsh in Delhi as part of an experimental initiative. This move aimed not only at reducing reliance on fossil fuels but also at lowering air pollution levels.</p><p>Furthermore, ONGC Videsh installed a 5.25-kilowatt solar power system at a hospital in Sudan, ensuring a consistent power supply during daytime hours. This installation demonstrates the group's dedication to expanding renewable energy applications both locally and globally.</p><p>ONGC has also implemented a comprehensive strategy for managing water resources at its various locations. This plan encompasses minimizing water consumption during operations, increasing the utilization of recycled water in processes, and cultivating rainwater harvesting systems to restore groundwater resources. Through these combined efforts, the company is demonstrating its commitment to sustainable resource management and environmental conservation.</p><p>By implementing innovative clean energy solutions and carefully managing their impact on water resources, ONGC is making significant strides toward reducing their overall environmental footprint. These initiatives reflect the organization's understanding of the growing importance of sustainable practices across industries and illustrate their commitment to becoming an environmentally responsible corporate entity.</p><p>Asian paints</p><p>• Reduce water and electricity consumption</p><p>The company is highly committed to playing an instrumental role in environmental conservation efforts. In order to uphold this commitment, the organization implements a series of strategic measures aimed at promoting sustainability and reducing its environmental footprint. During the financial year 2022-2023, the company successfully managed to replenish an impressive 548 million liters of water, reflecting its dedication to preserving precious natural resources.</p><p>Furthermore, the company has made significant strides in utilizing clean energy sources by ensuring that 54% of its electricity consumption is derived from renewable resources. This demonstrates the company's forward-thinking approach towards embracing sustainable energy solutions and reducing its reliance on non-renewable sources.</p><p>In addition to its efforts in water conservation and renewable energy consumption, the company is ardently involved in waste management initiatives as well. Over 600,000 kilograms of single-use post-consumer plastic packaging materials have been tactfully diverted away from municipal landfills and water bodies. Through these waste management initiatives, the company effectively prevents further pollution and contamination of these critical environmental spaces.</p><p>ITC</p><p>• Waste management</p><p>ITC's prestigious "Well-being Out of Waste" (WOW) campaign concentrates on fostering consciousness, separation, gathering, and reusing municipal solid waste throughout the entire value chain. Over 89 lakh Indian citizens benefit from this ground-breaking initiative. ITC is committed to adopting a low-carbon growth approach by reducing specific energy consumption and augmenting renewable energy usage. The company derives approximately 41% of its overall energy needs from renewable sources, reflecting their dedication.</p><p>Utilizing ITC's top-notch fiber-line situated in Bhandrachalam, Classmate and Papercraft notebooks exemplify the environmental capital that the company has cultivated in its paper business. This facility is India's first ozone-treated elemental chlorine-free establishment, ensuring the highest quality products. Pioneering advances in technology, ITC has set up the nation's premier elemental chlorine-free fiber line armed with ozone bleaching technology. This state-of-the-art facility adheres to world-class environmental standards while promoting a greener and more sustainable future.</p><p>UltraTech cement</p><p>• Waste heat recovery systems</p><p>UltraTech, the largest cement producer in India, is consistently committed to playing a significant role in developing effective and responsible solutions to preserve the environment. In the financial year 2022-23, the company experienced a reduction of over 1.1% in specific direct greenhouse gas emissions, showcasing their dedication towards reducing their carbon footprint. As part of their sustainable efforts, the use of recycled materials also increased from 14.2% to 16.2%.</p><p>Moreover, they have invested in waste heat recovery systems to further enhance their eco-friendly initiatives. The installed capacity of these recovery systems has seen a commendable increase from 59 MW to 85 MW, reflecting the organization's continuous pursuit of implementing environmentally responsible practices across all aspects of its operations. By focusing on such sustainable measures, UltraTech aims to pave the way for other industry players and contribute significantly to a greener planet for generations to come.</p><p>Bharti Airtel</p><p>• Recycling electronic waste</p><p>Bharti Airtel Limited, a leading global telecommunications company, boasts operations spanning across 25 countries in Asia and Africa. In their annual report for the fiscal year 2022-23, Bharti Airtel announced a series of environmentally conscious initiatives. Among these green endeavors are the following:</p><p>Firstly, Bharti Airtel has made significant efforts in recycling electronic waste, successfully processing approximately 5,300 tons over the past two years. During this time, they have also refurbished more than 840,000 Direct-To-Home (DTH) setup boxes, further reducing pollution and conserving resources. This initiative not only minimizes hazardous waste disposal but also promotes a circular economy within the sector.</p><p>In addition to tackling e-waste, the company has taken considerable strides towards reducing paper usage. By implementing Aadhar-based paperless activation for over 96% of their prepaid wireless subscribers, Bharti Airtel has substantially decreased their carbon footprint while simultaneously streamlining customer onboarding processes.</p><p>Bharti Airtel's commitment to environmental sustainability is further showcased through their noteworthy reduction of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions resulting from network infrastructure. By achieving an impressive 83% decrease in CO<sub>2</sub> emissions per terabyte at the infrastructural level, the company ensures that its services are increasingly eco-friendly without compromising on quality.</p><p>Lastly, Bharti Airtel has made a conscious effort to prioritize renewable energy sources by increasing their procurement of clean energy by more than 15%. This shift towards renewables not only lessens the company's reliance on traditional energy generation methods but also supports the global transition to environmentally sustainable practices.</p><p>In conclusion, Bharti Airtel Limited's annual report highlights numerous green initiatives that demonstrate the company's dedication to environmental responsibility. Through actions such as recycling e-waste, implementing paperless activation processes for customers, cutting CO<sub>2</sub> emissions in network infrastructure, and investing in renewable energy sources, Bharti Airtel is playing a vital role in mitigating climate change and championing eco-friendly business practices within the telecommunications sector.</p><p>Infosys</p><p>• Solar photovoltaic (PV) plants and LEED platinum certifications</p><p>Infosys, a leading global technology services company, has taken significant strides towards sustainability by installing 2.7-megawatt solar PV plants across various campuses. This initiative aligns with the firm's commitment to reducing its carbon footprint and conserving energy. Between fiscal years 2008 and 2019, Infosys recorded a remarkable 50% reduction in per capita electricity consumption.</p><p>Furthermore, in 2019, the company's newly constructed SDB building at the Infosys Shanghai campus earned the coveted LEED Platinum certification, signifying its adherence to rigorous green building standards. This achievement is not isolated; several other facilities within the Infosys family have garnered similar recognitions: the Mysore campus, Mahindra City in Chennai, and their Chandigarh campus all boast LEED Platinum certifications.</p><p>To date, Infosys has completed an impressive 30 projects that meet the highest criteria for green building ratings. Cumulatively, these developments span over 19 million square feet of sustainably designed and energy-efficient spaces.</p><p>Water conservation is another key area in which Infosys has excelled. During the fiscal year 2018-19, they recycled an astonishing 2,666,279 kiloliters of water – a volume equivalent to nearly 85% of their total freshwater consumption during that period. By implementing state-of-the-art water-saving measures throughout its campuses, the Infosys team successfully minimized their dependence on freshwater for operational requirements.</p><p>In summary, Infosys demonstrates an unwavering commitment to environmental stewardship and sustainable practices across its campuses through energy conservation initiatives like solar PV plants and optimized electricity usage. These efforts have undoubtedly resulted in significant environmental benefits such as substantial reductions in electricity consumption and freshwater use. With numerous LEED Platinum-certified facilities to its name and millions of square feet dedicated to green building projects, Infosys stands as an exemplary model of corporate responsibility and environmental consciousness.</p><p>• Challenges faced by Indian companies for adopting green marketing practices</p><p>I. Cost considerations: Green marketing focuses on promoting eco-friendly products and services. In order to do this effectively, companies must invest significantly in research and development, product innovation, and supplementary promotional activities. These expenditures inevitably lead to an escalation in overall costs.</p><p>II. Customer persuasion: The concept of green marketing remains relatively unfamiliar in India. Consequently, businesses face the challenge of ensuring they take all necessary measures to educate and persuade their target audiences about the advantages of environmentally-friendly products and services. Establishing loyal customers is essential for long-term success.</p><p>III. Reaching rural India: While urban consumers tend to have a better understanding of green marketing, their rural counterparts are often less exposed to such initiatives. Smaller companies in rural India have yet to fully comprehend the significance of green marketing for sustainable development. Therefore, it is necessary to tailor strategies that will foster awareness and engagement in these remote areas.</p><p>IV. Overcoming stakeholder resistance: Companies that embrace green marketing concepts need to work diligently in order to convince stakeholders of the long-term benefits associated with such practices. Unfortunately, they sometimes encounter non-cooperation from stakeholders who might be skeptical or reluctant to acknowledge these long-term advantages as valid arguments.</p><p>V. Sustainability concerns: Initially, firms that adopt eco-friendly approaches may experience lower profit margins due to the higher costs associated with renewable materials, recyclable products, and the implementation of green technologies. Moreover, these environmentally-conscious approaches are typically more expensive than traditional methods. Green marketing strategies ultimately aim for enduring profitability instead of immediate gains.</p><p>To ensure that green marketing becomes widely accepted across India, both urban and rural regions need targeted educational campaigns about its long-lasting benefits. These endeavors would help raise public awareness about environmental issues and emphasize the critical role green products and services can play in addressing them. Companies must make sure they communicate effectively with their target audience in a way that resonates with them culturally and linguistically.</p><p>Additionally, collaboration among businesses, government agencies, and non-governmental organizations would be essential in creating a robust support system for green marketing initiatives. This network would help in sharing knowledge, resources, and best practices across various stakeholders. It would also provide reinforcement for companies that face resistance or skepticism from traditionalist partners or investors.</p><p>To incentivize companies to adopt green marketing tactics, government bodies could consider offering tax breaks or financial incentives to those that invest in eco-friendly strategies. This approach would help reduce the financial burden on businesses and encourage more of them to implement sustainable practices.</p><p>Training and development programs aimed at educating employees about the importance of green marketing and sustainable development would be another significant step forward. By fostering a workforce that is well-versed in these concepts, companies can better align their operations with environmental best practices.</p><p>Lastly, implementing green marketing principles should be viewed as a long-term goal for businesses rather than an immediate profit-generating tactic. As global awareness and demand for sustainable solutions continue to grow, early adoption of these strategies will establish a strong brand reputation and a competitive advantage in the marketplace.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>7. Result and discussion</title>
      <p>Green marketing revolves around the triple bottom line principle and encompasses more than creating environmentally friendly products. It has its own unique marketing mix, including green products, brand experience, brand image, trust, and satisfaction. Green consumers exhibit strong cognitive behavior, showing interest in the product's ingredients, manufacturing process, and supply chain. Thus, greenwashing can damage a brand as it erodes trust.</p><p>As green consumers form a niche segment, building a solid brand image is vital for long-term success. To design an effective green marketing strategy, companies should adhere to the following guidelines:</p><p>a. Establish a clear green objective and communicate it within the organization. Employees, managers, and executives must understand this vision before implementing marketing strategies.</p><p>b. Avoid using symbolic "green" products that can diminish consumer trust. Instead, focus on ensuring that the product's utilitarian benefits align with eco-friendly concepts.</p><p>c. Communicate sustainability through both the product and packaging to demonstrate the company's genuine commitment to environmental responsibility.</p><p>d. Emphasize transparency as a crucial factor in earning and maintaining customer loyalty in the green market space.</p><p>By adhering to these principles, firms can successfully engage with environmentally conscious consumers and thrive in the competitive green marketing landscape.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>8. Conclusion</title>
      <p>In India, the concept of green marketing remains in its infancy for many companies. Recognizing the many benefits of adopting environmentally-friendly practices in the long run, Indian firms have become increasingly committed to implementing green marketing strategies. Over the past decade to 15 years, more and more Indian companies have shifted their focus toward these sustainable practices.</p><p>Customer attitudes have also evolved substantially over time. They are now willing to pay a premium for products and services that contribute to environmental preservation efforts. As a result, organizations have come to understand that incorporating green marketing strategies into their operations is no longer optional but essential to navigating an intensely competitive business landscape.</p><p>In addition to boosting an organization's public image, green marketing initiatives offer numerous other advantages. For one, these strategies contribute to conserving our planet's resources by minimizing waste generation and promoting cost efficiencies. Furthermore, they foster employee satisfaction and benefit society as a whole.</p><p>However, it is important not to disregard the economic aspects of marketing when adopting a green approach. Companies need to carefully balance their pursuit of environmental sustainability with maintaining profitability and brand success.</p><p>As green marketers continue to gain momentum within India, they can expect increasing support from both government agencies and consumers alike. Consequently, this backing serves as a strong indication that green marketing practices will continue to expand across the country as organizations recognize the importance of sustainable development in ensuring their long-term success.</p><p>The rise of green marketing has prompted businesses in India to explore various ways of incorporating eco-friendly practices into their operations. By focusing on sustainable materials, waste reduction methods, energy conservation measures, and product lifecycle management, companies are striving to create a greener marketplace.</p><p>From packaging materials made from recycled or biodegradable components to energy-efficient manufacturing processes and facilities, these efforts aim to mitigate negative environmental impacts. In doing so, businesses are making products more appealing not only to eco-conscious consumers but also to regulatory bodies that enforce environmental compliance standards.</p><p>It is evident that Indian consumers are increasingly drawn to brands that prioritize sustainability and CSR. As awareness about the consequences of climate change and environmental degradation grows, consumers are more likely than ever to support companies that actively invest in greener practices.</p><p>While green marketing can undeniably lead to short-term cost implications, companies that adopt these strategies will likely realize long-term benefits. Examples of such advantages include improved customer loyalty, enhanced brand reputation, and a heightened sense of corporate ethics. Moreover, green initiatives often translate into cost savings through energy efficiency gains and waste reduction measures.</p><p>The adoption of green marketing in India is still relatively new, with much room for improvement on both organizational and consumer levels. Businesses need to prioritize communication efforts and publicize their commitment to sustainability as part of their marketing mix. Educating consumers on the benefits of eco-friendly products and services will play a crucial role in driving demand for environmentally responsible offerings.</p><p>Ultimately, the continued growth of green marketing in India will depend on the collective efforts of businesses, consumers, and government agencies alike.</p><p>It is with an optimistic outlook that we anticipate all those concerned with our environment to collaborate in preserving it, by reviving the ancient philosophy of "Vasudev Kutumbakam". This concept emphasizes that the entire world, including Earth itself, constitutes a unified family. This familial connection extends to various organisms within the ecosystem, such as plants, trees, birds, and animals. Each of these living beings possesses an atma (soul) and is an integral part of our kotumba (family). As such, conservation becomes an essential responsibility.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>9. The role of government and policy makers</title>
      <p>The Indian government plays a crucial role in shaping the environment for green marketing. Policy interventions can significantly influence both consumer behavior and corporate practices. Some key areas where government action can support green marketing include:</p><p>• Strengthening and clarifying environmental regulations: Developing clear, consistent, and enforceable environmental standards can provide a level playing field for businesses and increase consumer confidence in green claims.</p><p>• Providing incentives: Offering tax breaks, subsidies, or other financial incentives for eco-friendly products and practices can help offset the higher costs often associated with green initiatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Kumar, 2016</xref>).</p><p>• Supporting research and development: Government funding for research into sustainable technologies and practices can drive innovation and make green solutions more accessible to businesses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Nair &amp;amp; Menon, 2008</xref>).</p><p>• Promoting eco-labeling: Developing and promoting standardized eco-labeling schemes can help consumers make informed choices and reduce confusion in the marketplace (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Maheshwari &amp;amp; Malhotra, 2011</xref>).</p><p>• Public procurement policies: Incorporating environmental criteria into government procurement policies can create a significant market for green products and services (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">OECD, 2015</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>10. Future prospects and research directions</title>
      <p>As India continues to grapple with the dual challenges of economic development and environmental protection, the role of green marketing is likely to become increasingly important. Several trends suggest a promising future for green marketing in India:</p><p>• Growing environmental awareness: As education levels rise and information becomes more accessible, environmental awareness among Indian consumers is likely to increase, potentially driving demand for green products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Kumar &amp;amp; Ghodeswar, 2015</xref>).</p><p>• Technological advancements: Ongoing innovations in clean technologies are likely to make green products more affordable and accessible over time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Nair &amp;amp; Menon, 2008</xref>).</p><p>• International pressure: As India becomes more integrated into the global economy, international pressure to adopt sustainable practices is likely to intensify, potentially driving more companies towards green marketing.</p><p>• Urbanization: The rapid urbanization of India is likely to increase environmental concerns in cities, potentially creating new markets for green products and services (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">Sankhe et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>However, to realize this potential, researchers will require continued research and innovation in several areas:</p><p>• Consumer behavior: More in-depth studies on the factors influencing green purchase decisions in different segments of the Indian market are needed to inform effective marketing strategies.</p><p>• Measurement and reporting: Developing standardized methods for measuring and reporting the environmental impact of products and services can help increase transparency and consumer trust.</p><p>• Green supply chains: Research into sustainable supply chain management practices tailored to the Indian context can help companies implement more holistic green marketing strategies.</p><p>• Policy effectiveness: Evaluating the impact of different policy interventions on green marketing adoption can inform more effective government strategies.</p><p>• Sector-specific strategies: Exploring green marketing approaches tailored to different industries can provide valuable insights for businesses across various sectors.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>36</issue>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bhatia</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5070/g313618392</pub-id>
          <article-title>Green marketing: A study of consumer perception and preferences in India</article-title>
          <source>Electronic Green Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>117-126</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2012</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cherian</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacob</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5539/ass.v8n12p117</pub-id>
          <article-title>Green marketing: A study of consumers' attitude towards environment friendly products</article-title>
          <source>Asian Social Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Creswell</surname>
              <given-names>J. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Creswell</surname>
              <given-names>J. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Research Design: Qualitative, Quantitative, and Mixed Methods Approaches (Fifth Edition)</source>
          <publisher-name>Sage, Los Angeles</publisher-name>
          <year>2018</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>339-357</page-range>
          <year>1978</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Denzin</surname>
              <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Triangulation: A case for methodological evaluation and combination</article-title>
          <source>Sociol. Methods</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>532-550</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>1989</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eisenhardt</surname>
              <given-names>Kathleen M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/258557</pub-id>
          <article-title>Building theories from case study research</article-title>
          <source>The Academy of Management Review</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fuller</surname>
              <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Sustainable Marketing: Managerial-Ecological Issues</source>
          <publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name>
          <year>1999</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geertz</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The Interpretation of Cultures</source>
          <publisher-name>New York, NY: Basic Books</publisher-name>
          <year>1973</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>46</volume>
          <page-range>79-84</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ginsberg</surname>
              <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bloom</surname>
              <given-names>P. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Choosing the right green marketing strategy</article-title>
          <source>MIT Sloan Manag. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>187-205</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaur</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/097215090400500203</pub-id>
          <article-title>Green marketing: An attitudinal and behavioural analysis of Indian consumers</article-title>
          <source>Global Business Review</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>107-146</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2006</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>Sanjay K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaur</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1300/j046v18n03_06</pub-id>
          <article-title>Role of socio-demographics in segmenting and profiling green consumers: An exploratory study of consumers in India</article-title>
          <source>Journal of International Consumer Marketing</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>41</volume>
          <page-range>60-69</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jaiswal</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kant</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jretconser.2017.11.008</pub-id>
          <article-title>Green purchasing behaviour: A conceptual framework and empirical investigation of Indian consumers</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>34</volume>
          <page-range>137-158</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/mip-03-2015-0061</pub-id>
          <article-title>State of green marketing research over 25 years (1990-2014)</article-title>
          <source>Mark. Intell. Plan.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>33</volume>
          <page-range>330-347</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghodeswar</surname>
              <given-names>B. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/mip-03-2014-0068</pub-id>
          <article-title>Factors affecting consumers’ green product purchase decisions</article-title>
          <source>Mark. Intell. Plan.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>1-15</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maheshwari</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malhotra</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Green marketing: A study on Indian youth</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Manag. Strateg.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>1-14</page-range>
          <issue>1/4</issue>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maheshwari</surname>
              <given-names>S. P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Awareness of green marketing and its influence on buying behavior of consumers: Special reference to Madhya Pradesh, India</article-title>
          <source>AIMA J. Manag. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>19</volume>
          <page-range>364-377</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2007</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manaktola</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jauhari</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/09596110710757534</pub-id>
          <article-title>Exploring consumer attitude and behaviour towards green practices in the lodging industry in India</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Contemporary Hospitality Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>50</volume>
          <page-range>193-200</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2000</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mathur</surname>
              <given-names>L. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mathur</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0148-2963(99)00032-6</pub-id>
          <article-title>An analysis of the wealth effects of green marketing strategies</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miles</surname>
              <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huberman</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Qualitative Data Analysis: An Expanded Sourcebook</source>
          <publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name>
          <year>1994</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>National Mission for a Green India</article-title>
          <source>, https://moef.gov.in/green-india-mission-gim</source>
          <year>2014</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>National Environment Policy 2006</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.india.gov.in/national-environment-policy-2006</source>
          <year>2006</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>9-14</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mishra</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Green marketing in India: Emerging opportunities and challenges</article-title>
          <source>J. Eng. Sci. Manag. Educ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>467-479</page-range>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nair</surname>
              <given-names>S. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menon</surname>
              <given-names>C. G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bse.586</pub-id>
          <article-title>An environmental marketing system–A proposed model based on Indian experience</article-title>
          <source>Business Strategy and the Environment</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>125</volume>
          <page-range>693-707</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nyilasy</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gangadharbatla</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paladino</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10551-013-1944-3</pub-id>
          <article-title>Perceived greenwashing: The interactive effects of green advertising and corporate environmental performance on consumer reactions</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Business Ethics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>Going Green: Best Practices for Sustainable Procurement</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.oecd.org/en/publications/going-green-best-practices-for-sustainable-procurement_3291acbf-en.html</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <publisher-name>OECD Publishing</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Patton</surname>
              <given-names>M. Q.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Qualitative Research and Evaluation Methods (4th ed.)</source>
          <publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>123-134</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paul</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Modi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patel</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jretconser.2015.11.006</pub-id>
          <article-title>Predicting green product consumption using theory of planned behavior and reasoned action</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>357-370</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2005</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peattie</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crane</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/13522750510619733</pub-id>
          <article-title>Green marketing: Legend, myth, farce or prophesy?</article-title>
          <source>Qualitative Market Research: An International Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>64</volume>
          <page-range>1311-1319</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Polonsky</surname>
              <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2011.01.016</pub-id>
          <article-title>Transformative green marketing: Impediments and opportunities</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>285-297</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2002</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prakash</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bse.338</pub-id>
          <article-title>Green marketing, public policy and managerial strategies</article-title>
          <source>Business Strategy and the Environment</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>2111545</page-range>
          <year>2012</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rawat</surname>
              <given-names>S. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garga</surname>
              <given-names>P. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.2111545</pub-id>
          <article-title>Understanding consumer behaviour towards green cosmetics</article-title>
          <source>SSRN Electronic Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sankhe</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vittal</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dobbs</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gulati</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ablett</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paul</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanghvi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sethy</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>India's Urban Awakening: Building Inclusive Cities, Sustaining Economic Growth</source>
          <publisher-name>Mumbai: McKinsey Global Institute</publisher-name>
          <year>2010</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>6</volume>
          <page-range>277-291</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saxena</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khandelwal</surname>
              <given-names>P. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Can green marketing be used as a tool for sustainable growth?: A study performed on consumers in India-An emerging economy</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Environ. Cult. Econ. Soc. Sustain.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>22-30</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2012</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>P. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pandey</surname>
              <given-names>K. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Green marketing: Policies and practices for sustainable development</article-title>
          <source>Integr. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>207-222</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2003</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tranfield</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Denyer</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smart</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-8551.00375</pub-id>
          <article-title>Towards a methodology for developing evidence‐informed management knowledge by means of systematic review</article-title>
          <source>British Journal of Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>51-61</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verma</surname>
              <given-names>V. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanwar</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Green marketing: An exploratory study on Indian youth</article-title>
          <source>J. Manag. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>65-74</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vernekar</surname>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wadhwa</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Green consumption: An empirical study of consumers attitudes and perception regarding eco-friendly FMCG products, with special reference to Delhi and NCR region</article-title>
          <source>Opinion</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Wipro’s solutions to sustainability for an imperishable future</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.wipro.com/sustainability/</source>
          <year>2022</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>134</volume>
          <page-range>114-122</page-range>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yadav</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pathak</surname>
              <given-names>G. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2016.12.019</pub-id>
          <article-title>Determinants of consumers' green purchase behavior in a developing nation: Applying and extending the theory of planned behavior</article-title>
          <source>Ecological Economics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yin</surname>
              <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Case Study Research and Applications: Design and Methods (6th ed.)</source>
          <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>
          <year>2018</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>