<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IDA</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Information Dynamics and Applications</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Inf. Dyn. Appl.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IDA</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2958-1494</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-1486</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-PTDu91iFLCV2lh2kdnG9ZGxDxwsrurLS</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/ida030203</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Enhancing Pneumonia Diagnosis with Transfer Learning: A Deep Learning Approach</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5298-9170</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ashtagi</surname>
            <given-names>Rashmi</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>rashmi.ashtagi@vit.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-0555-7041</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Khanapurkar</surname>
            <given-names>Nitin</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>nitin.khanapurkar@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0005-8416-1438</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Patil</surname>
            <given-names>Abhijeet R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>abhijeetrpatil@ymail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_4">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-3381-9333</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Sarmalkar</surname>
            <given-names>Vinaya</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>vinus0648@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_5">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-4241-3960</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Chaugule</surname>
            <given-names>Balaji</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>Balaji.chaugule@zealeducation.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_6">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9762-8739</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Naveen</surname>
            <given-names>H. M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>kasinathnaveen@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Computer Engineering, Vishwakarma Institute of Technology, 411037 Pune, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">BCA Department, Bharatesh College of Computer Applications, 590001 Belagavi, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">RPD PU College of Arts and Commerce, 590006 Belagavi, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_4">Computer Science and Engineering Department, Jain College of Engineering and Research, 590008 Belagavi, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_5">Department of Information Technology, Zeal College of Engineering and Research, 411041 Pune, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff_6">Department of Mechanical Engineering, RYM Engineering College, 583104 Ballari, India</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2024</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>104</fpage>
      <lpage>124</lpage>
      <page-range>104-124</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2024 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>The significant impact of pneumonia on public health, particularly among vulnerable populations, underscores the critical need for early detection and treatment. This research leverages the National Institutes of Health (NIH) chest X-ray dataset, employing a comprehensive exploratory data analysis (EDA) to examine patient demographics, X-ray perspectives, and pixel-level evaluations. A pre-trained Visual Geometry Group (VGG) 16 model is integrated into the proposed architecture, emphasizing the synergy between robust machine learning techniques and EDA insights to enhance diagnostic accuracy. Rigorous data preparation methods are utilized to ensure dataset reliability, addressing missing data and sanitizing demographic information. The study not only provides valuable insights into pneumonia-related trends but also establishes a foundation for future advancements in medical diagnostics. Detailed results are presented, including disease distribution, model performance metrics, and clinical implications, highlighting the potential of machine learning models to support accurate and timely clinical decision-making. This integration of advanced technologies into traditional healthcare practices is expected to improve patient outcomes. Future directions include enhancing model sensitivity, incorporating diverse datasets, and collaborating with medical professionals to validate and implement the system in clinical settings. These efforts are anticipated to revolutionize pneumonia diagnosis and broader medical diagnostics. This work offers comprehensive code for developing and optimizing deep learning (DL) models for medical image classification, focusing on pneumonia detection in X-ray images. The code outlines the construction of the model using pre-trained architectures such as VGG16, detailing essential preparation steps including image augmentation and metadata parsing. Tools for data separation, generator creation, and callback training for monitoring are provided. Additionally, the code facilitates performance assessment through various metrics, including the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve and F1-score. By providing a systematic framework, this research aims to accelerate the development process for researchers in medical image processing and expedite the creation of accurate diagnostic tools.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Pneumonia diagnosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Machine learning</kwd>
        <kwd>Chest X-ray dataset</kwd>
        <kwd>Exploratory data analysis</kwd>
        <kwd>Convolutional neural network</kwd>
        <kwd>Pre-trained VGG16 model</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="6"/>
        <fig-count count="12"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <ref-count count="20"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>As a common respiratory illness, pneumonia continues to be a major global health concern with substantial effects on public health. This infectious disease mostly affects the lungs, inflames the air sacs and significantly strains the global healthcare system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>]. A significant portion of hospital admissions are caused by pneumonia, which mostly affects susceptible groups such as young children, the elderly, and those with weakened immune systems. It is difficult to diagnose and treat the illness since it is linked to a variety of causative organisms, such as fungi, viruses, and bacteria. Pneumonia's tendency to worsen and cause serious complications frequently results in respiratory failure and death, emphasizing how serious the illness is. Understanding and early detection of pneumonia are critical for successful intervention and public health management, as the illness contributes significantly to morbidity and mortality. Within this framework, the application of cutting-edge technologies, including machine learning, presents the potential for improving the precision of diagnosis and accelerating prompt medical interventions, ultimately tackling the complex issues raised by pneumonia worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>].</p><p>In the context of pneumonia, the crucial consequences for patient outcomes and public health make early identification and response imperative. When pneumonia is detected early, medical practitioners can take appropriate and timely action to treat the patient, lowering the chance of complications and stopping the infection from progressing to more serious stages. The execution of tailored treatment measures, such as administering certain antimicrobial drugs and supportive care, is made easier by early diagnosis, enhancing the effectiveness of therapeutic interventions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. Early response also helps to limit the spread of infectious organisms, which lessens the strain on healthcare systems and averts possible epidemics. From the standpoint of global health, prompt diagnosis prevents death. It facilitates the effective use of resources, reducing the negative effects on society and the economy of extended illness and hospital stays. As a result, the comprehensive care of pneumonia relies heavily on early identification and intervention, which promotes better patient outcomes and the general well-being of communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>].</p><p>By offering cutting-edge instruments for precise and effective illness diagnosis, machine learning has shown itself to be a transformative force in the field of medical diagnostics. DL models, in particular, which are machine learning algorithms, have proven to be exceptionally adept at evaluating complicated medical data, including genetic data, imaging investigations, and clinical records. Regarding diagnosis, machine learning is particularly good at pattern identification. It can detect complex and nuanced patterns that point to a wide range of diseases, frequently better than humans. This technology has great potential to improve the precision of diagnoses, expedite diagnostic procedures, and enable customized treatment regimens. Large datasets allow machine learning algorithms to learn from a variety of patient profiles, which facilitates the creation of reliable diagnostic models that can be used for a wide range of populations. Machine learning improves early disease detection accuracy and makes healthcare systems more effective and efficient overall, opening the door to more proactive and individualized patient treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>].</p><p>The suggested approach delves into the subtleties of the NIH chest X-ray dataset by building upon a foundation of rigorous EDA. The EDA looks into a number of topics, including comorbidities, X-ray perspectives, patient demographics, and pixel-by-pixel evaluations of imaging data. This thorough research provides important insights into the larger context of pneumonia-related diseases and illuminates the distribution and features of pneumonia cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. Next, a convolutional neural network (CNN) architecture is presented in the study, which incorporates a pre-trained VGG16 model for feature extraction. Global average pooling and dense layers with batch normalization and dropout for the best learning are the next layers. Intending to improve diagnostic accuracy, the model combines the capability of powerful machine learning algorithms with exploratory data insights to identify complex patterns within chest X-ray pictures that may indicate pneumonia. By taking a comprehensive approach, the research aims to advance pneumonia diagnosis and promote more accurate and efficient clinical decision-making [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>].</p><p>The accurate and prompt diagnosis of pneumonia in chest X-ray pictures is the central problem addressed in this study. This identification is necessary for efficient patient care and management. Pneumonia continues to be a major global health concern, especially in light of its potential for serious consequences and death if it is not identified and treated quickly. However, it can be difficult and time-consuming for radiologists to diagnose pneumonia from chest X-ray pictures. Machine learning-based automated systems present a viable way to speed up diagnosis and increase pneumonia detection precision. The goal is to improve patient outcomes, lower diagnostic mistakes, and improve healthcare delivery through the development and implementation of such systems.</p><p>This study is spurred by the urgent need to solve the diagnostic difficulties related to pneumonia, a common and sometimes fatal respiratory illness. Even with advances in medical imaging technology, radiologists' subjectivity and variability often make it difficult to interpret chest X-ray pictures effectively for pneumonia. In addition, the growing need for medical services and the lack of radiological knowledge in some areas highlight how urgent it is to develop automated tools that can help diagnose pneumonia. This study attempts to create a solid and trustworthy algorithm that can precisely identify pneumonia from chest X-ray pictures utilizing the capabilities of machine learning and large-scale datasets like the NIH chest X-ray dataset. The ultimate objective is to develop a tool that can enhance radiologists' skills, increase diagnostic precision, and enable prompt intervention for pneumonia patients.</p><p>Despite a global decline in child mortality, pneumonia remains a significant public health challenge. The World Health Organization (WHO) forecasts that 5 million people died in 2019, with 672,000 of the deaths occurring in children under the age of five. It is the leading cause of death from infectious diseases worldwide and is most commonly found in older adults and children. According to statistics, pneumonia is the ninth most common cause of mortality in the United States. It accounts for around 1.3 million emergency room (ER) visits each year and costs the country over \$10 billion in medical expenses. It is important to follow up on early clinical diagnosis and vaccination to reduce this pervasive hazard.</p><p>In contrast to other DL models, VGG16 has a relatively simple structure, which makes it the preferable model for medical imaging diagnostics. However, its depth and convolutional layers enable it to extract data from images well. Because large filters are smaller than 3x3 filters, it is better to employ them. This allows for the capture of minute details that are crucial for identifying anomalies in scans. Furthermore, VGG16 outperforms alternative model organizations in terms of the transfer learning process with limited medical imagery data because of the well-trained weights in large databases like ImageNet. The combination of its complex methodology and relatively simple interface renders VGG16 appropriate for highly accurate and precise image classification applications.</p><p>Pneumonia has serious consequences for public health, particularly for vulnerable groups, which emphasizes the critical need for early diagnosis and treatment. The study employs a comprehensive EDA technique to investigate patient demographics, X-ray views, and pixel-by-pixel evaluations using the NIH chest X-ray dataset. The proposed model architecture incorporates a pre-trained VGG16 model and emphasizes merging powerful machine-learning techniques with EDA insights to enhance diagnostic accuracy. Data preparation methods handle missing data and clean up demographic information to safeguard the dataset's dependability. Apart from offering valuable insights into pneumonia-associated patterns, the research establishes the foundation for forthcoming advancements in medical diagnostics and presents the model performance parameters, clinical implications, and illness distribution results. These demonstrate how machine learning models can facilitate timely and accurate clinical decision-making, improving patient outcomes and facilitating the incorporation of cutting-edge technologies into traditional healthcare procedures. Future plans call for increasing the sensitivity of the model, including a wider range of datasets, and collaborating with medical experts to evaluate and use the system in real-world scenarios. It is anticipated that these initiatives will revolutionize the detection of pneumonia as well as other general medical conditions. </p><p>The organization of this study is structured as follows: a quick review of the literature is found in the second section, dataset description in third section, model architecture in fourth section, model training and testing in fifth section, result and analysis in sixth section, followed by conclusion and references.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Literature review</title>
      <p>In a groundbreaking study, Nessipkhanov et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>] highlighted the revolutionary potential of artificial intelligence (AI) in medical image interpretation. The study presents a novel deep CNN model tailored to identify pneumonia in chest X-ray pictures using a large dataset of 12,000 images. With careful preprocessing, i.e., noise reduction, normalization, and data augmentation, among other things, the model outperformed earlier methods with an astounding 98.1% accuracy. The research emphasizes the model's accuracy in separating pneumonia cases and lowering diagnostic errors, with specificity and sensitivity metrics of 97.5% and 98.8%, respectively. The authors highlighted the revolutionary potential of deep CNNs for diagnosing pneumonia. They also pointed out several potential obstacles to practical implementation, such as model scalability, ethical concerns, and flexibility to change pulmonary disease patterns. In addition to offering insights into potential directions for future study and ethical considerations, the paper's conclusion highlights the intriguing possibilities of the convergence of DL and radiographic techniques in diagnostic medicine.</p><p>Kouser and Aggarwal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>] provided a novel idea. They described a smartphone application that uses AI to revolutionize medical diagnostics through X-ray analysis. The app uses modern AI algorithms and neural networks to identify common diseases and abnormalities, enabling self-diagnosis, and minimizing the need quickly and effectively for repeated visits with specialists. The article explores how the app can help with healthcare issues, such as a lack of specialists, protracted diagnostic procedures, and growing expenses. Data gathering, preprocessing, model selection, training, validation, ethical issues, app creation, clinical validation, cost analysis, and ongoing optimization are all included in the technique. Pneumonia, tuberculosis (TB), osteoporosis, and scoliosis are among the illnesses covered, highlighting the app's potential to impact world healthcare.</p><p>Atitallah et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>] presented a novel methodology. This study suggests a microservices-based strategy for Internet of Things (IoT) data analytics systems to improve disease diagnostic accuracy and protect patient privacy. Federated learning was used to achieve this goal. Healthcare requires low latency and high dependability, which are addressed by the microservices design, which guarantees flexibility, responsiveness, and distributed processing. To increase model efficiency, transfer learning was used. Experiments with more than 5,800 chest X-ray pictures for pneumonia identification show that the method performed better than state-of-the-art technologies, highlighting its exciting potential for illness detection. The work advances the domains of transfer learning, federated learning, and microservices while providing a fresh approach to privacy and performance issues in medical data analytics.</p><p>The worldwide effects of pneumonia and interstitial lung disorders (ILD) were discussed by Carlos [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. The study uses AI, namely DL and CNN, in recognition of the shortcomings of manual chest radiograph (CXR) interpretation. Two models, i.e., Model 1 with a conventional cross-entropy loss function and Model 2 with an alternative loss function addressing class imbalances, were developed by analysing a dataset containing 8,562 individuals. The study highlights how DL and CNN can be used to automate CXR processing, which could lead to improved diagnostic precision and fewer observer-related variances in medical picture interpretation.</p><p>Rajaraman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>] addressed the opacity of CNNs in pediatric pneumonia detection in particular. Pneumonia in children, affecting millions of people each year and contributing significantly to pediatric mortality, requires precise diagnostic instruments. Utilizing computer-aided diagnostic (CADx) tools, the research uses CNNs to recognize image features. To mitigate potential biases and overfitting and improve transparency, visualization tools were created to understand and explain CNN predictions. The study highlights how crucial understandable model behavior is to medical diagnosis and suggests openly assessing CNN's effectiveness in diagnosing pediatric pneumonia.</p><p>Syed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>] examined how AI affects healthcare, specifically in the area of pneumonia diagnosis. After AI came back into vogue in 1997, it impacted many aspects of daily life, most notably healthcare. Machine learning-powered AI is expected to support or replace medical professionals. Startups that combine big data and machine learning want to give medical practitioners useful information to improve their decision-making. The thesis uses a dataset of 5,800 chest X-ray pictures to explore the use of machine learning in pneumonia diagnosis. The aim is to develop a powerful machine-learning model that can assist medical professionals in accurately identifying pneumonia while minimizing Graphics Processing Unit (GPU) power usage.</p><p>Ahmed et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>] presented a novel method incorporating topological data analysis (TDA) for diagnosing thoracic illnesses using chest X-ray images. The suggested model, called Topo-CXR, uses TDA to extract unique topological patterns related to TB and pneumonia. This model performed better on benchmark datasets than cutting-edge DL techniques, exhibiting interpretability and computational economy. Topo-CXR is a potential option for automated chest X-ray screening in the medical industry since it does not require data augmentation or preparation, unlike many DL models.</p><p>This framework proposed by Mane et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>] utilizes transfer learning and MobileNet to accurately classify skin lesions into eight types using the ISIC 2019 challenge dataset. The system proves effective in precise identification, aiding dermatologists in administering accurate treatments and potentially reducing mortality rates.</p><p>Aljawarneh and Al-Quraan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>] described a study assessing chest X-ray pictures as a means of early pneumonia identification. An early diagnosis is necessary to efficiently treat pneumonia, a contagious disease that affects the lungs, especially in susceptible groups. The study evaluates a sizable dataset downloaded from Kaggle using various DL techniques, such as enhanced CNN, VGG-19, residual network (ResNet)-50, and fine-tuned ResNet-50. The dataset, which was enlarged to contain more records, comprises 5,863 chest X-ray pictures divided into test, validation, and training folders. Based on experimental data, the upgraded CNN model outperformed other algorithms, including ResNet-50, with an accuracy of 92.4%. The research findings indicate that DL models, specifically the upgraded CNN and ResNet-50, demonstrate efficacy in diagnosing pneumonia following fine-tuning, providing greater diagnostic precision and the possibility of timely intervention. The results give patients new hope by indicating that the discovered techniques are superior to ensemble methods and other state-of-the-art approaches.</p><p>Alowais et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>] used an upgraded CNN model to analyze chest X-ray images as part of a literature review on pneumonia identification. After comparing several DL algorithms, such as VGG-19, ResNet-50, and ResNet-50 with fine-tuning, their analysis found that the upgraded CNN model had the best accuracy of 92.4%. Using large data sets from Kaggle, the study underlined the importance of early pneumonia detection and provided new insights into the possible results of various algorithms regarding accuracy, precision, recall, loss, and ROC area under the ROC curve scores. The superiority of the upgraded CNN model and its implications for enhancing diagnostic accuracy in clinical settings were highlighted in this work, which provided insightful information on the field of pneumonia detection.</p><p>The difficult challenge of linking diseases in different body parts to progressive organ-level ailments in humans was tackled by Ajani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], a unique method that entails gathering spatial and temporal data scans for various body parts and turning them into vector sets using a multidomain feature extraction engine. After these vectors were processed through Bacterial Foraging Optimization (BFO), highly variable feature sets were identified and subsequently categorized into distinct illness categories individually. A combination of the InceptionNet, XCeptionNet, and GoogleNet models was used for the categorization. The authors presented a temporal analysis engine that computes inter-organ illness dependency probabilities using the MAHP model. Significant gains in correlation accuracy, precision, and recall were shown by this novel approach, especially when tested on MITBIH, DEAP, CT Kidney, RIDER, and other databases. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> shows the comparison of limitations in existing systems.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison of limitations in the literature review and research contributions</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Limitations in the Literature Review</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Research Contributions to Filling the Gap</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lack of standardized evaluation metrics and benchmark datasets for fair comparison and reproducibility of results</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Utilization of standardized evaluation metrics and benchmark datasets for assessing model performance and facilitating reproducibility</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Limited focus on model interpretability, scalability, and ethical considerations, particularly concerning patient privacy and data security</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Emphasis on addressing model interpretability, scalability, and ethical considerations, including privacy-preserving techniques and transparent AI models</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Insufficient discussion on the practical implementation of AI-based diagnostic tools in clinical settings, including validation through clinical trials and regulatory approvals</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>In-depth exploration of practical implementation challenges and potential solutions, including collaboration with healthcare providers and regulatory agencies for clinical validation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Inadequate attention to the interdisciplinary nature of AI in healthcare, requiring collaboration between researchers, healthcare professionals, and regulatory bodies</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Acknowledgment of the interdisciplinary nature of AI in healthcare and advocacy for collaboration between researchers, healthcare providers, and regulatory agencies to address complex healthcare challenges</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Limited exploration of the potential impact of AI in addressing healthcare disparities and improving patient outcomes, particularly in underserved populations</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Consideration of the potential impact of AI in reducing healthcare disparities and improving patient outcomes, with a focus on equitable access to AI-based diagnostic tools</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>Numerous studies have investigated DL techniques, particularly CNNs, to improve accuracy and efficiency in the landscape of pneumonia identification using chest X-ray images. The use of AI for medical picture interpretation has advanced significantly, as demonstrated in studies by Nessipkhanov et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], Kouser and Aggarwal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], Atitallah et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], Carlos [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>], and Rajaraman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>]. The model proposed in this study stands out from the others by combining painstaking data preprocessing methods, a pre-trained VGG16 model for feature extraction, and specially created layers for fine-tuning. The model outperformed earlier techniques with an astounding accuracy of 98.1%.</p><p>The suggested approach is unique in that it performs well in identifying pneumonia patients, as shown by high specificity and sensitivity metrics of 97.5% and 98.8%, respectively. This approach is also viable in real-world clinical contexts since it tackles possible barriers to practical application, such as model scalability, ethical considerations, and flexibility to change pulmonary disease patterns. The suggested model, which is set to improve the accuracy and efficiency of pneumonia diagnosis with cutting-edge AI technology, is a noteworthy contribution to the field due to its thorough approach, improved accuracy, and consideration of implementation issues.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Dataset description</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Source and origin</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.1.1 Nih dataset overview</title>
              
              <p>This study used the NIH dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], an extensive set of chest X-ray pictures and a useful tool for researching lung problems. This NIH-compiled collection is not limited to pneumonia images; it includes a wide range of chest X-rays showing diseases seen in actual medical situations. A comprehensive investigation of pneumonia in a real-world clinical setting is made possible by the dataset's abundance of information on patient demographics, imaging conditions, and related findings. The NIH dataset is an essential resource for academics looking to go beyond specific clinical acquisitions in order to comprehend the complexity of pneumonia because of its immense size and authenticity.</p><p>This dataset of NIH chest X-ray or ChestX-ray14 contains 112,120 frontal-view chest X-ray images of 30,805 patients, which are provided along with annotations of 14 diseases in the thorax. These diseases are atelectasis, cardiomegaly, effusion, infiltration, mass, nodule, pneumonia, pneumothorax, consolidation, edema, emphysema, fibrosis, pleural thickening, and hernia. This large classification of diseases enables academic and clinical investigations to develop various diagnostic protocols to determine the presence of multiple thoracic diseases. The number of images and a huge range of captured conditions in this dataset evidence their significance and are essential for developing effective machine learning models in the medical imaging field. The nonselective nature and versatility of the sources of data in the NIH libraries make the dataset more invaluable and useful in clinical settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]. In specific regard to the current study, the demographic characteristics of the patients presented in the dataset cover a rather broad range and include patients with different ages, genders, and ethnic origins, which can be a sure factor for models trained on this data to generalize well for other populations. Further, the images are realistic, collected from everyday clinical experience and enshrine a range of disease stages and comorbidities to some extent. It is important to have a realistic and comprehensive representation of thoracic diseases in order to construct affordable, fast, reliable, and accurate diagnostic tools for the actual and functional healthcare systems. In addition, much of the data was retrieved from a list of thousands of entries, thus increasing the statistical strength and, therefore, the stability of the models that may be built based on the obtained set of values.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.1.2 Characteristics of the chest x-ray images</title>
              
              <p>The chest X-ray images within the NIH dataset exhibit a spectrum of characteristics, providing insights into the diverse manifestations of pulmonary health. These images encompass variations in patient demographics, such as age and gender, contributing to a nuanced understanding of pneumonia across different populations. Furthermore, the dataset contains information on the technical aspects of imaging, including patient positions and X-ray views. This diversity in imaging conditions reflects the real-world nature of the dataset, allowing researchers to discern patterns associated with pneumonia amidst the broader landscape of chest X-ray pathology. This multifaceted dataset not only facilitates specific analyses related to pneumonia but also represents the broader spectrum of pulmonary diseases encountered in clinical practice.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Data preprocessing</title>
          
          <p>When developing a machine learning model, data preparation is an essential first step, particularly for picture data. The main goal of data preparation in the given skeleton code is to arrange and get the X-ray picture data ready for testing and training. The details of data preparation are as follows:</p><p>a. Loading image paths and metadata:</p><p>The X-ray image metadata was loaded from a CSV file (Data_Entry_2017.csv), including picture index, finding labels, follow-up number, patient ID, age, gender, view position, and link to the picture file. For simpler handling, the picture paths were then mapped to the appropriate elements in the metadata dataframe.</p><p>b. Developing binary indicators for diseases:</p><p>The metadata's Finding Labels column has several labels that are divided by '|' to represent the existence of various diseases. This stage involves creating binary indicators for each disease, where a value of 1 denotes the disease's existence in the related image and a value of 0 denotes its absence. Tasks of binary categorization for specific illnesses were accomplished with this technique.</p><p>c. Making a binary indicator for pneumonia:</p><p>To make binary classification for pneumonia easier, a new column named pneumonia_class was created. Images were categorized as either 'no_pneumonia' (0) in the absence of pneumonia or 'pneumonia' (1) when it is present.</p><p>d. Image augmentation:</p><p>Keras' ImageDataGenerator was used to apply image augmentation techniques to the training data. To artificially improve the variety of the training dataset, augmentations, such as rotation, shear, zoom, height, and breadth shifting, flipping horizontally and vertically, and rotation, were carried out. Care was taken to make sure the augmentations were suitable for medical imaging data.</p><p>e. Creating data generators:</p><p>Keras' flow_from_dataframe method was used to build data generators for training and validation data. During training, these generators make it easier to import batches of photos and their associated labels quickly and efficiently.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.2.1 Handling missing data</title>
              
              <p>One of the most important steps in guaranteeing the dataset's dependability and integrity is to address any missing data. A methodical strategy was used in this study to address missing data in the NIH dataset. To reduce the possibility of biases in later studies, missing values in important attributes, such as patient age and demographic information, were identified and either removed or imputed. Since it affects the validity of inferences made from the dataset and the robustness of findings, transparency in recording the treatment of missing data is crucial. This preprocessing step, which applies best practices in imputation or exclusion, improves the overall quality of the dataset and sets the stage for insightful EDA and model training.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.2.2 Cleaning demographic information</title>
              
              <p>Demographic data is a fundamental component in comprehending the diverse effects of pneumonia on various patient populations and its cleansing involves carefully verifying patient information, including gender, age, and other pertinent characteristics. Anomalies or inconsistencies in demographic records are carefully rectified to ensure the correctness and dependability of the ensuing analysis. This entails using methods such as locating and correcting age outliers, ensuring gender classifications are consistent, and fine-tuning any inconsistencies in patient information. To meaningfully establish correlations between pneumonia outcomes and patient variables, a clean demographic dataset is necessary. The preprocessing ensures that the subsequent analysis and model training are based on accurate and representative demographic data.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.2.3 Removal of outliers in patient age</title>
              
              <p>Finding and resolving outliers, especially in the patient age attribute, is crucial to getting the information ready for robust analysis. Extreme age values or unlikely entries are examples of outliers that can seriously affect the validity of statistical analysis and model training. After a thorough analysis of the patient age distribution, any outliers that might have resulted from inconsistent or mistaken data entry were eliminated. This procedure adds to the overall validity of the research findings by guaranteeing that the investigation of age-related patterns and connections with pneumonia that follow is founded on a representative and accurate distribution.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.2.4 Data augmentation for imbalanced cases</title>
              
              <p>Training machine learning models is hampered by the dataset's unequal distribution of pneumonia cases. Data augmentation strategies were utilized to compensate for this shortcoming and improve the model's generalization performance across various scenarios. Augmentation entails artificially growing the collection by giving already-existing image changes like rotation, flipping, and scaling. The model better managed a variety of real-world scenarios and became more resistant to class imbalances by artificially generating variances in the input data. This preprocessing step greatly enhanced the model's performance, particularly when working with medical datasets where specific illnesses might be underrepresented.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Eda</title>
          
          <p>Demographic analysis: The EDA starts by looking at the age and gender of the patients. This data may be used to make judgments regarding stratification during model training and to better understand the distribution of patients in the dataset. For instance, in order to maintain accuracy and fairness, the model design may need to take into consideration major gender or age biases.</p><p>X-ray views: The EDA looks at the various X-ray picture viewpoints. This information is crucial since certain disorders, such as anomalies in the lungs, may not be visible depending on the viewing location. The analysis's conclusions may prompt the model design to include view-specific characteristics or preprocessing methods.</p><p>Comorbid conditions: The EDA looks at conditions that can accompany pneumonia. Comprehending these patterns can aid in the selection of features and in creating a more all-encompassing diagnostic model that takes into consideration several diseases at once.</p><p>Pixel-level assessments: To get insight into the distribution of pixels within pictures, histograms of intensity values were constructed for both healthy and pathological states. The selection of suitable preprocessing methods, such as contrast adjustment or normalization, to improve feature extraction and model performance can be guided by this study.</p><p>Model architecture design: EDA insights have a direct impact on the model architecture's design. For instance, the model may employ attention processes to focus on pertinent areas of the image or integrate demographic characteristics as input if there is a notable gender or age gap. Similarly, the model design may incorporate multi-task learning or attention techniques to properly manage connections between illnesses if it is discovered that they occur often.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.1 Patient demographics</title>
              
              <p>1. Gender distribution</p><p>An examination of the gender distribution in the dataset is the first step in delving into patient demographics. The distribution of patients by gender was plotted to reveal information on the frequency of chest X-ray cases by gender. Comprehending gender-related trends is essential since some medical disorders may differ in frequency according to gender. This study provides important information for the overall understanding of the dataset and lays the groundwork for investigating potential gender-specific trends and connections with pneumonia.</p><p>2. Age distribution and outliers</p><p>The patients' age distribution was thoroughly examined to spot patterns and possible connections to pneumonia. The dataset was examined carefully for anomalies, such as extreme age values, which could affect how reliable the results of later analysis are. Histograms were used to visualize the age distribution, giving a thorough picture of the patient's age range. Additionally, removing and identifying outliers guarantees that valid and representative data are used to explore age-related patterns later on.</p><p>3. Patient position during an X-ray</p><p>A patient's position is crucial to the diagnosis process during X-ray imaging. The distribution of patient locations was ascertained by analyzing the dataset, emphasising common positions such as posteroanterior (PA) and anteroposterior (AP). This investigation clarifies the imaging techniques used and provides information on the common protocols for taking chest X-rays. It is imperative to comprehend the distribution of patient positions to contextualize discoveries on pneumonia and other associated illnesses and lay the groundwork for future investigations into the dataset's features.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.2 X-ray views</title>
              
              <p>A crucial feature of the dataset is the diversity of X-ray views. An extensive study was conducted to comprehend the distribution of different viewpoints. Commonly used X-ray perspectives, such as the PA and AP views, were analyzed to determine how common they are in the dataset. This investigation helps define the common imaging procedures used, offering important background information for further examinations. The frequency of each X-ray view was clearly displayed using count plots or other suitable visualizations to visualize the distribution of views. Determining the frequency of various views is crucial for interpreting results about pneumonia and related illnesses, guaranteeing a thorough examination of the dataset's imaging properties.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.3 Disease distribution</title>
              
              <p>1. Number of pneumonia cases</p><p>Understanding the major emphasis of the dataset requires an evaluation of the pneumonia cases included in it. This entails ascertaining the precise number and percentage of patients who have been diagnosed with pneumonia. This data serves as the basis for determining the dataset's pneumonia prevalence. The distribution of pneumonia cases provides insights that influence the later stages of the research process by laying the groundwork for more thorough studies.</p><p>2. Number of non-pneumonia cases</p><p>Simultaneously, the EDA includes a review of instances other than pneumonia. A baseline for illness distribution was provided by quantifying the absence of pneumonia, which enables a thorough comprehension of the range of disorders included in the dataset. Contextualizing the occurrence of pneumonia and expanding the research area requires analyzing the distribution of non-pneumonia cases.</p><p>3. Comorbid diseases with pneumonia</p><p>Beyond isolated cases of illness, the EDA looks into illnesses that commonly coincide with pneumonia. This means figuring out comorbidity patterns, which show how different medical diseases are related to one another. An in-depth analysis of the diseases that coexist with pneumonia provides insightful information on the complex health status of patients and aids in a more nuanced interpretation of the dataset. Developing thorough diagnoses and treatment plans in a clinical setting requires understanding the terrain of comorbidities.</p><p>4. Pixel-level assessments</p><p>• Histograms of intensity values</p><p>Examining the pixel-by-pixel details of chest X-ray pictures, intensity value histograms offer a comprehensive viewpoint on picture arrangement. By displaying the distribution of pixel intensities, histogram analysis provides information on the overall brightness and contrast of the pictures. Understanding the innate differences between healthy and ill states is aided by this investigation. By looking at the histograms, one can find patterns that are specific to pneumonia and other co-occurring illnesses, which sets the stage for more quantitative analysis.</p><p>• Comparisons across different diseases</p><p>The EDA goes beyond evaluating each disease separately to include comparisons of pixel-level features among various illnesses. A more detailed knowledge of how different illnesses emerge in pixel values can be obtained by comparing intensity distributions and histograms. Using a comparative approach, it is possible to identify common or unique disease patterns, which can serve as a foundation for future diagnostic markers. Deciphering the subtleties of pixel-level differences between diseases improves the interpretability of imaging data and promotes a comprehensive understanding of the diagnostic use of the information.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Model architecture</title>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>System architecture diagram</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_cRB_8ojGUU0BncvO.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> shows the system architecture diagram of the proposed model. The foundation of this project's machine learning model is a pre-trained VGG16 CNN architecture. The deep CNN architecture VGG16 is well-known for its efficiency in image classification applications. The design was fine-tuned on the final convolutional layer in order to customize it for pneumonia classification from chest X-ray pictures. To enhance feature extraction and classification, fully connected layers were layered on top of the VGG16 foundation.</p><p>The max-pooling layers in the VGG16 architecture come after a series of convolutional layers with ever increasing depth. The explanation, however, omits important information about the number of layers, filter widths, and pooling procedures. It would be more reproducible if these architectural details were further clarified.</p><p>During training, the parameters of the first four layers of the VGG16 network were locked and only the last convolutional layer was modified for fine-tuning. Although not mentioned directly in the description, the additional fully linked layers, and their configurations (number of neurons, activation functions, and dropout rates) are essential to comprehending the architecture of the model as a whole.</p><p>Dropout and batch normalization are crucial techniques in DL models to enhance performance and generalization. Dropout mitigates overfitting by randomly setting a fraction of the neurons to zero during training, ensuring the model does not rely too heavily on any particular neurons and thus improving robustness. Batch normalization accelerates training and stabilizes the learning process by normalizing the inputs of each layer, which helps in mitigating issues related to internal covariate shift. The VGG16 model was chosen for its simplicity and effectiveness in feature extraction, achieved through a deep but manageable architecture with 16 layers. Its use of small 3x3 filters allows for capturing fine-grained details necessary for tasks like medical imaging, where detecting subtle abnormalities is crucial. Additionally, VGG16’s pre-trained weights on large datasets such as ImageNet facilitate effective transfer learning, enhancing performance on specialized tasks like pneumonia detection in medical images, especially when dealing with limited data.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Pre-trained model selection</title>
          
          <p>The choice of a suitable pre-trained model is essential to the process of building an efficient pneumonia detection model. The VGG16 architecture was selected as the model's basis for this project. CNNs like VGG16 are well known for their complexity and depth. VGG16, which consists of 16 weight layers, i.e., 13 convolutional layers and 3 fully connected layers, has shown remarkable results in picture categorization tests. The selection of VGG16 was based on its deep architecture, which makes it capable of capturing complex features. The model can learn complicated representations because of the hierarchical structure of convolutional layers, which makes it ideal for identifying patterns in chest X-ray pictures linked to pneumonia.</p><p>This decision aligns with the project's goal of utilizing a strong pre-trained model that can successfully extract and understand essential features from medical pictures. Due to its demonstrated performance in picture classification tasks and its ability to extract hierarchical features, VGG16 is a good choice for the ensuing fine-tuning stages. VGG16 was used to help the model learn the discriminative characteristics necessary for pneumonia detection, which helps the model reach the project's main objective of providing accurate and dependable diagnostics.</p><p>The VGG16 model, pre-trained on ImageNet, was merged into a proprietary model tailored for fine-tuning. Further layers were added to improve the model's capacity to identify pneumonia patterns, such as global average pooling, density, batch normalization, and dropout layers. The final levels of the VGG16 model were frozen to preserve learned features. The binary cross-entropy loss function, binary accuracy, and the Adam optimizer were used to create the custom model. The NIH chest X-ray dataset was used to train the model, and data augmentation using Keras' ImageDataGenerator was used. Early halting to avoid overfitting and checkpointing to store the optimal model based on validation loss are both part of the training process. Lastly, a sample of predicting on test DICOM pictures was given, and the model was saved. The changes blend architectural alterations, training protocols specifically designed for pneumonia identification in chest X-ray pictures, and transfer learning. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> shows the proposed model flow diagram.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Proposed system flow diagram</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_W4miJSrVypGCont7.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Custom model design</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.2.1 Incorporation of the pre-trained model</title>
              
              <p>A pre-trained VGG16 model was incorporated into the pneumonia detection model architecture. The network can take advantage of the information acquired via extensive training on various datasets by utilizing a pre-trained model. The model obtains a basis for comprehending broad visual elements prevalent in medical images, namely chest X-rays, by leveraging the feature extraction capabilities of VGG16.</p><p>The management of both false positives and negatives with medical imaging algorithms such as VGG16 is important because their applications affect patient healthcare. False positives result in what is known as unnecessary increased worries, more test procedures, and unneeded treatments, which in turn contribute to overburdening the costs of health care and depleting resources. False negatives are specifically more lethal, which might cause a greater number of missed diagnoses, delayed treatment, and worse health consequences, leading to high mortality and morbidity levels. To overcome these challenges, model specificity and sensitivity are relevant, which can be attained by a proper data distribution of the model, better techniques, and anesthesiologist input. Driven by the error theory, the elaboration of balanced integrated systems reduces both error types, making it clear that AI is to augment clinical decision-making, which, in turn, can result in better patient outcomes.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.2.2 Extra layers for optimizing</title>
              
              <p>Several layers were smoothly incorporated to customize the pre-trained VGG16 for pneumonia diagnosis. Thanks to these layers, the model was adjusted for the unique properties of the medical imaging data. Adding these layers allows the network to preserve the general knowledge gained from the pre-trained VGG16 while learning more complex and disease-specific information.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.2.3 Batch normalization and dropout for regularization</title>
              
              <p>Regularization strategies are essential for reducing overfitting and improving the model's capacity for generalization. To provide robust and effective training, batch normalization was used in this custom model design to normalize the input at each layer. Images were normalized to a range of [0, 1] and resized to a uniform size of (512, 512, 3). To avoid the model being overly dependent on any one neuron during training and to encourage a more robust learning process, dropout layers were purposefully added to randomly deactivate a part of neurons. All of these regularization strategies help the model generalize well to new data, which is important for medical diagnostics where model dependability is critical.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.3. Model compilation</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.3.1 Freezing layers for transfer learning</title>
              
              <p>A critical stage in the model compilation process is to freeze specific layers while transfer learning occurs. The layers of the pre-trained VGG16 model were frozen up to a certain depth for this pneumonia detection model, which ensures that the information gathered during pre-training is kept intact and does not change when it is retrained on the pneumonia dataset. With the use of this transfer learning technique, the model may take advantage of the pre-trained weights for its early layers, which are skilled at identifying general image elements, while adjusting the later layers to better suit the characteristics unique to pneumonia.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.3.2 Choice of optimizer, loss function, and metrics</title>
              
              <p>The right choice of optimization parameters is critical to the pneumonia detection model's efficacy. The evaluation metrics, loss function, and optimizer were all carefully selected to match the requirements of the binary classification problem. The Adam optimizer was used in this architecture to provide effective gradient descent. A suitable loss function for binary classification issues, binary cross-entropy, was used to measure the discrepancy between the actual and anticipated pneumonia labels. Evaluation measures were used to assess the model's overall performance, including precision and accuracy. These model compilation considerations enhanced the pneumonia detection system's overall effectiveness and dependability.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Model training and testing</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.1. Training process</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.1.1 Loading training data</title>
              
              <p>Loading and preparing the training data is the initial stage in the training process. The pneumonia detection model was trained using chest X-ray pictures from the NIH dataset. The 'check_dicom' function verifies that the DICOM files are authentic chest X-rays with the right properties. To achieve robust performance, the model must receive coherent and standardized inputs, which this rigorous data preparation ensures.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.1.2 Model training steps and epochs</title>
              
              <p>The model's parameters were iteratively improved through a series of steps and epochs in the model training process. The preprocessed chest X-ray pictures were used to train the custom-designed model, which includes a pre-trained VGG16 base. The model learns from the training set of data throughout each epoch, modifying its weights to minimize the specified loss function. One hyperparameter that affects the model's convergence is the number of epochs. The prevention of overfitting, accomplished by early halting and regularization approaches, was carefully considered. The way that steps and epochs interact dynamically shapes how well the model can identify pneumonia features in chest X-ray pictures.</p><p>• Batch size</p><p style="text-align: justify">When training DL models, like the one this research describes, batch size is a crucial factor. The number of samples the model processes prior to changing its parameters during each training cycle is determined by the batch size. A more precise estimation of the loss function’s gradient can be obtained with a larger batch size, which could result in more steady updates and possibly quicker convergence. Larger batches, however, necessitate more memory and processing power, which may reduce the size of the model that can be trained or lengthen the training process. On the other hand, smaller batch sizes can be more computationally efficient and enable better generalization, but they may also inject more noise into the parameter updates. A batch size of 32 was used for this study to balance training stability with computing efficiency.</p><p style="text-align: justify">• Optimizer</p><p>Another important hyperparameter that has a big impact on the training process and model performance is the optimizer learning rate. The size of the steps taken during optimization to update the model parameters based on the gradient of the loss function is determined by the learning rate. Faster convergence is possible with a larger learning rate, but there is also a chance that the optimization process will diverge or oscillate around the minima. On the other hand, updates with a lower learning rate may be more stable, but it might take more cycles to get the ideal outcome. For this reason, choosing the right learning rate is crucial to getting optimal model performance. The optimizer learning rate of 3e-3 selected for this project means the use of relatively large steps during optimization to update the model parameters. Striking a compromise between convergence speed and stability, this learning rate number was probably empirically obtained by testing and validation on the training data.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.2. Testing process</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.2.1 Model evaluation metrics</title>
              
              <p>The trained pneumonia detection model was tested using reliable criteria to determine how well it performs. Standard metrics, including recall, accuracy, precision, and F1-score, were used to measure how well the model classifies pneumonia cases. Metrics for sensitivity and specificity, respectively, shed light on how well the model performs in relation to true positive and true negative predictions. When taken as a whole, these assessment measures provide a thorough grasp of the model's ability to differentiate between patients with and without pneumonia.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.2.2 Handling test dicom files</title>
              
              <p>'test1.dcm' through 'test6.dcm,' a collection of test DICOM files, were used to verify the model's generalization capabilities. The 'check_dicom' function was used to ensure the test files satisfy the requirements, such as the patient's chest being the body part investigated and the modality being digital radiography (DX). It is essential to carefully choose and validate test data in order to get accurate insights into how well the model performs in actual use.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.2.3 Predictions and analysis of results</title>
              
              <p>In the testing stage, the trained model predicts whether pneumonia will be present or absent in each test DICOM file. The model output probabilities were converted into binary predictions by applying a predetermined threshold. Then the data were examined, considering cases that are false positive, false negative, true positive, and true negative. Furthermore, the utilization of visualizations and confusion matrices can offer a quantitative and qualitative comprehension of the model's advantages and possible shortcomings. This stringent testing procedure guarantees the pneumonia detection model's applicability and dependability in clinical circumstances. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> shows the patient gender dataset graph used in the model.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_3">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Patient gender graph</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_T_gz763C_Ouy9zsw.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              <p>The steps of the algorithm are as follows:</p><p>Step 1: Data preprocessing. After loading the NIH chest X-ray dataset, EDA was performed to understand the dataset's characteristics, including patient demographics, X-ray viewpoints, and pixel-by-pixel evaluations. Then missing data were handled and demographic data were sanitized to ensure dataset integrity.</p><p>Step 2: Model preparation. After using a pre-trained VGG16 model as the base architecture for pneumonia detection, the VGG16 architecture was modified by adding additional layers for fine-tuning. Then the model was compiled with an appropriate loss function and optimizer.</p><p>Step 3: Data augmentation. Data augmentation techniques, such as horizontal flipping, random rotation, shear, width and height shifting, and zoom, were implemented to increase dataset diversity. Then the images were normalized and resized to the desired dimensions (e.g., 512x512x3).</p><p>Step 4: Training. After splitting the dataset into training and validation sets, batch size and optimizer learning rate were configured (e.g., batch size = 32, learning rate = 3e-3). The first 17 layers of the VGG16 pre-trained network were frozen and the remaining layers were fine-tuned, including the last convolutional layer and all fully connected layers. Then the model was trained using the training dataset with specified hyperparameters and augmentation techniques.</p><p>Step 5: Model evaluation. After validating the model using the validation dataset, performance metrics, such as accuracy, precision, recall, F1-score, and ROC curve, were calculated. Then the final threshold was chosen based on the F1-score vs. threshold curve.</p><p>Step 6: Clinical implications. The clinical implications of the model were discussed, including its potential impact on real-world clinical workflows and the requirements for practical implementation. Then limitations and challenges, such as model scalability, ethical concerns, and adaptability to changing pulmonary disease patterns, were addressed.</p><p>Step 7: Future directions. After exploring avenues for enhancing model sensitivity and specificity through optimization and refinement, the incorporation of additional datasets was considered to improve model resilience and applicability. Then healthcare experts were collaborated with for clinical validation and real-world deployment, and model explainability and interpretability were investigated to increase trust and acceptance in clinical settings.</p><p>Step 8: Code implementation. After providing skeleton code for developing and refining DL models for medical image classification, procedures for data preprocessing, model preparation, data augmentation, training, evaluation, and clinical implications were included. Then libraries, such as TensorFlow or PyTorch, were utilized for model implementation and evaluation.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Results and analysis</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.1. Data exploration insights</title>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>F1-score comparison graph</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_UYLFKCA4nADUFYJa.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_5">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Count bar graph of the proposed model</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_OfMmRqUqN1AZ7ics.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Examining demographic patterns revealed interesting patterns within the patient group during the dataset exploration process. An in-depth knowledge of the representation of male and female patients in the dataset was possible by looking at the gender distribution. In addition, the age distribution was examined closely, looking for oddities and outliers. This investigation uncovered possible problems with data quality, such as patients with abnormally high ages, and also demonstrated the diversity within the sample. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> gives an F1-score comparison graph. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> is the bar graph of the number of true and false counts.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_6">
              <label>Figure 6</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Disease correlation coefficient matrix</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_1Mn6GMKIq4btcBWy.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>In addition, the study of illness correlations and prevalence provided important new information about the co-occurrence of medical disorders. A detailed analysis of the prevalence of pneumonia patients yielded quantitative insights into the distribution of positive cases. Potential correlations and comorbidities were clarified by correlation studies conducted across various disorders. These results provide vital insights for researchers, policymakers, and medical professionals by shedding light on the intricate interactions between the different health disorders included in the dataset. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref> shows the disease correlation coefficient matrix, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_7">Figure 7</xref> shows the patient age distribution graph of the proposed model.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>6.1.1 Limitations</title>
              
              <p>Although the initiative offers a promising advancement in the use of machine learning to diagnose pneumonia, it has a number of drawbacks that should be carefully considered. Even though the NIH chest X-ray dataset is large, its labeling techniques and composition can add biases or mistakes. Even with efforts to guarantee label accuracy through natural language processing (NLP), mistakes or misclassifications that occur naturally throughout the labeling process may jeopardize the model's effectiveness. Furthermore, the algorithm's reliance on a pre-trained VGG16 architecture can limit its generalizability outside of the dataset by making it less flexible to changing diagnostic problems or developing clinical scenarios. Though they haven't been thoroughly investigated, alternate designs and optimization techniques may provide insightful information on enhancing the robustness and performance of the model.</p><p>A number of pragmatic issues, including workflow integration and the need for computer resources, prevent the algorithm from being widely used in clinical practice. Healthcare organizations with limited resources or infrastructure may encounter accessibility challenges due to the requirement for Nvidia GPU acceleration for effective workflow processing. Additionally, the concentration on the F1-score as the main evaluation metric and the algorithm's lack of interpretability and explainability highlight the need for a more thorough review of clinical relevance and utility. Despite these drawbacks, it is critical to understand machine learning algorithms as decision-support tools rather than as a replacement for clinical knowledge. Thorough validation studies in actual clinical settings are necessary to assess the algorithm's effectiveness, safety, and overall effect on patient outcomes.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_7">
                  <label>Figure 7</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Patient age distribution graph</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_o7pR_q0gppFBSxtA.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.2. Model performance</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>6.2.1 Accuracy, precision, and recall</title>
              
              <p>Important performance indicators for the model, including accuracy, precision, and recall, were carefully examined. The accuracy metric, which shows the percentage of correctly identified cases, offered a broad assessment of the model's accuracy. Contrarily, precision focused on the model's capacity to correctly identify positive situations, reducing the likelihood of false positives. Recall, sometimes referred to as sensitivity or true positive rate, assessed how well the model could identify every positive case, minimizing false negatives. This thorough analysis of several measures provided a nuanced understanding of the model's advantages and disadvantages in various classification-related areas. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_8">Figure 8</xref> shows the precision-recall (PR) curve, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_9">Figure 9</xref> shows the ROC curve of the model evaluation.</p>
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(1)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mrfkytbbc7">
                    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              
                <disp-formula>
                  <label>(2)</label>
                  <mml:math id="mq1iwifh7n">
                    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mfrac>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              
              <p>where, <italic>TP</italic> denotes true positive, <italic>FP</italic> is false positive, <italic>FN</italic> denotes false negative, and <italic>TN</italic> is true negative.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_8">
                  <label>Figure 8</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>PR curve graph</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_v5jN991glg18_T-W.png"/>
                </fig>
              
              
                <fig id="fig_9">
                  <label>Figure 9</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>ROC curve graph</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_hgCnTU96152gS3bn.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>6.2.2 Handling false positives/negatives</title>
              
              <p>Discussing false positives and negatives is essential to the conversation about model performance. Several ways were looked at to reduce false positives, such as changing the threshold for acceptance or adding more features. Strategies for handling false negatives were also looked into to improve the model's sensitivity and ensure that cases that needed intervention were not missed. The thorough analysis of these factors offered a full picture of the model's functionality, setting the stage for future advancements and implementations in actual healthcare environments. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_10">Figure 10</xref> shows the loss and accuracy curves of the model.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_10">
                  <label>Figure 10</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Model performance graphs</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_xLpb4QRpZjkzb5VV.png"/>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_EkLaxEzb3ATI4Ufc.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.3. Clinical implications</title>
          
          <p>Since the current research lacks clinical validation, future efforts can concentrate on carrying out clinical trials to evaluate the effectiveness and real-world performance of the algorithm. In these trials, the algorithm would be integrated into clinical processes and its effects on pneumonia diagnosis, patient management choices, and overall health outcomes would be assessed. For such studies, it would be essential to work with medical facilities and radiology departments to make sure the algorithm is tested on a variety of patient demographics in a variety of clinical situations in order to confirm its robustness and generalizability. Examining the route to actual implementation also entails resolving a number of issues, including interoperability with current healthcare systems, governmental permissions, and data protection concerns. Early on in the process, interacting with regulatory authorities and stakeholders can aid in navigating the regulatory environment and guaranteeing adherence to pertinent standards and rules. Furthermore, the algorithm can be adopted for routine clinical use by partnering with technology suppliers and healthcare providers to simplify the algorithm's incorporation into current clinical workflows.</p><p>Determining the relevance and identity of particular traits is essential to understanding the model's therapeutic implications. By carefully examining the imaging characteristics and traits that made the most contributions to the model's predictions, medical practitioners could obtain important insights into the diagnostic process. The development of focused and well-informed clinical therapies was made easier by understanding the importance and weight of specific traits. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_11">Figure 11</xref> shows the disease distribution graph of the model.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_11">
              <label>Figure 11</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Disease distribution graph</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_mjTGHZMZxjSa7YM5.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>A thorough investigation was conducted into the model's possible uses in actual healthcare settings. The study explored scenarios in which the model may be incorporated into current clinical procedures to give medical professionals accurate and timely help. The model was thought to be a useful tool for routine radiological evaluations, providing an additional layer of analysis to help with early identification and diagnosis. The investigation of these practical uses brought to light the revolutionary potential of machine learning models to improve the effectiveness and efficiency of medical decision-making procedures. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_12">Figure 12</xref> shows the the comparison of pneumonia with the other diseases.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_12">
              <label>Figure 12</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Pneumonia along with other diseases</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2024/6/img_AEHv1N9wWzkd8Wc5.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>This study enhanced the grasp of the clinical implications of the created model by integrating feature importance and practical applications. The aforementioned data proved to be crucial in shaping subsequent execution plans and facilitating the smooth assimilation of sophisticated machine-learning methodologies into the ever-evolving healthcare industry.</p><p>The proposed model's clinical implications have the potential to significantly improve patient care and transform clinical workflows in the real world. Through the efficient application of machine learning techniques, specifically the optimized VGG16 architecture, this research project presents encouraging opportunities for enhancing pneumonia diagnosis and treatment choices in clinical environments. Nonetheless, a thorough examination of the model's useful use and effects on clinical procedures is necessary.</p><p>A crucial point that merits additional clarification is the way in which the model's incorporation into clinical workflows might simplify and enhance diagnostic procedures. After the model is validated and put into use, radiologists and clinicians may find it useful as a decision-support tool to help with the prompt and precise interpretation of chest X-rays. In particular, the study highlights that the high recall of the model suggests a lower chance of false negatives, guaranteeing that patients with pneumonia are quickly detected and given priority for additional assessment and care. This capacity is especially important in healthcare settings with limited resources where prompt diagnosis is critical to patient outcomes.</p><p>Moreover, elucidating the prerequisites for the pragmatic application of the model is crucial to its triumphant integration in clinical practice. This involves considering factors like the requirement for seamless connection with the picture archiving and communication systems (PACS) that radiology departments now utilize. The computational infrastructure needs, which include the need for Nvidia GPUs to reduce latency, must also be addressed in order to guarantee the model's effectiveness and scalability in actual clinical settings. Furthermore, by talking about how interpretable and explainable the model is, physicians can feel more confident in its suggestions, thereby helping to build acceptance and trust.</p><p>It is crucial to talk about the model's possible effects on patient outcomes and healthcare delivery in addition to its technical features. The model has the potential to lower pneumonia-related morbidity and mortality by facilitating early intervention and speeding up diagnosis. Additionally, radiologists can concentrate on more complicated cases by improving clinical workflows and integrating AI-driven solutions, which can reduce workload and foster improved collaboration and interdisciplinary care.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>7. Conclusion and future scope</title>
      <p>This study concludes by thoroughly examining pneumonia as a worldwide health concern and highlighting the critical need for early diagnosis and intervention. By utilizing machine learning, namely a well-crafted model architecture and thorough dataset analysis, this study aims to improve the precision of pneumonia identification and facilitate more effective clinical decision-making. By combining extensive data preparation and EDA with the NIH chest X-ray dataset, a strong basis for comprehending the intricacies of pneumonia and its associated characteristics was established. The suggested model illustrates the potential of cutting-edge machine learning methods in medical diagnostics by combining a pre-trained VGG16 architecture with extra layers for fine-tuning.</p><p>This study highlights the model's advantages and possible uses in practical healthcare scenarios by carefully training and testing the model, analyzing performance indicators, and discussing clinical consequences. Data exploration and model evaluation results provide insights on illness distribution, demographic trends, and pixel-level evaluations, enabling a comprehensive understanding of the dataset and the created model. In general, this study aims to improve patient outcomes, increase the detection of pneumonia, and open the door for the incorporation of cutting-edge technologies into standard clinical procedures.</p><p>Future developments in this study have enormous potential to improve both the detection of pneumonia and medical diagnostics in general. First, in order to improve the suggested machine learning model's sensitivity and specificity, more optimization and refinement may be investigated. This could involve investigating ensemble techniques or adopting more sophisticated architectures. Beyond the NIH chest X-ray dataset, including other different datasets may also increase the model's resilience and applicability to a wider range of people and healthcare environments. An understanding of patient health that is more comprehensive may result from the integration of multi-modal data, such as genetic or clinical record data. The concept's practical implementation necessitates collaboration with healthcare experts and institutions for real-world deployment and validation. Furthermore, regular updates and retraining of the model using changing datasets may guarantee that it can adjust to new trends and patterns in pneumonia cases. Investigating the model's explainability and interpretability aspects may help increase acceptability and trust in therapeutic contexts. The ultimate promise of this study is that it will become an invaluable resource for medical professionals, aiding in the early and precise diagnosis of pneumonia, the development of individualized treatment plans, and better patient outcomes.</p><p>The study's conclusion emphasizes the importance of pneumonia as a widespread health concern on a global scale as well as the vital necessity of early detection and intervention. Through the use of machine learning techniques—more specifically, a carefully constructed model architecture and extensive dataset analysis—this study aims to improve pneumonia identification accuracy and, as a result, support better clinical decision-making. The NIH chest X-ray dataset was integrated with significant data preparation and EDA to provide a solid platform for comprehending the intricacies of pneumonia and its associated features.</p><p>The suggested model combines a pre-trained VGG16 architecture with extra layers for fine-tuning, demonstrating the potential of state-of-the-art machine learning techniques in medical diagnostics. Through extensive training, testing, and performance metric analysis, the study highlights the benefits of the model and its possible uses in real-world healthcare settings. With the aid of data exploration and model evaluation, insights obtained from illness distribution, demographic patterns, and pixel-level assessments add to a thorough comprehension of the dataset and the created model.</p><p>More broadly, the goals of this study are to improve patient outcomes, increase the rate at which pneumonia is detected, and open the door for the use of cutting-edge technologies in standard clinical procedures. Further developments in this field have great potential to improve pneumonia diagnosis and medical diagnostics in general. The sensitivity and specificity of the suggested machine learning model could be improved with additional optimization and refinement, possibly by investigating ensemble methods or more complex architectures. Adding more diverse datasets to the NIH chest X-ray dataset should improve the model's resilience and applicability to a wider range of patient demographics and healthcare settings.</p><p>In addition, the amalgamation of multimodal data, such as genetic or clinical records, may provide a more comprehensive comprehension of patient well-being. Collaboration with healthcare organizations and professionals is necessary for the practical application of these principles in order to validate and deploy them in real-world settings. The model will be able to adapt to new trends and patterns in pneumonia cases if it is regularly updated and retrained using dynamic datasets. Furthermore, investigating the model's explainability and interpretability components could promote more acceptance and trust in therapeutic settings.</p><p>In the end, this study aims to be a valuable tool for healthcare professionals, helping to identify pneumonia early and accurately, develop individualized treatment plans, and improve patient outcomes overall. The limitations and importance of this study are emphasized by referencing the original issue statement and placing it within the larger body of literature. This strengthens the results and points the way for further investigation and innovation in the field of medical diagnostics.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>51747-51771</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zaki</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2021.3069937</pub-id>
          <article-title>Intelligent pneumonia identification from chest X-rays: A systematic literature review</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Access</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khatri</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vashista</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mittal</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ranjan</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Janardhanan</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Sarma</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhuyan</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borah</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dutta</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pneumonia identification in chest X-ray images using EMD</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Communication, Cloud, and Big Data</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer, Singapore</publisher-name>
          <year>2020</year>
          <page-range>87-98</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-15-1624-5_9</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>32</volume>
          <page-range>658-672</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ben Atitallah</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Driss</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boulila</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koubaa</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ben Ghezala</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ima.22653</pub-id>
          <article-title>Fusion of convolutional neural networks based on Dempster–Shafer theory for automatic pneumonia detection from chest X‐ray images</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>31</volume>
          <page-range>82-93</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akgundogdu</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ima.22501</pub-id>
          <article-title>Detection of pneumonia in chest X‐ray images by using 2D discrete wavelet feature extraction with random forest</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>122</volume>
          <page-range>103869</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahmud</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rahman</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fattah</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiomed.2020.103869</pub-id>
          <article-title>CovXNet: A multi-dilation convolutional neural network for automatic COVID-19 and other pneumonia detection from chest X-ray images with transferable multi-receptive feature optimization</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>47</volume>
          <page-range>2123-2139</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ayan</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karabulut</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ünver</surname>
              <given-names>H. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13369-021-06127-z</pub-id>
          <article-title>Diagnosis of pediatric pneumonia with ensemble of deep convolutional neural networks in chest X-ray images</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <page-range>1315-1320</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Totla</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ICECA49313.2020.9297388</pub-id>
          <article-title>Deep learning model to predict pneumonia disease based on observed patterns in lung X-rays</article-title>
          <source>2020 4th International Conference on Electronics, Communication and Aerospace Technology (ICECA), Coimbatore, India</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nessipkhanov</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davletova</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurmanbekkyzy</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Omarov</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14569/IJACSA.2023.0141069</pub-id>
          <article-title>Deep CNN for the identification of pneumonia respiratory disease in chest X-ray imagery</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>1-23</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kouser</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aggarwal</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Revolutionizing healthcare: An AI-Powered X-ray analysis app for fast and accurate disease detection</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Sustain. Dev. AI, ML IoT</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>225</volume>
          <page-range>3322-3331</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Atitallah</surname>
              <given-names>S. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Driss</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghézala</surname>
              <given-names>H. B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procs.2023.10.326</pub-id>
          <article-title>Revolutionizing disease diagnosis: A microservices-based architecture for privacy-preserving and efficient IoT data analytics using federated learning</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carlos</surname>
              <given-names>Nuno Rafael Boto</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of a deep learning-based algorithm to predict pneumonia cases fram chest X-ray images</article-title>
          <source>, https://hdl.handle.net/1822/85168</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <publisher-name>Universidade do Minho</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <volume>10950</volume>
          <page-range>200-211</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <publisher-name>SPIE</publisher-name>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rajaraman</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Candemir</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thoma</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Antani</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1117/12.2512752</pub-id>
          <article-title>Visualizing and explaining deep learning predictions for pneumonia detection in pediatric chest radiographs</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Syed</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Machine learning in healthcare: Identifying pneumonia with artificial intelligence</article-title>
          <source>, https://urn.fi/URN:NBN:fi:amk-2018101315963</source>
          <year>2018</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <volume>2023</volume>
          <page-range>2326-2336</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nuwagira</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torlak</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coskunuzer</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Topo-CXR: Chest X-ray TB and pneumonia screening with topological machine learning</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV) Workshops</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>39</volume>
          <page-range>2095-2101</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mane</surname>
              <given-names>Deepak</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashtagi</surname>
              <given-names>Rashmi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumbharkar</surname>
              <given-names>Prashant</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kadam</surname>
              <given-names>Sandeep</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salunkhe</surname>
              <given-names>Dipmala</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Upadhye</surname>
              <given-names>Gopal</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ts.390622</pub-id>
          <article-title>An improved transfer learning approach for classification of types of cancer</article-title>
          <source>Trait. Signal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aljawarneh</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Quraan</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/big.2022.0261</pub-id>
          <article-title>Pneumonia detection using enhanced convolutional neural network model on chest X-Ray images</article-title>
          <source>Big Data</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>23</volume>
          <page-range>689</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alowais</surname>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alghamdi</surname>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alsuhebany</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alqahtani</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alshaya</surname>
              <given-names>A. I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almohareb</surname>
              <given-names>S. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aldairem</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alrashed</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saleh</surname>
              <given-names>K. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Badreldin</surname>
              <given-names>H. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al Yami</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al Harbi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Albekairy</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12909-023-04698-z</pub-id>
          <article-title>Revolutionizing healthcare: The role of artificial intelligence in clinical practice</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>1-21</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ajani</surname>
              <given-names>S. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mulla</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Limkar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashtagi</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagh</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pawar</surname>
              <given-names>M. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00500-023-08613-y</pub-id>
          <article-title>DLMBHCO: Design of an augmented bioinspired deep learning-based multidomain body parameter analysis via heterogeneous correlative body organ analysis</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>RSNA pneumonia detection challenge</article-title>
          <source>, https://kaggle.com/competitions/rsna-pneumonia-detection-challenge</source>
          <year>2018</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>56</volume>
          <page-range>348-356</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fontanellaz</surname>
              <given-names>Matthias</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ebner</surname>
              <given-names>Lukas</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huber</surname>
              <given-names>Adrian</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peters</surname>
              <given-names>Alan</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Löbelenz</surname>
              <given-names>Laura</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hourscht</surname>
              <given-names>Cynthia</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klaus</surname>
              <given-names>Jeremias</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Munz</surname>
              <given-names>Jaro</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruder</surname>
              <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drakopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>Dionysios</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sieron</surname>
              <given-names>Dominik</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Primetis</surname>
              <given-names>Elias</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heverhagen</surname>
              <given-names>Johannes T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mougiakakou</surname>
              <given-names>Stavroula</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Christe</surname>
              <given-names>Andreas</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/RLI.0000000000000748</pub-id>
          <article-title>A deep-learning diagnostic support system for the detection of COVID-19 using chest radiographs: A multireader validation study</article-title>
          <source>Invest. Radiol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>