<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ATG</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Acadlore Transactions on Geosciences</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Acadlore Trans. Geosci.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">ATG</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2958-1877</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-1869</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-Wf9VA66iGFVceFic6xKZyPzSfl49cZ9h</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/atg020104</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Impact of Climate Disasters on Railway Infrastructure: Case Study of Northeast India</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1,2">1,2</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Roy</surname>
            <given-names>Stabak</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6937-9301</contrib-id>
          <email>stabak.geography@tripurauniv.in</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1">1</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Debnath</surname>
            <given-names>Pradip</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2863-2213</contrib-id>
          <email>dbtpradip@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1">1</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Mitra</surname>
            <given-names>Saptarshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2100-2315</contrib-id>
          <email>saptarshigeotu2000@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="1">Department of Geography and Disaster Management, Tripura University, 799022 Suryamaninagar, India</aff>
        <aff id="2">Institute of Socio-Economic Geography and Spatial Management, University of Gdansk, 80-309 Gdansk, Poland</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <year>2023</year>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>33</fpage>
      <lpage>45</lpage>
      <page-range>33-45</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <month>01</month>
          <day>09</day>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <month>03</month>
          <day>01</day>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="pub">
          <month>03</month>
          <day>30</day>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2023 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <license>. Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the <a href='https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/' target='_blank' class='text-yellow-700 hover:underline'>CC BY 4.0 license</a>.</license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Climate disasters have become increasingly frequent in India, severely affecting the railway infrastructure every year. Physical damages to railway tracks, bridges, and signaling systems, caused by floods, cyclones, and landslides, are well documented. However, the impact of these disasters on the railway infrastructure was beyond direct physical damages. This paper aimed to explore the impact of climate disasters on railway infrastructure in Northeast India using case study approach. Three cases were studied to analyse the impact of climate disasters on railway infrastructure, including geological disasters and extreme weather. Infrastructure development and operation of railway transport system in Assam, Mizoram, and Manipur proved to be challenging, especially when coping with natural disasters, such as floods, landslides, and earthquakes. This paper found that disruption of railway services was associated with geo-physical structure of the region, which triggered the disaster vulnerability. The results showed that climate disasters had a significant impact on railway infrastructure in Northeast India in many aspects. Formulation and implementation of strategic policies might reduce the disaster risks. Therefore, policymakers and Ministry of Railways, Government of India should consider this possible probability approach over environmental determinism.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Railway geography</kwd>
        <kwd>Railway infrastructure</kwd>
        <kwd>Northeast India</kwd>
        <kwd>Environmental determinism</kwd>
        <kwd>Possible probability</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors">3</count>
        <fig-count>6</fig-count>
        <table-count>2</table-count>
        <ref-count>50</ref-count>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Climate change has become a significant stimulating factor in many environmental disasters. Climate disasters refer to events that are either caused or worsened by climate change effects, including rising temperatures, changing rainfall patterns, sea level increments, and frequent violent weather [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], which harm human societies and ecosystems in countless ways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], leading to loss of life, displacement, economic harm, and food scarcity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. Railway transport has been making significant contributions to the Indian economy, with the Indian Railways being one of the largest employers in the country [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>]. Railway infrastructure plays a critical role in goods transport across India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. As an essential component of the transportation system, railways may be faced with immense challenges when dealing with the effects of climate change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. Climate disasters cause considerable harm to the railway infrastructure of India, because India has vast railway network in a wide range of regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>]. Landslides, floods, and cyclones are the major climate disasters affecting Indian railway infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], which only account for a small proportion of disasters due to the diverse geography of India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. Those climate events damage railway tracks, bridges, and railway stations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]. Apart from direct physical damages, those climate disasters significantly affect railway infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], by disrupting railway services, which affects supply chains, resulting in delayed delivery of goods and increased transportation costs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>], as well as economic losses for the railways and the wider economy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. In Northeast India, there is a high risk of various climate disasters, including floods, landslides, and cyclones, which have a substantial impact on the railway infrastructure in the region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>]. Due to relatively young terrain, weak geologic foundation, and active tectonics, this region is susceptible to landslide events, which contains nearly one fifth of India's landslide-prone zones and has further exacerbated because of numerous development activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]. Indian Railways has adopted various measures to alleviate the impact of climate disasters on railway infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], including construction of retaining walls, erection of bridges with increased spans, and utilization of geo-synthetic materials for slope stabilization purposes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>]. Moreover, Indian Railways has been investing in cutting-edge technologies, such as remote sensing and geographic information systems, to monitor and predict natural disasters, thus taking proactive steps to prevent or mitigate any harm to railway infrastructure.</p><p>This paper aimed to find the impact of climate disasters on railway infrastructure in Northeast India.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>2. Methodology</title>
      <p>Case study approach was used to study the impact of climate disasters on the railway infrastructure in Northeast India in the following steps:</p><p>Step 1: The research question was defined, "What is the negative impact of climate disasters on the railway infrastructure in Northeast India?"</p><p>Step 2: A suitable case study was selected after assessing several factors, including the severity of climate disasters and the availability of relevant data. Three events were considered for this purpose, namely, the Assam floods in 2022, the Mizoram landslides in 2020, and the Manipur earthquake in 2016, which caused extensive damages to the railway infrastructure in the region.</p><p>Step 3: Relevant data on the impact was collected from diverse sources, such as scholarly publications, media coverage, official government documents, and railway regulatory bodies.</p><p>Step 4: The collated data was thoroughly examined to determine the impact. Various methodologies were used to analyse the data, such as content and thematic analysis, statistical scrutiny, and logistic regression.</p><p>Step 5: The outcomes of scrutinized data were effectively used to identify the impact.</p><p>Step 6: Communicate the results to all relevant parties, such as the public, policy makers, and railway officials. The results may be presented by various means.</p><p>The case study methodology was used to examine the impact of climate disasters on Indian railway infrastructure, by describing the research question, identifying the specific case study, gathering empirical evidences, scrutinizing the data, interpreting the resultant discoveries, and effectively conveying the outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>3. Study area</title>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>Location map of the study area</caption>
          <abstract>Source: Prepared by the authors, 2023</abstract>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/3/img_xNVFQeMJVvoVI7bh.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p><span style="color: windowtext">Northeast India is situated in easternmost India and comprises eight states, namely, Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland, Sikkim, and Tripura </span>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>]. T<span style="color: windowtext">his region shares its borders with neighbouring countries, such as Bhutan, China, Bangladesh, Myanmar, and Nepal (</span><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>)<span style="color: windowtext">, with the majestic Himalayan Mountain range in the north, the Patkai Hills and the alluvial plains of the Brahmaputra Valley in the south, and the verdant Barak Valley in the west</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]. N<span style="color: windowtext">ortheast India has several significant rivers, such as Brahmaputra, Barak, and Meghna</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>]. <span style="color: windowtext">This region is known for its rugged and mountainous landscape, dotted with countless hills, valleys, and plateaus</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>].<span style="color: windowtext"> Its geological formations are heterogeneous, encompassing rock formations from the ancient Precambrian era to the younger Tertiary perio</span>d [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]. <span style="color: windowtext">Furthermore, the region is prone to seismic activities and regularly experiences earthquakes due to its location in active seismic zones</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>].<span style="color: windowtext"> The climate of Northeast India is varied, with lower sub-tropical temperatures and higher alpine temperatures. The monsoon brings heavy downpour that often causes floods and landslides </span>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]. <span style="color: windowtext">Climate change has significantly made extreme events more frequent and intense almost every year. Northeast India is renowned for its abundant cultural diversity because it has more than 200 ethnic groups and languages</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="results">
      <title>4. Results</title>
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>4.1. Case study 1: assam floods (2022)</title>
          
          <p>Assam boasts a vast river system comprising the Brahmaputra, Barak and their tributaries. Although these rivers provide fertile land for agriculture and efficient transport system, they make the state vulnerable to frequent floods. Heavy rainfall upstream causes the rivers and their tributaries to overflow and submerges the surrounding areas, leading to recurring floods in Assam (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>). Assam experiences devastating floods almost every year, and some regions are more susceptible to flooding, including Dhemaji, Lakhimpur, Biswanath, Sonitpur, Darrang, Nalbari, Barpeta, Bongaigaon, Kokrajhar, Dhubri, Goalpara, Morigaon, Nagaon, Hojai, and Karbi Anglong in the northern and central parts of the state, which are located along the banks of the Brahmaputra and its tributaries. Floods are not strange to Assam because about 77.97 percent of this state is flood-prone (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>). However, the floods in 2022 were particularly devastating, affecting millions of people and causing significant damages to the infrastructure in Assam, including railway transportation system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>].</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>Railway infrastructure in Assam with drainage and relief</caption>
              <abstract>Source: Prepared by the authors, 2023</abstract>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/3/img_fBphzfW3MwedcDHU.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>The floods in 2022 were caused by various factors, particularly heavy monsoon rains and water drainage from upstream dams in the neighbouring Arunachal Pradesh [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>]. Heavy monsoon rains inundated low-lying areas from June to September in 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>] and the resulting torrential rains triggered flooding across Assam [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>]. The Brahmaputra River and its tributaries burst their banks, submerging huge expanses of land. The downpour also resulted in landslides and soil erosion, contributing further to the flooding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>]. In addition, the water drainage from upstream dams in Arunachal Pradesh worsened the flooding in Assam. The dams were part of a hydroelectric project on the Brahmaputra River, and water drainage was crucial to sustaining the water levels for power generation. However, the sudden gush of water swelled the river, flooding Assam downstream. The districts of Dibrugarh, Tinsukia, and Jorhat with several tea gardens were severely affected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>].</p><p>This output represented a linear regression model without specifying the dependent variable. However, it included coefficients, standard error coefficients, Z-values, p-values, and Variance Inflation Factors (VIF) for the predictor variable "number of railway stations" as well as the intercept term "constant".</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>Railway infrastructure and flood prone districts in Assam state</caption>
              <abstract>Source: Prepared by the authors, 2023</abstract>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">No.</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Name of the district</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Number of railway stations</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone district</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Disaster category</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Baksa</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">4</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Non-flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">2</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Barpeta</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">11</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">3</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Biswanath</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">4</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">4</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Bongaigaon</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">10</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">5</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Cachar</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">15</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Non-flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">6</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Charaideo</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">7</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Chirang</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">4</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">8</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Darrang</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">7</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">9</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Dhemaji</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">5</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">10</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Dhubri</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">9</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">11</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Dibrugarh</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">7</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">12</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Dima Hasao</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">3</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Non-flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">13</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Goalpara</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">6</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">14</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Golaghat</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">10</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">15</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Hailakandi</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">5</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Non-flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">16</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Hojai</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">17</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Jorhat</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">9</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">18</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Kamrup</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">3</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Non-flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">19</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Kamrup Metropolitan</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">12</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Non-flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">20</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Karbi Anglong</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">7</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">21</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Karimganj</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">7</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Non-flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">22</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Kokrajhar</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">6</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">23</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Lakhimpur</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">10</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">24</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Majuli</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">2</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">25</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Morigaon</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">6</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">26</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Nagaon</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">12</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Non-flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">27</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Nalbari</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">7</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">28</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Sivasagar</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">6</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">29</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Sonitpur</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">12</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">30</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Mankachar</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">3</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Non-flood prone</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">31</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Tinsukia</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">12</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">1</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="color: black; font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Flood prone</span></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p><span style="color: windowtext">The coefficient for "number of railway stations" was -0.016. This meant that for a one-unit increase in the number of railway stations, the predicted value of the dependent variable decreased by a factor of 0.016 when all other predictor variables were held constant. The standard error of the coefficient was 0.110, which indicated the amount of variability in the estimates of the regression coefficient. The Z-value (-0.14) was obtained by dividing the coefficient by the standard error. The p-value (0.887) of the coefficient was not significant (greater than 0.05), indicating that the variable (number of railway stations) did not significantly affect the dependent variable.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">VIF indicated the amount of multi-collinearity between predictor variables. In this case, the VIF for the predictor variable was 1, which was relatively low and indicated no significant correlation between the predictor variable "number of railway stations" and any other predictors in the model.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">On the whole, this model suggested that the variable (number of railway stations) was not a significant predictor variable of the dependent variable.</span></p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> <span style="color: windowtext">shows information on the goodness of fit in statistical model. The deviance measured how well the model fit the data, with lower values indicating better fit. In this case, the deviance was relatively high, suggesting that the model was not a good fit.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">Regression equation was as follows:</span></p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>P</mi>
                <mi>exp</mi>
                <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <msup>
                    <mi>Y</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msup>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mo>/</mo>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="NONE">⁡</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                  <mi>exp</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msup>
                      <mi>Y</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msup>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(2)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msup>
                  <mi>Y</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi data-mjx-alternate="1">′</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </msup>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>−</mo>
                <mn>1.004</mn>
                <mn>0.016</mn>
                <mi>N</mi>
                <mi>u</mi>
                <mi>m</mi>
                <mi>b</mi>
                <mi>e</mi>
                <mi>r</mi>
                <mi>o</mi>
                <mi>f</mi>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mi>a</mi>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>l</mi>
                <mi>w</mi>
                <mi>a</mi>
                <mi>y</mi>
                <mi>S</mi>
                <mi>t</mi>
                <mi>a</mi>
                <mi>t</mi>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>o</mi>
                <mi>n</mi>
                <mi>s</mi>
                <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                  <mspace width="0.167em"/>
                </mstyle>
                <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                  <mspace width="0.167em"/>
                </mstyle>
                <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                  <mspace width="0.167em"/>
                </mstyle>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p><span style="color: windowtext">The R-squared value indicated the proportion of variability in the response variable that the model explained. In this case, the R-squared value was extremely low, indicating that the model explained only a tiny fraction of the variation in the data. The adjusted R-squared value considered the number of predictor variables in the model and was, therefore, a more accurate measure of goodness of fit when multiple predictor variables existed. AIC, AICc, and BIC were measures of model complexity and provided a method of comparing different models. Lower values of these measures indicated better models. In this case, all three values were relatively high.</span></p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>Summary of logistic regression model</caption>
              <abstract>Computed by the authors, 2023</abstract>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Deviance R-Sq</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Deviance R-Sq (adj)</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">AIC</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">AICc</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">BIC</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">Area under ROC curve</span></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0.05%</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0.00%</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">41.33</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">41.76</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">44.20</span></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p style="text-align: center"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman, serif">0.4773</span></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p><span style="color: windowtext">Finally, the area under the ROC curve measured the model's ability to classify cases into categories correctly. The value was 0.4773 in this case, indicating that the classification ability was not much better than chance.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">The flooding in Assam in 2022 inflicted extensive harm on the infrastructure, particularly the railway transport system</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>]. T<span style="color: windowtext">he Northeast Frontier Railway (NFR), operating in Northeast India, suffered serious damages to its tracks and bridges. The entire railway service network was severely affected. In conclusion, heavy monsoon rains and subsequent water drainage from upstream dams in Arunachal Pradesh caused the 2022 flooding in Assam. Geographic location, low-lying areas and proximity to the Brahmaputra River aggravated the vulnerability of Assam to flooding.</span></p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>Major hydro-meteorological hazards and their impact on railway infrastructure in Assam, 2022</caption>
              <abstract>Source: different newspapers. A. Down To Earth, B. Deccan Herald, C. Scroll. in and D. Mint</abstract>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/3/img_FJAEh3IA4LlYM0Sc.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p><span style="color: windowtext">According to a report from Northeast Now, the Haflong railway station in the Dima Hasao district was completely submerged by torrential rains in 2022. Pictures revealed that devastating floods and landslides inundated and destoryed train tracks (</span><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref><span style="color: windowtext">). Train services between Haflong and Silchar were completely affected by flooding at Kapurcherra. Heavy landslides in different areas also affected Haflong-Lanka rail transportation. During extreme floods, railway services were affected in certain parts of Tripura, Mizoram and Manipur, threatening human safety and causing significant disruption and associated economic crisis. Assam State Disaster Management Authority reported about 200,000 people in different districts of Assam were affected by the recent flood. The Dima Hasao railway line, which dated back to 1899, underwent a conversion from metre-gauge to broad-gauge that was approved between 1996-1997. The railway became a national project in 2004 and began to transport passengers in November 2015. However, the principal director of audit issued a theme-based audit report during the conversion process, which warned the railway authorities of potential issues caused by inadequate geotechnical investigation, flawed planning, and failure to anticipate soil strata behaviour. Subsequently, the Commissioner of Railway Safety issued a report, which highlighted significant deficiencies to be addressed before operating passenger trains safely. The disruption of train services was significant, because many passengers relied on the railway transport system for daily commuting and goods transportation. The floods suspended several passenger trains, causing inconvenience and hardship to passengers.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">Impact on the railway transport system in Assam showed that infrastructure planning and investment needed to be improved urgently to enhance its resilience against natural disaste</span>rs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>].<span style="color: windowtext"> Many tracks and bridges of the NFR were either washed away or severely damaged, disrupting train services throughout the region. NFR officials estimated that around 200 km railway tracks were damaged in Assam alone, with the worst-hit areas in the districts of Dibrugarh, Tinsukia, and Jorhat. Landslides, erosion, and embankment breaches caused the damages, making it challenging to repair the tracks quickly</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>].</p><p><span style="color: windowtext">Moreover, floods significantly affected the economy of Assam, particularly tea transport from gardens to markets, resulting in decreased production and revenue</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>].<span style="color: windowtext"> The floods also damaged many roads and highways, making it difficult to transport goods by road. The NFR worked tirelessly to repair the damaged tracks and bridges in order to restore train services promptly. However, due to continuing rains and difficult terrain, it took several weeks to fully restore train services. Therefore, the floods in 2022 were a stark reminder that the infrastructure in Assam was vulnerable to natural disasters. The impact on the railway transport system highlighted the need for better planning and investment in infrastructure, thus making it more resilient to such events.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">There are several strategic solutions to mitigate the effects of floods on railway infrastructure in Assam. The first step is to map the flood-prone areas using satellite imagery, topographic maps, and other remote sensing techniques. Once the flood-prone areas are identified, it becomes easier to plan and design the railway infrastructure accordingly. The railway infrastructure can be elevated or designed to resist flood events. Other steps can be taken, such as flood-resistant infrastructure, proper drainage systems, monitoring systems, and emergency response plans. These solutions require collaborative efforts between government agencies, railway authorities, and local communities, thus ensuring that the transportation system maintain normal operation during floods.</span></p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>4.2. Case study 2: mizoram landslides (2020)</title>
          
          <p><span style="color: windowtext">Situated in a region with high seismic activities, Mizoram has complex geological structure, including sedimentary, igneous and metamorphic rocks. The area is prone to tectonic movements and earthquakes, which trigger landslides by destabilizing slopes. Geologically, Mizoram was formed in the tertiary era, and the dominant rock types are shale and unconsolidated sandstone. It is hilly with rugged terrain and steep slopes and the topography is characterized by deep valleys, narrow ridges, and sharp crests. The soil in Mizoram is predominantly clayey and highly weathered, with poor permeability and low shear strength, which makes the slopes prone to erosion and landslides, especially in case of heavy rainfall. Situated in Northeast India, Mizoram has abundant rainfall, which often make it susceptible to landslides and other natural calamities</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">44</xref>]. Mi<span style="color: windowtext">zoram experiences heavy landslides every year during the monsoon season, mainly caused by heavy rainfall and soil erosion. In July 2020, several parts of Mizoram, including the districts of Sairang and Lunglawn, were devastated by landslides triggered by heavy rainfall. Four children, with two of them under the age of five, died on the spot, in accordance with local police report. The landslides caused significant damages to roads, bridges and other infrastructure, including railway tracks</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>]. <span style="color: windowtext">The NFR identified many of its railway tracks and bridges were severely damaged or washed away, disrupting train services in the region. According to NFR officials, around 15 km railway tracks were destroyed in Mizoram alone, with Sairang and Lunglawn districts damaged the most (</span><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>)<span style="color: windowtext">.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">Damages to railway infrastructure significantly affected the people of Mizoram, many of whom depended on the railway transport system for daily commuting and goods transportation. Disruption of train services caused inconvenience and hardship to passengers and also affected the economy in the state. The Ministry of Railways data showed that the NFR operated around 3,000 km railway tracks in Northeast India, including Mizoram. The NFR has been developing a new broad-gauge railway line project, which is 51.38 km long and connects Bhairabi with Sairang at an estimated cost of 65.27 billion rupees. Once completed, this project will link the state capital of Mizoram, Aizawl, with the rest of the region, making it a "project of national importance". As a part of this project, four new stations, 55 crucial bridges, 87 smaller bridges, 11 Road Over Bridges/Road Under Bridges, and 12.6 km tunnel will be constructed. This initiative is a crucial step in enhancing socio-economic growth and connectivity in the regio</span>n [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>]. <span style="color: windowtext">The railway network is vital in connecting the remote areas of the region with the rest of the country and serving as a lifeline for goods transportation</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">47</xref>].</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>Railway infrastructure of Mizoram with landslide data</caption>
              <abstract>Source: prepared by the authors, 2023</abstract>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/3/img_qoOlz_m9k3jV88HP.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p><span style="color: windowtext">The 2020 Mizoram landslides have highlighted the pressing need to improve infrastructure planning and investment in order to enhance its resilience to natural disasters. The state government and NFR have taken actions to repair the damaged tracks and bridges and improve the safety of railway infrastructure. With adequate measures in place, the railway transport system can continue to play a critical role in connecting remote areas in Northeast India with the rest of the country.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">Geotechnical investigation and monitoring along the railway not only help identify areas prone to landslides, but also provides information on the stability of slopes and the nature of soil and rock formations, thus helping design effective slope stabilization measures. Proper drainage management is critical in preventing landslides. Drainage system design should prevent water from accumulating on the slopes, which increases the weight and pressure on the soil and rock formations, leading to landslides. Drainage system should also be regularly inspected and maintained to ensure effective functioning. The combination of various measures helps mitigate the impact of landslides on railway infrastructure in Mizoram, such as geotechnical investigation and monitoring, slope stabilization measures, drainage management, vegetation management, and early warning systems. These strategic solutions help ensure the safety and stability of railway infrastructure, while reducing economic losses caused by transportation disruptions.</span></p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>4.3. Case study 3: manipur earthquake (2016)</title>
          
          <p><span style="color: windowtext">Located in Northeast India, Manipur has been grappling with issues of underdevelopment and poor connectivity for a long time</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">48</xref>].<span style="color: windowtext"> However, the state has been making strides in infrastructure development in recent years, including railway transport system. The railway transport system in Manipur has several challenge</span>s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], <span style="color: windowtext">because the hilly terrain is prone to landslides, which makes the construction process difficult. </span><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> <span style="color: windowtext">shows the challenges confronting the railway construction from Jiribam to Imphal.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">In addition, Manipur has insurgency issue, which has delayed the construction process. Another challenge of the railway transport system in Manipur is lack of proper maintenance, because heavy rainfall and landslides often damage tracks and disrupt train services.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">In early January 2016, Manipur experienced a strong earthquake measuring 6.7 on the Richter scale, caused by the collision of the Indian and Eurasian tectonic plates. The earthquake, with its epicentre in the Tamenglong district and approximately 17 km deep, caused widespread damages to infrastructure and buildings across the state. The region where the earthquake occurred is characterized by several active faults, including the Imphal fault, which is known to be a highly active fault. Due to the movement along the Imphal fault, energy was suddenly released in the form of seismic waves and caused earthquake. The Imphal fault is a part of the larger Indo-Burmese arc, which is the boundary between the Indian plate and the Burmese microplate. The movement along this boundary formed the Himalayas, and the region is characterized by high-level seismic activities. The impact of earthquake on the railway infrastructure in Manipur was significant, with several railway bridges and tracks damaged.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">The NFR said that many tracks and bridges were severely damaged or washed away by the earthquake. According to NFR officials, around 30 railway bridges were damaged in Manipur alone, with the worst-hit areas in the districts of Tamenglong and Noney (</span><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref>). <span style="color: windowtext">Damages to the railway infrastructure had a significant impact on the people of Manipur, many of whom depended on the railway transport system for daily commuting and goods transportation. Disruption of train services caused inconvenience and hardship to passengers and also affected the economy in the state. According to data from the Ministry of Railways, the NFR operated around 3,000 km railway tracks in Northeast India, including Manipur. The railway network plays a crucial role in connecting the remote areas of the region with the rest of the country and also serves as a life-line for goods transportation.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">The earthquake in Manipur in 2016 has highlighted the need for better planning and investment in infrastructure, thus making it more resilient to natural disaster</span>s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>]. <span style="color: windowtext">The state government and the NFR have taken steps to repair the damaged tracks and bridges and improve the safety of railway infrastructure. With proper measures in place, the railway transport system can continue to play a crucial role in connecting the remote areas in Northeast India with the rest of the country.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">The railway transport system in Manipur has the potential to transform the state's connectivity and improve its overall development. However, the state government needs to address the challenges faced by the system. With proper planning and implementation, the railway transport system in Manipur can become a vital component of infrastructure in the state and contribute to its growth</span> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">50</xref>].</p><p><span style="color: windowtext">The railway transport system in Manipur has the potential to transform the state's connectivity and improve its overall development. However, the state government needs to address the challenges faced by the system. With proper planning and implementation, the railway transport system in Manipur can become a vital component of infrastructure in the state and contribute to its growt</span>h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">50</xref>].</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_5">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>Railway infrastructure of Manipur with earthquake sites</caption>
              <abstract>Source: Prepared by the authors, 2023</abstract>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/3/img_hOrKmzq-VaFJClzj.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>This paper suggested some strategic solutions to mitigate the impact of earthquakes on railway infrastructure in Manipur. The first step is to make comprehensive seismic hazard analysis, which helps identify the areas most susceptible to earthquake events and provide information on the expected intensity and frequency, thus helping engineers design earthquake-resistant railway infrastructure. Then the next step is to transform the existing railway infrastructure to resist earthquakes, including reinforcing railway structures, tracks, bridges, tunnels, and viaducts, as well as stabilizing slopes and embankments. Advanced technologies, such as sensors and real-time monitoring systems, can be used to help detect seismic activities early and provide alerts to railway operators, thus allowing them to take precautionary measures, including slowing down or stopping trains in high-risk areas. It is crucial to have a well-defined earthquake emergency response plan in place, including procedures for evacuating passengers and personnel from trains, as well as repairing any damages to railway infrastructure. Finally, it is essential to increase public awareness of earthquake safety and preparedness, including providing information on what to do in earthquake, as well as conducting drills and exercises to help people prepare for such events.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_6">
              <label>Figure 6</label>
              <caption>Different railway tunnels (A-B) and bridges (C-D) in Manipur railway</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/3/img_MbXWcBySKrgYx238.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>5. Findings</title>
      <p><span style="color: windowtext">Climate change poses significant challenges for railways in India. Extreme weather events, such as landslides, floods, and earthquakes, cause severe damages to railway infrastructure. Disruption of railway services caused by climate disasters leads to economic losses for the railways and the wider economy. Indian Railways has adopted various measures to alleviate the impact of climatic disasters on railway infrastructure, including use of advanced technologies for monitoring and predicting natural disasters. The railway transport system plays a significant role in Indian economy and daily life of many citizens. The states of Assam, Mizoram and Manipur have faced challenges in railway infrastructure development and maintenance, particularly in dealing with natural disasters, such as floods, landslides, and earthquakes.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">To mitigate the effects of climate change, Indian Railways has adopted various measures, particularly use of advanced technologies for monitoring and predicting natural disasters, including satellite imaging, remote sensing, geographic information systems (GIS), and other advanced data analysis tools. By using these tools, the railways can identify areas with higher-risk natural disasters and take preventative measures to mitigate the risks. Another important measure taken by Indian Railways is the development and maintenance of railway infrastructure, including construction of new railways and maintenance of existing railways to ensure their durability and resilience to climate disasters. In addition, Indian Railways has been investing significantly in infrastructure development and maintenance, thus ensuring that rail passengers and cargo can be transported safely and efficiently, even in climate disasters. However, more efforts always can be made to reduce the impact of climate change on railway infrastructure.</span></p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>6. Policy recommendation</title>
      <p>Climate disasters have a significant impact on railway infrastructure and operation, which in turn affects the safety and well-being of passengers and staff. It is critical for Indian Railways to make clear disaster response plans to deal with floods, earthquakes, landslides, and other related events. One critical aspect is emergency rescue planning, which involves contingency plans in place for evacuating passengers and staff in disasters, as well as ensures emergency response teams are well equipped and trained to respond effectively. Another critical aspect is investment in funding, manpower, and material resources. Indian Railways should allocate resources to ensure that adequate infrastructure and safety measures are in place to prevent and mitigate the impact of disasters, including technology investment to monitor and detect impending disasters, such as weather forecasting equipment, and investment in strong and durable infrastructure and safety equipment.</p><p>Furthermore, Indian Railways should clearly know the potential risks and challenges associated with different types of disasters, and tailor their response plans accordingly. For example, Assam is prone to flooding, and the Indian Railways should take steps to strengthen the infrastructure in that region to resist the potential impact of flooding. To sum up, climate disaster response plans for railway infrastructure should be comprehensive, flexible, well funded, and tailored to the specific risks and challenges of different types of disasters. By prioritizing emergency rescue planning and investing in infrastructure and safety measures, Indian Railways can help protect their passengers and staff from the potentially devastating impact of climate disasters.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>7. Conclusions</title>
      <p><span style="color: windowtext">Climate events, such as floods, landslides, earthquakes with specific set of geo-physical structure, create disasters in unique form, which have a negative impact on railway infrastructure. Due to its unique topography and location, Northeast India is particularly vulnerable to climate disasters. A wide range of disasters, including floods, landslides, and earthquakes, significantly affect the railway transport system in the region. Three case studies of different climate disasters showed that geo-physical structure of the region mainly caused the disaster vulnerability. Risks of disaster vulnerability vary in different regions. However, in order to prevent disasters and reduce their effects, Indian Railways should invest resources to ensure that necessary infrastructure and safety procedures are in place, including investment in both technology for tracking and predicting disasters, such as weather forecasting tools, and sturdy and long-lasting infrastructure and safety gear. In addition, Indian Railways should understand the potential dangers and difficulties of various disasters to adjust their reaction strategies.</span></p><p><span style="color: windowtext">It is feasible to assume philosophically that environmental determinism is a significant factor to railway development in Northeast India. However, policy interventions at different levels have created possible probability, which might reduce the disaster risks on railway system in the region.</span></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><span style="color: windowtext">The contributions of each author in the following statement: "Conceptualisation, S.R. and S.M.; methodology, S.R. and P.D.; software, S.R.; validation, S.R., S.M. and P.D.; formal analysis, S.R.; investigation, P.D.; data curation, S.R.; writing—original draft preparation, S.R.; writing—review and editing, S.R., S.M and P.D.; visualisation, S.R.; supervision, S.M. All authors have read and agreed to the publication of the manuscript.".</span></p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p></p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p><span>The data [Geo-spatial Data] supporting our research results are included within the article.</span></p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Alimonti</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Mariani</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Prodi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
              <surname>Ricci</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A critical assessment of extreme events trends in times of global warming</article-title>
          <source>Eur Phys. J. Plus</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>137</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1140/epjp/s13360-021-02243-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">112</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
              <surname>Marselle</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Stadler</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Korn</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K. N.</given-names>
              <surname>Irvine</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Bonn</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title/>
          <source>Biodiversity and Health in the Face of Climate Change</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>C. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Boda</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Faran</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Scown</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Dorkenoo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B. C.</given-names>
              <surname>Chaffin</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Nastar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
              <surname>Boyd</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Loss and damage from climate change and implicit assumptions of sustainable development</article-title>
          <source>Clim Chang.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>164</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-021-02970-z</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mitra</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Railway transport system in Tripura, India: An geographical analysis</article-title>
          <source>Geogr Rev. India</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>40-57</page-range>
          <fpage>40</fpage>
          <lpage>57</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mitra</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Infrastructural development and future scope of railway transport system in Tripura: A spatial analysis</article-title>
          <source>Purvottaran - The Rise of North East: Paradigms of Development in the VUCA World</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>Bloomsbury</publisher-name>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mitra</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Does physio-environmental determinism influence the infrastructural development of railway stations?</article-title>
          <source>J. Infrastruct. Dev.</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>91-126</page-range>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>126</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1177/09749306221140720</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Y. Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Zeng</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Ran</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>X. B.</given-names>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Optimal pricing and service for the peak-period bus commuting inefficiency of boarding queuing congestion</article-title>
          <source>Sustain.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>0</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/su10103497</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3497</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>E. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Palin</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
              <surname>Stipanovic Oslakovic</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Gavin</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Quinn</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Implications of climate change for railway infrastructure</article-title>
          <source>Clim Chang.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1002/wcc.728</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e728</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Impacts of natural hazards and climate change on EU security and defence</article-title>
          <source>European Commission Joint Research Centre</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <uri>https://ec.europa.eu/newsroom/jrc_drm/items/733859/</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Migoń</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
              <surname>Pijet-Migoń</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Natural disasters, geotourism, and geo-interpretation</article-title>
          <source>Geoheritage</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>629-640</page-range>
          <fpage>629</fpage>
          <lpage>640</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s12371-018-0316-x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Hore</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mitra</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Chaberek</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Delineating regional differentiation on the development of the railway infrastructure in northeast India through an efficient synthetic indicator</article-title>
          <source>Transp. Probl.</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>149-162</page-range>
          <fpage>149</fpage>
          <lpage>162</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.20858/tp.2022.17.3.13</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Chinowsky</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Helman</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Gulati</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Neumann</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Martinich</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Impacts of climate change on operation of the US rail network</article-title>
          <source>Transp. Policy</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>183-191</page-range>
          <fpage>183</fpage>
          <lpage>191</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tranpol.2017.05.007</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>T. N.</given-names>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z. H.</given-names>
              <surname>Qu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z. L.</given-names>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Nichol</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Dimitriu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Bowden</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P. T.</given-names>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Impact analysis of climate change on rail systems for adaptation planning: A UK case</article-title>
          <source>Transp. Res. D Transp. Environ.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trd.2020.102324</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102324</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M. T.</given-names>
              <surname>Chaudhary</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Piracha</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Natural disastersOrigins, impacts, management</article-title>
          <source>Encyc.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>1101-1131</page-range>
          <fpage>1101</fpage>
          <lpage>1131</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/encyclopedia1040084</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mitra</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Railway stations of Tripura, India: An assessment of infrastructural conditions</article-title>
          <source>Urbanization and Regional Sustainability in South Asia</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-23796-7_11</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
              <surname>Dolcemascolo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Bianchi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Ranieri</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Climate change adaptation of railway networks: a framework for action</article-title>
          <source>J. Infrast. Syst.</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1061/(ASCE)IS.1943-555X.0000481</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">04019020</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Chaudhury</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Ghosh</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Jat</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Climate change and disaster resilience in South Asian countries: A systemic review of policies and practices</article-title>
          <source>Int J Disast Risk Re</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijdrr.2020.101293</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101293</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mitra</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Bera</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar De</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A geomorphological investigation of gurpisey landslide in eastern himalayas</article-title>
          <source>Malays J. Trop Geogr.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>1-16</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>16</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Ghosh</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar De</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Geophysical investigation and management plan of a shallow landslide along the NH-44 in Atharamura Hill, Tripura, India</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Geohazards Environ.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>119-130</page-range>
          <fpage>119</fpage>
          <lpage>130</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.15273/ijge.2016.03.013</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Sengupta</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Nath</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>GIS-based landslide susceptibility mapping in eastern boundary zone of northeast India in compliance with indo-burmese subduction tectonics</article-title>
          <source>Geospatial Technology for Environmental Hazards, Cham</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>19-37</page-range>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>37</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-75197-5_2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Naswa</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Garg</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Managing climate-induced risks on Indian infrastructure assets</article-title>
          <source>Curr. Sci.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>395-404</page-range>
          <fpage>395</fpage>
          <lpage>404</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Thaduri</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Garmabaki</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Impact of climate change on railway operation and maintenance in Sweden: A state-of-the-art review</article-title>
          <source>Maint. Reliab. Condit. Monit.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>52-70</page-range>
          <fpage>52</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.21595/mrcm.2021.22136</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Mukherjee</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Abhinay</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
              <surname>Rahman</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Yangdhen</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Sen</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B. R.</given-names>
              <surname>Adhikari</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Nianthi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Sachdev</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Shaw</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extent and evaluation of critical infrastructure, the status of resilience and its future dimensions in South Asia</article-title>
          <source>Prog. Disaster Sci.</source>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pdisas.2023.100275</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100275</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Blackwood</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F. G.</given-names>
              <surname>Renaud</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Gillespie</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nature-based solutions as climate change adaptation measures for rail infrastructure</article-title>
          <source>Nature-Based Solutions</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nbsj.2022.100013</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100013</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mitra</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Infrastructural status of railway transport system in northeast India: A geographical analysis</article-title>
          <source>Asian J. Spatial Sci.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>89-100</page-range>
          <fpage>89</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Debnath</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mitra</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The growth pattern and future developmental trends of national highways in the north-eastern states</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Reg. Sci.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>84-100</page-range>
          <fpage>84</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K. R.</given-names>
              <surname>Dikshit</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Dikshit</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title/>
          <source>North-East India: Land</source>
          <publisher-loc>People and EconomyDordrecht</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-7055-3</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S. B.</given-names>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Rivers for life</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the International Symposium on River Biodiversity: Ganges-Brahmaputra-Meghna River System</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>IUCN India</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>V. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Kale</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title/>
          <source>Landscapes and Landforms of India</source>
          <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-017-8029-2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Henderson</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Najman</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Parrish</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Barford</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
              <surname>Garzanti</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Andò</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Geology of the Cenozoic Indus Basin sedimentary rocks: Paleoenvironmental interpretation of sedimentation from the western Himalaya during the early phases of India-Eurasia collision</article-title>
          <source>Tectonics</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1029/2009TC002651</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Dey</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Paul</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Sarkar</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Morphological and microstructural evidences of paleo-seisminc occurrences in an earthquake prone zone of Tripura, India</article-title>
          <source>J. Earth Sci.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>289-298</page-range>
          <fpage>289</fpage>
          <lpage>298</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s12583-014-0430-x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Ghosh</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar De</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Evaluation of hydro-geomorphic responses to climate change in North Sikkim District, Sikkim, India</article-title>
          <source>Climate Change, Disaster and Adaptations, Cham</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>21-33</page-range>
          <fpage>21</fpage>
          <lpage>33</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-91010-5_3</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Debbarma</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Darlong</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mitra</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Livelihood of traditional handloom weavers of Darlong community in Unakoti District of Tripura, India</article-title>
          <source>Geographic</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>35-47</page-range>
          <fpage>35</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="newspaper">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"/>
          <article-title>Recovering from disaster in Assam, India</article-title>
          <source>Guwahati</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <uri>https://bettershelter.org/recovering-from-disaster-assam/</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="newspaper">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"/>
          <article-title>Floods in Assam: The Case for Rethinking Adaptation</article-title>
          <source>Guwahati</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <uri>https://www.vifindia.org/article/2022/july/04/floods-in-assam-the-case-for-rethinking-adaptation</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
              <surname>Palash</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S. R.</given-names>
              <surname>Bajracharya</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. B.</given-names>
              <surname>Shrestha</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Wahid</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Hossain</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Mogumder</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>L. C.</given-names>
              <surname>Mogumder</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Climate Change Impacts on the Hydrology of the Brahmaputra River Basin</article-title>
          <source>Clim.</source>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>18-18</page-range>
          <fpage>18</fpage>
          <lpage>18</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/cli11010018</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mondal</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Lal</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysing frequent extreme flood incidences in Brahmaputra basin, South Asia</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0273384</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0273384</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="newspaper">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"/>
          <article-title>Understanding the Brahmaputra and the annual flooding in Assam</article-title>
          <source>The Hindu</source>
          <year>2017</year>
          <uri>https://www.thehindu.com/news/national/other-states/in-the-hands-of-the-brahmaputra-understanding-the-annual-flooding-in-assam/article20948196.ece</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Gamble</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>How dams climb mountains: China and India's state-making hydropower contest in the Eastern-Himalaya watershed</article-title>
          <source>Thesis Eleven</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>150</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>42-67</page-range>
          <fpage>42</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1177/0725513619826204</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Gogoi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
              <surname>Siddique</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Flood, displacement and politics: The Assam chapter</article-title>
          <source>Econ. Polit Weekly</source>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>1-12</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Investing in resilience: ensuring a disaster-resistant future</article-title>
          <source>Asian Development Bank (ADB)</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <uri>http://hdl.handle.net/11540/89</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="newspaper">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"/>
          <article-title>Northeast Frontier Railway completes restoration of damaged track in Dima Hasao district of Assam</article-title>
          <source>The Economic Times</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <uri>https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/industry/transportation/railways/northeast-frontier-railway-completed-restoration-of-the-hill-section-of-damaged-track-in-dima-hasao-district-of-assam/articleshow/92834378.cms</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Disaster-Resilient Infrastructure: Unlocking Opportunities for Asia and the Pacific</article-title>
          <source>Asian Development Bank</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <uri>https://www.adb.org/publications/disaster-resilient-infrastructure-opportunities-asia-pacific</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Bhusan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Pande</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
              <surname>Kayal</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Landslide affected areas and challenges imposed in North Eastern Region of India: An appraisal</article-title>
          <source>Aust. J. Eng. Innov. Technol.</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>32-44</page-range>
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.34104/ajeit.022.032044</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Landslide Due to Heavy Rainfall Kills Ten in Mizoram</article-title>
          <source>The WIRE</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <uri>https://thewire.in/environment/landslide-due-to-heavy-rainfall-kills-ten-in-mizoram</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Developing Railway infrastructure in Mizoram Aimed to bring economic prosperity to the state and the NE region</article-title>
          <source>Ministry of Railways, Government of India</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <uri>https://nfr.indianrailways.gov.in/view_detail.jsp?lang=0&amp;id=0,4,268&amp;dcd=1906&amp;did=1655467844494090875A090964B1811BFB34A36768832</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mitra</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Rail freight transport system in Tripura: An analysis of performances and prospects</article-title>
          <source>Railway Transportation in South Asia</source>
          <publisher-loc>Chem</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>103-130</page-range>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>130</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-76878-2_7</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Nayak</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Mishra</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Status of development of NE states in India in the national perspective</article-title>
          <source>East Panor Shillong Meghalaya India</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>2013</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>1-11</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2295863</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>T. Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Humtsoe</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>From pathways to roadways: Issues and challenges of road transport in Nagaland</article-title>
          <source>Growth Change</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>1417-1436</page-range>
          <fpage>1417</fpage>
          <lpage>1436</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1111/grow.12383</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Gogoi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Goswami</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K. C.</given-names>
              <surname>Borah</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Problems of border areas in north east India: Implications for the thirteenth finance commission the thirteenth finance commission</article-title>
          <source>Doctoral Dissertation</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <publisher-name>Dibrugarh University</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Dibrugarh, India</publisher-loc>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>