<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="review-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HF</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Healthcraft Frontiers</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Healthcraft. Front.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">HF</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">3005-799X</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">3005-7981</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-51GGK9gx1AfEOvGxqZg55vVGUcSd22Ia</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/hf030104</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Non-Invasive Vibration-Based Assessment of Tibial Mechanical Properties: Advances, Challenges, and Prospects</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-5521-5024</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Al-Wasti</surname>
            <given-names>Hydar Saadi Hassan</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>hydaralwasti@comed.uobaghdad.edu.iq</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Anatomy Department, College of Medicine, University of Baghdad, 10071 Baghdad, Iraq</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>03</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>27</fpage>
      <lpage>46</lpage>
      <page-range>27-46</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>01</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>09</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Accurate evaluation of tibial mechanical properties is essential for the diagnosis of bone-related disorders, the monitoring of fracture healing, and the optimization of orthopedic rehabilitation outcomes. Conventional diagnostic approaches, including dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) and other imaging-based methods, provide valuable information but are limited by radiation exposure, invasiveness, or insufficient sensitivity to early structural changes. To address these limitations, non-invasive vibration-based techniques have been developed as promising alternatives for quantitative, real-time, and radiation-free assessment of tibial biomechanics. Methods such as resonance frequency analysis (RFA), modal analysis, acoustic emission (AE), and laser doppler vibrometry (LDV) have been applied to estimate parameters including bone stiffness, bone mineral density (BMD), and healing dynamics. By introducing controlled vibrational input and recording the tibial response, structural integrity can be characterized, and early indicators of injury, degeneration, or impaired healing can be detected. Recent advances in high-resolution sensors, signal processing algorithms, and wearable technologies have enhanced the sensitivity and applicability of these techniques, while the integration of machine learning has enabled more robust interpretation of complex biomechanical signals. Despite these advances, significant challenges remain, including inter-patient variability, soft tissue damping effects, and the absence of standardized testing protocols. Furthermore, the clinical translation of vibration-based diagnostics requires validation against established imaging modalities and the development of predictive, individualized models of bone health that integrate artificial intelligence (AI) and multimodal data. Current evidence suggests that vibration analysis has the potential to offer a non-invasive and personalized approach to skeletal monitoring. Future research should focus on addressing methodological limitations, improving standardization, and advancing the integration of vibration assessment into routine orthopedic practice and precision medicine frameworks.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Tibial biomechanics</kwd>
        <kwd>Non-invasive diagnostics</kwd>
        <kwd>Vibration analysis</kwd>
        <kwd>Resonance frequency analysis</kwd>
        <kwd>Acoustic emission</kwd>
        <kwd>Bone stiffness</kwd>
        <kwd>Bone mineral density</kwd>
        <kwd>Tibial structural integrity</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="1"/>
        <fig-count count="6"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <ref-count count="30"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>1. Introduction to tibial biomechanics and its importance</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.1. Overview of the tibia and its functions</title>
          
          <p>The tibia, commonly referred to as the shinbone, is the second longest and one of the strongest bones in the human body, located in the lower leg. It is quite important in supporting weight and movement, especially during walking, running and jumping. The femur exerts enormous weight on the tibia in the movement. The tibia contains three major components in its anatomy: the proximal end, connected to the femur by the knee bone; the diaphysis, or the shaft, which makes the bone long and strong; and the distal point, known as the talocrural articulation, which connects the bone to the fibula and talus in the ankle. The knee mechanics and ligament and tendon attachment point in the proximal face contain condylar structures. The outer (spongy bone tissues) and inner tibia look like cortical tissues. The tight lamellae of the cortical bone are allegedly supposed to give it its strength and stability, and the trabecular bone is allegedly supposed to give it its lightness and strain. The combination makes it very rigid when compression stress is applied to it and very elastic when dynamic motions happen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>).</p><p>Maintaining bone health requires an understanding of the mechanical properties of the tibia, such as rigidity and BMD. A reduction in these properties increases the risk of injury and the development of conditions such as osteoporosis. A reduction in BMD significantly increases the risk of fracture, even under relatively low or secondary mechanical loading. Vibration measuring methods have been developed as non-invasive approaches to administer these mechanical properties in vivo. Use of these sensors allows the investigation of internal bone conditions as vibrational responses to stimuli or physiological activity that do not involve invasive procedures. These are relatively in line with conservative tests like DXA which also assesses the risk of fracturing. Vibration analysis of tibial biomechanics may have valuable applications in both injury prevention and rehabilitation. These procedures can be used to optimize orthopedic care by tailoring treatment to the unique biomechanical characteristics of the tibia, thereby enabling effective monitoring of recovery following surgery or fracture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Campos et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>The continued improvement in sensor technology and the data analysis software is enhancing the ability to capture and measure time-varying vibrational data related to how the tibia is performing. These inventions make it possible to monitor and make more appropriate decisions during recovery after injury in real time. In preventing the onset of injuries, chronic musculoskeletal disorders provide a wider platform of preventive strategies such as training patients on the art of healthy lifestyles that reduce body injuries that accompany musculoskeletal disorders and other related sedentary lifestyles that predominate osteogenesis in the aging population due to associated changes in hormones. Biomechanical behavior related to the distribution of body weight is relevant to promoting effective physical therapy practices in reducing the risk of falls in older patients. The importance of the tibia causes the conclusion related to the physiological role of the tibia and the need for further investigation devoted to the development of new innovative and non-invasive procedures used to measure the main parameters of the orthopedic outcome. Such a focus is driven by the need to achieve the best quality life by preventing and rehabilitating injuries with the aim of achieving healthier communities and having individuals make more informed decisions that can serve the greater good of the society. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> shows the cellular targets of vibration. Vibration at the physiological level is mediated through the activities of individual cells. The mechanical signals of low magnitude are aimed at numerous cell types such as mesenchymal stem cells, osteoblasts, osteocytes, adipocytes, osteoclasts, myocytes and neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Thompson et al., 2014</xref>).</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Cellular targets of vibration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Thompson et al., 2014</xref>)</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/8/img_xco5DvPmhUAbW3lu.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.2. Significance of assessing mechanical properties of the tibia</title>
          
          <p>The assessment of mechanical characteristics of the tibia is very important in clinical practice and research, in the evaluation of the health status of bones, and in the diagnosis of the condition as well as treatment strategies. Knowledge of these properties aids the conclusion of the strength of the tibia to resist forces as people engage in daily activities. Being one of the main bones involved in weight bearing, anything changing its structure can reduce mobility. Using the stiffness, strength and elasticity, medical workers receive a chance to analyze the chance of fracture, especially of the patients, who have osteoporosis conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>). Sufficient examination of the mechanical properties of the tibia facilitates medical intervention at the right time. When patients with certain pathological issues like osteoporosis or osteogenesis imperfecta are considered, the information about the mechanics in the tibia might serve as a guide on how to treat them individually, control their progress, and make sounder decisions regarding surgery or rehabilitation. In addition, by studying tibial mechanisms, one can be able to study how he is hurt and, as such, come up with measures to prevent this. Such a method of diagnosing strained athletes in sports medicine can facilitate the safety and performance of an athlete since his or her loading reaction can elucidate the training changes and prevention measures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Vien et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>The tibial property measurement effects on the community health would determine the demographic strata of the standards and disclose community trends in skeletal health. Fine policies may be made to improve bone education and corrective modifiable risks to populations using this. Moreover, the non-invasive technique of measuring mechanical properties of the tibia is aligned with the development of biomedical engineering which is more friendly to the patients regarding its positive outcomes as well as the reduction of dangers of the use of traditional imagery systems such as X-rays. Vibration-based assessment is emerging not only as a practical diagnostic approach but also as a platform for active monitoring of changes without exposing patients to ionizing radiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Razaghi et al., 2020</xref>). Research is developing further to bring it closer to vibrational assays and other non-invasive bone-density scratch test devices such as DXA and is giving a greater level of accuracy to the identification of bone quality. Using various forms of diagnostics, clinicians are able to gain a deep understanding of the mechanisms occurring within the bones, not only in their shape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Pastrav et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Researchers have examined the relationship between vibrational properties and individual variation, whether genetic or lifestyle-related, thereby opening new perspectives for personalized skeletal treatment. In this context, several recent advances have been reported. The limitations of current invasive assessment techniques underscore the need to adopt non-invasive methods of measurement, such as vibration analysis, which can be easily maintained and, simultaneously, preserve the integrity of the retrieval of the necessary information on the mechanisms of the bones. Generally, deep discussion of the mechanical properties of the tibia is required in various aspects such as optimization of patient management to improve the lives of individuals by addressing the needs of specific subjects and defining the science of skeletal health of the population. Advances in technology and biomechanical understanding are driving transformative developments in diagnostics and in the assessment of quality-of-life indicators for individuals with musculoskeletal disorders related to impaired bone integrity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Christiansen et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>1.3. Implications for injury prevention and rehabilitation</title>
          
          <p>The significance of these findings lies in the implications of tibial vibration assessment for injury prevention and rehabilitation. It would be extremely advantageous to the clinical institutions as well as the athletic institutions to conduct studies on the mechanical properties of the tibia with regard to its vibration profile. In this way, both at the time of initial diagnosis and follow-ups, the examinations reveal important information regarding the well-being of the bones missing in the other imaging technologies. Tibial trauma or fracture is a usual occurrence whose complication during revisit is non-union or sluggish recovery in a long-term outlook. Vibration testing is one potential solution to these problems because it offers an opportunity to monitor the fractures in real time. By monitoring any slight alteration in the vibration pattern, healthcare specialists can predict any impending issue and stop it before it results in absolutely nothing but a basic clinical phenomenon. This early intervention capability not only contributes to improving the results of the patients but also is an essential step of the process of the injury prevention. Besides that, the recovery programs may also be supplemented with another type of rehabilitation practice, vibration assessment. The interdependence between the mechanical load on the rehabilitating process and the bone healing is not a new finding; thus, the vibrational method used in the functional exercises may increase the thickness and strength of the bone. Vibration therapy has shown promise in stimulating osteogenic activity, particularly in patients with tibia injuries or those who have undergone surgery, for whom traditional loading protocols may be difficult to perform due to pain or immobilization-induced weakness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Hoffman et al., 2025</xref>).</p><p>Vibrational analysis, other than in fracture recovery, is a highly significant part of the muscle-bone interaction complex. Since it has been observed that the impact made by the muscles’ movement on the bones is quite significant, the impact of vibration on the muscle activity could be viewed as useful information in the overall rehabilitation plans. Low-intensive vibration training, however, has been found to increase muscle contractility which, in its turn, may improve the mechanical loading on bones during periods of regeneration. Moreover, another exciting opportunity to make medicine personal using orthopedic treatment is the further advancement in the non-invasive application of vibration. Due to the developed technologies that enable a more subtle evaluation of the patient without resorting to the use of ionizing radiation and in a non-invasive manner, clinicians can create a rehabilitation program based on the individual biomechanical profile. This individualized treatment can enhance the probability of success, as specific weaknesses can be addressed based on the architecture of the affected individual and a history of prior trauma. In practice, in the context of clinical services, tibial vibration measurement may facilitate the decision-making process in terms of both the choice of surgical procedure and the post-operative plan. Using the example, during the work with the complicated fragmentation or already conducted surgeries with the implants, such as plates or screws, the operations may be modified by the constant control of the vibrational processes as it would be possible to receive the real-time data on the progress of the healing process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Pires et al., 2025</xref>).</p><p>Furthermore, the technology can prove quite promising in sporting populations where players insist on being at the peak of their performance but at minimal risk of damaging their bodies. Repetitive loading patterns are given to athletes in order to prevent stress fracture; therefore, constant vibrational measurements would enable observing bone integrity in a proactive way and make decisions regarding the changes to be adopted in the process of training programs. It is indisputable that there are barriers to the widespread adoption of these advanced methods in clinical subscriptions. The presence of difference among the patients (age, sex, distribution of activities, etc.) can produce an enormous difference in the vibrational responses and data interpretation. Furthermore, the operational problems that encircle measurement accuracy require further research that would contribute to simplifying methodological approaches to refer to their further implementation on other populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Sekiguchi &amp;amp; Hirayama, 1979</xref>).</p><p>Nevertheless, the benefits of these techniques greatly surpass the concerns once they are taken into account in the context of studies that are intended to achieve the standardization and validation of these techniques in the orthopedic context. The future of vibrodiagnostics in the assessment of tibial biomechanics looks very promising, as technological advancements—including improved sensors and analysis software—are expected to augment the quality and depth of available information. In this, instead of being a diagnostic tool that would only be used in clinical practice, vibration assessment would be a tremendous channel or bridge between interdisciplinary practice represented by biomechanics engineering and rehabilitative science and would offer terrific opportunities for healthcare development in many musculoskeletal healthcare management areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Sekiguchi &amp;amp; Hirayama, 1979</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Fundamentals of vibration techniques</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Principles of vibration mechanics</title>
          
          <p>Mechanics of vibration is the science of the oscillatory motions of mechanical systems. In the case of tibial vibration, the procedure involves a complete picture of the vibration wave passing along the tibia and how the vibration itself can be measured and used to measure different mechanical properties of the bone. There are some fundamental ideas such as natural frequency damping, resonance and modal analysis that are crucial in this area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Christiansen et al., 2008</xref>). Another crucial attribute of any vibrating system is its natural frequency—the frequency at which the system tends to oscillate in the absence of external forces. This frequency is dependent on the mass and stiffness of the bone structures, such as the tibia. When external vibrational force is applied on the tibial structure, it can vibrate at a natural frequency, resulting in large vibrations that can be measured by using specific sensors. Such a phenomenon is significant relative to the evaluation of bone strength and health state, as the natural frequencies of a bone may change with changes in the bone density or the structuring, which can be caused by osteoporotic cases or by the existence of fractures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">Seth et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>Damping is the mechanism by which the amount of vibrational energy declines as time proceeds. It can be caused by internal material properties of biological tissues (e.g., viscoelastic behavior) or by the influence of external tissue (e.g., other muscles or tendons). Damping ratio is a dimensionless parameter that shows how fast the oscillations, after being perturbed, reduce in magnitude. To properly determine tibial vibration assessment, knowledge of damping behavior is necessary because this can help interpret the measurements since more damping may indicate that the materials are absorbent. An external force effected on a system at its natural frequency behaves in a manner called resonance in a greater amplitude (than other frequencies) with respect to vibrating. In the process of performing tibial assessments, it is advisable to exercise great control over the parameters of vibrational inputs, as it is seen that such methods can be used to resonate the subject matter without compromising the health and comfort of the subjects. With the help of the methods targeted at the specific frequencies near the ones that are considered resonant with regard to healthy and pathological states of the bone, the health of the bones can be more accurately assessed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Ozmen et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>For a given system, modal analysis is an important technique in the field of vibration mechanics that seeks to determine the mode shapes of the system as well as the modal frequencies. With the assistance of such an analysis method, such complex bones are evaluated systematically; the decomposition of the shaking and oscillation modes is carried out. Each of the mode shapes is proportional to the different movement patterns that arise in the assemblage during intrinsic vibrating; studying the shapes can assist researchers to reveal the existence of biomechanical problems associated with injuries or bone strength diseases. Many methodologies have cropped up in the practice of conducting vibration analysis of biological tissues. One approach involves attaching accelerometers at strategic positions along the tibia while controlled vibrational stimuli are applied using external equipment, such as mechanical vibrators or haptic actuators. Response data collected using these sensors can be correlated with known inputs responding to different loading conditions to allow inferences into a mechanical property, e.g., stiffness, to be made using mathematical modeling techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Arami et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>Some vibration testing protocols also function as feedback mechanisms. Once a response is obtained, additional excitation methods can be applied in an adaptive manner, thereby improving measurement accuracy, reliability, and subject comfort. It must be stated that the interrelations of different structures of the body are important factors in defining the vibrational properties of the bones under test; the stiffness of the joints and the mechanical properties of soft tissues should also be mentioned as factors to be considered when one relies on the results of the modal examination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Scanlan et al., 2024</xref>). Future developments in tibial biomechanics, particularly in the area of non-invasive diagnostic treatment, may benefit from the exploration of new computational techniques to improve current models of vibrational phenomena across patient groups with differing anatomical characteristics. In conclusion, the understanding of the basic concepts of vibration mechanics gives invaluable knowledge on the formulation of relevant strategies to check the health status of the tibia based on non-invasive procedures allied to the possibility of transforming injury prevention and rehabilitation practices over time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Scanlan et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> shows the experimental design of the vibration analysis. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>a indicates the vibrator attached to a saw bone with an adjustable assembly and illustrates the accurate movement of the vibrator along the X, Y, and Z axes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>b gives a more detailed perspective of the system in one of the cadaveric experiments and labels major components of the system up to the vibrator, force sensor, accelerator, and sensor cube to measure the response of the bone to vibration.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Experimental design of the vibration analysis: (a) Vibrator in the positioning assembly with the adjustable fit over a saw bone, (b) A more detailed picture of the stimulation system and the measurement systems during a cadaveric experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Arami et al., 2018</xref>)</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/8/img_sydnI8zn84FP_M1X.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> shows where the vibrator and sensor cubes are located in the experiment. The image gives a general view of the arrangement with an emphasis on the positioning of the vibrator and sensors relative to the tibia of the test subject. This was built to experiment with bone vibrational response during the healing of fractures.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> presents the analytical model of the tibia and knee. It shows the forces that act on the tibia and knee joint, including the point of measurement and other stiffness characteristics (flexion/extension and internal/external torsion stiffnesses). The model explains the mechanical behavior of the tibia and knee during vibration testing and includes detailed labels describing the forces and stiffness values used.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>The position of the vibrator and sensor cubes in the experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Arami et al., 2018</xref>)</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/8/img_wZ8tnFTc05gnkqmz.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Analytical model of the tibia and knee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Ozmen et al., 2021</xref>)</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/8/img_btHlOUiRusUNaOfK.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Types of vibration analysis methods</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.2.1 Rfa</title>
              
              <p>RFA is rather important in the tibial vibration measurements, and it provides very useful information concerning the mechanical properties of the bone tissue. The process relies on the idea that bones do resonate at certain frequencies, which are also directly related to bone strength and rigidity. At these frequencies, the clinicians are able to determine quantitative values of the conditions of the bones, healing process and existing weaknesses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>). A significant aspect of RFA is the calculation of the vibrational excitation on the tibia, and this can be ensured because of a large pool of alternatives, such as harmonic excitation and impact testing. Passing vibrations through the bone causes a response which is predetermined by the natural frequencies where the bone vibrates best. This frequency of the first resonant is also unusual because, in a certain sense, it is a very sensitive response to the stiffness changes between injury and healing and is often related to bending modes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Campos et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>It was determined that the mechanism by which hardness was gained, which in turn involved callus formation, would also be linked to the concomitant rise in resonant frequency and, therefore, to the fact that RFA could be used to monitor the dynamics of the fracture healing process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Vien et al., 2022</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Mattei et al. (2021)</xref> also used this concept and treated complex external fixation fractures using RFA. It was concluded that in the course of time, the healing process varied greatly because the square resonant frequencies varied. In particular, it was found that the squared resonant frequencies increased by approximately 20 percent per month when callus was beginning to develop; that is, some form of amplified stiffening and structural integrity must be in action. The in vivo vibration study provides an explicit correlation between the mechanical characteristics of bones and their vibration pattern. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Pastrav et al. (2009)</xref> has confirmed, differences in natural frequencies between the osteoporotic subject and the normal subject may serve as an indicator of changes of inherent stiffness, and the inherent stiffness is strongly correlated with natural frequencies. The specified clinical symptoms can also be used to demonstrate the potential of RFA in the framework of bone healing monitoring alongside an initial indication of the presence of degenerative processes, such as osteoporosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Kadhim et al., 2024b</xref>).</p><p>Technological improvement is one of the reasons why the reliability and applicability of RFA have continuously enhanced through clinical testing. Sensors and analytical software can be updated to provide more precise measurements and real-time processing of data during the implementation of a diagnostic test. The innovations enhance the knowledge of the most imperative information about the behavior of the bones with assorted loading conditions. However, there are some issues that may undermine the quality of RFA in clinical practice. One of the challenges that can be determined by measuring the soft tissues is tissue interference since the surrounding muscle can dampen the vibrational response and attenuate the higher-frequency signals required for accurate measurements. In fact, recent studies even attempt to diminish this damping by improving measurements or using elaborate filtering concepts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Mattei et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>Moreover, even though RFA has also been reported as one of the promising non-invasive technologies to be applied in the process of monitoring the healing process of fractures as an alternative to the classical radiographic methods, the absence of consistency due to differences in anatomy cannot be overlooked in the discussion of the outcomes of the given tests. Lastly, RFA could be regarded as one of the efficient tools of tibial vibration measurement since the instrument is capable of providing objective data that is closely related to mechanical values associated with bone health and postoperative rehabilitation patterns following injury or surgery. Ongoing efforts to enhance the precision of such measurements and to overcome existing limitations may broaden the application of the method to larger scales in routine orthopedic clinical practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Mattei et al., 2021</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.2.2 Modal analysis</title>
              
              <p>An important purpose of modal analysis in the investigation of the tibia’s mechanical properties is to understand its vibrational behavior. The method can also be applied in the determination of natural frequencies, mode shapes and damping ratios which are very important in explaining the behavior of bone structures in various loading situations and recovery following trauma with or without injuries. It involves the vibration of the bone by an energy spike hammer that creates a vibrant reaction. The measurements of these vibrations are recorded by an accelerator or laser Doppler vibrometer and the frequency response function (FRF) is usually a plot that indicates reaction to forces at specific locations within the tibia. The Fourier Transform is typically applied to data analysis to convert the signals in the time domain to the frequency domain to determine the resonant frequencies that trigger the tibia vibration in the most intense manner. Each natural frequency has its own mode shape, or shows how the different parts of the tibia move relative to each other as the tibia vibrates. The properties are important in determining bone strength and the issues surrounding fracture healing. Bone density and health changes are especially sensitive to the modal analysis. Experiments indicate that the alteration in modal properties has a positive association with the alteration in BMD. A reduction in natural frequencies due to low BMD may indicate structural weakness, whereas elevated resonance frequencies observed during healing may reflect positive recovery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>).</p><p>This analysis offers a non-invasive method of long-term bone healing determination, thus replacing other more invasive methods such as biopsies or radiographic analyses, which expose patients to ionizing radiation. The clinicians can obtain objective information on the process of healing through the observation of changes in modal parameters. The modern modal analysis is a computation method. Finite element modeling (FEM) helps investigators to build predictive models based on the properties of materials and geometrical shapes of bones. These types of models can be simulated with different loading conditions, allowing a better understanding of how applied loads affect a structure. In clinical practice, practical applications are also possible because the vibration assessment equipment can be attached as a component of the regular orthopedic examination of fractured or operated patients. The possibility to repeat the vibrations and, consequently, to control them constantly, would allow intervention in case of complications in case other symptoms would signal at earlier stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Vien et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>However, there are barriers due to the difference in anatomy among patients that can be translated into measurements. Other reasons like interference of soft tissues can be considered, which may bring serious consequences to vibratory measurements. Therefore, continuous studies have been conducted on how such correction can be carried out to acquire knowledge on modal analyses in the right manner. Technological advances are also making vibrational measurement of bones increasingly accurate. Other innovations include advancements in sensor technologies, which are able to detect data at higher fidelities and wider frequency bands despite the increased interference of the adjacent tissues when data is being detected. As the research on this topic continues, some unified processes could be prepared in which best practices in the application of modal analyses to clinical diagnostics could be established. However, even though modal analysis is an effective method of determining the mechanical properties related to injury regeneration, the process has yet to be optimized to provide answers to the orthopedic questions related to the tibial health dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Vien et al., 2022</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>2.2.3 Taxonomy of vibration analysis methods</title>
              
              <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_5">Figure 5</xref> categorizes the various methods of examining vibration, namely, bone stiffness, bone density, and bone healing dynamics. This taxonomy includes sub-groups of modal analysis and other techniques, which in turn subdivide into smaller methods like RFA, LDV and AE.</p><p>Having taken into account the basic methods of vibration analysis that are applied in tibial biomechanics, namely RFA, modal analysis, AE and LDV, it is evident that each method possesses its advantage of providing the information concerning the mechanical behavior and health of the tibia. Regardless of the weaknesses and strengths of every method, they serve to contribute to the overall image of bone integrity.</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_5">
                  <label>Figure 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Bone stiffness, density, and healing dynamics</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/8/img_8isdHUkvQeF6M4hV.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Current non-invasive vibration techniques</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Overview of existing methodologies</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.1.1 Ae techniques</title>
              
              <p>Transient elastic waves that occur when a body has its energy rapidly released at tiny points in a material. Such techniques have gained much attention in the field of biomechanics, especially in the measurement of tibial injury status and well-being. When the patient is carried out a tibial vibration test, which is in the state of rest, AEs form a good source of information pertaining to the mechanical and structural integrity of the bone, particularly when the test is used on an injured bone or a diseased bone. The vibrational characteristics of bones under different types of loads is one of the most interesting studies using AE methods in orthopedic diagnostics. Localized damage (tear of a meniscus in a knee joint) has been shown to affect vibrational behavior. Studies have also established that AEs can detect changes in natural frequencies and the damping ratios that are symptoms of underlying injuries. When the knee joint is flexed and extended, one of the unconscious signals the body generates is characteristic acoustic data in accordance with the structural change that the traumas cause. Experimental evidence provides support for the fact that AE is able to diagnose meniscal tears, as well as to identify that the vibrational parameters of the healthy and damaged joints do not coincide. In a study of 55 participants (46 with healthy knees and 9 with diagnosed meniscal tears), the analytical modeling (a beam structure based on Euler-Bernoulli) was applied to describe how these vibrations are manifested as mechanical changes. The findings indicated that there was a correlation between meniscal injury and the low natural frequencies calculated by assessing AE, meaning that sound markers could be considered non-invasive biomarkers of the disorder diagnosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Ozmen et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>AE techniques are useful in the screening of chronic bone-related musculoskeletal conditions alongside acute ones such as meniscal injury. An example is vibrational analysis, which can assist in monitoring the healing process after a bone fracture or surgery, such as determining the level at which structural integrity is restored. The ability to detect early signs of delayed union or complications—well before they could be identified with conventional radiography—highlights the potential role of AE techniques in improving patient care. The other reason is the existing tendencies in sensor development that have made its AE measurements more sensitive and accurate. As piezoelectric sensors and computing analysis systems become integrated together, it is possible to test and even further analyze the biomechanically emitted signal of the stressed bones in real time. Such capability contributes not only to the ability to spot it earlier but also to the production of beneficial information that can be turned into rehabilitation models grounded in individual recovery processes. The AE methodologies would not only bring their benefits to the field of diagnostics but also give certain opportunities for the management and short-term assessment of the successful post-traumatic rehabilitation after an injury or a surgery. Through the continuous monitoring of the phases of recovery, clinicians would be in a position to determine any gains or losses based on the change in the vibrational pattern because of the increase or decrease in the bone density or stability. It is the feedback mechanism that renders more sense to the individualized practices of care that have to be set into motion by orthopedic procedures in order to produce the highest results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Safaei et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>However, some issues remain which relate to the widespread application of the AE techniques in clinics. There are still problems in terms of consistency of measurements in various anatomical structures because of patient variability as well as individual anatomical peculiarities. Moreover, the research conducted today represents promising perspectives of correlations of alterations in vibration and pathological conditions, but studies that are more extensive are required to increase the idea of the research on more different populations. To conclude, the AE technique is a rapidly emerging domain in tibial biomechanics with great prospects in non-invasive diagnostics and therapeutic monitoring. This can be trained in the structure of tissue integrity as well as the vibration feedback on injury or response to repair mechanisms, and thus these techniques promise a favorable turn to the field of clinical practices dealing with musculoskeletal health management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Safaei et al., 2021</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.1.2 Ldv</title>
              
              <p>LDV, an optical non-contact method, is used to measure vibrations in any structure, including the tibia. It uses the Doppler effect so that the variation in the frequency of the light that bounces off a vibrating surface would give a hint on its velocity and displacement. The reason why LDV is valued in particular is due to its accuracy and sensitivity in biomechanics in general and in the measurement of the mechanical properties of bone in particular. The tibial surface is tipped with a laser beam in LDV systems. The reflected light frequency varies with the vibration of the bone and this makes it possible to extract the parameters of vibration characteristics: amplitude and FRFs as well as modal properties without necessarily making physical contact with the bone. It is a non-destructive process that eliminates the problems involved in the use of the contact technologies. For example, natural vibration is modified in the process of contacting a sensor used with the technique of mass loading; this could have far-reaching consequences on the subsequent understanding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>). A major advantage of LDV compared with measuring tibial vibrations is that LDV measures complex dynamic responses over the frequency range. By means of this type of data capture, the influence of structural changes that take place throughout the line of injuries/recovery on the vibrational properties of bones can be effectively analyzed. Most of the studies have found a correlation between variation in tibial stiffness and density and variation in resonance frequencies measured using LDV, which may assist the clinicians to make suitable decisions during the healing and recovery phase of the observed fractures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Campos et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>Using the LDV has also been advantageous to the research area of dynamical testing of the replica of the human tibia under various conditions. Experimental studies using external fixation systems have indicated that LDV can also confirm the presence of vibrational behavioral differences between non-operated bones and those that have undergone the fixation procedure. The disadvantages of the conventional imaging are that they are mostly indirect, dependent on the development of a callus or the location of the bones and the explicit comments on whether the bones are structurally intact during the healing process. By contrast, LDV enables real-time measurements of the mechanical characteristics by measuring the vibrational response that is directly associated with the material characteristics during recovery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Ozmen et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>An examination of the advances in laser laboratory and data query systems can enhance the measurements of tibial vibration by LDV. High-speed laser vibrometer cameras can also provide high time-resolution data, which is particularly important when analyzing vibrational events at small scales, such as those occurring during walking or running. Such innovations would enable gathering baseline data and the accurate monitoring of all changes throughout the course of rehabilitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Cheung et al., 2021</xref>). In spite of the advantages, LDV cannot be stripped of its disadvantages. Unless checked, influences such as the coloring of light can disturb accuracy since such influences are not relevant in the case of pinpoint records. More recent works concentrate on the development of these methodologies with the addition of machine learning algorithms to handle large datasets captured in the process of carrying out the assessment itself under vibration, thus potentially enhancing the diagnosis and patient outcomes process. The orthopedic care industry has a lot of potential because once LDV is adjusted and adapted to a predictive model in a clinical practice, it becomes simpler to conduct an individualized medicine practice. By providing objective evidence of mechanical responsiveness to the injury recovery process, LDV is establishing new paradigms in the research of tibia biomechanics assessment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Mehrabi &amp;amp; Farhangdoust, 2018</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Comparison with invasive methods</title>
          
          <p>The tibia assessment method using non-invasive vibration measurement techniques has extremely numerous benefits compared to the traditional methods which are considered invasive, particularly concerning patient safety, repeatability and comfort. The most traditional ones tend to be intrusive, for example, through biopsies or through the use of imaging systems that may expose patients to radiation and even become more disturbing in that one may need to make multiple measurements within a constrained timeframe to check the healing or condition improvement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>). DXA may help provide useful information on the tissue bone density; however, it does not help much with determining the mechanical properties of the bone tissue. DXA is used to measure BMD and is not an indicator of the mechanical strength or stiffness of the tibia. This is absolutely essential because mechanical properties could be different depending on whether the mineral is dense or not. Although DXA is primarily characterized as a fracture risk measure because it is based on density measurements, it cannot provide a complete picture of the overall health or load-bearing performance of the bone. The vibration techniques are dynamic tests of the bones, i.e., tests of how the bones respond to the vibrations. This type of procedure obtains the principle of the response examination and modifies the parameters of the resonance frequency and damping in order to produce the sound structural integrity and the stiffness. This enables the medical practitioners to quantitatively predict both the bone density and the functional biomechanical quality of the bones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Kadhim et al., 2024b</xref>).</p><p>The study has further reported that changes in the tibial stiffness during the post-fracture rehabilitation process could be measured using non-invasive vibration methods without causing radiation to the patient. One investigation has discovered that the vibrational test can identify the same results as three-point bending tests, without being invasive. Furthermore, the methodologies help in conducting follow-ups during the entire process and this is crucial in deciding the path of the recovery trend and whether the treatment is working or not. The non-invasive methods like AE and LDV can display real-time information of the healing of the bones compared to the sound waves or the pattern of the light. These methods produce minimal discomfort to the patient and create a safer diagnostic environment compared to conventional imaging methods, which may require sedation or disrupt the injured area and impede wound healing. This may be regarded as a benefit since the ability to conduct constant reviews is realized through the application of non-invasive procedures, thus rendering the process of conducting reviews more practical compared to invasive procedures which are limited when continuous evidence tracking is required in clinical settings. For example, while X-rays are restricted by radiation exposure concerns, vibration analysis does not face such limitations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Fellinger et al., 1994</xref>).</p><p>Practically, the technologies used in non-invasive vibration assessment methods are usually less specialized in terms of training, unlike more classical methods of imaging (radiology or orthopedics), which have been in development for thousands of years. This practicability increases its use in other healthcare settings. However, non-invasive techniques are affected by uncertainties, including the variability of a reading because of the environment or the variation because of individual anatomies. Invasive approaches could enable the establishment of controlled conditions during assessments; however, they are not so safe in terms of statistical profile and beneficial in terms of patients as the vibration-based tests. The outcomes of non-invasive vibrational techniques of evaluation might be added to the technique of conventional evaluation to give joint control over sickness of the tibia due to extra data concerning the structural and functional integrity of the body. This augments total treatment of the patient in line with the safeguarding of the injury and healing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Liang et al., 2024</xref>). Having known the methodologies of measuring tibial vibrations available, it is pertinent to consider how the methodologies are finding their way into clinical practice.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Technological advances in vibration-based assessment</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Emerging technologies in vibration measurement</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.1.1 Advanced sensors and instrumentation</title>
              
              <p>The introduction of sensor technologies has remarkably achieved phenomenal advancement in terms of clinical use and research and development in tibial vibration assessment. One powerful innovation is the non-contact methodology of measurements involving optical sensors, such as laser-based sensors, which are much more precise and do not need to be connected to the patient body. This removes the interference and retains the mechanical properties in question (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Razaghi et al., 2020</xref>). LDV is another important development in non-invasive tibial testing. LDV is characterized by its ability to measure the amplitude and frequency of vibrations by detecting variations in the frequency of reflected coherent light as the surface moves. This approach can also result in highly resolved vibration measurements in multifaceted geometrical structures, which is necessary when the bone structures are analyzed under a range of loads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Hoffman et al., 2025</xref>).</p><p>Vibration analysis is another recent advancement and it is also at the forefront of fast motion vision systems where special cameras are used to record the fast movement at a very high frame rate. To boost the attenuation of the high-frequency vibration signal at the subpixel level, Zero-Mean Normalization Sum of Squared Differences (ZNSSD) or the like can be deployed to enhance the accuracy of vibration signal measurement and enable real-time processing in clinical procedures. More sensitive, sophisticated accelerometers which consume less power have also been developed. This multi-sensor system is actually a combination of an assortment of various sensors such that it is capable of getting a great deal of information about the density and the structure of bones during locomotion such as walking or running (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Arami et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>Successful discrimination between the noise and the relevant swipes of the vibration has been achieved with the aid of data processing, interpretation and software research. It has been observed that machine learning can be used to predictively simulate the events using the vibrational data which may instruct the clinician on how the patient in the rehabilitation chair should respond to the exercises or even before undergoing any kind of surgery. Of particular interest has been the optimization of sensor location based on modal assurance criteria (MAC) to determine the optimum points on the tibia for recording valid vibration data with minimal perturbation of the surrounding tissue; this is informed by the recorded measurements. Having the right positioning can enhance the accuracy of diagnosis as the method involves a real quantification of the mechanical responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Mehrabi &amp;amp; Farhangdoust, 2018</xref>).</p><p>The flexibility of the experiments and monitoring of the patients is being enhanced by the availability of wireless transmission to enable the patients to move freely while carrying out activities without compromising the quality of information collected. This potential alignment progressing with the digital twin technologies could affect the tibial biomechanics analysis process, since clinicians are able to monitor patients in real time and respond to their needs. Current interdisciplinary research aims to refine these technologies by introducing new approaches to tibial vibration analysis and developing complementary techniques such as quantitative ultrasound. These advances can support individualized rehabilitation programs tailored to specific anatomical features or trauma conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Liang et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p>Excessiveness coupled with spaciousness has been significant in the adoption of the wide clinical lens. Healthcare facilities are trying out avenues through which they could include these tools in the normal assessment without incurring prohibitive costs for advanced medical equipment. Technology that incorporates biomechanical knowledge, particularly regarding vibrations and structural integrity, can provide clinicians with powerful diagnostic instruments. These instruments not only improve current assessment but also offer predictive capabilities, enabling evaluation of future health outcomes related to loading responses during various activities, ultimately reducing the risk of re-injury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Kazemian et al., 2023</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_6">Figure 6</xref> shows the prototype 3D sensor cube for tibial implant vibration measurement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Arami et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
              
                <fig id="fig_6">
                  <label>Figure 6</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Prototype 3D sensor cube: (a) First prototype large-scale 3D sensors (two 2D sensors embedded as a cube), (b) The cube was closed and glued on the end of the tibial implant to measure the vibration sent to the tibial part (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Arami et al., 2018</xref>)</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/8/img_uBSgCNfBzJrM0sFB.png"/>
                </fig>
              
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>4.1.2 Software developments for data analysis</title>
              
              <p>The vibrational data analysis software method has been monumentally evolving both in the complexity of the measurement technology and the requirement to interpret the vibrational measures properly. Complex algorithms play a central role in examining big data gathered by vibration sensors and can be employed to calculate mechanical properties of structures such as the tibia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Hoffman et al., 2025</xref>). Among these innovations are machine learning and AI being used to study vibrational data. The technologies enhance the prediction, detection and classification of vibrations. Researchers have applied machine learning to identify patterns in collections of data related to a specific condition or structural issue of the tibial structure in such a way that models may predict the risk of fracture or structure failure prior to clinical complications occurring. The other innovation is algorithm optimization in real-time monitoring. Traditional methods typically involve time-consuming manual processing of information after which early steps are delayed. Now, however, at the current development, it is now possible to store data and analyze it locally with the help of mobile devices. That is, when the practitioner notices a faulty vibrational signature, the one which may indicate a fault of the mechanism, he/she can fix the problem quickly because the data is stored and can be analyzed at the location where the practitioner is currently working (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Arami et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>A key technological advancement supporting the development of high-speed cameras is the creation of non-invasive measurement techniques, in which advanced algorithms decompose vibrational motions through image contrast analysis. Diffraction imaging and high-frequency extraction methods have been employed to isolate fine-scale vibrational content, enabling subpixel resolution and providing detailed information on the dynamic behavior of biological tissues such as bone. In parallel, software advancements have improved the compatibility of heterogeneous sensor groups with diverse measurement systems, facilitating the establishment of an integrated assessment model that accommodates both contact-based accelerometers and non-contact laser vibrometers. This integration enables vibrations to be monitored across multiple sources simultaneously, with minimal disruption to ongoing diagnostic or remedial processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Mehrabi &amp;amp; Farhangdoust, 2018</xref>).</p><p>The rise of modern processors, with their consequent higher computational power, is also a considerable reason that contributes to the advances in the field of software creation: it gave the opportunity to simulate the most demanding approaches to mathematical modeling of the complex behavior of the vibration patterns under different loading conditions. The clinicians can measure the stress distribution in the tibia in different activities that they apply during the rehabilitation and prevention of any patient at risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Kazemian et al., 2023</xref>). The study of vibrational biomechanics is becoming more complex, and, consequently, there is a possibility of predicting changes in dynamic behaviors due to other external factors such as changes in temperature. The software is also integrating such variables into its analytical framework, and the outcomes can be adapted to reflect patient-specific disorders and anatomical variability. The dynamics of cross-disciplinary collaboration between biomechanical scientists and engineers stimulate innovation in the sphere of vibration assessment applications and address theoretical and practical problems. Better visualization instruments are in development to enable the practitioners to analyze the crude data and create presentations using graphics that indicate important findings regarding the mechanics of the tibia with time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">US National Science Foundation, 2024</xref>).</p><p>Cloud-based computing platforms are also finding uses in the large volume of data storage generated by the constant monitoring required to accomplish the sequential studies needed to understand the health behavior of the tibia. The sphere will be brought closer to the strategies that may introduce augmented reality (AR) technologies to the procedures of diagnosis, which implies that software will need to be easily flexible to accommodate the requirements of simple alternations between conventional diagnostic methods and revised evaluation solutions that include the use of AR technologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Rho et al., 1998</xref>). The other trend is to implement the automated systems, which learn the patterns of the historical input data and adjust the functionality according to the user interventions or environmental changes in the test conditions. Ongoing advancement of software development on vibrational analysis plays a key role not only in the medical field but also in other parts of the engineering industry to improve safety measures against structural failures or any other injuries due to the unknown mechanical inconsistencies in bio-interfaces like bones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Luo et al., 2022</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Clinical applications of vibration techniques for the tibia</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.1. Use in orthopedic diagnostics</title>
          
          <p>It has been called a revolution of orthopedic diagnostics based on the dynamic approaches that provide an objective and non-invasive way to follow the healing processes of the bones. In comparison to the traditional radiographic procedures that are not only risky in terms of secondary consequences such as the exposure to ionizing radiation by the oral cavity but also are based on subjective evaluation, the vibration-based diagnoses give the answer needed by the medical decision-making, i.e., the mechanical properties of the healing bone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>).</p><p>The main argument of vibrational analysis is that it allows us to analyze the degrees of bone stiffness, damping and structures. By applying a quantitative stimulus (vibration) to bone tissue and examining the response, clinicians can report on quantitative measurements of the response which relates to changes in the control of mechanical properties. Apart from identifying the process of healing locally in the correct direction, any complications can be detected at an earlier stage, such as delayed union or non-union. It has been established that diagnosis procedures can be enhanced by vibration means. For example, a study on mechanically vibrated lower leg fractures reported that computerized analysis of mechanical vibration was found to help identify delayed union, significantly varying between fractured and intact tibia. It is possible that the protocol is implemented to offer real-time monitoring of a healing bone’s stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Kadhim et al., 2024b</xref>).</p><p>Another technology element, which would be helpful in testing the response of the bones to vibration at different frequencies, is the frequency response analysis. It has been established that transformation in vibrating frequencies is related to the change in names of bone rigidity as a matter of healing the bone. With the example of fracture healing, initial resonant frequencies can also grow exponentially during the various phases of the healing process, which could be considered the quantifiable outputs of the recovery state. In conjunction with frequency response techniques, other more advanced techniques, including AE and LDV, are employed to refine diagnosis plans, as they do not subject the bone to any form of harmful radiation. The benefits of these technologies are that they are associated with patient safety and may be used to carry out more frequent surveillance monitoring that is mandatory throughout the patient treatment process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Mattei et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>The decision-making processes of the vibrational treatment are also carried out, and this fact permits obtaining the opportunity to consider the strategies of the care on a case-by-case basis and select them in accordance with the peculiarities of the needs of the patient. Only objective assessment, which is a tool that is based on the vibration data, may assist a clinician in making the right decisions concerning the kind of treatment that should be applied, determining whether a patient can be provided with some conservative therapy, such as physical therapy and whether he should perform surgery, and aligning treatment choices with the personal healing experience of a specific individual. Despite these key benefits, when applied on a higher scale, it comes with some limitations that restrict clinical application. The poor validation of a range of patient groups is concerning for a consistent and sound reputation of vibrational tests. Further research is required to create a set of standard procedures that can be used in orthopedic diagnostics. The anatomical variability of patients is another challenge; age, weight-bearing, underlying disease, etc., can also influence the reaction to vibration. This type of difference must be known because in this manner it becomes possible to improve techniques and not to criticize people when it comes to different groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Fellinger et al., 1994</xref>).</p><p>In the future, a combination of tibial vibration measures and other diagnostic modalities, including ultrasound or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), may propose itself as a way to expand the knowledge base on bone health and overcome the drawbacks of each of the separate technologies. Studies aimed at enhancement in vibration evaluation training procedures, especially using high-end machine learning programs, have the potential of breaking revelations in forecasting managing breakage recovery paths dependent on preliminary vibrational signatures. The development of sensor technologies is an indicator of improved accuracy and reliability of tracking mechanical properties over time and this aspect has led to new developments in this field of specialization. Finally, the integration of the vibration techniques in orthopedic diagnostics is a major step to advanced forms of diagnosis, with the help of which clinical practices and patient results could be enhanced because of informed decision-making (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Mattei et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.2. Comparison of tibial assessment methods</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> presents the comparison of four tibial assessment systems (RFA, AE, LDV, and modal analysis) in terms of performance, clinical use, and diagnostic value.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Performance, clinical application, and diagnostic utility of four tibial assessment systems</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Method</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Performance</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Clinical Use</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Diagnostic Value</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>RFA</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sensitive to changes in stiffness, especially during fracture healing</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Monitoring fracture healing and assessing bone stiffness</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Provides real-time data on bone stiffness and healing progress</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AE</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Detects microdamage, cracks, and damage progression</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Detecting bone microfractures and evaluating bone health</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Identifies early damage before visible signs appear</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LDV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Highly accurate, measures displacement and velocity</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Measuring tibial vibrations and non-invasive monitoring during healing</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High precision in dynamic response measurements and non-invasive</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Modal analysis</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Measures natural frequencies, mode shapes, and damping characteristics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Assessing structural integrity and identifying abnormalities</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Used to assess overall tibial integrity and biomechanical properties</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Challenges and limitations in vibration-based methods</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.1. Technical challenges in measurement accuracy and reliability</title>
          
          <p>A large number of technical problems face all these clinical diagnostics and monitoring of bone health using vibrations in the tibia that undermine the accuracy and reliability of the technique. One of the problems is caused by the fact that soft tissues that surround the tibia like the muscle, the skin, and the fatty tissues absorb the transmission of the vibration. It is usually this damping effect that masks the high-frequency resonance modes which are needed to study the phenomena. These soft tissues are engaging with the structure of the bones, rendering the procedure of deriving useful information upon the basis of the measurements of the vibration quite complicated. It has been experimentally shown that significant vibrational responses are masked by the presence of soft tissue, thereby reducing the sensitivity of the system to variations in bone health. Moreover, it is also another important characteristic regarding individual variability of the patients in the case of vibration-based assessment. The composition, bone structure, and mass distribution of body tissue may vary widely amongst individuals. Such differences might produce different frequency responses when computing the tibial vibrations of different patients. Therefore, it is difficult to develop a standard approach and easily compare various cases or individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>).</p><p>The weaknesses of contemporary vibration analysis protocols add to the complexity of sensitive measurement of vibrational responses. To explain this, even though RFA is a routine test to quantify accidents in the vibration characteristics of bones to establish the mechanical characteristics of bone, it has several drawbacks in the frequency shift monitoring and mode coupling candles in examinations. It is estimated that the uncertainties below may cause the RFA results to be quite inaccurate, especially in the dynamic environment where many factors may affect the vibrational response. Furthermore, unlike intricate devices like lasers and Doppler vibrometry that can be purchased with great precision in vibration measurements, non-invasive devices require close calibration and noise variables in the environment (which make measurements noisy) need to be factored in. It is impossible to overrate the importance of strict control over the environmental conditions of experiments; temperature changes, or general movement, during testing may introduce artifacts in the process of data collection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Razaghi et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>The other major aspect of the challenge is the optimization of the location of sensors and methods of attachment either to the tibia or around the tibia during the testing. The use of different sensor placements may cause discrepancy in the quality of data due to the way vibrations are transmitted in different tissues to the measurement devices. To date only a small number of studies have been conducted to examine novel ways to attach sensors or novel designs that may enhance contact elements between sensors and bony structures whilst minimizing contact with adjacent soft tissues. With these concerns about the accuracy and reliability of measurements of tibial vibrations, scientists have begun to consider more sophisticated methods to identify more specific vibrational modes that can be related to the healing of the injury or disease of bones. Others contemplate using contemporary signal processing algorithms capable of eliminating the noise generated by the surrounding soft tissues and enhancing the signals associated with the well-being of the bones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Ozmen et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>One interesting possibility is that subsequent research investigations in which machine learning strategies might be implemented to the existing practice of evaluating vibration might provide an interesting opportunity to refocus the diagnostic process according to the capacity to adapt such tests in line with patient-specific characteristics or even anatomical characteristics. With smarter algorithms trained on more extensive data reflecting changes in patient conditions and corresponding vibrational responses, predictive models could not only be developed but also be refined to more accurately evaluate bone health over time. Even though the problem of technical difficulty remains constant in the current routine practice of tibial vibration assessment blocks, such as parameters of individual patient anatomy and other external influence factors through soft tissue, it is expected that the improvement of sensor technology in the future will trigger a range of improvements as people enter the clinical practice-focused grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Vien et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>A methodical process not only simplifies modalities of measurements but also offers general guidelines that would benefit a wide range of patients and yet deliver credible outcomes under a variety of clinical conditions. All of these can ultimately facilitate more effective early staging processes that are pertinent in the context of timely interventions in the prevention of any long-term complications that might be caused directly by undiagnosed musculoskeletal disorders or bone diseases, such as osteoporosis or stress fractures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Karpiński et al., 2024</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>6.2. Limitations related to patient variability and anatomical differences</title>
          
          <p>Patient differences and anatomical deviations are too great to allow reliable tibial examination through vibration analysis. All these complications are linked to the personal anatomic deformities, the influence of the soft tissues, bone properties, and traditional diagnostic methods. The anatomy of the human body is incredibly diverse. In particular, the structural aspects of the tibia can depend on the age, gender, body composition, and health and can sometimes be defined as variable factors. The elderly might also differ as predictors in terms of bone densities from younger patients and, thus, their vibrational responses. The same difference has made it difficult to interpret any data which arises after the vibration testing and has resulted in the necessity of means that are unique in that the differences between individuals of the anatomy are taken into consideration as part of defining the vibrational patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>).</p><p>The tibial vibration assessment accuracy is also affected by the soft tissues. The tissue surrounding the tibia can absorb vibrational information and alter the signal that in reality should be one of a bone. This is exacerbated by the fact that there could be differences in the mass of soft tissues of patients; patients with a higher number of muscles could be subject to various vibrational responses compared to patients with more fat. Therefore, the isolation of the bone responses, rather than the affected ones exerted by the surrounding tissues, requires new methodologies. In addition, vibration measurements vary because there are no consistent protocols regarding the location of the sensors. Even when dealing with multiple patients or even within the same patient over time, procedural variation in how the sensors are applied (e.g., the adhesive strengths employed or sensor placements) may cause variable outputs. Such problems of consistency make comparative assessment and repeatability of vibrational measurements dubious to practitioners that seek to develop reliable diagnostic parameters using vibrational data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Ozmen et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>Because of comorbidities, the findings of the analysis might be skewed by patient-specific factors. One such example is the osteoporotic patients who are capable of demonstrating a change in bone stiffness and expressing this differently when subjected to the vibrating device compared with healthy counterparts. This means that standard procedures that were being administered on various populations could not identify the low-level responses that are significant in correct diagnosis. The tibial vibration is difficult to assess due to subjective movements of the human being. The other activities also place a different loading on the bones, which have a unique design, and, therefore, these vibrational characteristics can be affected due to changes in the distribution of the stress. It is not only the question of recording baseline vibrations but also the understanding of how various activities may interfere with the measurements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Vien et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>The methodologies available are inclined to be based on some definite frequencies of considering vibratory signals which are applied to assess bone health, but these frequencies are not universal since any patient is a biological person and his or her bones are different. Therefore, there is a probability of the frequency bands reflecting various bone-health regions of the specific person based on the organization of the specific person and hence individual solutions should be applied to avoid false general assumptions. To overcome these shortcomings, the interaction of various patient parameters with mechanical properties measured with vibrations should receive increased research attention. The studies ahead should focus on designing adaptive algorithms that are guided by machine learning models to consider individual variation in clinical decisions. Enhancement of the calibration methods relying on the variability of the patient would elevate the accuracy of the measurements and might eliminate the external influence of the soft tissues or other changes of the dynamics of movement that might happen during the usual daily routine activity. Collaboration with biomechanics experts to develop new technologies and promote the widespread adoption of standardized protocols could enable healthcare workers to successfully employ innovative diagnostic equipment for assessing tibial mechanical properties without surgery, thereby addressing these barriers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Karpiński et al., 2024</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>7. Future directions in vibration-based tibial assessment</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>7.1. Integration with other diagnostic modalities for enhanced assessment capabilities</title>
          
          <p>Application of modalities on panel bouts and vibration ratings via the integration of the conventional methods of diagnosis signify a never-seen-before revolution in the field of tibial biomechanical analysis and recovery. This combination is implemented in order to improve the precision of diagnosis, the effectiveness of the treatment and personal offers, and the monitoring of the efficiency of the rehabilitation program. An important feature of this form of integration is cooperation between vibration and visual data such as X-rays and MRI. Contrary to the traditional imaging studies, the meaningful information of the skeletal structure is presented, but usually some information of functionality is not present, which can be found by usage of vibration. The mechanical properties (stiffness and damping) in the test with vibration determine the well-being of the bones during the recovery period. Vibration analysis and imaging can provide an excellent picture of structural and functional stages of tibial healing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>).</p><p>This longitudinal study integration examines how things evolve over time. To ensure the healing process within a clinical degree environment, vibration measurements provide real-time measures of the response to mechanical strains of the bones. The process of healing is observed to be accompanied by different resonant frequencies, and the difference in the resonant frequencies for different parts can be compared by the clinicians with the biological mechanism of remodeling of bones. Through timely communication, healthcare providers can be corrected on how they need to change the way they administer the treatment in order to effectively address the needs of the patient. In addition, AI and machine learning are helpful in processing complicated clusters of information using a wide range of diagnostic apps. Apart from analyzing patients, AI algorithms can be applied to processing the information provided by the vibration inspection and the scanning images, which allows practitioners to more efficiently identify patterns that indicate whether a patient is recovering or regressing. This enhances the accuracy of the diagnosis and approaches it with a specific method. The patient-reported outcomes can enhance the scope of assessment as a component of this integrated model. Inclusion of subjective measurements, e.g., amount of pain and movement, in the objective data delivered when the patient is tested on vibration provides the entire picture of how the patient has improved. This poly-dimensional view of clinical indicators also accounts for the patient experience with a view of reclaiming (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Mattei et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>The sensor technology is also viewed to bring about improved advancements to the feasibility and availability of integrated systems within the clinical environment. Further miniaturization of sensors and a decrease in their costs make wearable devices capable of continuously sensing tibial vibrations during everyday work or rehabilitation feasible. With such a transition in place, it would be available to analyze dynamically in real-life situations in which tibial biomechanical changes have taken place. In addition, focal muscle vibration therapy in combination with methods of vibrational rehabilitation assessment can be used to maximize treatment. It has been found that low-frequency therapeutic vibration has the potential to promote a response in bone growth as well as in neuromuscular functions related to post-injury or post-surgical muscle recovery. Therefore, assessment approaches that analyze therapeutic vibrations, together with the therapeutic vibrations, stimulate healing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Bessaguet et al., 2025</xref>).</p><p>Other than tibial assessment, combining the vibration analysis with other non-invasive methods such as vibroarthrography improves the identification of minimal conditions of joint degeneration or complications after the repairs of the fractures. Such ability gives valuable information on the general health of limbs to an orthopedic specialist whose intervention strategy needs prior knowledge on the state of health. Overall, the synergy of non-invasive means of determining vibration and other diagnostic methods allows achieving higher sensitivity and decreasing the dependence of food on radiology-based measurements, which is more important to preserve patient health without impairing the quality of patient care. Future research should focus on developing approaches that facilitate interdisciplinary collaboration in orthopedic care, ultimately delivering individualized care to the patient using the comprehensive assessment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Bessaguet et al., 2025</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>7.2. Research opportunities for improving vibrational assessment methods specific to the tibia</title>
          
          <p>This has been the case in research devoted to establishing vibrational assessment methods for the tibia, which represent a promising approach with the potential to significantly influence diagnostic processes and recovery in orthopedic medicine. The other factor, which is also heading in the right direction, is the establishment of the standardized system of measurement procedures, which would ensure reproducibility or, accordingly, regularity under varying clinical conditions. Fluctuation of outcomes of the present research is common because of the dissimilarity in the use of different methods, dissimilarity in the population of the patient, and use of different equipment. Whenever a standard would be set up, then comparative studies would be enhanced which would add reliability to the validity. To know more about the vibrational responsiveness of the tibia, the obligatory task is to research the anatomical and pathological variation between populations. These changes in bone density, structure, soft tissue makeup, and general biomechanics could amount to vibrational properties. Further studies should attempt to define full databases characterizing such differences so that more individual assessment models can be formed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>).</p><p>The next technology to be improved with regard to sensitivity and specificity is the vibration-sensing technology. Fine vibrational patterns may be neglected in common accelerometer applications due to tissue damping and blackout of the signal. It can be added to the more recent detection methods, which yield more of the frequency responses and would indicate the early pathology responses, or healing responses. Moreover, the investigation of vibrations using the help of imaging data (ultrasound or MRI) has a chance to give a more meaningful and better picture of bone health as well. Another possible opportunity is to use machine learning algorithms for information obtained in the process of conducting the vibration tests. These techniques are capable of identifying small patterns that might otherwise be overlooked when analyzing large datasets across different populations and situations. An additional opportunity that the methodology would give is the possibility to monitor the treatment in real time and actively modify the therapy process with the assistance of clinicians by considering the response of the patients to the treatment. In addition to that, the biomechanical effect of several loading conditions in a controlled vibrational environment is also of interest for understanding how exogenous factors affect tibial healing integrity and rate. Such research studies as that which utilized low tibial vibration models should be helpful in achieving the most desirable parameters as far as the regulation of therapeutic use of vibration as a treatment mode is concerned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Vien et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>Moreover, the wearable technology may be deployed to establish self-monitoring processes through which a patient is informed about his/her progress post-rehabilitation according to the home-based or physical therapy-based evaluation. This pragmatic realization not only would be helpful to follow through with the rehabilitation plans but also would serve as a good source of information that can be utilized in the secondary study. Regarding clinical use, however, having advanced to more recent literature, it probably would be fruitful to compare the findings of vibrational research to less modern forms of diagnosis, e.g., radiography images or biochemical assays, to conclude at a stronger vision of the bone healthcare practice. These integrative processes may contribute to assessing preoperative surgical risks and evaluating fracture healing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Christiansen et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>Lastly, longitudinal research like investigating the short-term effects associated with non-invasive vibration measurements has an important role in deciding the use of non-invasive vibration in clinical practice. The generation of good longitudinal data not only enhances the knowledge of the world but also gives the practitioners credibility as far as the predictive power of such practices in the future is concerned. Key areas of future research include standardization, technological advancement of detecting tibia-related vibrations, incorporation of applications based on machine learning, biomechanical measurement at varying loads, and the role of patients in tibia-related research with wearables and correlations between non-traditional and conventional diagnostics. And the analysis of long-term outcomes helps the research community to effectively streamline the methodology provisions of estimating the tibia through vibrations in effect, benefiting the patient-care activity in the broad spectrum of orthopedic practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Christiansen et al., 2008</xref>). It maps out what is likely to happen in the future and provides a clear path forward to the introduction and validation of the next-generation tibial assessment tools by incorporating the following specific experimental designs and algorithmic structures.</p>
          <p>A. Experimental designs</p><p>1. Comparison of vibration methods</p><p>Comparison of the conventional procedures (e.g., DXA and radiography) with the non-invasive procedures that involve vibration (e.g., RFA, AE, and LDV) could involve:</p><p><p>Participants: A population of patients with a fracture of the tibia, osteoporotic patients, and a healthy bone density control group.</p><p>Design: The study is a randomized controlled trial (RCT) in which subjects receive a series of traditional and vibration-based tests at various points in the fracture healing process (acute, subacute, and recovery).</p></p><p>2. Bone longitudinal healing study</p><p>Tracking tibial bone health with wearables and machine learning to measure bone health by assessing vibrations.</p><p><p>Participants: Post-surgical tibial fracture patients or patients with chronic bone diseases like osteoarthritis.</p><p>Design: 6-12 month cohort study, including periodic vibration-based studies, MRI testing, and biochemical indicators (e.g., bone turnover indicators).</p></p><p>3. Multi-sensor integration/real-time monitoring</p><p>Initiating wearable sensors with AI algorithms would track the tibial vibrations in real time, hence measuring the healing process along with the activity levels.</p><p><p>Participants: Healthy adults, elderly people at risk of fractures and patients who have undergone a fracture or joint replacement surgery.</p><p>Design: Cross-sectional study with baseline data obtained with wearables, vibration sensors and X-ray or MRI.</p></p><p>B. Algorithmic frameworks</p><p>1. AI to create individualized rehabilitation plans</p><p>Training machine learning to learn vibration data and predict recovery paths with variables added such as age, gender, comorbidities, and type of fracture.</p><p><p>Framework: Vibration signal processing, patient demographics and medical history using neural networks to produce a deep learning model.</p><p>Validation: Testing the algorithm on a separate cohort and comparing the predictions against clinical consequences (e.g., healing time and functional recovery).</p></p><p>2. Wearable AI to monitor the home</p><p>Developing an AI-driven wearable to gather vibration data continuously send real-time feedback on bone health and rehab status to both patients and clinicians.</p><p><p>Framework: Predictive models in the form of machine learning that are installed on wearables, which recognize abnormal patterns of vibration on a device and notify the user.</p><p>Validation: Clinical trials on the effectiveness of the wearable in improving the outcomes of rehabilitation against traditional in-clinic testing.</p></p><p>C. Participant cohorts</p><p><p>General population: Towards this end, no less than two healthy adults to serve as baseline data on normal bone stiffness and healing.</p><p>Aging population: This is an extension of the last cause because the elderly are more susceptible to fractures due to other illnesses such as osteoporosis.</p><p>Post-surgery patients: This group of patients would require real-time monitoring because they have undergone tibial fracture or orthopedic surgeries.</p></p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>8. Conclusion</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>8.1. Summary of key findings regarding non-invasive techniques for tibial assessment</title>
          
          <p>Non-invasive vibration measurement techniques have become an invaluable contribution towards the examination of the mechanical properties and healing process of the tibia. Recent literature shows that these techniques are applicable to the tracking of alterations in bone stiffness and structural integrity during the recovery of fractures and provide a potential substitute to other conventional images such as X-rays. One of the aspects that can be taken as significantly important is that the use of assessments with vibration can bring quantifiable data on many different phases of the healing process, which would otherwise be overlooked by conventional approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Kadhim et al., 2024a</xref>). As an example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Mattei et al. (2019)</xref> showed the benefit of a non-invasive vibrational technique by monitoring the full healing of a complex tibial fracture that was managed with the help of external fixation. Their study emphasized that the progress of the evolution of squared frequency increments (SFIs) of resonant frequencies might match the altering stiffness of callus formation with time and thus give a light to the process of healing. It was revealed that it is possible to detect healing early since regular biweekly measurements over a long period can be taken, once again enforcing the prospects of vibrational techniques of substituting radiographic assessment in clinical practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Mattei et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>Similarly, other researchers such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Vien et al. (2022)</xref> applied modal analysis and related modal frequencies to musculoskeletal parameters such as the length of the femur, demonstrating that modal analysis would be an efficient way to measure bone health. It was concluded that some modes of frequencies may express some natural structural soundness and may be utilized in the determination of the even-handed principles in the healing process of the fractures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Vien et al., 2022</xref>). The question of standardization and validation of other patients and anatomical variations nevertheless remains. The process of implementing the techniques of vibration analysis requires intensive validation experiments so that it is possible to have a homogenous information collection and interpretation. In the meantime, there are patient variability incompatibilities, which are unacceptable in the mainstream, but one active line of research is exceptionally trying to address it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Pires et al., 2025</xref>).</p><p>Non-invasive measurements in this field are increasingly becoming more powerful in conjunction with a technology which is ever-growing and enhancing. Instrumentation and sensor technology may provide more data for measurement at various times through the fracture healing process. In addition, the computer developments that could lead to the development of a better data analysis can aid in improved integration of testing based on vibration into clinical practice. The vibration methods can be used during the diagnostics and monitoring of the rehabilitation process. By evaluating tibial vibrations consistently as recovery progresses, the clinicians can offer a more objective assessment of the advancement, rather than providing a subjective evaluation alone. This extra weight can be used to promptly introduce interventions as issues emerge during the recovery process, ultimately leading to improved patient outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Mattei et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>Better still, non-invasive vibrational tests open chances of mastering personal treatment plans based on the tangible arrangement of people. With further evolution of research on the vibration-based procedures of assessment, one of the most promising prospects is to view the incorporation of those procedures with other assessment procedures (imaging or bioelectronic sensors) to define a full procedure of assessment of tibial health. However, when certain positive outcomes were achieved regarding the views of vibration tests, it was necessary to concentrate on the incorporation of these tests into medical practice while considering a significant number of practical issues. It is recommended in new initiatives that sample size should be increased in several demographic exemplifications to establish a sound empirical base that would support the validity and efficacy of these experimental diagnostic mechanisms. In a nutshell, the vibration-based evaluation is a new technology in orthopedic diagnostics that, besides fracture healing evaluation, provides non-invasive devices to facilitate improved recovery results through real-time intervention when recovering patients receive feedback on whether their rehabilitation exercises are being performed correctly. It is a technology whose enormous possibilities promise a better notion of the application of tibial biomechanics and disclose new opportunities for better methods of patient care by new clinical application (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Ortolani et al., 2024</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>8.2. Final thoughts on future trends in tibial biomechanics evaluation using vibration techniques</title>
          
          <p>New technologies are making vibration-based tibial biomechanical assessment increasingly attractive as a diagnostic alternative. Non-invasive techniques like vibration analysis of monitored bone healing have demonstrated that the different stages of fracture healing can be identified as differences in resonant frequencies. The more likely the data is to be converted to different clusters of patients, the more beneficial vibrational tests will be for increasing the level of diagnostic confidence. Diagnostic modalities such as ultrasound and advanced imaging are combined with vibrational testing, which has become one of the most topical trends. By developing a global image that would capture mechanical and biological features of the sites of injuries, this multivariate method would enhance diagnostics of the tibia. Individual rehabilitation plans in orthopedic practice can be achieved by improving treatment schedules using the combination of different levels of diagnostics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Kadhim et al., 2024b</xref>).</p><p>Technology is improving the clinical use of vibration measurements with enhanced sensors and information processing schemes. Less experienced practitioners could employ sophisticated procedures with the aid of training programs and automated diagnostic tools to support appropriate interpretation of results. Machine learning algorithms are even being used to process vibrational data and may prove helpful at identifying patterns in large-scale data that are not readily visible to a more traditional algorithm. AI and past data allow clinicians to improve the diagnostic capabilities and predictions of outcomes. With the increase in outpatient care and home rehabilitation, portable devices to assess vibration may appear which in turn can give patients a chance to take an active part in their healing process and allow healthcare providers to monitor them constantly. It is possible to perform research to determine the characteristics of certain vibrational features corresponding to the presence of some pathologies or stages of healing of tibial trauma. The identification of how various factors such as age, gender, level of activity, and density of bones affect responses to vibrations may result in personal rehabilitation plans to maximize recovery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Mattei et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>Future breakthroughs will depend on orthopedics, engineering, and biomechanics collaboration. Cross-sector research can contribute to generating new solutions to improve bone repair based on novel materials or methods by means of stimulation applying vibrations. Patient consent ethics and privacy of patient data have to be addressed hand in hand as such technologies are developed and patients demand to know how their data can be accessed and safeguarded in their health systems. In general, the development of the non-invasive approach to vibration in tibia improvement in the realization of biomechanics will make a significant contribution to the preciseness of the diagnostic process, not to mention the rehabilitation activity. The integration of AI and the current routine will improve the predictive medical models of healing bone and recovery, leading to the production of personal treatment plans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Cheung et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>Moreover, recent improvements in wearable technology will transform the procedure of vibration evaluation and the potential to check it on a continuous basis within routine life. Creation of standard measures of tibial vibration tests will facilitate continuous use of the test in clinical practice with increased comparability of results. The studies carried out to determine a relationship/correlation among the variables, including age, pre-existing conditions and vibrational properties, will be important in carrying out an effective assessment. Vibration methods applied to the difference of diagnostics and curative solutions might be very useful in a setting of the recovery process. The imperative to discover non-invasive solutions also socializes the acquisition of high-quality knowledge of low exposure of radiation to the patients. Moreover, software analytics will help clinicians draw some beneficial conclusions concerning the integrity of the bone over a long period, which can be of great value since diagnostic means will be available to everyone. It describes the reason why the future of the vibration-based technique used in the evaluation of tibial biomechanics is bright when fused technologies and multidisciplinary contributions are taken into account (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Mattei et al., 2021</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The author declares no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>46</volume>
          <page-range>97-107</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arami</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delaloye</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rouhani</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jolles</surname>
              <given-names>B. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aminian</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10439-017-1941-2</pub-id>
          <article-title>Knee implant loosening detection: A vibration analysis investigation</article-title>
          <source>Ann. Biomed. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>e102838</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bessaguet</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandez</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malejac</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nerriere</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Velarde</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coiffet</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rimaud</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lapole</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2025-102838</pub-id>
          <article-title>Effect of tibialis anterior focal muscle vibration for gait rehabilitation in hemiplegic individuals during the subacute phase after stroke: The NEUROVIB-AVC study protocol—A multicentric randomised controlled trial</article-title>
          <source>BMJ Open</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>13</volume>
          <page-range>909317</page-range>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Campos</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Volpon</surname>
              <given-names>J. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ximenez</surname>
              <given-names>J. P. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franttini</surname>
              <given-names>A. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalloul</surname>
              <given-names>C. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sousa-Neto</surname>
              <given-names>M. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kacena</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zamarioli</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2022.909317</pub-id>
          <article-title>Vibration therapy as an effective approach to improve bone healing in diabetic rats</article-title>
          <source>Front. Endocrinol.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>52</volume>
          <page-range>S97-S100</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cheung</surname>
              <given-names>Wing Hoi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>Ronald Man Yeung</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choy</surname>
              <given-names>Victoria Man Huen</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Meng Chen Michelle</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>Keith Yu Kin</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chow</surname>
              <given-names>Simon Kwoon Ho</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.injury.2020.05.020</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enhancement of osteoporotic fracture healing by vibration treatment: The role of osteocytes</article-title>
          <source>Injury</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>130</volume>
          <page-range>044502</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Christiansen</surname>
              <given-names>B. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bayly</surname>
              <given-names>P. V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1115/1.2917435</pub-id>
          <article-title>Constrained tibial vibration in mice: A method for studying the effects of vibrational loading of bone</article-title>
          <source>J. Biomech. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>113</volume>
          <page-range>93-96</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1994</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fellinger</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leitgeb</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szyszkowitz</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peicha</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Passler</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seggl</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schanner</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf00572913</pub-id>
          <article-title>Early detection of delayed union in lower leg fractures using a computerised analysis of mechanical vibration reactions of bone for assessing the state of fracture healing</article-title>
          <source>Arch. Orthop. Trauma Surg.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>43</volume>
          <page-range>622-631</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoffman</surname>
              <given-names>D. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schifino</surname>
              <given-names>A. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cooley</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhong</surname>
              <given-names>R. X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heo</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>C. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campbell</surname>
              <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warren</surname>
              <given-names>G. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greising</surname>
              <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Call</surname>
              <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.26023</pub-id>
          <article-title>Low intensity, high frequency vibration training to improve musculoskeletal function in a mouse model of volumetric muscle loss</article-title>
          <source>J. Orthop. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>23</volume>
          <page-range>49-73</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kadhim</surname>
              <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aubad</surname>
              <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Juboori</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32852/p9jpjf68</pub-id>
          <article-title>An extensive review of vibration methods for bone healing assessment</article-title>
          <source>Iraqi J. Mech. Mater. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>25</volume>
          <page-range>1-11</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kadhim</surname>
              <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aubad</surname>
              <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Juboori</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.29354/diag/192180</pub-id>
          <article-title>Analyzing frequency response analysis experimentally for bone healing detection: Examining the potential of vibrational evaluations</article-title>
          <source>Diagnostyka</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>279</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karpiński</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prus</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jonak</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krakowski</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app15010279</pub-id>
          <article-title>Vibroarthrography as a noninvasive screening method for early diagnosis of knee osteoarthritis: A review of current research</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>2</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kazemian</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yee</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oguzmert</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amirgholy</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goff</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s43251-023-00081-6</pub-id>
          <article-title>A review of bridge scour monitoring techniques and developments in vibration based scour monitoring for bridge foundations</article-title>
          <source>Adv. Bridge Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>1644</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>M. T. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Auslander</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rocha-Rangel</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Musculoskeletal loading from road cycling and distance running on bone bending strength and BMD in athletes</article-title>
          <source>J. Clin. Med. Images Case Rep.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>43-54</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>B. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21642583.2021.2024099</pub-id>
          <article-title>High-speed vision measurement of vibration based on an improved ZNSSD template matching algorithm</article-title>
          <source>Syst. Sci. Control Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>1-11</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mattei</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Di Fonzo</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marchetti</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Di Puccio</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/23335432.2021.1874528</pub-id>
          <article-title>A quantitative and non-invasive vibrational method to assess bone fracture healing: A clinical case study</article-title>
          <source>Int. Biomech.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>1-6</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mattei</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Di Puccio</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marchetti</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/jtehm.2019.2901455</pub-id>
          <article-title>Fracture healing monitoring by impact tests: Single case study of a fractured tibia with external fixator</article-title>
          <source>IEEE J. Transl. Eng. Health Med.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2018</volume>
          <page-range>8640674</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mehrabi</surname>
              <given-names>A. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farhangdoust</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/8640674</pub-id>
          <article-title>A laser‐based noncontact vibration technique for health monitoring of structural cables: Background, success, and new developments</article-title>
          <source>Adv. Acoust. Vib.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <volume>2024</volume>
          <page-range>1-4</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ortolani</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martarelli</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Annessi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scalise</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/memea60663.2024.10596782</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessment of bone vibrational transmissibility in tibia with external fixator</article-title>
          <source>2024 IEEE International Symposium on Medical Measurements and Applications (MeMeA). Eindhoven, Netherlands</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>68</volume>
          <page-range>2241-2250</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ozmen</surname>
              <given-names>G. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Safaei</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Semiz</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whittingslow</surname>
              <given-names>D. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hunnicutt</surname>
              <given-names>J. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prahalad</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hash</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xerogeanes</surname>
              <given-names>J. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inan</surname>
              <given-names>O. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/tbme.2020.3048930</pub-id>
          <article-title>Detection of meniscal tear effects on tibial vibration using passive knee sound measurements</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Trans. Biomed. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>10</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pastrav</surname>
              <given-names>L. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaecques</surname>
              <given-names>S. V. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jonkers</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van der Perre</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mulier</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1749-799x-4-10</pub-id>
          <article-title>In vivo evaluation of a vibration analysis technique for the per-operative monitoring of the fixation of hip prostheses</article-title>
          <source>J. Orthop. Surg. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>20</volume>
          <page-range>105</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pires</surname>
              <given-names>Diogo G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>N. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Completo</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>M. P. S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13018-025-05534-4</pub-id>
          <article-title>Bioelectronic osteosynthesis plate to monitor the fracture bone healing using electric capacitive variations</article-title>
          <source>J. Orthop. Surg. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>39-47</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Razaghi</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saatchi</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bishop</surname>
              <given-names>N. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burke</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Offiah</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.37394/23208.2020.17.6</pub-id>
          <article-title>Evaluation of vibration analysis to assess bone mineral density in children</article-title>
          <source>WSEAS Trans. Biol. Biomed.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>20</volume>
          <page-range>92-102</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1998</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rho</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuhn-Spearing</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zioupos</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1350-4533(98)00007-1</pub-id>
          <article-title>Mechanical properties and the hierarchical structure of bone</article-title>
          <source>Med. Eng. Phys.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>350-359</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Safaei</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bolus</surname>
              <given-names>N. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whittingslow</surname>
              <given-names>D. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeong</surname>
              <given-names>H. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Erturk</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inan</surname>
              <given-names>O. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/tnsre.2021.3050439</pub-id>
          <article-title>Vibration stimulation as a non-invasive approach to monitor the severity of meniscus tears</article-title>
          <source>IEEE Trans. Neural Syst. Rehabil. Eng.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>71</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scanlan</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Umnova</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/aacus/2024056</pub-id>
          <article-title>Finite element modelling tibia bone vibration—The influence of shape, twist, and end scale</article-title>
          <source>Acta Acust.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>50</volume>
          <page-range>391-398</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>1979</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sekiguchi</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirayama</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/17453677908989781</pub-id>
          <article-title>Assessment of fracture healing by vibration</article-title>
          <source>Acta Orthop. Scand.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>100161</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seth</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beisheim-Ryan</surname>
              <given-names>E. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pohlig</surname>
              <given-names>R. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horne</surname>
              <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hicks</surname>
              <given-names>G. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sions</surname>
              <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arrct.2021.100161</pub-id>
          <article-title>Vibration sensitivity is associated with functional balance after unilateral transtibial amputation</article-title>
          <source>Arch. Rehabil. Res. Clin. Transl.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>447-453</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>W. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yen</surname>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rubin</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/med.0000000000000111</pub-id>
          <article-title>Vibration therapy: Clinical applications in bone</article-title>
          <source>Curr. Opin. Endocrinol. Diabetes Obes.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>I-corps: Translation potential of an optical vibration measurement technology for system monitoring and digital twin development</article-title>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>20</volume>
          <page-range>2993-3006</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vien</surname>
              <given-names>B. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiu</surname>
              <given-names>W. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Russ</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fitzgerald</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1475921720978224</pub-id>
          <article-title>A vibration analysis strategy for quantitative fracture healing assessment of an internally fixated femur with mass-loading effect of soft tissue</article-title>
          <source>Struct. Health Monit.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>670</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vien</surname>
              <given-names>B. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiu</surname>
              <given-names>W. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Russ</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fitzgerald</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s22020670</pub-id>
          <article-title>Modal frequencies associations with musculoskeletal components of human legs for extracorporeal bone healing assessment based on a vibration analysis approach</article-title>
          <source>Sensors</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>