<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJEI</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.18280</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Environmental Impacts</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Int. J. Environ. Impacts.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IJEI</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2398-2659</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2398-2640</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-qQr-yNisFphuddOaIH3ywNG0a0KE9FP3</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18280/ijei.060405</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Customer Loyalty in Green Marketing Research: A Systematic Review</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-1615-6949</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Adnan</surname>
            <given-names>Adimas Rois</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>adimas.rois.psc20@mail.umy.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8596-6095</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Widowati</surname>
            <given-names>Retno</given-names>
          </name>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4998-9601</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Nuryakin</surname>
          </name>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Master Management Program, Universitas Muhammadiyah Yogyakarta, Yogyakarta 55183, Indonesia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>207</fpage>
      <lpage>214</lpage>
      <page-range>207-214</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2023 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>At present, green marketing attract the attention of academics and professionals around the world. Research on green marketing/sustainable marketing has increased in recent years. Through a systematics review, this study aims to analyze the development and trends of research with the theme customer loyalty within the scope of green marketing/sustainable marketing last 10 years (2013-2023). This study uses Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) method. Analysis is carried out based on productive countries, authors, institutions, journals, and distribution phrases. This study also analyzed articles based on the methods and variables used, along with outcomes. 33 selected documents were analysed using Wordstat. The results showed that United States is the most productive country that publishes articles on related topics. Green marketing, customer loyalty, customer satisfaction, green products, green image are phrases that often appear with a frequency limit of 200. Structural Equation Modelling (SEM) is a method that is often used.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Customer loyalty</kwd>
        <kwd>Green marketing</kwd>
        <kwd>Environment</kwd>
        <kwd>Sustainability</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="3"/>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="9"/>
        <ref-count count="27"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Currently, green marketing is a hot topic for companies, consumers, society, and the government in creating sustainable consumption [1]. Global warming, climate change, and air pollution, which are happening today, are some of the reasons that can be attributed to the shift to a “green” economy, which is considered a “policy and conceptual framework for sustainability” [2]. Every sector is required to have a good impact on the environment to create sustainability in the future, including from the business sector. The company, in terms of marketing, implements “green marketing”.</p><p>Green marketing encompasses the entire process of addressing environmental concerns, from product planning ideas to product distribution [3]. Its main objective is to promote environmental responsibility and contribute to a sustainable economy. The aim is not solely to enhance the company’s image or maximize profits, but also to encourage eco-friendly, green consumption [4]. The latter is an action where consumers purchase and consume products because the products are environmentally friendly (e.g., recyclable, sustainable, renewable, low energy consumption, low pollution, non-disturbing to the environment) [5].</p><p>In the company’s perspective, the application of green marketing is useful for changing the company’s organization, developing technology, helping companies create social responsibility for the environment [6]. In the study, companies oriented towards implementing green marketing have an impact on the creation of green image [7]. In another study, it was said that green marketing has a significant positive effect on brand loyalty [8]. In the perspective of society and government, green marketing can reduce and provide solutions to environment problems, because green marketing integrates the concepts and practices of the environment, ecology, and social activities [1]. The majority of environmental problems are caused by the industrial sector which needs to be controlled [9].</p><p>In the business sector, marketing management is the art and science of choosing target markets and getting, keeping, and growing customer [10]. Companies that successfully retain consumers will create loyalty which is seen as a commitment from consumers to repurchase products in the future consistently [11]. Loyalty is created from companies that create products according to consumer needs [10].</p><p>Consumer loyalty is related to consumer satisfaction with the product, satisfied consumers will create loyalty to the product [12]. Satisfaction relates to the good impression of consumers on the product, because the performance of the product matches or exceeds the expectations of consumers [13]. In another study, it was found that consumer loyalty has an impact on positive Word of Mouth (WOM) [14]. WOM is the most effective from of marketing [15]. Positive WOM can have a good image impact on companies and products, and companies get “free” marketing from consumers.</p><p>Based on the explanation above, it is known that consumer loyalty is an important and interesting thing to research. However, there are still few published figures that discuss consumer loyalty in the scope of environmentally friendly/sustainable marketing. Therefore, through a systematics review, this research aims to analyse the development and trends of research on the topic customer loyalty in the scope of green marketing for the past 10 years from 2013 - 2023. The systematic review aims to provide a comprehensive, unbiased synthesis of many relevant studies in a single document [16]. Research developments and trends will be seen based on the number of publications per year, authors, journals that publish, most productive countries, affiliations, and subject areas. The data analyzed in this research was sourced from Scopus database. This study will also specifically explore the following research questions spanning from 2013 to 2013 (RQ):</p><p>RQ1: What are the trends of customer loyalty in the scope of green marketing research?</p><p>RQ2: Which specific phrases frequently emerge within the realm of customer loyalty in the context of green marketing research?</p><p>RQ3: What are the commonly used methods and variables in customer loyalty within the scope of green marketing research?</p><p>RQ4: What are the purposes and findings of customer loyalty in the scope of green marketing research?</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Method</title>
      <p>This research focuses on analyzing research developments and trends with the topic about customer loyalty within the scope of green marketing. The method used in this study is Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA), with the aim to help the authors improve the reporting of systematic reviews and meta-analyses [17]. The data in this study is based on internationally accredited articles published in the Scopus database from 2013 to 2023 using a systematic approach to select articles with keywords in the title or abstract. The Scopus database, created in 2004, (a product from Elsevier), is one of the largest curated databases covering scientific journals, books, conference proceedings, etc. [18]. The database of Scopus was utilized as the primary resource of information because academics regard it as a credible resource of scholarly papers [19]. The data obtained was then processed using the Wordstat application for keyword analysis. Furthermore, the process of searching for data is discussed in the subchapter of search strategies.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Search strategy</title>
          
          <p>The follow were the methodological steps used for this research:</p><p>1. The results are filtered via a Boolean search on the basis of their relevance to the objective of this work.</p><p>2. Duplicates are eliminated and literature stored as per their respective keywords in titles and abstracts, further introducing restrictions that would limit the search to only the relevant fields based on years, language, etc. (as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>3. Select articles that are appropriate for the purpose of the study.</p><p>4. Complete analyzes of the articles and summarize the results reported by the authors related to customer loyalty in green marketing.</p><p>5. Parsing and further elaboration of the findings in the context of the section.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> shows “The PRISMA Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA)” used by this study to conduct a systematic literature review. This study utilized the keywords “green marketing”, “sustainable marketing”, “Eco Marketing”, and “customer loyalty” in the title, abstract, and keywords of the author to acquire relevant data from Scopus database. The search query option used in data mining was as follows (TITLE-ABS-KEY (“green marketing” AND “customer loyalty”) OR TITLE-ABS-KEY (“sustainable marketing” AND “customer loyalty”) OR TITLE-ABS-KEY (“Eco Marketing” AND “customer loyalty”) AND (LIMIT-TO (Year, “2013-2023”)) AND (LIMIT-TO (Document Type, “Article”)) AND (LIMIT-TO (Source Type, “Journal”) AND LIMIT-TO (Language, “English”). We discovered 33 articles in this stage.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Study selection</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> describes the inclusion criteria and exclusion criteria used in selecting articles in the Scopus database.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>PRISMA</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_YmC314iNvCBtrQXU.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Inclusion criteria and exclusion criteria</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Inclusion Criteria</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>-Research work is related to environmentally friendly or sustainable marketing.</p><p>-Research discusses customer loyalty.</p><p>-Research papers are published between 2013 and 2023.</p><p>-The research papers are written in English.</p><p>-The research follows the appropriate structure of research according to the research method.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Exclusion Criteria</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>-Research work is not related to environmentally friendly or sustainable marketing.</p><p>-Research discusses not on customer loyalty.</p><p>-Research papers are not published between 2013 and 2023.</p><p>-The research papers are not written in English.</p><p>-The research does not follow the appropriate structure of research according to the research method.</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Result and discussion</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Publications per year</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> shows the development of publications about customer loyalty within the scope of sustainable marketing published in Scopus database from 2013-2023.</p><p>Based on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>, 2019 registered the highest number of publications (9 publications) on the researched topic. After 2019, the number of publications on customer loyalty within the scope of sustainable marketing on the Scopus database has continued to decline. There was an increase in publications in 2021, from 3 to 5, but after that, the number of publications decreased again. We suspect this to be due to the effect of the Covid-19 pandemic which has affected the research productivity in all fields of knowledge [20]. After the government announced the end of the pandemic period, it is expected that there will be an increase in future publications about green marketing in Indonesia.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Annual publications</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_GvmLk42Iho7k2mRK.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Publications by journal</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> shows the distribution of publications on customer loyalty within the scope of sustainable marketing during the analyzed period.</p><p>Sustainability, published by the Multidisciplinary Digital Publishing Institute (Switzerland), is the journal with the highest number of publications on related topics, with a total of three publications. After that, two journals that have two publications each with related topics are the International Journal of Sustainable Development and World Ecology from Taylor and Francis Ltd (United Kingdom) and Quality - Access To Success from Societatea Romana Pentru Asigurarea Calitatii (Romania). The data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> can serve as a valuable journal reference for researchers who are interested in publishing articles within the scope of green marketing, sustainability marketing, or environmental studies.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Documents by Journal</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Journal</p></td><td><p>TP</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Sustainability</italic></p></td><td><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>International Journal of Sustainable Development And World Ecology</italic></p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Quality Access to Success</italic></p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Academy Of Strategic Management Journal</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Banks and Bank Systems</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Business Strategy and the Environment</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Communication Today</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Corporate Social Responsibility and Environmental Management</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Energies</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Frontiers in Environmental Science</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Horttechnology</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>International Journal of Contemporary Hospitality Management</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>International Journal of Emerging Markets</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Journal of Asian Finance Economics and Business</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Journal of Business Ethics</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Journal of Consumer Behaviour</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Journal of Consumer Marketing</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Journal of Global Responsibility</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Journal of Hospitality And Tourism Insights</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Journal of Hospitality Marketing And Management</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Journal of Interactive Marketing</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Journal of Services Marketing</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Kasetsart Journal of Social Sciences</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Pertanika Journal of Social Science And Humanities</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Plos One</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Social Responsibility Journal</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Society and Business Review</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Sustainable Development</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><italic>Tourism Analysis</italic></p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Publications by author and country/territory</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> shows the top five authors who published the most articles in the Scopus database on the topic of customer loyalty within the scope of sustainable marketing spanning the period 2013 - 2023.</p><p>Based on the information in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>, we can analyze that the productive authors in the field of “customer loyalty” papers in the area of “Green Marketing” are Athanasios Krystallis, Norazah Mohd Suki, Lalinthorn Marakanon, Erifili Papista, and Vinai Panjakajornsak, each with 2 publications. Other authors have produced 1 publication each.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref> provides an explanation of publications related to customer loyalty within the scope of green marketing. These publications are categorized based on countries/territories that have made a significant contribution.</p><p>At the top of the list is United States with a total of 6 publications, followed by India, Malaysia, Spain, and Taiwan with 3 publications. Based on this data, it is evident that countries from the Asian continent have the highest number of published articles on related topics. Therefore, exploring research in Asian countries would be intriguing for future investigations [21].</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Documents by author</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Author - Country</p></td><td><p>TP</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Athanasios Krystallis - Greece</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Norazah Mohd Suki - Malaysia</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Lalinthorn Marakanon - Thailand</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Erifili Papista - Greece</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Vinai Panjakajornsak - Thailand</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_4">
              <label>Table 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Documents by country/territory</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Country/Territory</p></td><td><p>TP</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>United States</p></td><td><p>6</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>India, Malaysia, Spain, Taiwan</p></td><td><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Australia, Denmark, Greece, South Korea, Thailand</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>China, Ghana, Indonesia, Italy, Macao, Netherlands, Pakistan, Poland, Slovakia, Turkey, Vietnam</p></td><td><p>1</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_5">
              <label>Table 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Documents by affiliations</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Affiliation</p></td><td><p>TP</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Universiti Malaysia Sabah, Malaysia</p></td><td><p>4</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Athens University of Economics and Business, Greece</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Aarhus Universitet, Denmark</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.4. Publication by affiliations</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref> displays the affiliates who publish the highest number of articles on related topics.</p><p>The top three affiliates consist of three countries: Malaysia, Greece, and Denmark. Universiti Malaysia Sabah from Malaysia achieved the highest number of publications with 4. Following closely are Athens University of Economics and Business from Greece, and Aarhus Universitet from Denmark, each with 2 publications. There are also other affiliations with 1 publication.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Publications by subject areas</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_PURraZoDcXk-JlE4.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.5. Publications by subject areas</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> shows a pie chart that reflects research publications by subject areas.</p><p>The chart indicates that the majority (35%) of studies are published in the field of business, management, and accounting. This is followed by the domain of social sciences (23%) and environmental science (13%). Other domains include energy (8%); economics, econometrics, and finance (7%); arts and humanities (3%); computer science (3%); engineering (3%); and other (5%). Based on this data, we can conclude that research discussing “customer loyalty” in the context of “green marketing” can be found in several domains.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.6. Highly cited articles</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref> shows the five most cited from 33 articles based on the Scopus database.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_6">
              <label>Table 6</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Top five most cited articles</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Title</p></td><td><p>Authors</p></td><td><p>Year</p></td><td><p>Journal</p></td><td><p>TC</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Customer Loyalty: Exploring its Antecedents from a Green Marketing Perspective</p></td><td><p>Martinez, P.</p></td><td><p>2015</p></td><td><p>International Journal of Contemporary Hospitality Management</p></td><td><p>146</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Towards Green Loyalty: Driving from Green Perceived Value, Green Satisfaction, and Green Trust</p></td><td><p>Chen, Y.S.</p></td><td><p>2013</p></td><td><p>Sustainable Development</p></td><td><p>130</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Assessing the Effects of Perceived Value and Satisfaction on Customer Loyalty: A ‘Green’ Perspective</p></td><td><p>Hur, et al.</p></td><td><p>2013</p></td><td><p>Corporate Social Responsibility and Environmental Management</p></td><td><p>118</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Investigating the Types of Value and Cost of Green Brands: Proposition of a Conceptual Framework</p></td><td><p>Papista, E. &amp;amp;amp; Krystallis, A.</p></td><td><p>2013</p></td><td><p>Journal of Business Ethics</p></td><td><p>91</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Green Marketing Orientation: Achieving Sustainable Development in Green Hotel Management</p></td><td><p>Chung, K.C.</p></td><td><p>2020</p></td><td><p>Journal of Hospitality Marketing &amp;amp;amp; Management</p></td><td><p>87</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>The article titled “Customer Loyalty: Exploring Its Antecedents from a Green Marketing Perspective” published by the International Journal of Contemporary Hospitality Management was the most cited article, with 146 citations. Patricia Martinez from University of Cantabria is the author of the article. The main purpose of the study was to examine the relationship of three variables namely, green image, green trust, green satisfaction to green loyalty. The samples taken were hotel customers in Spain. The results showed that green image, green trust, and green satisfaction, have a significant influence on green loyalty. Hoteliers, in particular, must be proactive in promoting an environmentally friendly image. This can be achieved through active participation in ecological events and forums, sponsorship of environmental programs, and an increased presence on social media [22]. These managerial implications can help hoteliers establish and maintain a strong eco-friendly reputation.Furthermore, hotels can enhance their positive image by focusing on environmental aspects and taking tangible actions that consumers can trust.Also, companies, especially those in the hospitality industry, need to enhance employee and customer performance. This includes providing information about the environment to increase environmental trust and satisfaction [22].</p><p>The article authored by Chen, Y-S is the second most cited, with 130 citations. This is followed by the article by Hur et al, with 118 citations; Papista &amp;amp; Krystallis, with 91 citations, and Chung, K.C., with 87 citations.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.7. Distribution phrases</title>
          
          <p>Keyword analysis in this study by looking at the distribution phrases (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_7">Table 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>).</p><p>Distribution phrases in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_7">Table 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref> show phrases that are often used by the authors in their articles.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Distribution phrases</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/9/img_-zSYi8OrDBVmX9-6.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_7">
              <label>Table 7</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Distribution phrases</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><p>Freq</p></td><td><p>Cases (No.)</p></td><td><p>Cases (%)</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Green Marketing</p></td><td><p>718</p></td><td><p>28</p></td><td><p>84.85</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Customer Loyalty</p></td><td><p>585</p></td><td><p>31</p></td><td><p>93.94</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Customer Satisfaction</p></td><td><p>404</p></td><td><p>27</p></td><td><p>81.82</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Green Products</p></td><td><p>387</p></td><td><p>25</p></td><td><p>75.76</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Green Image</p></td><td><p>272</p></td><td><p>20</p></td><td><p>60.61</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Green Brand</p></td><td><p>257</p></td><td><p>21</p></td><td><p>63.64</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Green Trust</p></td><td><p>239</p></td><td><p>23</p></td><td><p>69.70</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Brand Equity</p></td><td><p>235</p></td><td><p>19</p></td><td><p>57.58</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Social Responsibility</p></td><td><p>219</p></td><td><p>26</p></td><td><p>78.79</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Eco Friendly</p></td><td><p>214</p></td><td><p>18</p></td><td><p>54.55</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Social Media</p></td><td><p>200</p></td><td><p>15</p></td><td><p>45.45</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>A total of 33 documents were studied to generate distribution phrases. These phrases are limited in frequency to 200. The top five phrases that frequently appeared were green marketing, customer loyalty, customer satisfaction, green products, and green image. Additionally, other phrases that often appeared included Green Brand, Green Trust, Brand Equity, Social Responsibility, Eco Friendly, and Social Media.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.8. Documents by methods and variables</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_8">Table 8</xref> shows the methods and variables used by 33 research articles.</p><p>Based on this data, we can conclude that Structural Equation Modelling (SEM) is the most commonly used method in the study, with 28 documents. Researchers can use structural equation modeling (SEM) to specify confirmatory factor analysis models, regression models, and complex path models [23]. SEM is a powerful technique that allows for the combination of complex path models with latent variables, also known as factors. The growing popularity of SEM among academic researchers and social science practitioners is driven by the need for effective methods to understand the structure and interaction of latent phenomena [24]. The research practice in management research is also dominantly based on Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) [25]. Complex models can be discussed simply through this technique [26].</p><p>Apart from the Customer loyalty variable, customer satisfaction is a variable that is often used in these 33 documents. Customer satisfaction is a condition reached whenever product performance meets or exceeds customer expectations [10].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.9. Research outcomes</title>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_9">Table 9</xref> explains the purposes and findings resulting from the five most cited articles listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref>.</p><p>The five articles listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_9">Table 9</xref> consist of four research articles and one conceptual article. The article titled “Towards Green Loyalty: Driving from Green Perceived Value, Green Satisfaction, And Green Trust”, examines three antecedents of green loyalty. In this research it was found that green perceived value, green satisfaction, and green trust have a significant effect in the creation of green loyalty [11].</p><p>The article with the title “Assessing the Effects of Perceived Value and Satisfaction on Customer loyalty: A ‘Green’ Perspective” examined the relationship of customer satisfaction to price consciousness. There is still little research that discusses the relationship between these two variables. This article concludes by saying that as consumers become more satisfied with a product, their price-consciousness tends to decrease [27]. Other findings state that customer satisfaction has an effect on increasing consumer loyalty.</p><p>The article with the title “Green Marketing Orientation: Archieving Sustainable Development in Green Hotel Management” discusses the benefits of green hotel management in protecting the earth and establishes a green marketing-oriented model. The study found that stakeholders and executive corporate social responsibility hotels could indirectly increase consumer loyalty to the image of the hotel through green marketing [7].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.10. Study limitation</title>
          
          <p>This article has limitations that should be acknowledged as part of its systematic review. Firstly, the study only utilized data from the Scopus database, which is just one database. Additionally, the study imposed restrictions on language, year, and selected only a few sources from journals. the data in this study was also only sourced from a few domains as listed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>. It is important to note that incorporating data from other databases, such as WOS or Google Scholar, would yield different results and conclusions. It is recommended that future studies should include additional databases so as to broaden the scope of their research and ensure wider applicability of the obtained results.Secondly, this study solely focuses on discussing Customer loyalty within the realm of green marketing or sustainable marketing. To enhance its comprehensiveness, future authors may consider incorporating additional variables.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_8">
              <label>Table 8</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Documents by methods and variables</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Author</p></td><td><p>Method</p></td><td><p>Variables</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Chen, Y.S.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Green Perceived Value, Green Trust, Green Satisfaction, Green Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Papista, E. &amp;amp;amp;</p><p>Krystallis, A.</p></td><td><p>Conceptual</p></td><td><p>Types of Value, Types of Cost, Psychographic Moderators, Customer Value of Green Brand, Relationship Quality, Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Hur et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Hedonic Value, Social Value, Functional Value, Customer Satisfaction, Customer Loyalty, Price Consciousness</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Chahal et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Green Marketing, Image, Customer Satisfaction, Employee Retention, Employee Satisfaction</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Martínez, P.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Green Image, Green Trust, Green Satisfaction, Green Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Rosenbaum, M.S. &amp;amp;amp; Wong, A.I.</p></td><td><p>Conceptual</p></td><td><p>Value, Brand, Relationship, Green, Marketing Program, Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Suki, N.M.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Environmental Friendliness of Product, Environmental Friendliness of the Company, Customer Environmental Satisfaction, Customer Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Chaudary et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Green Image, Perceived fit between Corporate Culture and CSR Activities, Perceived CSR Capability, Customer Perception of CSR Activities, Perceived Corporate Performance, Customer Loyalty, Customer Attachment, Repurchse Intention</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Marakanon, L. &amp;amp;amp; Panjakajornsak, V.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Perceived Quality, Perceived Value, Perceived Risk, Customer Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Marakanon, L. &amp;amp;amp; Panjakajornsak, V.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Perceived Quality, Customer Trust, Perceived Risk, Customer Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Suki, N.M.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Product Quality, Corporate Image, Store Image, Product Price, Customer Satisfaction, Customer Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Barton, S.S. &amp;amp;amp; Behe, B.K. </p></td><td><p>Not Mentioned</p></td><td><p>Social Media (Promotion, Advertising), Customer Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Lee, T.C. &amp;amp;amp; Ping Peng, M.Y.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Experiential Value, Satisfaction, Trust, Comitment, Behavioral Loyalty, Attitudinal Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Papista et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Value, Purchase Costs, Switching Costs, Customer Value, Relationship Quality, Brand Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Sukhu, A. &amp;amp;amp; Scharff, R.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Attitude, Trust, Subjective Norm’s, CSR beliefs, Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Mishra, A. &amp;amp;amp; Gupta, A.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Ambience, Design, Social, Green Service Encounters, Geen Experiential Value, Economic Value, Social Value, Hedonic Value, Altuistic Value, Green Brand Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Baktash, L. &amp;amp;amp; Talib, M.A.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Product Quality, Trust, Age, Education Level, Employment Status, Customer Attitude, Customer Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Platania et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Brand Love, Brand Attachment, Brand Commitment, Brand Trust, Self Expressive Brand, Brand Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Imaningsih et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Egoistic Value, Altuistic Value, Biospheric Value, Green Functional Benefir, Green Monetary Cost, Green Satisfaction, Green Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Lu, Q.S.&amp;amp;amp; Miller, R.</p></td><td><p>Not Mentioned</p></td><td><p>Social Media, Loyalty Program Reward, Customer Relation Management (CRM)</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Ho et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Customer Value, Green Marketing, Green Brand Loyalty, Brand Equtiy, Self Expressive Benefit, Brand Social Responsibility, Customer Behavioral Intentions</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Enwo et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Green Banking, Green Image, Bank Trust, Bank Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Amaoko et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Ethics, CSR, Green Marketing, Brand Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Issock et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Consumptions Value, Green Customer Satisfaction, Green Customer Trust, Green Customer Trust, Green Customer Loyalty, Positive Word-Of-Mouth</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Chung, K.C.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Corporate Social Responsibility, Stakeholders, Strategic Green Marketing Orientation, Tactical Green Marketing Orientation, Internal Green Marketing Orientation, Green Image, Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Gelderman et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Green Product Quality, Green Produc Price, Green Corporate Image, Salesperson’s Green Expertise, Green Customer Satisfaction, Green Customer Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Sarmiento-Guede et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Green Image, Trust, Satisfaction, Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Dudek et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Perceived Price Transparancy, Loyalty Program, Company Image, Green Image, Intention to Chage</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Moise, M.S. &amp;amp;amp; Saura, I.G.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Green Practices, Functional Value, Satisfaction, WOM, Revisit Intention</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Kim, J. &amp;amp;amp; Kang, E.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Environmental Awareness, Interest of Artworks, Interior Design, Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Pawar, D.S. &amp;amp;amp; Munuswamy, J.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Green Banking Practices, Green Image, Green Trust, Green Loyalty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Tran et al.</p></td><td><p>SEM</p></td><td><p>Customer Fulfillment, Price Value Image, Environmental Concerns for Fashion Production, Perceived Behavioral Control, Customer Satisfaction, Customer Loyalty, Purchase Intention to Eco-Friendly Fashion</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Marko, M. &amp;amp;amp; Kusa, A.</p></td><td><p>Qualitative</p></td><td><p>Marketing Communication, Customer Trust, Customer Loyalty</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_9">
              <label>Table 9</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Research Outcomes from 5 most cited articles</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Title</p></td><td><p>Purposes</p></td><td><p>Findings</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Customer loyalty: Exploring Its Antecedents from a Green Marketing Perspective</p></td><td><p>Analyze three antecedents of green loyalty: green trust, green satisfaction, and green image; and to examine the relationship between these variables.</p></td><td><p>Green image has positive direct effects on green trust, green satisfaction and green loyalty. At the same time, they reveal that both green trust and green satisfaction have positive effects on green loyalty. Green trust has a positive influence on green satisfaction.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Towards Green Loyalty: Driving from Green Perceived Value, Green Satisfaction, and Green Trust</p></td><td><p>Examine three variables that affect green loyalty: green perceived value, green satisfaction, green trust.</p></td><td><p>Green perceived value has a significant direct influence on green satisfaction, green trust, and green loyalty. Green satisfaction and green trust have a significant direct influence on green loyalty.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Assessing the Effects of Perceived Value and Satisfaction on Customer loyalty: A ‘Green’ Perspective</p></td><td><p>Analyze how customer satisfaction affects Customer loyalty and price consciousness. testing three antecedents of customer satisfaction: hedonic value, social value, functional value.</p></td><td><p>The results indicate that perceived social, emotional, and functional values have a significant positive effect on customer satisfaction with respect to green innovation. Customer satisfaction leads to Customer loyalty, while lowering price consciousness.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Investigating the Types of Value and Cost of Green Brands: Proposition of a Conceptual Framework</p></td><td><p>Conceptual Article</p></td><td><p>Conceptual Article</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Green Marketing Orientation: Achieving Sustainable Development in Green Hotel Management</p></td><td><p>Analyze green marketing orientation towards green image and loyalty. And to examine corporate social responsibility and stakeholders towards green marketing orientation.</p></td><td><p>Stakeholders and executive corporate social responsibility hotels could indirectly increase consumer loyalty to the image of the hotel through green marketing.</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Conclusion</title>
      <p>This study analyzed research developments and trends on the topic of Customer loyalty within the scope of green marketing using the Scopus database. Based on the results of the study, we can conclude:</p><p>i. Publications on related themes reached the highest number in 2019, after which the number of publications with related themes decreased. This is suspected to be due to the impact of the Covid-19 pandemic. Sustainability, International Journal of Sustainable Development and World Ecology, and Quality Access to Success are the most published journals on related topics. Athanasios Krystallis, Norazah Mohd Suki, Lalinthorn Marakanon, Erifili Papista, and Vinai Panjakajornsak are the authors who published the most articles on such topics. The United States is the most productive country when it comes to producing articles on related topics. Universiti Malaysia Sabah is the affiliation that produces the most articles with related themes. Business, Management, and Accounting is the domain that is most related to such topics.</p><p>ii. Green marketing, customer loyalty, customer satisfaction, green products, and green image are the top five phrases that often appear, with a frequency limit of 200.</p><p>iii. Structural Equation Modelling (SEM) is the most widely used research method. Customer satisfaction is the most analyzed variable with regards to relationship to Customer loyalty.</p><p>These findings may help future researchers determine the appropriate variables and methods in related themes.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>