<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAFAS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Accounting, Finance and Auditing Studies</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Account. Fin. Audit. Stud.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JAFAS</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2149-0996</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">3005-9844</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-IjgGX5CKEyzO-YFTQVagWATUQ5mBLVox</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jafas110105</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>AI-Driven and Data-Intensive Auditing: Enhancing Sustainability and Intelligent Assurance</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6801-6530</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Senturk</surname>
            <given-names>Ozden</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>ozden.senturk@ogr.iu.edu.tr</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Economics, Institute of Social Sciences, Istanbul University, 34000 Istanbul, Turkey</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>03</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>61</fpage>
      <lpage>71</lpage>
      <page-range>61-71</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>02</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>The integration of artificial intelligence (AI) and big data analytics has revolutionized audit practices, offering unprecedented advancements in efficiency, transparency, and sustainability. This study critically examines the role of AI-powered auditing in risk detection, anomaly identification, and the development of sustainable audit frameworks. Through an extensive literature review, the adoption of machine learning (ML), natural language processing (NLP), and continuous auditing methodologies is explored, highlighting their impact on audit quality and assurance. It is demonstrated that AI-driven auditing significantly enhances error detection and risk assessment while expediting audit procedures and improving overall accuracy. However, critical challenges remain, including data security risks, algorithmic opacity, and ethical concerns related to decision-making autonomy. Addressing these issues necessitates the establishment of robust governance mechanisms, increased algorithmic transparency, and the implementation of continuous professional training programs to ensure auditors' proficiency in AI-based systems. Furthermore, AI-driven automation enables real-time monitoring and predictive analytics, fostering a proactive approach to auditing that mitigates financial and operational risks. By leveraging AI and data-driven methodologies, audit frameworks can be rendered more adaptive, resilient, and aligned with the evolving digital economy. These findings underscore the necessity for organizations to integrate AI-driven auditing as a strategic imperative while ensuring regulatory compliance and ethical oversight.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Artificial intelligence (AI)</kwd>
        <kwd>Data-driven auditing</kwd>
        <kwd>Public sector assurance</kwd>
        <kwd>Big data analytics</kwd>
        <kwd>Algorithmic transparency</kwd>
        <kwd>Ethical governance</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="1"/>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <ref-count count="20"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Today, auditing, like many other fields, is undergoing significant changes due to rapidly advancing technology. In particular, artificial intelligence (AI) and big data analytics enable new approaches to be applied in auditing, strengthening transparency and accountability while ensuring that the audit process is carried out more efficiently, effectively, and with greater precision. AI refers to the development of systems that mimic human intelligence to solve complex problems. The foundations of this technology were laid in the 1950s, and since then, AI has been widely used in various fields. Subfields such as machine learning (ML) and deep learning (DL) further support its advancement. The successful implementation of AI in domains such as finance, healthcare, education, and defense has made its integration into auditing inevitable.</p><p>Traditional audit methods primarily rely on manual reviews and sample-based analysis. However, with the rise of data-driven auditing and AI-powered systems, the audit process has undergone a transformation. AI enables the analysis of large datasets, allowing for more comprehensive and detailed assessments. When combined with big data analytics, AI and ML algorithms can detect anomalies, irregularities, and risks with greater accuracy. These technologies not only automate and accelerate audit processes but also contribute to the development of sustainable auditing models. Data-driven audits validate large datasets, ensuring a more thorough and reliable evaluation of audit processes. By enhancing usability and accuracy, AI-supported audits improve overall efficiency. Moreover, AI algorithms continuously learn and evolve, offering not only short-term solutions but also proactive risk mitigation strategies for future challenges.</p><p>This study examines the impact of AI on sustainability in the audit process from a conceptual perspective. The concept of “Smart Auditing” is explored in terms of how AI-powered audit systems and big data analytics contribute to long-term sustainability, strategic vision, and accountability. The study first analyzes the role of AI in auditing, then discusses its benefits in promoting sustainability, and finally presents strategic recommendations for building a sustainable AI-supported auditing system. These strategies focus on critical elements such as data security, ensuring a more resilient and future-ready audit framework. The history of AI in auditing can be traced back to the early developments in expert systems and automated decision-making tools in the 1980s and 1990s. Initially, AI applications in auditing were limited to rule-based systems that supported financial statement analysis. However, with the rise of ML and big data analytics in the 2000s, AI-driven audit tools gained traction, offering more advanced risk assessment and anomaly detection capabilities. The integration of AI into auditing has accelerated in recent years due to improvements in computing power, cloud storage, and algorithmic sophistication. AI now enables auditors to process vast amounts of data, enhance fraud detection, and improve audit accuracy, marking a fundamental shift from traditional, manual auditing methods.</p><p>Given the rapid advancements in AI, it is essential to evaluate how these technologies have been integrated into auditing practices. The following section provides a comprehensive literature review, categorizing AI applications in auditing and analyzing existing research findings. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Research methodology</title>
      <p>This methodology was selected as it systematically compiles and evaluates prior studies on the research topic, facilitating a comprehensive review of existing knowledge in the field. By adopting this approach, gaps and contentious issues within the literature can be identified, thereby enhancing and refining the understanding of the subject. Moreover, this method obviates the necessity for primary data collection, optimizing time and resources by leveraging the analysis of established findings. Furthermore, it enables a comparative examination of trends and key results across a broad spectrum of literature, ensuring a well-substantiated evaluation grounded in the current body of knowledge. In this study, a systematic literature review methodology was employed to analyze the integration of AI and data-driven auditing approaches. The literature selection process was based on predefined inclusion and exclusion criteria. Only peer-reviewed articles published after 2015 were considered to ensure the relevance of the findings. The primary databases used for data collection included Google Scholar, Web of Science, and Scopus. These databases were chosen due to their extensive academic coverage and reliability in auditing research. The selection process focused on studies discussing AI applications in auditing, sustainability strategies, and smart auditing frameworks. The analysis involved categorizing findings based on AI-driven audit applications, risk management strategies, and ethical considerations in AI auditing. This structured approach enhances the reproducibility and rigor of the research.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Literature and research findings</title>
      <p>AI refers to the capability of computer systems to think, learn, reason, and make decisions in a manner similar to humans. The primary goal of AI is to develop solutions to complex problems by mimicking human cognitive processes. The origins of AI trace back to the 1950s, when John McCarthy first introduced the term "AI" during the Dartmouth Conference in 1956. Today, AI is recognized as one of the most significant and rapidly evolving fields in computer science (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Russell &amp;amp; Norvig, 2020</xref>).</p><p>AI is primarily categorized into two fields: narrow AI and artificial general intelligence (AGI). Narrow AI systems are designed to perform specific tasks, such as facial recognition, language translation, or playing chess. These applications are task-specific and limited in scope. On the other hand, AGI aims to replicate all aspects of human intelligence, enabling systems to learn, reason, and solve problems at a human level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Gültekin, 2021</xref>).</p><p>AI advancements are supported by subfields such as ML and DL. ML involves the development of algorithms that enable computers to learn autonomously by analyzing data and building predictive models. DL, a subset of ML, incorporates artificial neural networks inspired by the structure and function of the human brain. DL algorithms excel in processing large datasets and achieving high accuracy, making them highly preferred in areas such as image recognition, natural language processing (NLP), and gaming (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">LeCun et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>The 1980s marked a significant era for AI development, characterized by the emergence of neural networks and ML techniques. Artificial neural networks, inspired by biological neural structures, have demonstrated success in fields like data analysis and pattern recognition. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Rumelhart et al. (1986)</xref> developed backpropagation algorithms, which became a cornerstone for training neural networks. During this period, advancements in data mining, NLP, and image processing gained prominence. A notable milestone was IBM's Deep Blue, which defeated world chess champion Gary Kasparov in 1997, showcasing the power of AI.</p><p>The widespread adoption of the internet during this time also facilitated access to large datasets, which enhanced the performance of ML algorithms. DL techniques achieved remarkable results in areas such as image and audio recognition and NLP. For example, AlexNet, a DL model, demonstrated the potential of DL by winning the ImageNet competition in 2012.</p><p>In 2014, Google acquired DeepMind, a leading AI company, to strengthen its influence in the sector. In 2019, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Devlin et al. (2019)</xref> introduced Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT), a groundbreaking model based on transformer architecture, which has since become a core method in NLP. OpenAI launched the GPT-2 model with 1.5 billion parameters in 2019, followed by GPT-3 with 175 billion parameters in 2020. The introduction of DALL-E in 2021, capable of generating descriptive visual content, further underscored AI's transformative potential. OpenAI continued its advancements with GPT-3.5, GPT-4, and GPT-4.0 in 2023 and 2024. Despite these groundbreaking developments, several challenges accompany the adoption of AI. Issues such as data privacy, transparency, bias, and discrimination require careful attention. Moreover, the potential negative impacts of AI on the labor market, including social inequalities and disruptions, must be addressed to ensure ethical and sustainable implementation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Bostrom &amp;amp; Yudkowsky, 2018</xref>).</p><p>To provide a clearer understanding of AI applications in auditing, existing research can be categorized into the following key areas:</p><p>• AI in Risk Detection and Fraud Prevention: AI algorithms detect unusual transaction patterns and potential fraudulent activities by analyzing historical financial data.</p><p>• ML in Audit Decision Support: AI-driven audit analytics help in risk scoring, anomaly detection, and predictive modeling.</p><p>• NLP for Compliance Auditing: NLP tools automate the analysis of financial reports, contracts, and regulatory documents.</p><p>• Big Data Analytics for Continuous Auditing: AI-powered systems enable real-time audit monitoring, reducing reliance on periodic audits.</p><p>• Sustainability in AI Auditing: Research explores how AI contributes to sustainable audit practices by minimizing resource consumption and improving efficiency.</p><p>While the literature review highlights theoretical advancements, practical implementation remains a critical factor. The next section discusses smart auditing applications and presents real-world case studies demonstrating AI’s role in modern auditing.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. The concept of general audit and sustainability</title>
          
          <p>Audit refers to the systematic process of examining and evaluating whether an organization's activities, operations, or systems comply with predefined standards, regulations, laws, or objectives. The primary purpose of auditing is to verify the authenticity, reliability, efficiency, and legality of these activities, providing constructive feedback to improve processes. Audits must be conducted independently and objectively, ensuring that the auditor remains impartial and is not part of the organization or system being examined. This independence guarantees that audited entities operate in alignment with the principles of transparency and accountability, while also identifying areas for development to enhance organizational effectiveness. Auditing is typically performed by independent auditors or through internal audit functions. Historically, auditing emerged in the context of financial reporting and oversight. Financial audits, for example, ensure that an organization’s financial statements adhere to generally accepted accounting principles (GAAP). Such audits are often mandatory, particularly for publicly traded companies, and are conducted by independent audit firms. Financial audits provide assurance to investors and stakeholders by enhancing trust in the organization’s financial disclosures.</p><p>For example, in the public sector, audits are a systematic evaluation process designed to ensure that government agencies and public organizations comply with established rules, regulations, and standards. Public audits emphasize accountability and transparency, verifying that public resources are utilized effectively, efficiently, and economically. Modern auditing processes require auditors to continually improve their technological competencies and effectively implement advanced tools and systems. This is essential for creating a long-term, sustainable auditing framework. A proactive auditing approach, which includes early risk detection and management, strengthens the overall sustainability of the audit process. Moreover, environmental sustainability can also be integrated into auditing. By utilizing energy-efficient technologies and adopting digital systems, resource consumption can be minimized. These strategies not only increase the efficiency of audit processes but also align auditing methods with broader societal and environmental goals. To validate the effectiveness of the proposed sustainability strategies, real-world audit case studies and industry reports were examined. For instance, the Big Four accounting firms—Deloitte, PwC, EY, and KPMG—have implemented AI-driven auditing tools to improve efficiency and sustainability. Deloitte’s AI-powered audit analytics tool continuously monitors transactions to identify irregularities, reducing audit workload while enhancing accuracy. Similarly, PwC utilizes an AI-driven fraud detection system that minimizes financial misstatements. These examples demonstrate how AI enhances audit efficiency while aligning with sustainability goals. Future research should explore the impact of such implementations on resource consumption, regulatory compliance, and long-term sustainability metrics.</p><p>The sustainability of auditing processes depends heavily on technology adoption and adherence to ethical principles. Integrating innovative technologies such as AI, big data analytics, and automation can enhance the speed and accuracy of audits, thereby creating a more robust and sustainable auditing structure. These technologies enable more effective data analysis, anomaly detection, and process optimization, all of which contribute to an audit process that is both efficient and environmentally responsible. In conclusion, modern auditing not only ensures compliance and accountability but also plays a critical role in promoting sustainable practices within organizations. By embracing technological advancements and adhering to ethical standards, auditing can evolve into a more effective, sustainable, and impactful discipline for both organizations and society.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Data-driven audit processes</title>
          
          <p>The data-driven audit process focuses on analyzing large datasets and utilizing the insights derived from them to enhance the audit process. This approach enables a more comprehensive and detailed analysis compared to traditional inspection methods, thereby improving the efficiency of the auditing process. Data-driven audits offer significant advantages at every stage, particularly in risk assessment, error and anomaly detection, and reporting procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Alles et al., 2018</xref>). Data-driven auditing processes that use AI instantly detect risks and errors by analyzing continuous data. Thus, eliminating delays and errors that occur in manual inspections. And provide a more sustainable audit trail. Continuous auditing ensures the sustainability of the audit process as well as human resource time. The inspection process has been recorded and is more environmentally friendly. Big data analytics and AI technologies play a key role in data-driven auditing processes. Big data analytics manages the size, variety, and velocity of data sets used in the verification process and extracts meaningful information from this data. AI and ML algorithms analyze this data to find anomalies. Assess risk and create a decision support system. These technologies help auditors make faster and more accurate decisions. And improve the quality of the audit process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Kokina &amp;amp; Davenport, 2017</xref>). The capability of AI in identifying complex patterns and making strategic decisions has been notably demonstrated in DeepMind’s AlphaGo project, which utilized deep neural networks and advanced tree search techniques to outperform human players in the game of Go (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Silver et al., 2016</xref>). This pioneering success laid the groundwork for applying similar AI techniques in auditing to enhance risk detection and anomaly analysis.</p><p>The first step of a data-driven audit process is data collection and integration. In this step, auditors collect data from various sources. And put this information together in an analyzable format. This information includes financial reports. During the data integration process, the operational information compliance report and other associated documents guarantee the accuracy and completeness of the data and are suitable for analysis. This step is the basis of the verification process and affects the accuracy of the functional analysis in the following steps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Alles &amp;amp; Gray, 2016</xref>). The next step after data collection and integration is data analysis. Big data analytics and ML algorithms will now be used to analyze data and detect anomalies and risks. Data analysis helps investigators reveal information hidden in large data sets.</p><p>Risk assessment is a key step in any data-driven audit process. In this step, auditors assess the risks arising from the data analysis and determine the importance of these risks to the audit process. The risk assessment determines the areas on which the audit process should focus. And ensuring that audit resources are used most effectively. AI and ML algorithms help auditors in the risk assessment process and ensure that risk analysis is more accurate and reliable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Brown-Liburd et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>The final stage of data-based audit processes is audit reporting. At this stage, auditors prepare audit reports in line with data analysis and detected findings and present these reports to relevant stakeholders. Audit reports include the results of the audit process and the detected risks, anomalies, and irregularities. AI-based audit systems also assist auditors in the audit reporting process and ensure that reports are prepared faster and more accurately. In addition, these systems help stakeholders better understand audit results by making audit reports more visual and understandable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Appelbaum et al., 2017</xref>). Data-driven audit processes have many advantages in terms of sustainability. These processes use big data analytics and AI technologies to analyze all data sets. Thus ensuring that the use of resources is more efficient. Real-time monitoring and continuous monitoring can quickly detect anomalies, reduce costs, and support environmental sustainability. Automation also reduces human error. Increase process accuracy and save labor and time. Data-driven audits help achieve sustainability goals by simultaneously tracking compliance with environmental and social governance (ESG) criteria.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Smart control applications</title>
          
          <p>Smart audit applications involve the integration of advanced technologies, such as AI, big data analytics, ML, and NLP, into auditing processes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the core components of AI-powered smart auditing applications, emphasizing their role in enhancing sustainability. Big data analytics ensures comprehensive data evaluation, eliminating the need for manual sampling and reducing the risk of oversight. ML enables continuous learning and predictive risk detection, facilitating proactive audit interventions. NLP enhances document analysis, accelerating compliance reviews while reducing human error. Automation further strengthens sustainability by optimizing resource usage and minimizing redundant audit tasks. The integration of these elements enables real-time anomaly detection, contributing to a resilient and sustainable audit framework. Many organizations use AI to support risk assessment, anomaly detection, and automated reporting in audit engagements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">AuditBoard, 2024</xref>).</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Smart control applications</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/3/img_Z_VwVsNxtjK-EsaD.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>• Big Data Analytics</p><p>Big data analytics is at the core of smart auditing. It involves processing and analyzing large, complex datasets to extract meaningful insights. Unlike traditional sampling techniques, big data analytics allows auditors to evaluate entire datasets, resulting in more reliable and comprehensive audit findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Kokina &amp;amp; Davenport, 2017</xref>). By leveraging big data analytics, auditors can uncover patterns, detect anomalies, and gain deeper insights into organizational processes.</p><p>As AI transforms auditing, its role in sustainability must be examined. The next section explores sustainability strategies and discusses how AI enhances environmental and social responsibility in auditing.</p><p>• ML</p><p>ML is another crucial component of smart audit applications. ML algorithms learn from historical data and apply this knowledge to new datasets, enabling more accurate risk detection and anomaly prevention. This capability supports a proactive auditing approach, ensuring that potential issues are identified and addressed before they escalate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Sutton et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>• NLP</p><p>NLP is used to analyze and extract meaningful information from textual data, such as financial documents, contracts, and reports. NLP automates the review of these documents, enhancing the speed and accuracy of the audit process. By identifying inconsistencies and irregularities in text data, NLP contributes to more effective auditing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Brown-Liburd et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>• Continuous Auditing and Monitoring Systems</p><p>Traditional audits are often periodic, leaving room for errors or irregularities to go undetected between audit cycles. Continuous auditing and monitoring systems address this limitation by performing real-time data analysis. These systems ensure that audits are ongoing, allowing for the instant detection of errors or irregularities. This continuous approach enhances audit quality and efficiency, particularly in large and complex organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Vasarhelyi et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>• Automation and Strategic Focus</p><p>Smart audit applications automate routine tasks, such as data collection and preliminary analysis, using AI systems. This automation enables auditors to concentrate on more strategic, high-value activities, such as advanced evaluations and decision-making. As a result, audit processes become more efficient, and the risk of human error is significantly reduced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Alles &amp;amp; Gray, 2016</xref>). Smart audit systems also contribute to the sustainability of auditing processes. By reducing human intervention and relying on continuous learning algorithms, these systems enhance operational efficiency and minimize resource usage. Over time, smart audit systems can improve environmental sustainability by utilizing energy-efficient technologies and digital tools. For instance, ML algorithms can evolve continuously, improving their ability to detect future risks and creating a dynamic, adaptive audit framework. Smart audit applications represent a transformative shift in the auditing profession by integrating advanced technologies such as AI, big data analytics, ML, and NLP. These innovations enable auditors to perform more reliable, efficient, and proactive audits. Additionally, continuous auditing systems and automation reduce operational inefficiencies, enhance audit quality, and align the audit process with sustainability goals. By embracing these technologies, organizations can ensure transparency, accountability, and long-term value creation in their auditing practices. And ML and NLP tools are revolutionizing traditional audit procedures by improving accuracy and efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Fidyah et al., 2024</xref>).</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>AI use cases in auditing</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/3/img_IoS-hZ0TRY93BcEw.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref> illustrates the diverse applications of AI in auditing, demonstrating how AI-driven technologies enhance efficiency, accuracy, and reliability while supporting sustainability in audit processes. By leveraging AI, auditors can improve risk assessment, automate repetitive tasks, and ensure compliance with regulatory standards. AI-driven auditing not only increases operational effectiveness but also minimizes resource consumption, contributing to environmentally and economically sustainable practices. The key use cases include:</p><p>• Data Analytics: AI enables the processing and analysis of large datasets, identifying patterns and insights that improve decision-making. By reducing reliance on manual data review, AI contributes to sustainability by optimizing time and energy efficiency.</p><p>• Fraud Detection: AI-driven algorithms detect unusual financial activities and potential fraud by analyzing transactional data in real-time. Early fraud detection prevents financial losses, promoting long-term financial sustainability and trust in auditing practices.</p><p>• Predictive Analysis: ML models forecast risks and irregularities by leveraging historical data and trends. Proactive risk management reduces costly errors and helps organizations implement preventive measures, fostering sustainable financial stability.</p><p>• Planning &amp;amp; Resource Allocation: AI optimizes audit planning by assessing risk factors and allocating resources more effectively. More efficient resource distribution minimizes redundant work, lowering costs and environmental impact.</p><p>• Continuous Monitoring: Automated AI tools enable real-time tracking of financial transactions and compliance issues. Continuous auditing reduces the need for periodic large-scale audits, decreasing paper usage and enhancing sustainability through digital workflows.</p><p>• Risk Assessment: AI models assess financial risks and provide insights into potential vulnerabilities in organizational processes. Enhanced risk management ensures financial stability and promotes long-term organizational sustainability.</p><p>• Document Processing: NLP assists in analyzing and extracting critical information from financial reports and contracts. By automating document review and reducing paperwork, AI contributes to eco-friendly audit practices.</p><p>• Anomaly Detection: AI identifies deviations from standard financial patterns, flagging potential errors or fraudulent activities. Early detection and correction of errors enhance audit efficiency, reducing resource wastage.</p><p>• Journal Entry Testing: AI enhances audit accuracy by systematically verifying journal entries for inconsistencies. The automation of journal entry testing streamlines financial reporting processes and reduces human labor costs.</p><p>• Audit Reporting: AI-driven tools automate report generation, ensuring comprehensive and accurate financial reporting. Digital audit reports reduce the need for excessive paper documentation, aligning auditing processes with sustainability goals.</p><p>By integrating these AI applications, auditing processes become more proactive, risk-focused, and data-driven, ensuring greater transparency and efficiency in financial oversight. Additionally, AI-driven auditing promotes sustainability by minimizing waste, enhancing energy efficiency, and supporting digital transformation in audit practices. The adoption of AI in auditing is not just an advancement in technology but also a step toward more resilient and environmentally responsible financial governance.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Sustainability strategies for smart control applications</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Audit Focus Area</p></td><td><p>Description</p></td><td><p>Strategy</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Technological Innovation and Adaptation</p></td><td><p>Technologies such as AI, big data and automation are rapidly developing. The integration of these technologies into audit processes plays a critical role in ensuring the sustainability of audits. Audit processes must be flexible to adapt to changing technologies.</p></td><td><p>Flexible and modular audit processes will facilitate the integration of new technologies. Continuous monitoring of technological innovations and adaptation of these innovations to audit processes will be critical for long-term sustainability.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Data Management and Security</p></td><td><p>Data is the basis of intelligent auditing processes. Correct, secure and transparent processing of data is essential for sustainable auditing. Strengthening data management processes increases the quality of audits and ensures the reliability of processes.</p></td><td><p>Policies that comply with data security standards should be developed. The accuracy, confidentiality and integrity of data should be continuously monitored and the findings obtained from these data should be reported transparently.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Continuous Education and Competency Development</p></td><td><p>Smart auditing practices require auditors to interact with technology, so they need to participate in ongoing training programs to adapt to technologies such as AI and big data analytics.</p></td><td><p>Regular training and development programs should be created for audit personnel to adapt to AI, data analytics and automation systems. These trainings should teach how to use new technologies while also developing technology-based decision-making competencies in audit processes.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Environmental and Social Sustainability</p></td><td><p>Smart control applications should not only provide technological efficiency but also support environmental and social sustainability. Reducing energy consumption, efficient use of resources and minimizing environmental impacts are important for sustainable control.</p></td><td><p>Digitalization should be increased in audit processes, and environmentally friendly technologies should be used instead of traditional methods such as paper use. At the same time, audit processes should be shaped in accordance with social responsibility principles and social benefit should be taken into consideration.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Risk Management and Proactive Auditing</p></td><td><p>The sustainability of smart control systems depends not only on detecting risks but also on developing a proactive approach against them. AI-based risk analysis and anomaly detection must have the capacity to detect and manage future risks in advance.</p></td><td><p>AI should be integrated into risk assessment and management processes to identify potential risks in advance and shape audit processes accordingly. Proactive audit mechanisms should be developed and potential problems should be resolved before they grow with early warning systems.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Algorithmic Transparency and Ethical Decision Making</p></td><td><p>The use of AI systems in auditing processes should be based on the principles of algorithmic transparency and ethical responsibility. How algorithms make decisions, what data they are based on, and the results of these decisions should be transparent. Ethical principles should guarantee fair and impartial decision-making mechanisms in auditing processes.</p></td><td><p>In order to increase algorithmic transparency, the decision-making mechanisms of AI and automation systems used in audit processes should be made auditable and traceable. Algorithms that comply with ethical principles should be used and these systems should be constantly reviewed to prevent bias.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Continuous Monitoring and Improvement</p></td><td><p>Sustainability of smart auditing applications can be achieved by continuously monitoring and improving the processes. Data generated during auditing processes should be used to improve the processes and auditing systems should continuously improve themselves.</p></td><td><p>Audit processes should be supported by continuous monitoring and feedback mechanisms, and processes should be continuously improved with this data. Audit processes should be updated in line with technological developments and the changing needs of the organization.</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> provides a detailed summary of strategies aimed at ensuring the sustainability of smart auditing applications, addressing various dimensions such as technological adaptation, ethical considerations, environmental impact, and human resource development. These strategies emphasize the importance of integrating advanced tools and systems to maintain the efficiency, reliability, and relevance of auditing processes in the face of rapid technological advancements. Key components like data security and algorithmic transparency not only safeguard sensitive information but also foster trust by providing clarity regarding how decisions and evaluations are made within the auditing framework. Continuous monitoring further supports sustainability by enabling real-time analysis and proactive detection of anomalies, ensuring that auditing remains dynamic and responsive to emerging risks. In addition to these technical and ethical elements, the sustainability of smart auditing also depends on investing in human capital. Providing auditors with training and development opportunities equips them with the skills needed to adapt to innovative technologies and methodologies, thereby strengthening the human resource dimension of auditing. Environmental and social sustainability is equally emphasized, with strategies focusing on digitalization and the adoption of energy-efficient technologies to optimize resource utilization and minimize environmental impact. These measures not only reduce costs but also align auditing processes with broader organizational goals related to environmental and social responsibility.</p><p>By implementing these strategies, organizations can achieve a more comprehensive and future-oriented approach to auditing. The integration of these elements enables proactive risk management, improves resource efficiency, and facilitates continuous improvement in auditing processes. Collectively, these strategies ensure that smart auditing applications are not only effective and efficient but also aligned with the principles of long-term sustainability, benefiting both organizations and society at large.</p><p>Despite the advantages of AI-driven auditing, several practical challenges hinder its widespread adoption. Organizational resistance is a major barrier, as auditors may be reluctant to embrace AI technologies due to fears of job displacement or lack of technical expertise. Additionally, legacy information technology (IT) systems in many institutions pose integration challenges, making it difficult to implement AI-based auditing solutions. To overcome these barriers, organizations should adopt a phased AI transition strategy, starting with pilot implementations and gradually scaling AI capabilities. Comprehensive training programs should be introduced to equip auditors with the necessary AI and data analytics skills. Furthermore, regulatory bodies should establish standardized AI audit guidelines to facilitate seamless adoption and compliance. AI technologies such as ML and NLP tools are revolutionizing traditional audit procedures by improving accuracy and efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Leocádio et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p>While AI-driven auditing systems provide numerous advantages, their implementation is not without challenges. The next section discusses key practical barriers that hinder the widespread adoption of AI in auditing and suggests strategies to overcome them.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.4. Practical barriers to ai adoption in auditing</title>
          
          <p>Despite the significant advantages AI brings to auditing, its adoption is not without challenges. Several practical barriers hinder the seamless integration of AI into audit processes, affecting its feasibility and implementation. Automation supported by AI increases compliance, reduces human error, and speeds up the audit process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">HighRadius, 2024</xref>).</p><p>Organizational Resistance. One of the primary challenges in AI adoption is resistance from auditors and audit firms. Many professionals fear that AI may replace human auditors, leading to job losses. Additionally, there is skepticism about AI’s reliability and accuracy, as traditional auditors are accustomed to manual or sample-based approaches. Overcoming this resistance requires targeted training programs, change management strategies, and demonstrating AI’s role as an enhancement rather than a replacement for auditors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Kokina &amp;amp; Davenport, 2017</xref>).</p><p>Legacy Systems and Infrastructure Limitations. Many organizations, especially in the public sector and traditional audit firms, rely on outdated IT infrastructure that is incompatible with AI-driven audit tools. Legacy systems often lack the data integration capabilities needed for AI to function effectively. Transitioning from conventional IT systems to AI-powered audit platforms requires significant investment in technology upgrades, cloud-based storage solutions, and system interoperability improvements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Alles, 2015</xref>).</p><p>Data Quality and Accessibility. AI-driven auditing depends heavily on high-quality, structured, and standardized data. However, in many organizations, audit data is fragmented across different systems, making it difficult for AI models to analyze information effectively. Poor data governance, inconsistent reporting standards, and lack of real-time access to audit records hinder AI adoption. Organizations must implement strong data management frameworks and adopt standardized data formats to ensure AI can function optimally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Appelbaum et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Regulatory and Compliance Challenges. AI’s use in auditing raises concerns about compliance with regulatory standards and legal frameworks. Many jurisdictions lack clear guidelines on AI’s role in auditing, making it difficult for firms to integrate AI without facing potential legal risks. Regulatory bodies need to establish AI governance policies to provide clear guidance on how AI-driven audits can comply with industry standards and ethical requirements.</p><p>Algorithmic Transparency and Trust Issues. The "black box" nature of AI algorithms poses a challenge in auditing, where transparency and accountability are critical. If auditors and stakeholders cannot understand how AI reaches its conclusions, trust in AI-driven auditing systems may be undermined. To address this, organizations should adopt explainable AI (XAI) frameworks that provide clear insights into AI decision-making processes, ensuring that audit outcomes remain transparent and accountable.</p><p>Cost and Investment Considerations. The initial costs associated with AI implementation, including acquiring AI-driven audit software, upgrading IT infrastructure, and training personnel, can be a significant barrier, particularly for small and medium-sized audit firms. While AI adoption leads to long-term efficiency gains, organizations may hesitate to make large upfront investments without clear short-term financial returns.</p><p>To successfully overcome these barriers, organizations should take a phased approach to AI adoption, starting with pilot projects, gradually expanding AI applications, and investing in training programs to upskill auditors. Furthermore, collaboration between regulatory bodies, audit firms, and AI developers is essential to establish standardized frameworks that facilitate AI integration in a compliant, transparent, and sustainable manner.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>4. Conclusions</title>
      <p>The rapid advancement of technology has led to major changes in the inspection process. As in many other fields, AI and big data analytics are among the leaders of this change. This allows the inspection process to be carried out more efficiently and accurately. AI refers to the development of systems that can solve complex problems by imitating human intelligence. Data-driven auditing focuses on analyzing large datasets and leveraging the insights gained to enhance the auditing process. Compared to traditional inspection methods, this approach enables a more comprehensive and detailed analysis, improving the overall effectiveness of audits.</p><p>This study aimed to explore the integration of advanced technologies, such as AI and big data analytics, into auditing processes, with a particular focus on their role in promoting sustainability, transparency, and efficiency. Through a comprehensive review of literature and conceptual analysis, the research examined the transformative impact of smart auditing applications on modern auditing practices. The primary objective of the study was to identify how these technologies enhance the audit process by addressing key challenges such as accuracy, reliability, and timeliness, while simultaneously fostering long-term sustainability in terms of both environmental and social considerations. By analyzing existing frameworks and strategies, the study investigated how AI-powered auditing systems, data-driven methodologies, and automation contribute to improving the effectiveness and efficiency of audit operations.</p><p>The integration of AI, ML, and big data analytics enables real-time monitoring, anomaly detection, and proactive risk management, transforming traditional audit practices. These technologies enhance the speed, accuracy, and comprehensiveness of audits, providing more reliable insights for decision-making. Smart auditing applications contribute significantly to sustainability by reducing resource consumption and promoting environmentally friendly practices, such as digitalization and energy-efficient technologies. The shift away from traditional paper-based methods towards digital systems aligns auditing with broader environmental and societal goals. The study also highlighted the importance of continuous training and development programs for auditors to adapt to rapidly evolving technologies. Equipping auditors with technological skills ensures that human resources remain integral to the auditing process, fostering both adaptability and innovation. Algorithmic transparency and ethical decision-making were identified as critical components of sustainable auditing. Transparent decision-making mechanisms enhance trust among stakeholders and ensure that AI-driven processes remain fair, impartial, and accountable. A data-driven approach supports continuous monitoring and improvement of audit processes. By leveraging feedback mechanisms, organizations can adapt to emerging risks and technological advancements, ensuring that auditing remains dynamic and future-ready.</p><p>The study observed that while smart auditing applications offer numerous benefits, they also present challenges such as ensuring data security, addressing algorithmic bias, and maintaining ethical compliance. Additionally, organizations must invest in technological infrastructure and training to fully realize the potential of these systems. Therefore, it is recommended that organizations implement mechanisms to audit and monitor AI systems, ensuring transparency and fairness in decision-making processes. Ethical guidelines must be established to prevent bias and discrimination. Continuous training programs should be designed to equip auditors with the necessary skills to interact with advanced technologies, focusing on both technical expertise and strategic decision-making capabilities. Digitalization should be prioritized to reduce resource consumption. Adopting energy-efficient technologies and aligning auditing practices with ESG criteria will further enhance sustainability. AI-based risk detection systems should be integrated into audit processes to identify potential risks early and prevent escalation. Proactive mechanisms, such as early warning systems, will enhance audit effectiveness and organizational resilience. Establishing feedback loops and real-time monitoring systems will enable continuous improvement in auditing processes. Organizations should regularly update their methodologies to reflect technological advancements and evolving organizational needs.</p><p>While this study provides a comprehensive conceptual analysis of AI-driven auditing and sustainability strategies, several limitations must be acknowledged. First, the research primarily relies on secondary data sources, limiting direct empirical validation. The absence of primary case studies and experimental data restricts the ability to quantify the direct impact of AI applications in auditing. Additionally, variations in AI adoption across different industries and regulatory frameworks present challenges in generalizing the findings. Future studies should incorporate primary data collection methods, such as expert interviews, surveys, and real-time AI audit system evaluations, to strengthen empirical insights.</p><p>In conclusion, this study underscores the transformative potential of smart auditing applications in enhancing the efficiency, accuracy, and sustainability of audit processes. By integrating advanced technologies, adopting ethical practices, and investing in human capital, organizations can create robust, future-ready auditing frameworks. These strategies not only address current challenges but also ensure long-term value creation for both organizations and society, aligning auditing practices with principles of transparency, accountability, and sustainability.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The author declares no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alles</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brennan</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kogan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasarhelyi</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Continuous monitoring of business process controls: A pilot implementation of a continuous auditing system at Siemens</article-title>
          <source>Continuous Auditing: Theory and Application</source>
          <publisher-name>Leeds: Emerald Publishing Limited</publisher-name>
          <year>2018</year>
          <page-range>219-246</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/978-1-78743-413-420181010.</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>439-449</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alles</surname>
              <given-names>M. G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2308/acch-51067.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Drivers of the use and facilitators and obstacles of the evolution of big data by the audit profession</article-title>
          <source>Account. Horiz.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>44-59</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alles</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gray</surname>
              <given-names>G. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.accinf.2016.07.004.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Incorporating big data in audits: Identifying inhibitors and a research agenda to address those inhibitors</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Account. Inf. Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>36</volume>
          <page-range>1-27</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Appelbaum</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kogan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasarhelyi</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2308/ajpt-51684.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Big data and analytics in the modern audit engagement: Research needs</article-title>
          <source>Audit. J. Pract. Theory</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>AI 101 for audit practitioners: Practical use cases to elevate audits</article-title>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bostrom</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yudkowsky</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The ethics of artificial intelligence</article-title>
          <source>Artificial Intelligence Safety and Security</source>
          <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall/CRC</publisher-name>
          <year>2018</year>
          <page-range>57-69</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1201/9781351251389-4.</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>451-468</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brown-Liburd</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Issa</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lombardi</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2308/acch-51023.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Behavioral implications of big data's impact on audit judgment and decision making and future research directions</article-title>
          <source>Account. Horiz.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <page-range>4171-4186</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Devlin</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>M. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toutanova</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18653/v1/N19-1423.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Bert: Pre-training of deep bidirectional transformers for language understanding</article-title>
          <source>, https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/N19-1423.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>4350-4358</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fidyah</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Usman</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pradita</surname>
              <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Setyawati</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.38035/dijefa.v5i4.3224.</pub-id>
          <article-title>The impact of artificial intelligence on auditing processes and accuracy: A future outlook</article-title>
          <source>Dinasti Int. J. Econ. Finance Account.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>18</volume>
          <page-range>8432-8454</page-range>
          <issue>44</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gültekin</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26466/opus.944914.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Yapay Zekânın Luditleri Kimler Olacak?.</article-title>
          <source>OPUS Int. J. Soc. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>How AI is helping in automating the audit process</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.highradius.com/resources/Blog/leveraging-ai-in-accounting-audit/</source>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>115-122</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kokina</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davenport</surname>
              <given-names>T. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2308/jeta-51730.</pub-id>
          <article-title>The emergence of artificial intelligence: How automation is changing auditing</article-title>
          <source>J. Emerg. Technol. Account.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>521</volume>
          <page-range>436-444</page-range>
          <issue>7553</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>LeCun</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bengio</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hinton</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14539.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Deep learning</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>238</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leocádio</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malheiro</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reis</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/admsci14100238.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Artificial intelligence in auditing: A conceptual framework for auditing practices</article-title>
          <source>Adm. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>AI use cases in auditing: Reshaping audit practices</article-title>
          <source>, https://markovate.com/ai-use-cases-in-auditing/</source>
          <year>2025</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>323</volume>
          <page-range>533-536</page-range>
          <issue>6088</issue>
          <year>1986</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rumelhart</surname>
              <given-names>D. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hinton</surname>
              <given-names>G. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>R. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/323533a0.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Learning representations by back-propagating errors</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Russell</surname>
              <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Norvig</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Artificial Intelligence: A Modern Approach (4th ed.)</source>
          <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>
          <year>2020</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>529</volume>
          <page-range>484-489</page-range>
          <issue>7587</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Silver</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maddison</surname>
              <given-names>C. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guez</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sifre</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Den Driessche</surname>
              <given-names>G. et al.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature16961.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Mastering the game of Go with deep neural networks and tree search</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>22</volume>
          <page-range>60-73</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sutton</surname>
              <given-names>S. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holt</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arnold</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.accinf.2016.07.005.</pub-id>
          <article-title>“The reports of my death are greatly exaggerated”—Artificial intelligence research in accounting</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Account. Inf. Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>381-396</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vasarhelyi</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kogan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tuttle</surname>
              <given-names>B. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2308/acch-51071.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Big data in accounting: An overview</article-title>
          <source>Account. Horiz.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>