<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJTDI</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.2495</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Transport Development and Integration</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">Int. J. Transp. Dev. Integr.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">IJTDI</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2058-8313</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2058-8305</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-lw32VhQ92AhcuKUz_lxF8watfRxTWqyW</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2495/TDI-V3-N4-331-343</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Macroscopic Analysis of Transport Networks: The Influence of Network Design on Urban Transportation Performance</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1,2">
          <name>
            <surname>Dingil</surname>
            <given-names>Ali Enes</given-names>
          </name>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <name>
            <surname>Rupi</surname>
            <given-names>Federico</given-names>
          </name>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <name>
            <surname>Stasiskiene</surname>
            <given-names>Zaneta</given-names>
          </name>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Kaunas University of Technology, Institute of Environmental Engineering, Lithuania</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">University of Bologna, Civil Engineering Department, Italy</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub"/>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>331</fpage>
      <lpage>343</lpage>
      <page-range>331-343</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received"/>
        <date date-type="accepted"/>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2019 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p><span style="color: rgb(30, 30, 30); font-family: Lato, Helvetica Neue, Arial, sans-serif">This research aims at investigating the direct and indirect influence of network structures on urban transportation performance with a macroscopic perspective. Transport systems are complex – the functional properties of a transportation network can affect mobility patterns which in turn changes the network performance. Understanding the topology of transportation networks is important in order to upgrade transport network design and to improve transportation performance. This paper attempts to determine important network indicators such connectivity, centrality and clustering measures for different network types (road, rail and bike) from 86 urban areas and 32 countries, based on compa- rable, directly observable open-source data such as OpenStreetMap (OSM) and the TomTom congestion database. Relations between indicators are identified through correlation measures. In addition, regression models are calibrated which quantify the relations between infrastructure accessibility (IA) and network indicators and average traffic delay times. The indicator average road connectivity over average road circuity (RCRC), which is proposed in this study, has not been cited before in literature. The main results suggest that the determination of distance-based connectivity of networks is an important proxy to understand road transportation performance. Consequently, two main results were obtained: (1) an increase in average short-distance connectivity of road networks (average closeness centrality and RCRC) eases road congestion, presumably because the network distributes road traffic more homogenously while decreasing low-permeability choke points, (2) an increase of the average short-distance connectivity of networks of alternative modes such as rail or bike (average weighted rail clustering coefficient and average cycle closeness centrality) does alleviate road congestion. In particular, for cities with over 0.4 km per km$^2$  cycleway density, an increase in cycleway closeness centrality decreases road congestion and it does so almost as efficiently as an increase in road infrastructure accessibility. Presumably, well-connected, alternative networks with short and direct routes convince car users to shift to the alternative mode, which decreases road traffic volumes.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>network design</kwd>
        <kwd>topology</kwd>
        <kwd>infrastructure accessibility</kwd>
        <kwd>congestion</kwd>
        <kwd>open-source data</kwd>
        <kwd>OSM</kwd>
        <kwd>TomTom</kwd>
        <kwd>transportation performance</kwd>
        <kwd>transport planning</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="3"/>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="0"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body/>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>