<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JUDM</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Urban Development and Management</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Urban Dev. Manag.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JUDM</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2957-9597</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2957-9589</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-gE4YxVbBm75YPO7KNeaHlcM-AAMsXH_B</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/judm020101</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Third-Party Logistics Provider Selection for Sustainable Last-Mile Delivery: A Case Study of E-Shop in Belgrade</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1">1</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>šVadlenka</surname>
            <given-names>Libor</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6484-6660</contrib-id>
          <email>libor.svadlenka@upce.cz</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1">1</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>BošKović</surname>
            <given-names>Sara</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0331-4262</contrib-id>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="1">1</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>JovčIć</surname>
            <given-names>Stefan</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9162-2133</contrib-id>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="2">2</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Simic</surname>
            <given-names>Vladimir</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5709-3744</contrib-id>
          <email>vsima@sf.bg.ac.rs</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="3">3</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>Shashank</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0841-987X</contrib-id>
          <email/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="4">4</xref>
          <name>
            <surname>Zanne</surname>
            <given-names>Marina</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7288-670X</contrib-id>
          <email>marina.zanne@fpp.uni-lj.si</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="1">Department of Transport Management, Marketing, and Logistics, Faculty of Transport Engineering, University of Pardubice, 53210 Pardubice, Czech Republic</aff>
        <aff id="2">Faculty of Transport and Traffic Engineering, University of Belgrade, 11010 Belgrade, Serbia</aff>
        <aff id="3">Operations and Supply Chain Management, Symbiosis Institute of Operations Management, Nashik, India</aff>
        <aff id="4">Faculty of Maritime Studies and Transport, University of Ljubljana, 6320 Portorose, Slovenia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <year>2023</year>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>13</lpage>
      <page-range>1-13</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <month>02</month>
          <day>02</day>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <month>03</month>
          <day>13</day>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="pub">
          <month>03</month>
          <day>29</day>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2023 by the authors</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <license>. Licensee Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article can be downloaded for free, and reused and quoted with a citation of the original published version, under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 license</ext-link>.</license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>Last-mile delivery (LMD) is one of the crucial phases of the shipping process. Since e-commerce rapidly evolves, there are many issues that should be addressed in city logistics. This paper specifically tackles the issue of Third-Party Logistics (3PL) provider selection for sustainable last-mile delivery. The 3PL selection problem has been solved for the e-shop company from Belgrade, which has online sales. The management of the e-shop company has identified five possible 3PL providers. Those five 3PL providers have been evaluated according to six criteria such as distribution cost, on-time delivery, flexibility of distribution, IT capability, good cultural fit, and customer satisfaction index. To evaluate and rank the 3PL providers, two multi-criteria decision-making methods were coupled. The first one is a Best-Worst Method (BWM) used to find the criteria weights, while the second one is a Combined Compromised Solution (CoCoSo) method utilized to rank the 3PL providers from best to worst one. To check the stability as well as the robustness of the applied methods, sensitivity and comparative analyses are performed. The results show high confidence in the applied methods.</abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Third-party logistics</kwd>
        <kwd>Multi-criteria decision making</kwd>
        <kwd>Last-mile delivery</kwd>
        <kwd>Combined compromised solution</kwd>
        <kwd>Best-worst method</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors">6</count>
        <fig-count>4</fig-count>
        <table-count>12</table-count>
        <ref-count>57</ref-count>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Last-Mile Delivery (LMD) describes the final and one of the most important and sensitive phases of the shipping process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>]. This is the phase where the final customers receive the ordered shipments at their addresses. Due to globalization as well as the rapid development of e-commerce, there is a notable increasing number of online orders. The other reason for the increasing number of online orders is the epidemiological situation all over the world. People would rather explore online shops on a website and simply order the desired products to their addresses than physically go there. Bearing that fact in mind, shippers have found themselves in difficulties and doubts, especially in the cities, when it comes to the overall organization of the shipping process. The development of e-commerce markets had opened many questions regarding last-mile delivery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]. On the other hand, in the last few years, there had been many challenges when performing deliveries due to many of the market risks such as COVID-19, the increase in urban population, and traffic congestion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. According to the European Commission document from Brussels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], at least 30 million zero-emission vehicles would be in operation on European roads and 100 European cities would be climate neutral. Therefore, it is of huge importance to make all transport modes more adaptable and sustainable. From a sustainability perspective, the shippers in terms of last-mile delivery should follow many factors. E-commerce companies that sell their products online must carefully monitor the standards and procedures to make their business more effective and viable. Some e-commerce companies perform the last-mile delivery by themselves, while others contract a third party. One of the issues in the last-mile delivery process is the collaboration with the external business partners i.e., 3PL service providers, and their selection. Since the 3PL providers (DHL, FedEx, TNT, Posts, etc.) is the main connection between sellers and buyers, choosing the right one is significant for sustainable last-mile delivery.</p><p>This paper aims to address the 3PL provider selection problem for sustainable last-mile delivery. Namely, an e-shop company from Belgrade should decide on the best 3PL service provider that will perform the LMD of its products to the final customers in the territory of Belgrade. The 3PL selection problem is not so easy task for decision-makers since multiple conflicting criteria interfere in a decision-making process. Nowadays, there are many multi-criteria decision-making methods used to solve this or similar kinds of problems. In this paper, to solve the problem mentioned, the two multi-criteria decision-making methods are coupled. The first one is the Best-Worst Method (BWM) used to find the criteria weights, while the second one is the Combined Compromise Solution (CoCoSo) method used to rank the alternatives from best to worst. In addition, the sensitivity analysis is performed to test the stability of the applied CoCoSo method. Besides, a comparative analysis is done to compare the results with some multi-criteria decision-making (MCDM) methods.</p><p>There are some contributions of this paper:</p><p>1) For the first time, the BWM-CoCoSo methods are coupled to find the best 3PL alternative for the e-shop company in Belgrade.</p><p>2) The BWM-CoCoSo method is applied to a real-life case study in Belgrade which should be seen as a practical contribution.</p><p>3) The applied methodology is tested and verified in the case study involving 5 3PL providers. The sensitivity analysis of the applied methods is performed, and the high stability of the results is demonstrated; In addition, the comparative analysis is provided, and the presented results are highly confident.</p><p>In addition to contributions, there are certain limitations of this study such as:</p><p>    i) There are not so many criteria considered in a decision-making process. The identified criteria from the literature were of special interest to the e-shop company’s management who decides on the best 3PL. The six identified criteria were enough according to the e-shop company’s management opinion because the economic, social, and technical pillars need to be tackled.</p><p>    ii) Since the 3PL selection problem deals with uncertainty, the applied methods are not combined with fuzzy logic. This limitation should be considered as a future research direction of the paper.</p><p>The rest of the paper is structured in the following manner: Section 2 reveals the review of the literature in terms of criteria and methods used to solve the 3PL selection problem. Section 3 elaborates on the methodology that is applied to the problem mentioned. Section 4 is the application of the methodology to the real-life case study of the e-shop company from Belgrade. Section 5 gives some general managerial implications on the considered problem. Section 6 concludes and gives future directions for the paper.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>2. Literature review</title>
      <p>The literature review is organized into three sub-sections. The first one identifies the evaluation criteria for 3PL provider selection. The second one reveals the available methods used to solve the 3PL provider selection problem, while the third one focuses on the existing state-of-the-art applications of the Best-Worst Method (BWM) and CoCoSo method.</p>
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.1. Evaluation criteria for 3pl service provider selection</title>
          
          <p>This subsection investigates the criteria that are used in 3PL service provider selection by various authors. Many conflicting criteria affect the 3PL selection process. However, some of the criteria that should be used in this paper are sorted out from the literature review. The identified criteria are briefly defined and summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>According to the review of the literature, six criteria have been sorted out as the crucial ones for the e-shop company. Those six criteria are distribution costs, on-time delivery, the flexibility of distribution, IT capability, good cultural fit as well as customer satisfaction index. In addition, as can be noticed from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>, many authors in this field used some of those criteria to solve the 3PL provider selection problem. </p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>Evaluation criteria for the 3PL selection process</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Criterion</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Definition</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>References</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Distribution Cost</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The Cost that 3PL should require for the distribution process.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>On-Time Delivery</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Whether the 3PL respects the promised distribution timeframes</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Flexibility of Distribution</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The ability to react faster to market turbulences</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IT Capability</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The level of IT capability in terms of customer order management, track and trace technologies, web portal, etc.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good Cultural Fit</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>How well will the 3PL and the e-shop company be able to collaborate based on their respective internal business cultures</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Customer Satisfaction Index</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The index of customer satisfaction in terms of collaboration with the 3PL provider</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.2. Evaluation methods for 3pl service provider selection</title>
          
          <p>This subsection surveys the existing methods for the 3PL provider selection process. Many methods were applied to solve the 3PL provider selection problem. Most of the methods belong to the multi-criteria decision-making methods. The available methods from the literature are briefly summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>Existing MCDM methods in 3PL provider selection</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Reference</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Method(s)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Govindan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fuzzy-ELECTRE</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kilincci &amp;amp; Onal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fuzzy-AHP and Fuzzy-Objective LP</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Arikan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fuzzy-AHP</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Laptate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fuzzy-Modified-TOPSIS</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Jayant and Singh [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AHP-VIKOR</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Gürcan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AHP</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rezaeisaray et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>DEMATEL, Fuzzy-ANP, DEA</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kumar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>TODIM, PROMETHEE</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Garside and Saputro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fuzzy-AHP, Grey-TOPSIS</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Singh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fuzzy-AHP, Fuzzy-TOPSIS</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Raut et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>DEA, ANP</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sremac et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rough SWARA, Rough WASPAS, Rough SAW, Rough EDAS, Rough MABAC, Rough TOPSIS</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Zarbakhshnia et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SWARA, COPRAS</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bianchini  [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AHP, TOPSIS</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Roy et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>FARE-MABAC based on IVFRN</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Paché and Aguezzoul [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AHP, ELECTRE I</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Özcan and Ahıskalı [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AHP, TOPSIS, Goal Programming</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ulutas and Topal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SWARA, RPSI, IOCRA</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ulutas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Grey-SWARA, Grey-CODAS</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Our Study</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>BWM-CoCoSo</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>As can be noticed, there are various MCDM methods used to solve the 3PL Service Provider selection problem. Most of the methods are coupled with fuzzy logic and the expert's opinions and participation are mostly included. In this paper, the CoCoSo method is integrated with the BWM method to obtain the best 3PL provider solution for last-mile delivery. The combination of those methods has not been previously applied to the E-shop company to solve a real-life case study, which should be considered as one of the practical contributions. The next subsection reveals the current state of applications of the BWM and the CoCoSo methods in various fields.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>2.3. An overview of the application of the best-worst method (bwm) and cocoso method</title>
          
          <p>This subsection reveals the application of the Best-Worst Method (BWM) and the CoCoSo method to various MCDM problems. The summary of the available applications of the BWM and CoCoSo is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>, respectively. </p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>Summary of the available applications of the BWM</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Reference</p></td><td><p>Problem considered</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Ortega et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Sustainable Park and Ride Facility Location</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Pamučar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Renewable Energy</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Zhou et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Evaluation of Urban Photovoltaic Charging Station </p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Moslem et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Mobility choice after COVID-19 in Italy</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Kant and Gupta [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Sustainable Urban Freight Strategies in Jaipur city </p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Ali and Rashid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Robot Selection Process</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Mahmoudi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Multiple Experts MCDM problem under uncertainty</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Ozmen and Aydogan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Logistics Center Location</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Rodríguez-Gutiérez et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>]</p></td><td><p>SMEs under sustainability perspective</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Duleba et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Commuting Modal Spit</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Guler and Yomralioglu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">44</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Bicycle Station and Lane Location Selection</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>Based on the articles reviewed, there are various fields addressed by the BWM and CoCoSo methods. When it comes to the BWM method, there were considered the problems such as sustainable park-and-ride facility location, renewable energy, evaluation of urban photovoltaic charging stations, mobility choice after COVID-19 in Italy, logistics center location, robot selection process, etc. On the other side, regarding the CoCoSo method, the addressed problems were in Manufacturing Technology Selection, Electric Vehicle Selection, Sustainable Supplier Selection, Temporary Hospital Location, Logistics Center Location, Personnel Selection, etc. Nevertheless, it can be noticed that the applications of the BWM and CoCoSo have not previously been tackling the last-mile delivery issue in the e-commerce industry. Bearing in mind the potential of combining the BWM and the CoCoSo methods, this paper deals with the 3PL provider selection for sustainable last-mile delivery in the e-shop company. Since e-shop companies sell their products online, it is of huge importance to have a great business partner for the last-mile delivery of shipments to the final customers. For that reason, the integration of the mentioned methods should be considered an excellent approach in the 3PL selection process to make the LMD process more effective and sustainable. </p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_4">
              <label>Table 4</label>
              <caption>Summary of the available applications of the CoCoSo method</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <table><tbody><tr><td><p>Reference</p></td><td><p>Problem considered</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Yazdani and Chatterjee [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Manufacturing Technology Selection</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Biswas et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Electric Vehicle Selection</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Wen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">47</xref>]</p></td><td><p>HFL-CoCoSo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Ecer and Pamučar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">48</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Sustainable Supplier Selection</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Zolfani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">49</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Temporary Hospital Location</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Ulutaş et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">50</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Logistics Center Location</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Peng and Florentin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">51</xref>]</p></td><td><p>China’s rare earth industry security</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Popović [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_52">52</xref>]</p></td><td><p>Personnel Selection</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Our Study</p></td><td><p>3PL Provider Selection for Sustainable Last-Mile Delivery</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>3. Methodology</title>
      <p>This section describes the methodology that is to be used to solve the 3PL service provider selection problem for sustainable last-mile delivery. A flowchart of the proposed BWM-CoCoSo methodology is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>.</p><p>Namely, the two multi-criteria decision-making methods are coupled to obtain the final rank of the alternatives. The first one is the Best-Worst Method (BWM), which is used to find the criteria's importance since not all criteria are equally important. The second one is the Combined Compromise Solution (CoCoSo) method which is used to obtain the final rank of the 3PL alternatives. The methodology is applied to a real-life case study in an e-shop company in Belgrade.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>A flowchart of the BWM-CoCoSo methods</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_NdWYLrTfMaOSpLIs.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>3.1. Best-worst method</title>
          
          <p>The Best-Worst method was originally developed by Rezaei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">53</xref>]. This method aims at obtaining the criteria weights since not all criteria are equally important. This method is based on the idea that when making a pairwise comparison <italic>a<sub>ij</sub></italic>, the decision-maker considers both the direction and the strength of the preference<italic> i</italic> over<italic> j.</italic> The Best-Worst Method is elaborated through the following steps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">53</xref>]:</p><p>Step 1. Determine a set of decision criteria. </p><p>The criteria {<italic>c<sub>1</sub>, c<sub>2</sub>, … c<sub>n</sub></italic>} are determined to be used to make a desirable decision.</p><p>Step 2. Determine the Best (e.g., most desirable, most important) and the Worst (e.g., less desirable, less important) criterion. </p><p>In the case that more than one criterion is the best or the worst one, one of them can be chosen arbitrarily. At this step, the decision-maker identifies the best and the worst criterion in general, and no comparison is performed.</p><p>Step 3. Determine the preference of the best criterion to all the other ones, using a scale between 1 and 9. </p><p>The resulting vector Best-to-Others should be defined:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msub>
                  <mi>A</mi>
                  <mi>B</mi>
                </msub>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo>,</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>a</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>B</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>a</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>B</mi>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                      <mo>,</mo>
                      <mo>…</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>a</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>B</mi>
                      <mi>n</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <italic>a<sub>Bj</sub></italic><sub> </sub>shows the preference of the best criterion<italic> B</italic> over criterion <italic>j</italic>. So, it is clear that <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>a</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>B</mi>
        <mi>B</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mn>1</mn>
  </math>
</inline-formula>.</p><p>Step 4. Determine the preference of all the other criteria to the worst one, using a scale between 1 and 9. </p><p>The resulting Others-to-Worst vector should be defined: </p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(2)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msub>
                  <mi>A</mi>
                  <mi>w</mi>
                </msub>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <msup>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo>,</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>a</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mn>1</mn>
                        <mi>w</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>a</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mn>2</mn>
                        <mi>w</mi>
                        <mo>…</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>a</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>n</mi>
                        <mi>w</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>T</mi>
                </msup>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <italic>a<sub>jw</sub></italic> indicates the preference of the criterion<italic> j</italic> to the worst one <italic>W</italic>. It is clear that <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>a</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>w</mi>
        <mi>w</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mn>1</mn>
  </math>
</inline-formula>.</p><p>Step 5. Find the optimal weights <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mo>…</mo>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
      <msubsup>
        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
          <mi mathvariant="normal">w</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mn>1</mn>
        <mo>∗</mo>
      </msubsup>
      <msubsup>
        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
          <mi mathvariant="normal">w</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mn>2</mn>
        <mo>∗</mo>
      </msubsup>
      <msubsup>
        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
          <mi mathvariant="normal">w</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
            <mi mathvariant="normal">n</mi>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mo>∗</mo>
      </msubsup>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula>.</p><p>The optimal weight for the criteria is the one where for each pair of <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>B</mi>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </msub>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>w</mi>
    </msub>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula>, we have <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>B</mi>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>a</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>B</mi>
        <mi>j</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mo>=</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>w</mi>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>a</mi>
      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
        <mi>j</mi>
        <mi>w</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mo>=</mo>
  </math>
</inline-formula>. To fulfill these conditions for all <italic>j</italic>, we should find a solution where the maximum absolute differences <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">|</mo>
      <mo>−</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">|</mo>
      <mfrac>
        <msub>
          <mi>W</mi>
          <mi>B</mi>
        </msub>
        <msub>
          <mi>W</mi>
          <mi>j</mi>
        </msub>
      </mfrac>
      <msub>
        <mi>a</mi>
        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
          <mi>B</mi>
          <mi>j</mi>
        </mrow>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">|</mo>
      <mo>−</mo>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">|</mo>
      <mfrac>
        <msub>
          <mi>W</mi>
          <mi>j</mi>
        </msub>
        <msub>
          <mi>W</mi>
          <mi>w</mi>
        </msub>
      </mfrac>
      <msub>
        <mi>a</mi>
        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
          <mi>j</mi>
          <mi>w</mi>
        </mrow>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
  </math>
</inline-formula><italic> </italic>for all <italic>j </italic>is minimized. Considering the non-negativity and sum condition for the weights would lead to the following problem:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(3)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">min</mo>
                <munder>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
                  <mi>j</mi>
                </munder>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">{</mo>
                  <mo>,</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">}</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">|</mo>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">|</mo>
                    <mfrac>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>W</mi>
                        <mi>B</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>W</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </msub>
                    </mfrac>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>a</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>B</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">|</mo>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">|</mo>
                    <mfrac>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>W</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>W</mi>
                        <mi>w</mi>
                      </msub>
                    </mfrac>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>a</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>j</mi>
                        <mi>w</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>s.t. <inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <munder>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </munder>
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo>;</mo>
    <mo>≥</mo>
    <mn>1</mn>
    <mn>0</mn>
  </math>
</inline-formula> for all <italic>j</italic>. </p><p>After Eq. (3), the problem can be reformulated to the following linear programming problem: Min <italic>ξ</italic> </p><p>s.t. </p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(4)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mtable displaystyle="true" columnalign="right left" columnspacing="0em" rowspacing="3pt">
                  <mtr>
                    <mtd/>
                    <mtd>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">|</mo>
                        <mo>−</mo>
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">|</mo>
                        <mfrac>
                          <msub>
                            <mi>W</mi>
                            <mi>B</mi>
                          </msub>
                          <msub>
                            <mi>W</mi>
                            <mi>j</mi>
                          </msub>
                        </mfrac>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>a</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mi>B</mi>
                            <mi>j</mi>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mrow>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi mathvariant="normal">j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>≤</mo>
                      <mo>,</mo>
                      <mo>.</mo>
                      <mi>ξ</mi>
                      <mtext> for all </mtext>
                    </mtd>
                  </mtr>
                  <mtr>
                    <mtd/>
                    <mtd>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">|</mo>
                        <mo>−</mo>
                        <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">|</mo>
                        <mfrac>
                          <msub>
                            <mi>W</mi>
                            <mi>j</mi>
                          </msub>
                          <msub>
                            <mi>W</mi>
                            <mi>w</mi>
                          </msub>
                        </mfrac>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>a</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mi>j</mi>
                            <mi>w</mi>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mrow>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi mathvariant="normal">j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>≤</mo>
                      <mo>,</mo>
                      <mo>.</mo>
                      <mi>ξ</mi>
                      <mtext> for all </mtext>
                    </mtd>
                  </mtr>
                </mtable>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p><inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <munder>
      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </munder>
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </msub>
    <msub>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mo>;</mo>
    <mo>≥</mo>
    <mn>1</mn>
    <mn>0</mn>
  </math>
</inline-formula> for all $j<inline-formula>
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo>&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mo>
    <mo>&amp;gt;</mo>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
      <mo>/</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>B</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>v</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>E</mi>
    <mi>q</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mn>4</mn>
  </math>
</inline-formula>\left(\mathrm{w}_1^*, \mathrm{w}_2^*, \ldots, \mathrm{w}_{\mathrm{n}}^*\right)$ and<italic> ξ<sup>*</sup></italic> are obtained. The consistency ratio of the model is calculated using the following equation:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(5)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>C</mi>
                <mi>o</mi>
                <mi>n</mi>
                <mi>s</mi>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>s</mi>
                <mi>t</mi>
                <mi>e</mi>
                <mi>n</mi>
                <mi>c</mi>
                <mi>y</mi>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mi>a</mi>
                <mi>t</mi>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>o</mi>
                <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                  <mspace width="0.167em"/>
                </mstyle>
                <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                  <mspace width="0.167em"/>
                </mstyle>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mfrac>
                  <mi>ξ</mi>
                  <mrow>
                    <mi>C</mi>
                    <mi>I</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </mfrac>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <italic>ξ</italic> is the optimal objective value of model (5), and <italic>CI</italic> is the consistency index which can be taken from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_5">
              <label>Table 5</label>
              <caption>Consistency index [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">53</xref>]</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><italic>a<sub>Bw</sub></italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CI max (<math>
  <mi>ξ</mi>
</math>)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.44</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.63</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.30</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.00</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.73</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.47</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.23</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>3.2. Combined compromise solution (cocoso) method</title>
          
          <p>A Combined Compromise Solution (CoCoSo) method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">54</xref>] belongs to multi-criteria decision-making methods. This method was originally developed by Yazdani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">54</xref>], where the authors applied the aggregation strategies. In addition, they considered a distance measure, which originates from the grey relational coefficient and targets to enhance the flexibility of the results. The CoCoSo method is based on an integrated Simple Additive Weighting (SAW) method and an Exponentially Weighted Product (EWP) model. The CoCoSo method can be explained through the following phases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">54</xref>]:</p><p>Phase 1: Determine the initial decision-making matrix with the input data</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(6)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi>X</mi>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>m</mi>
                <mi>j</mi>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>;</mo>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">[</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">]</mo>
                  <mtable columnalign="center center center center center" columnspacing="1em" rowspacing="4pt">
                    <mtr>
                      <mtd>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>x</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mn>11</mn>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mo>⋯</mo>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>x</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mn>12</mn>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mo>⋯</mo>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>x</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mn>1</mn>
                            <mi>n</mi>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mtd>
                    </mtr>
                    <mtr>
                      <mtd>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo>⋮</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mo>⋱</mo>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo>⋮</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mo>⋱</mo>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo>⋮</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mtd>
                    </mtr>
                    <mtr>
                      <mtd>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>x</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mn>21</mn>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mo>⋯</mo>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>x</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mn>22</mn>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mo>⋯</mo>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>x</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mn>2</mn>
                            <mi>n</mi>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mtd>
                    </mtr>
                    <mtr>
                      <mtd>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo>⋮</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mo>⋱</mo>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo>⋮</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mo>⋱</mo>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mo>⋮</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mtd>
                    </mtr>
                    <mtr>
                      <mtd>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>x</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mi>m</mi>
                            <mn>1</mn>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mo>⋯</mo>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>x</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mi>m</mi>
                            <mi>j</mi>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <mo>⋯</mo>
                      </mtd>
                      <mtd>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>x</mi>
                          <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                            <mi>m</mi>
                            <mi>n</mi>
                          </mrow>
                        </msub>
                      </mtd>
                    </mtr>
                  </mtable>
                </mrow>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mi mathvariant="normal">n</mi>
                </mrow>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>2</mn>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>Phase 2: Normalize the initial decision-making matrix from the first phase</p><p>There are two equations to be used in the normalization process, depending on the criteria type. If the criterion is a beneficial (B), there is the following equation for normalization: </p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(7)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msub>
                  <mi>r</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mi>j</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </msub>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>;</mo>
                <mfrac>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>x</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>x</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">min</mo>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </munder>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </munder>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">min</mo>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </munder>
                    <msub>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>x</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>x</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                  </mrow>
                </mfrac>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>m</mi>
                <mi>j</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>2</mn>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>2</mn>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mi mathvariant="normal">n</mi>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>If the criterion is non-beneficial i.e., cost (C), there is the following equation for normalization:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(8)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msub>
                  <mi>r</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mi>j</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </msub>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>;</mo>
                <mfrac>
                  <mrow>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </munder>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <msub>
                        <mi>x</mi>
                        <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                          <mi>i</mi>
                          <mi>j</mi>
                        </mrow>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>x</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </munder>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">min</mo>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </munder>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>x</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>x</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                  </mrow>
                </mfrac>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>m</mi>
                <mi>j</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>2</mn>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>2</mn>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mi mathvariant="normal">n</mi>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>Phase 3: Calculate the weighted sequences <italic>S<sub>i</sub></italic> and <italic>P<sub>i</sub></italic> for each alternative</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(9)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msub>
                  <mi>S</mi>
                  <mi>i</mi>
                </msub>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>;</mo>
                <munderover>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>n</mi>
                </munderover>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo>⋅</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>w</mi>
                    <mi>j</mi>
                  </msub>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>r</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>i</mi>
                      <mi>j</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>m</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(10)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msub>
                  <mi>P</mi>
                  <mi>i</mi>
                </msub>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>;</mo>
                <munderover>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mo>=</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>n</mi>
                </munderover>
                <msup>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>r</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>j</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <msub>
                      <mi>w</mi>
                      <mi>j</mi>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </msup>
                <mstyle scriptlevel="0">
                  <mspace width="1em"/>
                </mstyle>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>m</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>Phase 4: Calculate the three total utility strategies for each alternative</p><p>The first strategy of total utility (<italic>K<sub>ia</sub></italic>) expresses the arithmetic mean of the sum of <italic>S<sub>i</sub></italic><sub> </sub>and <italic>P<sub>i</sub></italic> values:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(11)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msub>
                  <mi>K</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mi>a</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </msub>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>;</mo>
                <mfrac>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>P</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>+</mo>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <munderover>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP">∑</mo>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mo>=</mo>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </mrow>
                      <mi>m</mi>
                    </munderover>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                      <mo>+</mo>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>P</mi>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                      </msub>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>S</mi>
                        <mi>i</mi>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mfrac>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>m</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>The second strategy of total utility (<italic>K<sub>ib</sub></italic>) expresses the sum of the relative relations <italic>S<sub>i</sub></italic> and <italic>P<sub>i</sub></italic> with their worst values:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(12)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msub>
                  <mi>K</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mi>b</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </msub>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>…</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>;</mo>
                <mfrac>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>S</mi>
                    <mi>i</mi>
                  </msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">min</mo>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </munder>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mfrac>
                <mfrac>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>P</mi>
                    <mi>i</mi>
                  </msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">min</mo>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </munder>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>P</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mfrac>
                <mi>i</mi>
                <mi>m</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>The third strategy of total utility (<italic>K<sub>ic</sub></italic>) expresses a balanced compromise of <italic>S<sub>i</sub></italic> and <italic>P<sub>i</sub></italic> values:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(13)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msub>
                  <mi>K</mi>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mi>i</mi>
                    <mi>c</mi>
                  </mrow>
                </msub>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mo>≤</mo>
                <mo>≤</mo>
                <mo>;</mo>
                <mfrac>
                  <mrow>
                    <mi>λ</mi>
                    <mi>λ</mi>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>P</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>+</mo>
                    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo>+</mo>
                    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <mi>λ</mi>
                    <mi>λ</mi>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </munder>
                    <munder>
                      <mo data-mjx-texclass="OP" movablelimits="true">max</mo>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </munder>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>P</mi>
                      <mi>i</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                </mfrac>
                <mn>0</mn>
                <mn>1</mn>
                <mi>λ</mi>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>Phase 5: Obtain the final rank of alternatives.</p><p>The final ranking of the alternatives is determined based on <italic>K<sub>i</sub>:</italic></p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(14)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <msub>
                  <mi>K</mi>
                  <mi>i</mi>
                </msub>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mo>;</mo>
                <msup>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                    <mo>⋅</mo>
                    <mo>⋅</mo>
                    <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>K</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>a</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>K</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>b</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>K</mi>
                      <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                        <mi>i</mi>
                        <mi>c</mi>
                      </mrow>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                    <mfrac>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                      <mn>3</mn>
                    </mfrac>
                  </mrow>
                </msup>
                <mfrac>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                  <mn>3</mn>
                </mfrac>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="INNER">
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="OPEN">(</mo>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <mo data-mjx-texclass="CLOSE">)</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>K</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>i</mi>
                      <mi>a</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>K</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>i</mi>
                      <mi>b</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>K</mi>
                    <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                      <mi>i</mi>
                      <mi>c</mi>
                    </mrow>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>4. Case study of 3pl provider selection for lmd in belgrade</title>
      <p>The previously described methodology is applied to the e-shop company from Belgrade, the capital of the Republic of Serbia. According to a discussion with the company’s top management, its name is not mentioned due to internal policy reasons. However, it is one of the leaders in Serbia in online selling goods and mostly operates on a national level. When it comes to storage goods, it has its warehouse where the ordered products come from to the final customers. Currently, the e-shop company has a contract with the two 3PL service providers for the last-mile delivery, which names are also not unfolded due to their policy of privacy. The final customers who buy their products online have the option to select the 3PL provider who should deliver the product to their final address. However, the e-shop company’s contract with the one 3PL service provider may end soon, according to a discussion with the top management. It will mean that the e-shop company will have only one 3PL service provider and will need to find another 3PL business partner for the last-mile delivery to collaborate with. As its manager stated, the e-shop company is looking for a 3PL service provider who would fulfill its expectations and perform the last-mile delivery process, in the territory of Belgrade, as efficiently and productively as possible. In addition, according to the literature review, the authors of this paper sorted out some of the crucial criteria (Distribution Cost (C<sub>1</sub>), On-time Delivery (C<sub>2</sub>), Flexibility of Distribution (C<sub>3</sub>), IT Capability (C<sub>4</sub>), Good Cultural Fit (C<sub>5</sub>) and Customer Satisfaction Index (C<sub>6</sub>)) for the 3PL selection process. The e-shop company’s management completely agreed with the criteria selected. In addition, five 3PL service providers operate in the territory of the Republic of Serbia as possible alternatives. Those five 3PLs are identified by the experts from the E-shop company and compared according to the above-mentioned criteria. The authors of this paper in collaboration with the top management of the e-shop company, by applying the BWM method, determined the criteria weights for the 3PL selection process since not all criteria have the same weight when deciding on the best 3PL. The illustrative description of the problem is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>. </p>
      
        <fig id="fig_2">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>Illustration of the problem</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_Bw_Nv0KlzKCYYsfr.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>According to the BWM method, the criteria weights are determined and presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref>.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_6">
          <label>Table 6</label>
          <caption>The criteria weights identified by the BWM method</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><p>Distribution Cost (€/km)</p></td><td><p>On-Time Delivery (%)</p></td><td><p>Flexibility of Distribution (1-5)</p></td><td><p>IT Capability (1-5)</p></td><td><p>Good Cultural Fit (1-5)</p></td><td><p>Customer Satisfaction Index (1-3)</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Weights</p></td><td><p>0.3421</p></td><td><p>0.1466</p></td><td><p>0.1099</p></td><td><p>0.1466</p></td><td><p>0.2199</p></td><td><p>0.0349</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>The obtained criteria weights from the BWM method are utilized within the CoCoSo method to rank the alternatives from best to worst. The initial decision-making matrix and all the following steps of the CoCoSo method are presented in the following Tables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_7">Table 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_8">Table 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_9">Table 9</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_10">Table 10</xref>).</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_7">
          <label>Table 7</label>
          <caption>The initial (CoCoSo) decision-making matrix</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <table><tbody><tr><td></td><td><p>Distribution Cost (€/km)</p></td><td><p>On-Time Delivery (%)</p></td><td><p>The flexibility of Distribution (1-5)</p></td><td><p>IT Capability (1-5)</p></td><td><p>Good Cultural Fit (1-5)</p></td><td><p>Customer Satisfaction Index (1-3)</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>3PL-1</p></td><td><p>0.95</p></td><td><p>99.98</p></td><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>3PL-2</p></td><td><p>0.93</p></td><td><p>99.88</p></td><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>3PL-3</p></td><td><p>0.97</p></td><td><p>98.85</p></td><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>3PL-4</p></td><td><p>0.99</p></td><td><p>99.99</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>3PL-5</p></td><td><p>0.95</p></td><td><p>99.90</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>0.93</p></td><td><p>99.99</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>0.99</p></td><td><p>98.85</p></td><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>2</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Weights</p></td><td><p>0.3421</p></td><td><p>0.1466</p></td><td><p>0.1099</p></td><td><p>0.1466</p></td><td><p>0.2199</p></td><td><p>0.0349</p></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><p>min</p></td><td><p>max</p></td><td><p>max</p></td><td><p>max</p></td><td><p>max</p></td><td><p>max</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_8">
          <label>Table 8</label>
          <caption>Normalization of the input data</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Distribution Cost (€/km)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>On-Time Delivery (%)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Flexibility of Distribution (1-5)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IT Capability (1-5)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good Cultural Fit (1-5)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Customer Satisfaction Index (1-3)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.6667</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9912</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.5000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9035</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3333</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.5000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.6667</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9211</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.5000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.0000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Weights</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3421</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1466</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1099</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1466</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2199</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0349</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_9">
          <label>Table 9</label>
          <caption>Obtained weighted sequences S<sub>i</sub> and P<sub>i</sub> for each alternative</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Distribution Cost (€/km)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>On-Time Delivery (%)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Flexibility of Distribution (1-5)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>IT Capability (1-5)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Good Cultural Fit (1-5)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Customer Satisfaction Index (1-3)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>S<sub>i</sub></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>P<sub>i</sub></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2281</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1453</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1100</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0349</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.5182</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.7278</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3421</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1325</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1466</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2199</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8411</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.9852</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1140</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0550</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1466</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0349</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3505</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.6134</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1466</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1099</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1466</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2199</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.6230</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.0000</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2281</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1350</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1099</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1100</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0349</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.6178</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.7171</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="2"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>min</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3505</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.6134</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>max</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8411</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.7171</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      
        <table-wrap id="table_10">
          <label>Table 10</label>
          <caption>Total utility strategies for each alternative and final rank</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Si*Pi</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kia</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kib</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kic</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rank</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.2460</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1847</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1797</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.7639</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.6699</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.8263</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2099</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2508</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8683</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8006</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.9639</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1724</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1432</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.7132</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.6031</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.6230</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2011</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2065</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8317</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.7388</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.3350</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2320</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2197</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.9598</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.8363</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22.9942</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p>The final rank of the 3PL alternatives is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>.</p>
      
        <fig id="fig_3">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>The final rank of the alternatives (3PL providers)</caption>
          <abstract/>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_9FwDX5SkM1MBTBhr.png"/>
        </fig>
      
      <p>When it comes to the ranking alternatives, it can be concluded that the best 3PL solution for performing the last-mile delivery was the 3PL-5 with a preference of 0.8363, followed by 3PL-2 (0.8006), 3PL-4 (0.7388), 3PL-1 (0.6699), and 3PL-3 (0.6031) respectively. To test the robustness of the methodology, a sensitivity analysis was proposed. The results of the sensitivity analysis are presented in the next subsection. </p>
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>4.1. Sensitivity analysis of the cocoso method</title>
          
          <p>The sensitivity analysis of the BWM-CoCoSo method is performed. The main objective of the sensitivity analysis was to examine the stability of the applied BWM-CoCoSo method. In other words, the method is stable if the change in weight of one criterion does not affect the final ranking of alternatives. If the weight of the <italic>n-th</italic> criterion changes by <italic>Δs</italic>, then the weight of other criteria changes by <italic>Δt </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_55">55</xref>].</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(15)</label>
              <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                <mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mi>
                <mrow data-mjx-texclass="ORD">
                  <mi mathvariant="normal">t</mi>
                </mrow>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mfrac>
                  <mrow>
                    <mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mi>
                    <mi>s</mi>
                    <mo>⋅</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>W</mi>
                      <mi>j</mi>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>W</mi>
                      <mi>s</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>−</mo>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </mrow>
                </mfrac>
              </math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>Based on the Eq. (10), the results of the sensitivity analysis are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_11">Table 11</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_11">
              <label>Table 11</label>
              <caption>Various weight variations of the “Distribution Cost” criterion</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Δ1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>W<sub>i</sub>, i=1,..,6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The Best-Ranked 3PL</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.40</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.5421</p><p>0.1021</p><p>0.0765</p><p>0.1021</p><p>0.1530</p><p>0.0243</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.0421</p><p>0.2135</p><p>0.1600</p><p>0.2135</p><p>0.3201</p><p>0.0508</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2421</p><p>0.1689</p><p>0.1266</p><p>0.1689</p><p>0.2533</p><p>0.0402</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.20</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3421</p><p>0.1466</p><p>0.1099</p><p>0.1466</p><p>0.2199</p><p>0.0349</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.30</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.4421</p><p>0.1243</p><p>0.0932</p><p>0.1243</p><p>0.1864</p><p>0.0296</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>The same procedure is applied to all the other criteria weights, and the obtained results of all other criteria are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_12">Table 12</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_12">
              <label>Table 12</label>
              <caption>Variations of all the other criteria weights</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Δ2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The Best-Ranked 3PL</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Δ3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The Best-Ranked 3PL</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Δ4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The Best-Ranked 3PL</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Δ5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>The Best-Ranked 3PL</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Δ6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="132"><p>The Best-Ranked 3PL</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.035</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.02</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.02</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="132"><p>3PL-5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.01</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.030</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.01</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-0.01</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="132"><p>3PL-5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.05</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="132"><p>3PL-5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.60</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="132"><p>3PL-5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3PL-5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.90</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" colwidth="132"><p>3PL-2</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>It can be concluded that the applied BWM-CoCoSo method is very strong and stable. The most stable criteria are the distribution cost, on-time delivery, and the flexibility of distribution, while the IT capability, the good cultural fit, and the customer satisfaction index leads to a change in ranking alternatives.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec disp-level="level2">
          
            <title>4.2. Comparative analysis</title>
          
          <p>After the CoCoSo method had been applied to rank the 3PL alternatives, a comparative analysis was performed. The results obtained by the BWM-CoCoSo method were compared to the other MCDM methods to check the reliability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_4">Figure 4</xref>). </p><p>The 3PL selection problem was solved by the two well-known MCDM methods such as WASPAS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">56</xref>], and ARAS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_57">57</xref>]. In the case of the BWM-CoCoSo method, the highest preference was assigned to 3PL-5, followed by 3PL-2. In addition, the ARAS method ranked 3PL-2 as the best possible solution, followed by 3PL-4 and 3PL-5. According to the WASPAS method, 3PL-4 was ranked the highest, 3PL-2 was ranked as the second best one, and 3PL-5 was ranked third, which is also a good position. In the end, after performing the comparative analysis, it can be stated that the BWM-CoCoSo method is effective and gives confidential results in a decision-making process.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_4">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>Comparative analysis with the WASPAS, TOPSIS, and ARAS</caption>
              <abstract/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2023/2/img_Y3R-_B8qk7SQtwoW.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>5. Managerial implications</title>
      <p>In city logistics, the 3PL providers for last-mile delivery should be one of the most essential factors. The quality of the last-mile delivery in cities will be depending on the 3PL companies, their strategies, organization, behavior, etc. In this regard, e-commerce companies should carefully monitor and assess the 3PL providers to make the last-mile delivery business more effective, sustainable, as well as up to date. Since there are many new 3PL players in the market, it is necessary to select the best one. Without using some of the multi-criteria decision-making techniques, the problem of 3PL selection for last-mile delivery can be harder, or wrong in many cases. It may badly affect not only the e-shop companies but also the final customers who are the most essential part of the last-mile delivery problem. In addition, the 3PL companies should follow future standards, trends, and procedures and offer a set of the best last-mile delivery solutions to their collaboration partners. This paper demonstrated a possible approach for ranking the 3PL providers that should be useful to managers in the e-commerce business in assessing the best 3PL collaboration partner. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="level1" sec-type="">
      <title>6. Conclusion</title>
      <p>This paper focused on the 3PL provider selection problem for sustainable last-mile delivery. The problem was applied to the real-life case study of the e-shop company from Belgrade, in the Republic of Serbia. Five 3PL providers were taken as possible alternatives for last-mile delivery. Those five 3PL providers were compared according to the six evaluation criteria; i.e., distribution cost, on-time delivery, flexibility of distribution, IT capability, good cultural fit, and customer satisfaction index. Two MCDM methods were used to assess the alternatives according to the mentioned criteria. The first one was the BWM used to obtain the importance of each criterion, while the second one was the CoCoSo method utilized to rank the 3PL providers. </p><p>When it comes to criteria weights, the BWM method evaluated the distribution cost (0.3421) as a criterion with the highest importance, followed by good cultural fit (0.2199), on-time delivery (0.1466), IT capability (0.1466), the flexibility of distribution (0.1099) and customer satisfaction index (0.0349), respectively. When the criteria weights were integrated with the CoCoSo method, the final rank of the alternatives was obtained: the highest importance was 3PL-5 (0.8363), followed by 3PL-2 (0.8006), 3PL-4 (0.7388), 3PL-1 (0.6699), and 3PL-3 (0.6031) respectively. The best suggestion for the e-shop company was to select the 3PL-5 to collaborate with while performing the last-mile delivery on the territory of Belgrade. In addition, the sensitivity analysis was performed to check the stability of the applied BWM-CoCoSo method. Namely, the criteria weights were varied to notice how the alternatives would be ranked. The change in criteria weights had shown a high level of stability since there were no dramatic changes in ranking alternatives. Nonetheless, the comparative analysis was performed to compare the results obtained by the BWM-CoCoSo method. The 3PL selection problem was solved by the WASPAS and ARAS methods, where both methods confirmed approximately the same order of the ranking alternatives.</p><p>This paper discloses some of its major contributions: <italic>i)</italic> For the first time, the BWM-CoCoSo methods were coupled to obtain the best 3PL provider for the e-shop company; <italic>ii) </italic>The BWM-CoCoSo method was applied to a real-life case study in Belgrade (the Republic of Serbia) which should be seen as a practical contribution. <italic>iii)</italic> The sensitivity analysis of the applied methods was performed, and the high stability of the results is demonstrated; <italic>iv) </italic>The comparative analysis was provided, and the presented results were highly reliable and confident. </p><p>Besides contributions, there were some limitations of this study: a) There have not been so many criteria considered in a decision-making process; However, the e-shop company’s management completely agreed on the selected criteria from the literature and there was no need for extending the list. b) Since the 3PL selection problem deals with uncertainty, the applied methods were not combined with the fuzzy sets. </p><p>The above-mentioned limitations should be overcome in the future directions of this paper. In the end, it can be concluded that the 3PL selection problem is a crucial and very serious one since they are the main connection between sellers and final customers. With the right selection of a 3PL partner, an e-shop company can have a bunch of benefits such as improved last-mile delivery, satisfied customers, saved costs, and time, while its focus may be on the core activities.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This research was part of the project “CK01000032-Sustainable Urban Mobility Plans, E-commerce, and Smart City Logistics.”</p>
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p></p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Lazarević</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Dobrodolac</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sustainability trends in the postal systems of last-mile delivery</article-title>
          <source>Perner’s Contacts</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.46585/pc.2020.1.1547</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Ewedairo</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Chhetri</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Jie</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Estimating transportation network impedance to last-mile delivery</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Logist. Manag.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>110-130</page-range>
          <fpage>110</fpage>
          <lpage>130</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1108/IJLM-10-2016-0247</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>H. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Na</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Kweon</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Park</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization and design for last mile logistics: A review of the state of the art and future directions</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Sci.</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>118-118</page-range>
          <fpage>118</fpage>
          <lpage>118</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/app12010118</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Sustainable and Smart Mobility Strategy – putting European transport on track for the future, Brussels, Belgium</article-title>
          <source>European Commission</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <uri>https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:52020DC0789</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>T. U.</given-names>
              <surname>Daim</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Udbye</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Balasubramanian</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Use of analytic hierarchy process (AHP) for selection of 3PL providers</article-title>
          <source>J Manuf.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>28-51</page-range>
          <fpage>28</fpage>
          <lpage>51</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1108/17410381311287472</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Y. M.</given-names>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
              <surname>Goan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P. N.</given-names>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Selection process in logistics outsourcing–a view from third party logistics provider</article-title>
          <source>Prod. Plan. Control</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>308-324</page-range>
          <fpage>308</fpage>
          <lpage>324</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09537287.2010.498611</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
              <surname>Bayazit</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Karpak</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Selection of a third-party logistics service provider for an aerospace company: An analytical decision aiding approach</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Logist. Syst. Manag.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>382-404</page-range>
          <fpage>382</fpage>
          <lpage>404</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1504/IJLSM.2013.054898</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
              <surname>Hwang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Yoon</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title/>
          <source>Multiple Attribute Decision Making: Methods and Applications</source>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
              <surname>Qureshi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An integrated model to identify and classify the key criteria and their role in the assessment of 3PL services providers</article-title>
          <source>Asia Pac. J. Mark. Logist.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>227-249</page-range>
          <fpage>227</fpage>
          <lpage>249</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1108/13555850810864579</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Rajesh</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A fuzzy AHP and TOPSIS methodology to evaluate 3PL in a supply chain</article-title>
          <source>J. Model. Manage.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>287-303</page-range>
          <fpage>287</fpage>
          <lpage>303</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1108/17465661211283287</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Sachdeva</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Bhardwaj</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A framework for selection of logistics outsourcing partner in uncertain environment using TOPSIS</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Ind. Syst. Eng.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>223-242</page-range>
          <fpage>223</fpage>
          <lpage>242</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.1504/IJISE.2012.048862</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Akman</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Baynal</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Logistics service provider selection through an integrated fuzzy multicriteria decision making approach</article-title>
          <source>J. Ind. Eng.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>2014</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1155/2014/794918</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">794918</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Vijayvargiya</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Dey</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An analytical approach for selection of a logistics provider</article-title>
          <source>Manage. Decis.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>403-418</page-range>
          <fpage>403</fpage>
          <lpage>418</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1108/00251741011037774</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Göl</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Çatay</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Third-party logistics provider selection: insights from a Turkish automotive company</article-title>
          <source>Supply Chain Manage. Int. J.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>379-384</page-range>
          <fpage>379</fpage>
          <lpage>384</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1108/13598540710826290</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Govindan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. C.</given-names>
              <surname>Grigore</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Kannan</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Rranking of third-party logistics provider using Fuzzy-Electre II</article-title>
          <source/>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>
          <conf-name>the 40th International Conference on Computers &amp; Industrial Engineering, Awaji</conf-name>
          <conf-acronym/>
          <conf-loc>Japan</conf-loc>
          <conf-date>2010</conf-date>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>1-5</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1109/iccie.2010.5668366.</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
              <surname>Kilincci</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
              <surname>Onal</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fuzzy AHP approach for supplier selection in a washing machine company</article-title>
          <source>Expert Syst. Appl.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <page-range>9656-9664</page-range>
          <fpage>9656</fpage>
          <lpage>9664</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eswa.2011.01.159</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Arikan</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An interactive solution approach for multiple-objective supplier selection problem with fuzzy parameters</article-title>
          <source>J. Intell. Manuf.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>989-998</page-range>
          <fpage>989</fpage>
          <lpage>998</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10845-013-0782-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>V. R.</given-names>
              <surname>Laptate</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fuzzy modified TOPSIS for supplier selection problem in supply chain management</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Innov. Res. Comput. Sci. Technol.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>22-28</page-range>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Jayant</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Application of AHP-VIKOR hybrid MCDM approach for 3pl selection: A case study</article-title>
          <source>ICAET</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>2015</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>4-11</page-range>
          <fpage>4</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Ö. F.</given-names>
              <surname>Gürcan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>İ.</given-names>
              <surname>Yazıcı</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Ö. F.</given-names>
              <surname>Beyca</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Ç. Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Arslan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Eldemir</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Third Party Logistics (3PL) provider selection with AHP application</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Soc. Behav. Sci.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>235</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>226-234</page-range>
          <fpage>226</fpage>
          <lpage>234</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sbspro.2016.11.018</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Rezaeisaray</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Ebrahimnejad</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Khalili-Damghani</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel hybrid MCDM approach for outsourcing supplier selection</article-title>
          <source>J. Model Manag.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>536-559</page-range>
          <fpage>536</fpage>
          <lpage>559</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1108/jm2-06-2014-0045</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>D. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Sen</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Datta</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Mahapatra</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A TODIM-based decision support framework for g-resilient supplier selection in fuzzy environment</article-title>
          <source>Asia Pac. J. Oper Res.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1142/s0217595916500330</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1650033</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Garside</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T. E.</given-names>
              <surname>Saputro</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Evaluation and selection of 3PL provider using fuzzy AHP and grey TOPSIS in group decision making</article-title>
          <source/>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>AIP</publisher-name>
          <conf-name>AIP Conference Proceedings, Industrial and Manufacturing Engineering Conference</conf-name>
          <conf-acronym>mimec2017</conf-acronym>
          <conf-loc>Miri, Malaysia</conf-loc>
          <conf-date>December 6-8, 2017</conf-date>
          <year>2017</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5010673.</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Gunasekaran</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Third party logistics (3PL) selection for cold chain management: a fuzzy AHP and fuzzy TOPSIS approach</article-title>
          <source>Ann. Oper Res.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>267</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>531-553</page-range>
          <fpage>531</fpage>
          <lpage>553</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10479-017-2591-3</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
              <surname>Raut</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Kharat</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Kamble</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C. S.</given-names>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sustainable evaluation &amp;amp; selection of potential third-party logistics providers (3PL): An Integrated MCDM Approach</article-title>
          <source>Benchmarking: Int J.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>76-97</page-range>
          <fpage>76</fpage>
          <lpage>97</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1108/BIJ-05-2016-0065</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Sremac</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Ž.</given-names>
              <surname>Stević</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Pamučar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Arsić</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
              <surname>Matić</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of a third-party logistics (3PL) Provider using a rough SWARA-WASPAS model based on a new rough dombi aggregator</article-title>
          <source>Symmetry.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/sym10080305</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
              <surname>Zarbakhshnia</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
              <surname>Govindan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
              <surname>Soleimani</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel hybrid multiple attribute decision-making approach for outsourcing sustainable reverse logistics</article-title>
          <source>J. Clean Prod.</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>242</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2019.118461</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">118464</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Bianchini</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>3PL provider selection by AHP and TOPSIS methodology</article-title>
          <source>Benchmarking: Int J.</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>235-252</page-range>
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          <lpage>252</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1108/BIJ-08-2016-0125</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Pamučar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Kar</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation and selection of third-party logistics provider under sustainability perspectives: An interval valued fuzzy-rough approach</article-title>
          <source>Ann. Oper Res.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>293</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>669-714</page-range>
          <fpage>669</fpage>
          <lpage>714</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10479-019-03501-x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Paché</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Aguezzoul</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An AHP-ELECTRE I approach for 3PL-provider selection</article-title>
          <source>Int J. Transp Econ.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>2020</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>37-50</page-range>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
              <surname>Özcan</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Ahıskalı</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>3PL service provider selection with a goal programming model supported with multicriteria decision making approaches</article-title>
          <source>Gazi U. J Sci.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>413-427</page-range>
          <fpage>413</fpage>
          <lpage>427</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.35378/gujs.552070</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Ulutas</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Topal</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A new hybrid model based on rough stepwise weight assessment ratio analysis for third-party logistics selection</article-title>
          <source>Soft Comput.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>2021-2032</page-range>
          <fpage>2021</fpage>
          <lpage>2032</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00500-021-06374-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Ulutas</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A grey hybrid model to select the optimal third-party logistics provider</article-title>
          <source>S Afr. J. Ind Eng.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>171-181</page-range>
          <fpage>171</fpage>
          <lpage>181</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://dx.doi.org/10.7166/32-1-2126</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Ortega</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Sarbast</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>János</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Tamás</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Palaguachi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Paguay</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Using Best Worst Method for Sustainable Park and Ride Facility Location</article-title>
          <source>Sus.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/su122310083</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10083</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Pamučar</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Ecer</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Cirovic</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
              <surname>Arlasheedi</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Application of Improved Best Worst Method (BWM) in Real-World Problems</article-title>
          <source>Mathematics.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <page-range>1342-1342</page-range>
          <fpage>1342</fpage>
          <lpage>1342</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/math8081342</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J. L.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Y. N.</given-names>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C. H.</given-names>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F. Y.</given-names>
              <surname>He</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>B. Y.</given-names>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F. T.</given-names>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A geographical information system based multi-criteria decision-making approach for location analysis and evaluation of urban photovoltaic charging station: A case study in Beijing</article-title>
          <source>Energ Convers. Manage.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>205</volume>
          <issue>0</issue>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enconman.2019.112340</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Moslem</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Campisi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Szmelter-Jarosz</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Duleba</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>K. M.</given-names>
              <surname>Nahiduzzaman</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
              <surname>Tesoriere</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Best-Worst Method for Modelling Mobility Choice after COVID-19: Evidence from Italy</article-title>
          <source>Sus.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <page-range>6824-6824</page-range>
          <fpage>6824</fpage>
          <lpage>6824</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/su12176824</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Kant</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Sustainable Urban Freight Strategies for Jaipur City, India</article-title>
          <source>Smart and Sustainable Supply Chain and Logistics–Trends, Challenges</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>Methods and Best Practices</publisher-name>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>153-163</page-range>
          <fpage>153</fpage>
          <lpage>163</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-61947-3_10</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Rashid</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Best–worst method for robot selection</article-title>
          <source>Soft Comput.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>563-583</page-range>
          <fpage>563</fpage>
          <lpage>583</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00500-020-05169-z</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Mahmoudi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>X. M.</given-names>
              <surname>Mi</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H. C.</given-names>
              <surname>Liao</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
              <surname>Feylizadeh</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Turskis</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Grey Best-Worst Method for Multiple Experts Multiple Criteria Decision Making Under Uncertainty</article-title>
          <source>Informatica</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>331-357</page-range>
          <fpage>331</fpage>
          <lpage>357</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.15388/20-INFOR409</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Özmen</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>E. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Aydoğan</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Robust multi-criteria decision-making methodology for real life logistics center location problem</article-title>
          <source>Artif Intell Rev</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>725-751</page-range>
          <fpage>725</fpage>
          <lpage>751</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10462-019-09763-y</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Rodríguez-Gutiérrez</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M. D.</given-names>
              <surname>Guerrero-Baena</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Luque-Vílchez</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Castilla-Polo</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An approach to using the best-worst method for supporting sustainability reporting decision-making in SME</article-title>
          <source>J. Environ. Plann. Man.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>2618-2640</page-range>
          <fpage>2618</fpage>
          <lpage>2640</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1080/09640568.2021.1876003</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Duleba</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
              <surname>Moslem</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Esztergár-Kiss</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Estimating commuting modal split by using the Best-Worst Method</article-title>
          <source>Eur. Transp. Res. Rev.</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>1-12</page-range>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12544-021-00489-z</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Guler</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
              <surname>Yomralioglu</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Bicycle station and lane location selection using open-source GIS technology</article-title>
          <source>Open-Source Geospatial Science for Urban Studies, Lecture Notes in Intelligent Transportation and Infrastructure, Springer</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>Cham</publisher-name>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>9-36</page-range>
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <lpage>36</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-58232-6_2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Yazdani</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>Intelligent decision-making tools in manufacturing technology selection</article-title>
          <source>Futuristic Composites, Singapore</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>113-126</page-range>
          <fpage>113</fpage>
          <lpage>126</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>T. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Biswas</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Ž.</given-names>
              <surname>Stević</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Yazdani</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>An integrated methodology for evaluation of electric vehicles under sustainable automotive environment</article-title>
          <source>Advanced Multi-Criteria Decision Making for Addressing Complex Sustainability Issues</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>CRC press</publisher-name>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume/>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>41-62</page-range>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Wen</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>H. C.</given-names>
              <surname>Liao</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>E. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Zavadskas</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Al-Barakati</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Selection third-party logistics service providers in supply chain finance by ahesitant fuzzy linguistic combined compromise solution method</article-title>
          <source>Econ. Res-Ekon. Istraz.</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>4033-4058</page-range>
          <fpage>4033</fpage>
          <lpage>4058</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1080/1331677X.2019.1678502</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Ecer</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
              <surname>Pamucar</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sustainable supplier selection: A novel integrated fuzzy best worst method (F-BWM) and fuzzy CoCoSo with Bonferroni (CoCoSo'B) multi-criteria model</article-title>
          <source>J. Clean. Prod.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>266</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range/>
          <fpage/>
          <lpage/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.121981</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">121981</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>S. H.</given-names>
              <surname>Zolfani</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Yazdani</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Ebadi Torkayesh</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Derakhti</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Application of a gray-based decision support framework for location selection of a temporary hospital during COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>
          <source>Symmetry</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>886-886</page-range>
          <fpage>886</fpage>
          <lpage>886</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3390/sym12060886</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Ulutaş</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>C. B.</given-names>
              <surname>Karakuş</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Topal</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Location selection for logistics center with fuzzy SWARA and CoCoSo methods</article-title>
          <source>J. Intell. Fuzzy Syst.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>4693-4709</page-range>
          <fpage>4693</fpage>
          <lpage>4709</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3233/JIFS-191400</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
              <surname>Peng</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
              <surname>Smarandache</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A decision-making framework for china’s rare earth industry security evaluation by neutrosophic soft CoCoSo method</article-title>
          <source>J. Intell. Fuzzy Syst.</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <page-range>7571-7585</page-range>
          <fpage>7571</fpage>
          <lpage>7585</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3233/JIFS-200847</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Popović</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An MCDM approach for personnel selection using the CoCoSo method</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Process Management New Technologies</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>78-88</page-range>
          <fpage>78</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5937/jouproman2103078P</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Rezaei</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Best-worst multi-criteria decision-making method</article-title>
          <source>Omega</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>49-57</page-range>
          <fpage>49</fpage>
          <lpage>57</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.omega.2014.11.009</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
              <surname>Yazdani</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
              <surname>Zarate</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
              <surname>Kazimieras Zavadskas</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Turskis</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A combined compromise solution (CoCoSo) method for multi-criteria decision-making problems</article-title>
          <source>Manage. Decis.</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <page-range>2501-2519</page-range>
          <fpage>2501</fpage>
          <lpage>2519</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1108/MD-05-2017-0458</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Alinezhad</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Amini</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sensitivity analysis of TOPSIS technique: the results of change in the weight of one attribute on the final ranking of alternatives</article-title>
          <source>J. Optim. Ind. Eng.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>23-28</page-range>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_56">
        <label>56.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
              <surname>Alinezhad</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
              <surname>Khalili</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor"/>
          <article-title>WASPAS method</article-title>
          <source>New Methods and Applications in Multiple Attribute Decision Making, International Series in Operations Research &amp; Management Science, Springer</source>
          <publisher-loc/>
          <publisher-name>Cham</publisher-name>
          <year>2019</year>
          <volume>2019</volume>
          <issue/>
          <page-range>93-98</page-range>
          <fpage>93</fpage>
          <lpage>98</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-15009-9_13</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_57">
        <label>57.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <given-names>E. K.</given-names>
              <surname>Zavadskas</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
              <surname>Turskis</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A new additive ratio assessment (ARAS) method in multi-criteria decision-making</article-title>
          <source>Technol. Econ. Dev. Eco.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <page-range>159-172</page-range>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>172</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.3846/tede.2010.10</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id"/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>