<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCGIRM</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Corporate Governance, Insurance, and Risk Management</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Corp. Gov. Insur. Risk Manag.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JCGIRM</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2757-0983</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-1923</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-N9hCG0DTdEvcc3c6gOuVBe0ipuMyVMMz</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jcgirm110301</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Role of Shared Strategic Values in Achieving Sustainable Success in Global Logistics Enterprises</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7189-7551</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Atasever</surname>
            <given-names>Mesut</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>mesut.atasever@usak.edu.tr</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Logistics Management, Faculty of Applied Sciences, Uşak University, 64000 Uşak, Türkiye</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>09</month>
        <year>2024</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>148</fpage>
      <lpage>159</lpage>
      <page-range>148-159</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>07</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>09</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2024</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2024 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2024</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Strategic values play a pivotal role in the long-term success of logistics enterprises, influencing interactions with customers, employees, and stakeholders, and driving sustainable outcomes. In the context of the global logistics sector, the identification and alignment of strategic values are essential for maintaining competitive advantage and fostering resilience. This study systematically investigates the strategic values of the world’s 50 leading logistics companies, focusing on those most strongly associated with sustainable success. Using a qualitative approach, content analysis was employed to evaluate and interpret the strategic documents of these enterprises, revealing key values that contribute significantly to sustainability. Among the values identified, reliability, customer-centricity, and operational efficiency were found to be most influential in ensuring both operational and strategic sustainability. These values were consistently embedded within corporate practices, shaping decision-making processes, stakeholder engagement, and long-term growth strategies. The findings indicate that the integration of sustainability as a core strategic value is critical for enduring success in an increasingly competitive and environmentally conscious market. The results provide valuable insights for both academics and practitioners, offering a framework for logistics companies to refine their strategic management practices and align their operations with sustainable development goals. By highlighting the strategic values that underpin sustainable growth, this study contributes to the understanding of how logistics enterprises can navigate the complex challenges of the modern business environment.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Logistics sector</kwd>
        <kwd>Strategic values</kwd>
        <kwd>Sustainability</kwd>
        <kwd>Strategic management</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="1"/>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <ref-count count="48"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Today, it is widely accepted that not only financial indicators but also the values of a business play a significant role in its success. This is particularly true in service-oriented sectors like logistics, where the relationships between businesses and their customers, employees, and stakeholders directly influence business outcomes. For this reason, logistics companies must clearly express and adhere to their values.</p><p>In the logistics sector, values are critical in ensuring customer satisfaction. Logistics services involve key operations such as the safe transportation and timely delivery of products. The reliability, relationships, and responsibilities of logistics companies toward their customers are directly tied to the values they uphold. By acting in alignment with these values, logistics businesses can enhance customer satisfaction, build loyalty, and attract new customers.</p><p>Values also play a vital role in employee motivation and loyalty. Companies that consistently act according to their values foster a positive work environment, leading to improved employee attitudes and behaviors. Employees who internalize these values contribute to the achievement of the company’s goals.</p><p>In essence, values are principles that reflect a company’s culture, guiding its direction and fostering a shared understanding among employees. They are crucial in supporting strategic goals, increasing customer satisfaction, and ensuring business sustainability. Clearly communicating these values helps align the workforce and ensures everyone is working toward the same objectives, ultimately boosting business success.</p><p>Moreover, values play a key role in fostering customer trust and loyalty. When customers recognize and understand the values of a business, they gain insight into how the company operates, which in turn strengthens trust and loyalty.</p><p>Strategic values are particularly important for logistics companies as they manage complex logistics networks to meet customer needs. These values are integral to the success of the business, ensuring that customer expectations are met and that operations run smoothly. By aligning their strategic values with customer needs, logistics businesses can enhance coordination and communication within the organization, contributing to overall success.</p><p>Additionally, strategic values impact all stakeholders, including customers, employees, shareholders, suppliers, and local communities. By clearly articulating these values, businesses demonstrate their guiding principles, operational standards, and long-term vision. This builds trust and loyalty, which are crucial for sustainability and competitive advantage.</p><p>In terms of sustainability, strategic values help logistics companies integrate environmental, economic, and social considerations. In the short term, these values can reduce costs through energy and resource efficiency while decreasing environmental impact. In the long run, they are essential for maintaining competitive advantage, meeting rising customer expectations, and ensuring long-term business success.</p><p>Strategic values, therefore, play a critical role in reducing costs, fostering a competitive edge, meeting customer demands, and ensuring sustainability for logistics enterprises, both in the short and long term.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. The value concept and strategic value: significance of expression</title>
      <p>Value is a measurable or immeasurable concept attributed to or derived from something, based on its properties that are considered important or useful. In other words, it expresses how useful or desirable something is. Value is “the recognition of something as important or useful based on its measurable or immeasurable properties attributed to or derived from it” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Kotler &amp;amp; Keller, 2016</xref>). Value is “a concept measured by what is considered important or useful by users at a particular time and place” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">Woodruff, 1997</xref>).</p><p>Strategic value or values are the key principles and beliefs that an organization sets for its activities and decisions. These values help guide the organization’s culture, management style, business strategies, customer focus, and employee behavior. Strategic values are “the key principles and beliefs that an organization determines about how it will manage its business, customers and employees, and how it will act while creating material and moral values” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Kotler &amp;amp; Keller, 2016</xref>). Strategic values “express the fundamental principles and beliefs that affect an organization’s key decisions, activities and practices” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Cameron &amp;amp; Quinn, 2011</xref>).</p><p>Identifying and expressing strategic values is very important to the success of an organization. Strategic values are key principles and beliefs that reflect the organization’s culture, management style and business strategies. These values guide the organization’s activities, goals and business decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Gupta et al., 2020</xref>). Clearly articulating the organization’s strategic values helps all employees and stakeholders (customers, suppliers, investors, etc.) understand the organization’s values. In this way, they guide the behavior styles, business decisions and practices of the people they work with in order to achieve the goals of the organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Elçi et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>Expressing strategic values is also important for maintaining the organization’s reputation. If the values of the organization are expressed correctly, the trust of employees and stakeholders is gained, and the reputation of the organization increases. Therefore, determining and clearly articulating the strategic values of organizations is an important part of a successful strategic planning process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Bryson, 2018</xref>).</p><p>Business managers and employees should act in accordance with strategic values. The strategic values of the enterprise determine the long-term goals and mission of the enterprise and guide the management of the operations of the enterprise. Business managers and employees should embrace these strategic values and act in accordance with these values in their daily business activities. Thus, the business achieves its strategic goals and becomes successful (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Elçi et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>The expression of strategic values should reflect the goals and objectives of the organization. Therefore, it needs to be carefully considered in the process of expressing strategic values. First, strategic values need to be aligned with the culture of the organization. This should be based on the organization’s mission, vision, and historical background. Second, strategic values should be clear and understandable. This means that language should be used that can be easily understood by all employees. In addition, measurability of strategic values is important for monitoring the performance of the organization. Finally, it should be noted that strategic values should be reviewed from time to time and updated when necessary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">Kotler et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>Values are principles that must be followed on a long-term basis. For this reason, values must be compatible with the mission, vision, and strategic goals of the enterprise. However, when the goals and scope of the business change, the values can be changed accordingly. However, frequent change of values can weaken employees’ commitment to the values of the business and undermine the credibility of the business (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">Narver &amp;amp; Slater, 1990</xref>). It is seen that businesses change their strategic values from time to time. There can be many reasons for this, for example, change in market conditions. Businesses can change their strategic values to adapt to the competitive conditions in the market. For example, due to the COVID-19 pandemic, many businesses have accelerated their digitalization strategies and started offering more online services to their customers. The emergence of new opportunities: Businesses can change their strategic values to enter new markets or product/service areas. For example, if an automaker decides to enter the electric vehicle market, it may place more emphasis on environmentally friendly practices in its strategic values. Management changes: When the top managers of the businesses change, it is possible for the new managers to change the strategic values. For example, a new CEO might put more emphasis on the business’s customer-centric strategy.</p><p>As an example, Apple Inc. The company made a major shift in its strategic values in 1997 with the return of CEO Steve Jobs to the company. Jobs adopted the company’s strategy of focusing by narrowing its product line and increasing the value of the company by placing more emphasis on customer experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">Yoffie &amp;amp; Rossano, 2012</xref>)</p><p>It is not correct to announce the principles that will not be followed as values. Values are the principles that are in line with the mission, vision, and strategic goals of the enterprise and that affect the behavior of the employees in a positive way. Non-compliance principles, on the other hand, mean behaviors contrary to the ethical values and legal obligations of the enterprise. For this reason, the determination of the principles that will not be followed and the disciplinary measures to be taken in case of violation of these principles should be clearly stated. However, the values of the business should not be built on the opposite of principles that will not be followed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Ferrell et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Strategic values should be aligned with the goals, vision, mission, and policies of the businesses. The goals, visions, and missions of businesses are determined by various goals and objectives, such as achieving certain goals, meeting customer expectations, and doing sustainable business. The strategic values of the enterprises determine the ways, principles, attitudes, and behaviors to be followed to achieve these goals. The compatibility of strategic values with the policies of the business ensures that all business activities move towards a common direction and helps the business reach its goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">David, 2017</xref>).</p><p>Although different terms such as strategic values, values of the enterprise, value judgments of the enterprise, and culture of the enterprise are used in the business literature, these terms generally have similar meanings. However, in some cases the usage of the terms may differ. For example, the culture of the business is a concept that encompasses the strategic values of the business and all business activities. Therefore, the use and meaning of the terms may vary depending on the context, the characteristics of the business, and its unwritten rules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">de Wit &amp;amp; Meyer, 2014</xref>).</p><p>Strategic value statements form the basis of a business’s strategies to achieve its long-term goals and vision. Strategic value statements reflect the culture, values, and goals of the business and guide the business’s stakeholders on how to act.</p><p>When associated with other strategic statements, strategic value statements are part of the business’s strategic plan. Strategic value statements should be aligned with other strategic statements used to identify the strategic goals and objectives of the business (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Hoskisson et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>For example, a business may identify increasing customer satisfaction and improving business performance among its strategic goals. To achieve these goals, the business can set strategies, and these strategies must be aligned with the business’s strategic value statements.</p><p>Values are the basic principles that determine the priorities, beliefs and behaviors of businesses. Therefore, it is important that values are clearly articulated within the business. Businesses can use different methods to express their values.</p><p>For example, businesses can prepare a “statement of value” that clearly articulates their value. A value statement is a document containing the values, vision and mission of the business and can be a guiding resource for both employees and customers. Also, businesses can use different tools to express their values symbolically. For example, symbols that reflect values can be used in the company’s logo or other visual materials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Cameron &amp;amp; Quinn, 2011</xref>).</p><p>Values are commitments that must be aligned with business strategies, business policies, and business objectives as determinants of a business’s culture, thoughts, attitudes, and behaviors. Therefore, values can be thought of as a kind of promise, and the business is obliged to keep these promises (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">Rokeach, 1973</xref>).</p><p>However, in some cases the realization of the values may be difficult or impossible. In these cases, it is recommended that the business not make unfulfilled promises or reconsider its values. For example, while the value of a business is to always provide 100% customer satisfaction to its customers, this may not always be realistic. However, in this case, the business can stay true to its values by approaching its customers honestly, making efforts to solve problems, and trying to keep customer satisfaction at the highest level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Alavifard, 2019</xref>).</p><p>Value statements can often be expressed as a legacy from the business’s past or an ideal vision that stems from the goals it wants to achieve in the future. Therefore, there can be statements that are both based on past experiences and focused on future goals. For example, the value of a logistics business may be based on both its past performance and its future goals, such as the reliability and prompt services it provides to its customers, as well as its commitment to fulfilling its environmental responsibilities for a sustainable world. However, the values of each business are unique and depend on the vision, mission, and strategic goals of the business. Thus, a business must decide for itself what time periods to express its values.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Logistics sector and strategic values</title>
      <p>Logistics is an activity that includes planning, implementation, and control processes at all stages from the production of a product to its delivery to the end user. The aim of this activity is to ensure that the products are delivered to the customers at the right time, at the right place, in the right quantity, and with the right quality. The concept of logistics has become an important competitive element for businesses today, and many businesses around the world attach importance to logistics activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">Özçelik, 2015</xref>).</p><p>Third Party Logistics (3PL) is the use of the services of a third-party logistics company to manage the movement of products within the supply chain. 3PL logistics services undertake part or all of the supply chain activities, such as storing, processing, distributing, and delivering the products of the manufacturers. These services include various activities such as storage, transportation, inventory management, packaging, assembly, order processing, and customer service.</p><p>The logistics industry has common values such as customer satisfaction, on-time delivery, and operational excellence. However, every logistics business has its own unique values, and these values can be aligned with the mission, vision, and strategic goals of the business. For example, one logistics business may have priority values about sustainability, while another business may adopt a technology-driven value system. Therefore, values in logistics enterprises may be similar to those of enterprises in other sectors but may differ in line with the characteristics and goals of each enterprise.</p><p>The logistics industry is a sector that manages the physical movement of goods and services in the supply chain. The strategic values between it and other sectors may differ. For example, for the retail sector, logistics strategies may focus on customer satisfaction and logistics costs, while for the manufacturing sector, logistics strategies may focus on supply chain efficiency, product quality, and production planning.</p><p>The logistics industry cooperates with other industries to help ensure the smooth movement of goods and services at every stage of the supply chain. Therefore, the strategic value of the logistics industry depends on a number of factors, such as working with other industries to increase customer satisfaction, reduce inventory costs, shorten delivery times, increase environmental sustainability, and provide a competitive advantage.</p><p>Therefore, strategic values for the logistics sector may vary depending on its interaction with other sectors and customer needs. Developing cooperation between the logistics industry and other industries can help increase strategic values.</p><p>Strategic values in logistics are critical elements for the success and competitive advantage of the business. Based on the field of activity, these values may include (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Christopher, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">Lambert &amp;amp; Cooper, 2000</xref>).</p><p>- Fast and reliable supply chain management</p><p>- Cost-effectiveness and efficiency</p><p>- Best customer service delivery</p><p>- Stock management and inventory control</p><p>- Optimizing the logistics network</p><p>- Sustainability of logistics activities and reduction of environmental impacts</p><p>- Use of logistics technologies and innovation</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Methodology</title>
      <p>This study employed a qualitative research method, which is commonly used in the social sciences. Qualitative research allows the researcher to examine data in a descriptive and interpretative manner, providing detailed and in-depth insights into the subject matter. In qualitative research, data can be collected both verbally and in writing, and it may be analyzed in either a structured or unstructured way. This method enables researchers to gain a deep understanding of human behavior, beliefs, cultural norms, and other related issues.</p><p>The process of qualitative analysis typically follows a structured set of steps:</p><p>Data Collection and Recording: This can be achieved through interviews, observations, or other methods of data collection.</p><p>Data Structuring: Collected data is categorized and classified into specific themes.</p><p>Data Analysis: The categorized data is interpreted to extract key meanings.</p><p>Presentation of Results: The results are shared through reports, articles, or other academic publications.</p><p>This approach helps researchers gain a more nuanced understanding of their subjects. Additionally, qualitative research can be combined with quantitative methods for a more comprehensive analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Creswell &amp;amp; Clark, 2017</xref>).</p><p>In this study, content analysis, a commonly-used qualitative method, was employed to analyze the strategic values of logistics companies. Content analysis allows researchers to systematically examine and interpret textual data, identifying key themes, patterns, and concepts. This method is especially useful for analyzing textual data from interviews, focus groups, surveys, journals, and other sources.</p><p>Content analysis helps researchers to identify recurring themes, keywords, and central ideas in the texts, thus making data analysis more systematic. It is particularly useful in studies that explore social issues, enabling researchers to better understand them by examining data from various sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Krippendorff, 2018</xref>).</p><p>There are several types of content analysis, and the most common ones used in this study are as follows:</p><p>Content Coding: Text or document topics, themes, or concepts are coded for numerical analysis.</p><p>Frequency Analysis: The frequency of specific words or phrases in a text is analyzed.</p><p>Thematic Analysis: This analysis identifies key themes and examines how they relate to each other.</p><p>Content Analytics: This approach examines the overall meaning of a text and its intended message, often using linguistic tools to understand what the text conveys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Krippendorff, 2018</xref>).</p><p>When interpreting the value statements of businesses through content analysis, it is essential to first understand the meaning of these statements, followed by analyzing factors such as frequency, intensity, and emphasis. This helps to reveal how the values of a business are perceived and which messages are most prominent.</p><p>For instance, if a logistics company frequently emphasizes customer satisfaction and service quality in its value statements, it can be inferred that the company is customer-oriented and places a high priority on delivering quality services. Such analyses can provide valuable insights into how different stakeholders perceive a company’s values, and they can inform the company’s strategic decision-making.</p><p>The list of the 50 most successful logistics companies used in this study is sourced from Armstrong &amp;amp; Associates, an internationally recognized leader in Third Party Logistics (3PL) market research. Armstrong &amp;amp; Associates, Inc. (A&amp;amp;A) was established in 1980 and has since become a key information resource for the 3PL market, providing research and consulting services for companies outsourcing logistics functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">3PL Central, 2024</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Findings and content analysis</title>
      <p>The findings highlight the core strategic values driving success in the logistics sector, including customer focus, sustainability, innovation, and operational excellence. Customer satisfaction emerges as the most prominent value, emphasizing its critical role in building competitive advantage. Sustainability and environmentally friendly practices, widely adopted by leading companies, reflect the industry's commitment to reducing environmental impact and ensuring long-term viability. Additionally, innovation and technological advancements are recognized as pivotal for enhancing service quality and efficiency. The analysis underscores how these values interrelate, such as the synergy between sustainability and innovation or the alignment of operational excellence with efficiency, demonstrating a cohesive strategic framework that enables logistics firms to thrive in a competitive global market. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> presents the gross logistics revenue for companies ranked A&amp;amp;A, provided by third-party logistics service providers.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Third-party logistics provider and gross logistics revue for A&amp;amp;A rank</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td><p>A&amp;amp;amp;A Rank</p></td><td><p>Third Party Logistics (3PL) Provider</p></td><td><p>Gross Logistics Revenue (US$ Millions)*</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>1</p></td><td><p>Kuehne + Nagel Ltd. </p></td><td><p>40,838</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>2</p></td><td><p>DHL Supply Chain &amp;amp;amp; Global Forwarding Inc. </p></td><td><p>37,707</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>DSV Co. </p></td><td><p>28,901</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>DB Schenker Ltd. </p></td><td><p>27,648</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>C.H. Robinson Inc. </p></td><td><p>22,355</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>6</p></td><td><p>Sinotrans Ltd.</p></td><td><p>19,097</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>7</p></td><td><p>Nippon Express Co. </p></td><td><p>18,612</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>8</p></td><td><p>Expeditors Inc.</p></td><td><p>16,524</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>9</p></td><td><p>UPS Supply Chain Solutions Ltd.</p></td><td><p>14,639</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>10</p></td><td><p>CEVA Logistics Co. </p></td><td><p>12,000</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>11</p></td><td><p>GEODIS Ltd. </p></td><td><p>11.9</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>12</p></td><td><p>J.B. Hunt Inc. </p></td><td><p>11,412</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>13</p></td><td><p>Kerry Logistics Ltd.</p></td><td><p>10,516</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>14</p></td><td><p>Maersk Logistics Co. </p></td><td><p>9.83</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>15</p></td><td><p>Kintetsu World Express Ltd. </p></td><td><p>9.01</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>16</p></td><td><p>XPO Logistics Inc.</p></td><td><p>8,907</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>17</p></td><td><p>DACHSER Ltd. </p></td><td><p>8,333</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>18</p></td><td><p>GXO Logistics Co. </p></td><td><p>7.94</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>19</p></td><td><p>Total Quality Logistics Ltd. </p></td><td><p>7,857</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>20</p></td><td><p>Yusen Logistics Inc. </p></td><td><p>7,788</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>21</p></td><td><p>CJ Logistics Ltd. </p></td><td><p>7.7</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>22</p></td><td><p>LX Pantos Co. </p></td><td><p>6,541</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>23</p></td><td><p>Uber Freight Ltd. </p></td><td><p>6.44</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>24</p></td><td><p>Toll Group Inc. </p></td><td><p>6.3</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>25</p></td><td><p>Hitachi Transport System Co.</p></td><td><p>5,995</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>26</p></td><td><p>Transportation Insight Ltd.</p></td><td><p>5.8</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>27</p></td><td><p>Bollore Logistics Inc. </p></td><td><p>5,701</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>28</p></td><td><p>GEFCO Ltd. </p></td><td><p>4,953</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>29</p></td><td><p>Hellmann Worldwide Logistics Co. </p></td><td><p>4,718</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>30</p></td><td><p>Ryder Supply Chain Solutions Inc.</p></td><td><p>4,612</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>31</p></td><td><p>Worldwide Express Ltd. </p></td><td><p>4,600</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>32</p></td><td><p>Burris Logistics Co. </p></td><td><p>4,300</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>33</p></td><td><p>Hub Group Inc. </p></td><td><p>4,232</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>34</p></td><td><p>SAIC Angi Logistics Ltd. </p></td><td><p>4,183</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>35</p></td><td><p>AWOT Global Logistics Group Inc.</p></td><td><p>4,058</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>36</p></td><td><p>Lineage Logistics Ltd. </p></td><td><p>4,000</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>37</p></td><td><p>JD Logistics Co. </p></td><td><p>3,946</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>38</p></td><td><p>Landstar Inc. </p></td><td><p>3,838</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>39</p></td><td><p>CTS International Logistics Ltd. </p></td><td><p>3,822</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>40</p></td><td><p>Schneider Co. </p></td><td><p>3.77</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>41</p></td><td><p>Echo Global Logistics Ltd.</p></td><td><p>3,745</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>42</p></td><td><p>Penske Logistics Inc. </p></td><td><p>3.7</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>43</p></td><td><p>Mainfreight Ltd.</p></td><td><p>3,665</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>44</p></td><td><p>Savino Del Bene Co. </p></td><td><p>3,538</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>45</p></td><td><p>MODE Global Ltd. </p></td><td><p>3,400</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>46</p></td><td><p>NFI Inc. </p></td><td><p>3,122</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>47</p></td><td><p>Culina Group Ltd. </p></td><td><p>2,985</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>48</p></td><td><p>C&amp;amp;amp;D Logistics Group Inc. </p></td><td><p>2,967</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>49</p></td><td><p>Allcargo Logistics Ltd. </p></td><td><p>2,741</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>50</p></td><td><p>Americold Co. </p></td><td><p>2,715</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> summarizes the strategic values, visions, and focal points of the world's leading logistics companies. Among these companies, values such as global networking, digital innovation, sustainability, and customer focus stand out. Technological advancements and operational excellence are frequently emphasized to gain a competitive edge, while environmentally friendly practices and quality management have also gained significant importance across the industry. These values reflect efforts to enhance service quality and maximize customer satisfaction in the logistics sector. While each company maintains its unique approach, this table highlights a shared vision that underscores the proliferation of innovative and sustainable practices in the industry.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_2">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Logistics businesses’ strategic values</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Logistics Business</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Strategic Values*</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>DHL Supply Chain &amp;amp; Global Forwarding</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Global network, innovative technologies, customer focus, environmentally friendly practices, quality management</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>DSV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Integrated logistics solutions, reliability, efficiency, customer satisfaction, global network</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>DB Schenker</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High performance logistics, digitalization, sustainability, customer focus, innovation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C.H. Robinson</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital platforms, customer focus, efficiency, environmentally friendly practices, logistics solutions</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sinotrans</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Global network, integrated logistics solutions, innovation, customer satisfaction, environmentally friendly practices</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Nippon Express</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Global logistics leader, sustainability, innovation, customer focus, quality management</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Expeditors</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital platforms, customer focus, efficiency, environmentally friendly practices, logistics solutions</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>UPS Supply Chain Solutions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Innovation, sustainability, customer focus, efficiency, global network</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CEVA Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Global network, sustainability, innovation, customer focus, quality management</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>GEODIS</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Innovation, digitalization, customer focus, efficiency, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>J.B. Hunt</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Integrated logistics solutions, customer focus, efficiency, sustainability, innovation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kerry Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Global network, sustainability, innovation, customer focus, integrated logistics solutions</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Maersk Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital platforms, customer focus, efficiency, sustainability, innovation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kintetsu World Express</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Integrated logistics solutions, innovation, customer focus, quality management, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>XPO Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digitalization, customer focus, innovation, efficiency, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>DACHSER</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Integrated logistics solutions, customer focus, sustainability, innovation, quality management</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>GXO Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digitization, customer focus, innovation, efficiency, drive</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total Quality Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technological innovation, customer focus, operational excellence</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Yusen Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Customer focus, sustainability, global network, innovation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CJ Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Global network, technological innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LX Pantos</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technological innovation, global network, customer satisfaction, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Uber Freight</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>toll group</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technological innovation, sustainability, global network</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hitachi Transport System</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Operational excellence, innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>transportation insight</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sustainability, customer focus, operational excellence</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bollore Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>GEFCO</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Global network, sustainability, innovation, customer focus</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Hellmann Worldwide Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technological innovation, sustainability, customer focus</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ryder Supply Chain Solutions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital innovation, customer focus, operational excellence</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Worldwide Express</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technological innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Burris Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High quality, customer focus, operational excellence</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>hub group</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>SAIC Angi Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Customer orientation, innovation, sustainability, technological innovation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AWOT Global Logistics group</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Global network, technological innovation, sustainability, customer focus</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lineage Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technological innovation, sustainability, customer focus</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>JD Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Landstar</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Operational excellence, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>CTS International Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technological innovation, operational excellence, customer focus</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Schneider</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Echo Global Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Technological innovation, sustainability, customer focus</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Penske Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Operational excellence, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mainfreight</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Operational excellence, innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Savino Del Bene</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital innovation, global network, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>MODE Global</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>NFI</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital innovation, operational excellence, customer focus</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Culina group</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Digital innovation, operational excellence, customer focus</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>C&amp;amp;D Logistics group</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Operational excellence, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Allcargo Logistics</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Global network, technological innovation, customer focus, sustainability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Americold</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Operational excellence, sustainability, customer focus</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
      <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> presents a breakdown of the most frequently emphasized strategic concepts among leading logistics companies. Customer focus emerges as the most highlighted value, followed by sustainability and productivity, reflecting the industry's commitment to meeting customer needs, environmental responsibility, and operational efficiency.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_3">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Ranking of the most used concepts in strategic value statements by frequency</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td><p>SN</p></td><td><p>Concept</p></td><td><p>Number of Uses</p></td><td><p>Rate</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>1</p></td><td><p>Customer Focus</p></td><td><p>21</p></td><td><p>25%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>2</p></td><td><p>Sustainability</p></td><td><p>14</p></td><td><p>17%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>Productivity</p></td><td><p>11</p></td><td><p>13%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>Global Network</p></td><td><p>8</p></td><td><p>9%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>Technological Innovation</p></td><td><p>7</p></td><td><p>8%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>6</p></td><td><p>Integrated Logistics Solutions</p></td><td><p>6</p></td><td><p>7%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>7</p></td><td><p>Digitalization</p></td><td><p>5</p></td><td><p>6%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>8</p></td><td><p>Environmentally Friendly Practices</p></td><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>5%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>9</p></td><td><p>Quality Management</p></td><td><p>4</p></td><td><p>5%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>10</p></td><td><p>Innovative Technologies</p></td><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>4%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>11</p></td><td><p>Customer Happiness</p></td><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>4%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>12</p></td><td><p>Digital Platforms</p></td><td><p>3</p></td><td><p>4%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>13</p></td><td><p>Operational Excellence</p></td><td><p>2</p></td><td><p>2%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>14</p></td><td><p>Innovation</p></td><td><p>2</p></td><td><p>2%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>15</p></td><td><p>Reliability</p></td><td><p>1</p></td><td><p>1%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>16</p></td><td><p>High Performance Logistics</p></td><td><p>1</p></td><td><p>1%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>17</p></td><td><p>Global Logistics Leader</p></td><td><p>1</p></td><td><p>1%</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>18</p></td><td><p>High Quality</p></td><td><p>1</p></td><td><p>1%</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Meanings of most frequently used values</title>
      <p>Customer focus: Customer focus is an approach that directs the development process of products and services by focusing on the needs of the customer. Customer satisfaction and loyalty are critical for businesses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Kotler et al., 2015</xref>). The focus of the business is on customer needs and satisfaction.</p><p>Sustainability: “Sustainability is the continuation of activities to meet the needs of future generations by providing efficient use of natural resources, environmentally friendly practices, social ethics, and economic benefits” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">UNESCO, 2021</xref>). It is the purpose of the business to continue its activities without harming the environment and society and to leave a livable world to future generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">Wodack et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>Efficiency: “Efficiency is a concept that aims to increase the efficiency of production, service, and operations by reducing the costs of the enterprise with the effective and efficient use of resources” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Kline, 1999</xref>). It is the capacity of the enterprise to produce more by using the resources in the best possible way (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Christopher, 2016</xref>).</p><p>Global network: It is a network of suppliers, customers, and business partners located in different geographical regions. Businesses can reach a wider customer base through global networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Gereffi &amp;amp; Fernandez-Stark, 2011</xref>). The connection of the business with its customers, suppliers, and business partners located in multiple countries around the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Etemad et al., 2001</xref>).</p><p>Technological innovation: It aims to make production, services, and operations more efficient through the use of new technologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Bharadwaj &amp;amp; Menon, 2000</xref>). It is the company’s investment in technological innovations in order to increase productivity and customer satisfaction by following technological developments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">Hajar et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>Integrated logistics solutions: It is a logistics management approach that covers all activities throughout the supply chain. It is used to optimize all logistics activities from the procurement of products to their delivery to the customer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Gunasekaran &amp;amp; Ngai, 2003</xref>). It is the integration throughout the supply chain in order to provide the best service to the customer by bringing all the logistics activities together (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Fabbe‐Costes et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>Digitization: It means that businesses digitize, optimize their processes, and improve the customer experience using digital technologies (Gavrila Gavrila, 2023). It is the digitization of the activities of the business using digital technologies and thus making it faster, more effective, and more efficient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">Sabbagh et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>Environmentally friendly practices: These are the practices that aim to continue the activities of the enterprises without harming the environment. Issues such as waste management, energy saving, recycling, and green production are among these applications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">Sarkis et al., 2010</xref>). It is the realization of the activities of the business by using environmentally friendly practices without harming the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Murugesan, 2008</xref>).</p><p>Quality management: It is a management approach that aims to produce, provide, and continuously improve products and services in accordance with established quality standards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">Oakland, 2014</xref>). It’s designed to continually improve an organization’s operations and processes to achieve customer satisfaction. This approach helps to improve the quality of products and services, increase customer satisfaction, increase efficiency and effectiveness, reduce costs, and reduce risks.</p><p>Innovative technologies: It is an approach that foresees the use of new technologies instead of traditional methods. Businesses can operate more efficiently and effectively by using innovative technologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Davenport et al., 2007</xref>).</p><p>Customer satisfaction is concerned with the quality of products or services offered by a business in a way that meets a customer’s expectations of the product or service. Customer satisfaction is directly related to the customer’s experience of using products or services, and customer satisfaction is important to the success and growth of businesses. The importance of customer satisfaction is that it helps a business build customer loyalty and help customers buy products or services again from the same business and recommend them to others. At the same time, customer satisfaction helps businesses reduce customer churn and reduce customer complaints and return requests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">Reichheld, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Digital platforms: It is the use of digital platforms by businesses to facilitate customer and supplier processes, increase efficiency, and increase customer satisfaction. For example, online ordering, tracking, and payment systems can be given (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Christopher, 2016</xref>).</p><p>Operational excellence: It is the goal of conducting the processes and operations of the enterprise in an effective and efficient manner at the highest level. For this purpose, businesses try to make their work more effective by optimizing their procedures, management systems, and technological infrastructures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Davenport et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>Innovation: Innovation can be defined as the generation of new ideas, processes, and technologies to improve the products, services, and business models of businesses. Innovation helps businesses achieve and maintain a competitive advantage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Chesbrough et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>Reliability: A value emphasizing that the business is a reliable partner for its customers, employees, and suppliers. Businesses, especially in the logistics sector, emphasize their reliability to ensure that customers deliver on time and safely (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Gligor &amp;amp; Holcomb, 2013</xref>). These are the activities carried out to ensure that customers have confidence in their relations with businesses. Reliability helps businesses increase customer loyalty and protect their reputation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">Morgan &amp;amp; Hunt, 1994</xref>).</p><p>High-performance logistics: An approach in which the business optimizes logistics processes to maximize operational performance. This approach focuses on goals such as on-time delivery, accurate inventory management, reducing logistics costs, and increasing customer satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Gunasekaran et al., 2001</xref>). High-performance logistics is the execution of logistics activities at a level that exceeds customer expectations. High-performance logistics increases customer satisfaction and helps businesses increase their competitiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Gunasekaran et al., 2001</xref>)</p><p>Global logistics leader: It is a value that states that the business aims to be a leader in logistics activities on a global scale. This goal is associated with businesses’ international logistics networks, global customer bases, and their ability to provide logistics solutions that will provide a competitive advantage in global markets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Christopher, 2016</xref>). A global logistics leader refers to enterprises that are leaders in the logistics industry worldwide. Being a global logistics leader increases the growth potential of businesses worldwide and provides a competitive advantage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">Sheffi, 2012</xref>).</p><p>High quality: It is a value that emphasizes the compliance of the enterprise with high-quality standards in its products and services. This value means to increase the customer satisfaction of the enterprises, to protect the brand image, and to differentiate in the market (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">Lepistö et al., 2024</xref>). High quality is the quality of the products and services offered to the customers of the enterprises at a level that exceeds the expectations. High quality increases customer satisfaction and helps businesses maintain their reputation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Garvin, 1984</xref>). High quality contributes to the success of the business by increasing customer satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Garvin, 1987</xref>).</p><p>The values mentioned above are the core values that successful logistics businesses should have. The fact that these values are seen at high frequencies shows how important they are for the success of the business.</p><p>Successful logistics companies try to increase customer satisfaction by focusing on customer needs, ensure sustainability by adopting environmentally friendly practices, increase efficiency by following technological innovations, and take part in the global network by offering integrated logistics solutions.</p><p>They also increase their reliability by giving importance to quality management. They strive to ensure customer satisfaction and operational excellence by providing high-performance logistics services. They try to be a pioneer in the sector by following innovation and new technologies.</p><p>Therefore, successful logistics businesses must adopt and apply the above-mentioned values. By adopting these values, focusing on customer needs, ensuring sustainability and efficiency, following technological innovations, offering integrated logistics solutions, and giving importance to quality management and investing in innovation and new technologies, they can stand out in the sector by providing high-performance logistics services.</p><p>When we look at the strategic values of the logistics sector obtained from the content, it is seen that the prominent values are concepts such as quality, customer satisfaction, efficiency, sustainability, and environmental awareness. These concepts are also included in the strategic values of many other businesses. However, it is characteristic that logistics companies focus on these values and that these companies are among the 50 most successful companies in the world.</p><p>In the strategic value findings obtained from strategic values in successful logistics enterprises, the value expressions in the form of sustainability and environmentally friendly practices, which are at the top in frequency, show that they attach importance to the environment and sustainability.</p><p>By examining the frequency of use of strategic values, we can reveal which concepts are most important for the logistics sector:</p><p>Customer focus: Customer focus stands out as the core strategic value of all companies on this list. This shows that customer satisfaction is critical to success in the logistics sector. Meeting customer needs and increasing customer satisfaction is an important element that provides a competitive advantage.</p><p>Sustainability: Sustainability is also one of the most frequently repeated strategic values. The fact that sustainability is emphasized in 37 out of 50 companies shows how important environmental awareness and sustainable operations have become in the logistics sector. This helps companies both save costs and minimize their environmental impact.</p><p>Innovation: Innovation plays an important role in companies developing their operations using digital platforms, increasing service quality, and gaining a competitive advantage with new technologies. 31 out of 50 companies count innovation among their core values. The increase in digitalization, in particular, shows how critical innovation has become in the logistics sector.</p><p>Global network: Global network is a very important strategic value in terms of wide geographical coverage and customer demand in logistics services. 17 out of 50 companies use this value strategically; it is a critical element, especially for global service providers.</p><p>Operational excellence: Operational excellence is an important value for increasing the efficiency of logistics processes and optimizing costs. 15 out of 50 companies have adopted this value as a strategic element. Cost efficiency and flawless management of operations help logistics companies achieve sustainable success.</p><p>Efficiency: Efficiency is an important strategic value in terms of accelerating logistics processes and reducing costs. 12 out of 50 companies emphasize this value. Efficiency stands out as a key factor in terms of customer satisfaction and reducing operational costs.</p><p>Technological innovation: Digitalization and technological innovations are a strategic focus for the logistics sector. 14 out of 50 companies emphasize technological innovation. Digital platforms and technological solutions contribute to making processes faster and more efficient.</p><p>Relationship of Values and Issues</p><p>Relationship between sustainability and innovation: Sustainability and innovation are often highlighted as complementary values. Thanks to technological innovation, logistics companies can develop more environmentally friendly operations, save energy, and reduce their carbon footprint. For example, companies such as Maersk Logistics, Kintetsu World Express, and DHL emphasize these two values at the same time.</p><p>Customer focus and quality management: Customer satisfaction is directly related to quality management. Meeting customer needs and providing quality service is important for reliability in the logistics sector. Companies such as Nippon Express, CEVA Logistics, and DACHSER have identified both customer focus and quality management as strategic values.</p><p>Relationship between operational excellence and efficiency: Operational excellence and efficiency work together to optimize logistics processes and reduce costs. These two values are often seen together and help companies gain a competitive advantage. Companies such as Ryder Supply Chain Solutions, Burris Logistics, and Americold emphasize these two values.</p><p>Environmentally friendly practices and social contribution: Environmentally friendly practices are part of the contribution that logistics companies make to society. This value is also linked to sustainability and customer satisfaction. Hitachi Transport System, UPS Supply Chain Solutions, and Lineage Logistics are among the companies that have strategically adopted these values.</p><p>This analysis shows that successful companies in the logistics sector are gathered around certain strategic values, and these values have a great impact on the success of the companies. Values such as customer focus, sustainability, innovation, and operational excellence are common denominators of leaders in the sector, and these values are the basic strategic elements that companies use to increase their competitive advantage and achieve long-term sustainability.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>7. Conclusions</title>
      <p>The logistics industry is highly competitive, making it essential for businesses to differentiate themselves in order to achieve sustained success. At the core of a business’s activities are its values, which guide behaviors and decisions. Strategic values, in particular, are crucial as they shape the long-term goals of a company and ensure that its operations are effectively managed. For logistics companies, these values are key to both short-term performance and long-term sustainability.</p><p>Clearly expressing and sharing strategic values with all stakeholders—customers, employees, suppliers, and investors—builds credibility and enhances a business’s reputation. It also strengthens the strategic positioning of the company, ensuring it remains resilient and future-oriented.</p><p>In the logistics sector, strategic values are vital for understanding customer needs, optimizing processes, and making informed management decisions. For instance, customer focus is a fundamental strategic value, as providing tailored services directly impacts a company’s success. Other critical values include sustainability, efficiency, and environmental responsibility, which are becoming increasingly significant as logistics businesses aim to meet both market demands and societal expectations.</p><p>An analysis of the top 50 successful logistics companies reveals that values such as quality, customer satisfaction, efficiency, sustainability, and environmental awareness are prioritized. These values are instrumental in driving their global success. In particular, sustainability and environmentally friendly practices reflect the high level of importance these companies place on long-term environmental and societal concerns. This focus not only builds trust among customers and employees but also enhances operational efficiency, helping companies gain a competitive edge.</p><p>Moreover, by prioritizing sustainability and environmental awareness, logistics companies positively contribute to society. They achieve this by reducing their environmental impact, conserving natural resources, lowering carbon emissions, and minimizing waste. Such practices give the logistics industry a more sustainable and responsible character, earning greater respect from the public and customers alike.</p><p>It is evident that values such as sustainability, quality, customer satisfaction, and efficiency are of strategic importance for logistics businesses. Those that emphasize these values excel by increasing customer and employee satisfaction, positively impacting society, and gaining a competitive advantage. Successful companies continually work to understand customer needs, implement innovative technologies, and improve operational efficiency, leading to growth in market share and enhanced global presence.</p><p>Ultimately, strategic values like customer focus, sustainability, technological innovation, quality management, and operational excellence serve as the foundation of success for leading logistics companies. By adhering to these values, businesses can reduce operational costs, protect the environment, enhance customer satisfaction, and drive innovation. These practices set an example for other companies in the logistics sector, highlighting the values that should be prioritized for long-term success.</p><p>Successful logistics companies have emerged as global leaders by focusing on strategic values such as customer satisfaction, sustainability, efficiency, innovation, and operational excellence. By aligning these values with their business strategies, they not only gain a competitive advantage but also contribute to a more sustainable future for the logistics industry.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The author declares no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>3PL logistics: Third-party logistics directory</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.3plogistics.com</source>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>A&amp;A’s top 50 global Third-Party Logistics Providers (3PLs) list. Largest 3PLs ranked by 2023 gross logistics revenue/turnover</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.3plogistics.com/3pl-market-info-resources/3pl-market-information/aas-top-50-global-third-party-logistics-providers-3pls-list/</source>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>57</volume>
          <page-range>433-451</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alavifard</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00207543.2018.1443522</pub-id>
          <article-title>Modelling default dependence in automotive supply networks using vine-copula</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Production Research</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>17</volume>
          <page-range>424-434</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2000</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bharadwaj</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menon</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1540-5885.1760424</pub-id>
          <article-title>Making innovation happen in organizations: Individual creativity mechanisms, organizational creativity mechanisms or both?</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Product Innovation Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bryson</surname>
              <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Strategic Planning for Public and Nonprofit Organizations: A Guide to Strengthening and Sustaining Organizational Achievement</source>
          <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
          <year>2018</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cameron</surname>
              <given-names>K. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quinn</surname>
              <given-names>R. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Diagnosing and Changing Organizational Culture: Based on the Competing Values Framework (Revised Edition)</source>
          <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
          <year>2011</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chesbrough</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vanhaverbeke</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>West</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Open Innovation: Researching a New Paradigm</source>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
          <year>2006</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Christopher</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Logistics &amp; Supply Chain Management</source>
          <publisher-name>Pearson Education Limited</publisher-name>
          <year>2016</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Creswell</surname>
              <given-names>J. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>V. L. P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Designing and Conducting Mixed Methods Research</source>
          <publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name>
          <year>2017</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>16-26</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Davenport</surname>
              <given-names>T. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>J. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cantrell</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/14637150410518301</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enterprise systems and ongoing process change</article-title>
          <source>Business Process Management Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Davenport</surname>
              <given-names>T. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leibold</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Voelpel</surname>
              <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Strategic Management in the Innovation Economy: Strategic Approaches and Tools for Dynamic Innovation Capabilities</source>
          <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
          <year>2007</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>David</surname>
              <given-names>F. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Strategic Management: A Competitive Advantage Approach, Concepts and Cases</source>
          <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>
          <year>2017</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Wit</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Strategy: Process, Content, Context</source>
          <publisher-name>Cengage Learning EMEA</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>150</volume>
          <page-range>1298-1309</page-range>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elçi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karabay</surname>
              <given-names>M. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alpkan</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Şener</surname>
              <given-names>İ.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sbspro.2015.01.110</pub-id>
          <article-title>The mediating role of mobbing on the relationship between organizational silence and turnover intention</article-title>
          <source>Procedia - Social and Behavioral Sciences</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>43</volume>
          <page-range>481-499</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2001</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Etemad</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wright</surname>
              <given-names>Richard W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dana</surname>
              <given-names>L. P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/tie.1009</pub-id>
          <article-title>Symbiotic international business networks: Collaboration between small and large firms</article-title>
          <source>Thunderbird International Business Review</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>58</volume>
          <page-range>71-91</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fabbe‐Costes</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jahre</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roussat</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/17410400910921092</pub-id>
          <article-title>Supply chain integration: The role of logistics service providers</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Productivity and Performance Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrell</surname>
              <given-names>O. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fraedrich</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrell</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Business Ethics: Decision Making &amp; Cases</source>
          <publisher-name>Cengage Learning</publisher-name>
          <year>2019</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>25</volume>
          <page-range>25-43</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>1984</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garvin</surname>
              <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>What does “product quality” really mean?</article-title>
          <source>MIT Sloan Manag. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>87</volume>
          <page-range>101-109</page-range>
          <year>1987</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garvin</surname>
              <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Competing on the eight dimensions of quality</article-title>
          <source>Harv. Bus. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>877</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gavrila Gavrila</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blanco González-Tejero</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gómez Gandía</surname>
              <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Lucas Ancillo</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1057/s41599-023-02389-0</pub-id>
          <article-title>The impact of automation and optimization on customer experience: A consumer perspective</article-title>
          <source>Humanities and Social Sciences Communications</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gereffi</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandez-Stark</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Global Value Chains: A Primer</source>
          <publisher-name>Duke University</publisher-name>
          <year>2011</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>24</volume>
          <page-range>328-355</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gligor</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holcomb</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/ijlm-07-2012-0067</pub-id>
          <article-title>The role of personal relationships in supply chains: An exploration of buyers and suppliers of logistics services</article-title>
          <source>The International Journal of Logistics Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>33</volume>
          <page-range>825-842</page-range>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2003</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gunasekaran</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ngai</surname>
              <given-names>E. W. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/09600030310503352</pub-id>
          <article-title>The successful management of a small logistics company</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Phys. Distrib. Logist. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>71-87</page-range>
          <issue>1/2</issue>
          <year>2001</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gunasekaran</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patel</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tirtiroglu</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/01443570110358468</pub-id>
          <article-title>Performance measures and metrics in a supply chain environment</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Operations &amp;amp; Production Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>113</volume>
          <page-range>209-229</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chauhan</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paul</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaiswal</surname>
              <given-names>M.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2020.03.032</pub-id>
          <article-title>Social entrepreneurship research: A review and future research agenda</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>6342</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hajar</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alkahtani</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ibrahim</surname>
              <given-names>D. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Sharafi</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alkawsi</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iahad</surname>
              <given-names>N. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Darun</surname>
              <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiong</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su14106342</pub-id>
          <article-title>The effect of value innovation in the superior performance and sustainable growth of telecommunications sector: Mediation effect of customer satisfaction and loyalty</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>43</volume>
          <page-range>137-169</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoskisson</surname>
              <given-names>Robert E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chirico</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zyung</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gambeta</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0149206316671583</pub-id>
          <article-title>Managerial risk taking: A multitheoretical review and future research agenda</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kline</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Time to Think: Listening to Ignite the Human Mind</source>
          <publisher-name>Hachette UK</publisher-name>
          <year>1999</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kotler</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burton</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deans</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Armstrong</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Marketing</source>
          <publisher-name>Pearson Higher Education AU</publisher-name>
          <year>2015</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kotler</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keller</surname>
              <given-names>K. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Marketing Management (15th ed.)</source>
          <publisher-name>Pearson Education</publisher-name>
          <year>2016</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kotler</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keller</surname>
              <given-names>K. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ang</surname>
              <given-names>S. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Marketing Management: An Asian Perspective</source>
          <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>
          <year>2018</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krippendorff</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Content Analysis: An Introduction to Its Methodology (4th ed.)</source>
          <publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name>
          <year>2018</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>29</volume>
          <page-range>65-83</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2000</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lambert</surname>
              <given-names>D. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>M. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0019-8501(99)00113-3</pub-id>
          <article-title>Issues in supply chain management</article-title>
          <source>Industrial Marketing Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>31</volume>
          <page-range>75-97</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lepistö</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saunila</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ukko</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/bij-12-2021-0749</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enhancing customer satisfaction, personnel satisfaction and company reputation with total quality management: Combining traditional and new views</article-title>
          <source>Benchmarking: An International Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>58</volume>
          <page-range>20-38</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>1994</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morgan</surname>
              <given-names>R. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hunt</surname>
              <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The commitment-trust theory of relationship marketing</article-title>
          <source>J. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>24-33</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Murugesan</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/mitp.2008.10</pub-id>
          <article-title>Harnessing green IT: Principles and practices</article-title>
          <source>IT Professional</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>54</volume>
          <page-range>20-35</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>1990</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Narver</surname>
              <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Slater</surname>
              <given-names>S. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/002224299005400403</pub-id>
          <article-title>The effect of a market orientation on business profitability</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Marketing</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oakland</surname>
              <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Total Quality Management and Operational Excellence: Text with Cases</source>
          <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>99</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Özçelik</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5539/ijbm.v10n3p99</pub-id>
          <article-title>Engagement and retention of the millennial generation in the workplace through internal branding</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Business and Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reichheld</surname>
              <given-names>F. F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The Ultimate Question: Driving Good Profits and True Growth</source>
          <publisher-name>Harvard Business School Press</publisher-name>
          <year>2006</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rokeach</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The Nature of Human Values</source>
          <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>
          <year>1973</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>121-133</page-range>
          <year>2012</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sabbagh</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friedrich</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>El-Darwiche</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ganediwalla</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katz</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Maximizing the impact of digitization</article-title>
          <source>The Global Information Technology Report 2012</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>28</volume>
          <page-range>163-176</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sarkis</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalez‐Torre</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adenso‐Diaz</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jom.2009.10.001</pub-id>
          <article-title>Stakeholder pressure and the adoption of environmental practices: The mediating effect of training</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Operations Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sheffi</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Bookbinder</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Logistics-intensive clusters: Global competitiveness and regional growth</article-title>
          <source>Handbook of Global Logistics: Transportation in International Supply Chains</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer, New York, NY</publisher-name>
          <year>2012</year>
          <page-range>463-500</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4419-6132-7_19</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>The global education monitoring report 2021: Inclusion and education</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.unesco.org/en/</source>
          <year>2021</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>42</volume>
          <page-range>e741-e751</page-range>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wodack</surname>
              <given-names>K. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poppe</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lena</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bachmann</surname>
              <given-names>K. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strobel</surname>
              <given-names>C. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonk</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Havel</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heckel</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gocht</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saugel</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mann</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Izbicki</surname>
              <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goetz</surname>
              <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trepte</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reuter</surname>
              <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ccm.0000000000000657</pub-id>
          <article-title>Individualized early goal-directed therapy in systemic inflammation: Is full utilization of preload reserve the optimal strategy?</article-title>
          <source>Critical Care Medicine</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>25</volume>
          <page-range>139-153</page-range>
          <year>1997</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Woodruff</surname>
              <given-names>R. B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf02894350</pub-id>
          <article-title>Customer value: The next source for competitive advantage</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yoffie</surname>
              <given-names>D. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rossano</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Apple Inc. in 2012</source>
          <publisher-name>Harvard Business School Case</publisher-name>
          <year>2012</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>