<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JEMSE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Engineering Management and Systems Engineering</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Eng. Manag. Syst. Eng.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JEMSE</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2958-3527</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2958-3519</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-z6qNj9NG7HJsnvexOrD77p6JzAZztAVC</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jemse050205</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Evidence Quality and Carbon Credit Outcomes in a Methane Abatement Project</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3713-972X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Rokhmawati</surname>
            <given-names>Andewi</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>Andewi.rokhmawati@lecturer.unri.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2146-3859</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Basuki</surname>
            <given-names>Akbari Indra</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>akba002@brin.go.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_3">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3123-0039</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Soeratin</surname>
            <given-names>Boyke Setiawan</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>boyke.soeratin@binus.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-3329-2535</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Berampu</surname>
            <given-names>Lailan Tawila</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>lailantawilaberampu@lecturer.unri.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_4">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-8535-067X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Iskandar</surname>
            <given-names>Iskandar</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>iskandarteknik@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">The Faculty of Economics and Business, Universitas Riau, 28293 Pekanbaru, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Artificial Intelligence and Cybersecurity Research Center, National Research and Innovation Agency, 40135 Bandung, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_3">BINUS Business School, BINUS University, 11530 Jakarta, Indonesia</aff>
        <aff id="aff_4">Master of Management Program, Universitas Riau, 28293 Pekanbaru, Indonesia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2026</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>204</fpage>
      <lpage>232</lpage>
      <page-range>204-232</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>04</month>
          <year>2026</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2026</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2026 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2026</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>The research analyzes whether monitoring system design, calibration management, timestamp consistency, data traceability, and verification procedures relate to the risk control of the financial aspects of methane-abatement engineering projects. An analytical case study based on a single project and involving a before-and-after comparison of the implementation of an monitoring, reporting, and verification (MRV) regime was conducted under fixed engineering and accounting conditions. This design allows the comparison to focus on differences in MRV evidence management conditions rather than on changes in physical mitigation technology. Conservative issuability was estimated using the low-confidence adjustment metric (LCAM). This analytical metric scales engineering emission reductions by evidence-related factors without supplanting registry rules or verifier judgment. With the enhanced MRV regime, the conservatively supportable fraction was 77.0% to 91.3%, while the realized price wedge declined from 0.30 to 0.12. The monitoring-to-issuance period was also shortened by 50 days.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>MRV system management</kwd>
        <kwd>Evidence quality</kwd>
        <kwd>Methane abatement</kwd>
        <kwd>Engineering project risk</kwd>
        <kwd>Carbon revenue</kwd>
        <kwd>Calibration governance</kwd>
        <kwd>Data traceability</kwd>
        <kwd>Conservative issuability</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="5"/>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="7"/>
        <ref-count count="47"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Methane-abatement projects are engineering systems whose finance-relevant outcomes are associated not only with physical mitigation but also with the quality of the monitoring, reporting, and verification (MRV) system used to document, validate, and support carbon-credit revenue claims [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. In practice, the conversion of measured mitigation into carbon-credit revenue is constrained by evidentiary and institutional conditions. Carbon credits are more than environmental units; they are evidence-based claims whose value depends on the credible demonstration and defense of avoided emissions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>]. In this study, carbon credits are treated analytically as evidentiary claims that become financial assets only when they are defensibly supported.</p><p>These evidentiary weaknesses are especially visible at the project level because they are closely linked to finance-relevant project outcomes. While a methane-reduction project might create measurable physical reductions, the commercial realization of the revenues generated by such reductions is less certain when data gaps, a lack of proper audit-trail documentation, or poor MRV governance prevail. Verification agencies tend to exercise conservative practices when reviewing data that is either incomplete or hard to verify [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. The lack of consistency in monitoring data, poor calibration documentation, lack of timestamps, or difficulty verifying evidence could make verifiers question the evidence and defer issuing or even issuing credits to avoid over-crediting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. Such issues are not merely procedural evidentiary problems but rather concern whether the measured reductions are defensible for issuance, can trade close to benchmark prices, and are financially viable.</p><p>The financial implications of the evidentiary issues above are often overlooked. In an environment where one party possesses more knowledge than another, the buyer might exercise discounts, contingency clauses, or other methods of mitigating risks, and this might have economic consequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. This issue is especially relevant in carbon transactions because settlement confidence often depends on the verification-readiness of technical records. Issuance delays may further increase financial uncertainty by extending the interval between mitigation and monetization. Credits remain illiquid until verification and issuance are completed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>]. Therefore, delays in verification and issuance may widen the gap between risk reduction and credit monetization, reduce present value, and elevate working-capital requirements, even when nominal credit volumes remain constant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>]. From a project-finance perspective, MRV quality should therefore be viewed not only as a compliance requirement but also as part of the project's engineering and management architecture for revenue-risk control.</p><p>Prior research has made important contributions to carbon market integrity and MRV governance. Still, it offers only limited project-level explanations of how engineering evidence-management practices are associated with finance-relevant project outcomes. Two studies focusing on integrity most consistently find systemic over-crediting and identify fundamental structural vulnerabilities in crediting mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>]. Governance-related research highlights the roles of transparency, disclosure, and institutional reform as preconditions for rebuilding trust [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>]. Emerging work on digital MRV suggests that enhanced data infrastructures may improve traceability and auditability, while also noting that such advances do not necessarily address more fundamental issues such as counterfactual uncertainty, additionality, or baseline rigor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]. For engineering project managers, the unresolved issue is not only whether mitigation has occurred, but whether monitoring records, calibration status, timestamps, and data lineage can be managed as a verification-ready system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>]. What remains underdeveloped is a transparent project-level mechanism for examining how evidentiary quality is associated with finance-relevant outcomes. Such a mechanism can connect monitoring continuity, calibration validity, timestamp coherence, and data traceability to project-finance-related indicators: the defensible fraction of measured reductions, realized settlement outcomes, and the timing of monetization.</p><p>In this analysis, a project-specific approach is adopted to examine the relationships among MRV system management, evidence defensibility, revenue-risk indicators, and finance-related project outcomes. The empirical setting involves a complete methane-abatement project in Indonesia, evaluated under two analytical MRV regimes: a legacy regime and an enhanced regime. Two MRV regimes are examined: a legacy regime and an enhanced regime. The research uses a within-project before-and-after design, with engineering activities and accounting practices held constant. In contrast, the evidence systems differ between the two regimes in monitoring consistency, calibration management, timestamp matching, and data traceability.</p><p>The analysis evaluates whether stronger MRV evidence is associated with a larger conservatively supportable portion of measured reductions, a smaller realized-price wedge, and a shorter lag from monitoring to issuance. The framework is analytical and does not replicate registry rules or serve as a substitute for verification. Its role is to make the gap between measured mitigation and defensible claims explicit.</p><p>The analysis is limited in scope. It does not state that improved MRV fixes higher-order integrity problems in carbon markets. A stronger evidentiary chain cannot address concerns about additionality, baseline construction, leakage, or permanence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]. Instead, stronger evidentiary conditions may be associated with lower project-level evidentiary uncertainty in the chain from quantified abatement to financially usable revenue. In doing so, the paper contributes to the discussion of MRV as part of the financial and institutional infrastructure through which evidence quality is associated with conservative issuability, settlement outcomes, and issuance timing within a project context.</p><p>Accordingly, the study is guided by three analytical expectations. Stronger MRV evidence is expected to be associated with a larger conservatively supportable share of measured emission reductions, a smaller realized-price wedge, and a shorter lag between monitoring closure and issuance. These expectations are evaluated within a single-project comparison under fixed engineering and accounting conditions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Materials and methods</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Research design and analytical scope</title>
          
          <p>An analytical single-project before-and-after case-study design was applied to compare two MRV regimes within the same methane-abatement engineering project, with engineering operations and accounting rules held constant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>]. This frames the analysis as a project-management question: whether differences in the MRV evidence structure are associated with the degree to which measured mitigation can be defensibly supported, made transaction-ready, and linked to revenue realization on a reasonably predictable timeline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>].</p><p>The analysis is limited to within-project associations and does not support cross-project generalization. Carbon credit outcomes are also influenced by factors beyond project-level MRV, including market conditions, contract design, verifier capabilities, and institutional procedures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]. Neither is a single-site project design immune to these problems, yet such a design helps reduce variation in engineering processes, site-specific factors, and accounting criteria across MRV frameworks. The novelty is the application of a management-based concept whereby the quality of evidentiary material is considered a project variable that is related to certain revenue and risk signals downstream [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>].</p><p>To keep the analysis clear, an attempt is made to distinguish between the observed and calculated data. The former includes monitoring statements, calibration validity periods, issuance dates, and settlement prices. The latter comprises emissions reductions from engineering calculations, conservative issuability assessed using the low-confidence adjustment metric (LCAM), price differential, and present value adjustment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Context of the study and the comparison framework</title>
          
          <p>The empirical context consists of a large-scale methane abatement project situated in Indonesia, using the UNFCCC methane recovery in wastewater treatment (AMS-III.H) guidelines on methane recovery from wastewater, as well as the CDM guidelines related to project emissions through flaring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>]. These protocols define baseline emissions, project emissions, and monitoring requirements. The present study does not modify these methodological rules. Instead, it focuses on how project-level evidence management supports the implementation of those rules and how different MRV evidence conditions are associated with finance-relevant project outcomes.</p><p>The project examined in this study is the Utilization of Palm Oil Mill Effluent (POME) for Biogas Co-Firing project, implemented at PKS Lubuk Dalam in Siak Regency, Riau Province, Indonesia. The project captures methane-rich biogas from anaerobic POME treatment using a Covered in-Ground Anaerobic Reactor (CIGAR), a covered lagoon anaerobic biodigester. The captured biogas is directed to a boiler via a biogas co-firing system, while excess biogas is flared. The project is owned and operated by PT Perkebunan Nusantara IV Regional III, while PT SUCOFINDO ICS conducted validation and verification. Further project-context details are provided in Appendix A, Table A1.</p><p>The official monitoring period reported in the project documents is 19 November 2021 to 18 November 2024. For the within-project before-and-after comparison, this period was divided into two analytical MRV regimes. The legacy MRV regime covers the period from 19 November 2021 to 31 December 2023, comprising 773 daily observations. The enhanced MRV regime covers the period from 1 January 2024 to 18 November 2024, comprising 323 daily observations. These terms are analytical labels used in this study to distinguish earlier and later evidence-management conditions within the same official monitoring period. They are not official labels used in the project design, monitoring, registry, or verification documents.</p><p>The legacy MRV regime is described as the earlier evidence-management condition, involving greater evidence fragmentation in preparation, manual record reconciliation, less calibration management, and lesser integration between the operation record and verification evidence. The enhanced MRV regime is described as the latter evidence-management condition, involving greater continuity in monitoring, calibration register management, timestamp management, missing data management, record management, and linkage among the raw monitoring record, the project monitoring calculation sheet, and verification evidence. The comparative description of the two MRV regimes is presented in Appendix A, Table A2.</p><p>In a before-and-after research design, the comparative analysis needs to be conducted carefully because the design cannot control all time-varying external factors. The physical mitigation technology, project location, methodology, and overall project boundary can be considered constant across the two MRV regimes. However, other time-dependent variables, such as buyer traits, contractual provisions, market mood, registry handling, verifier workload, and institutional factors, cannot be controlled for in this research design. It would therefore be inappropriate to attribute the observed differences in the project's finance-relevant indicators solely to the shift from the legacy MRV regime to the enhanced MRV regime. This study aims to examine whether the enhanced MRV evidence condition is associated with higher conservative issuability, a lower realized-price wedge, and shorter issuance cadence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Monitoring, reporting, and verification system-management framework</title>
          
          <p>The MRV process is considered an engineering management process consisting of seven interrelated steps: data acquisition, instrument calibration, recordkeeping, internal audit, verification inquiry management, issuance, and revenue realization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>]. There is a management activity associated with each step of the MRV process as well as potential failure modes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>]. Data acquisition may fail because of missing data and faulty sensors. Instrument calibration may fail due to an expired certification or a lack of traceability for the instruments. Recordkeeping may fail due to record destruction and a lack of spreadsheet management controls. An internal audit may fail if gaps are not identified before verification. Verification inquiry management may fail because of an untimely response without proper documentation. Issuance may be delayed when the evidence package is difficult to assemble, while price reductions or cash-flow delays may affect revenue recognition.</p><p>This workflow frames MRV as a project risk-control infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>]. This interpretation is consistent with risk-management and project-management standards that emphasize integrating risk control, monitoring, accountability, and performance measurement into routine project decision-making [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>]. These indicators are therefore interpreted as management indicators that connect engineering performance to conservative issuability, price-wedge exposure, issuance cadence, and revenue forecasting. The MRV system-management framework and its connection to revenue-risk control are summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Monitoring, reporting, and verification (MRV) system-management framework for revenue-risk control in a methane-abatement project</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2026/5/img_YKRZKf0q8m22RIWd.jpeg"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Data sources and traceability protocol</title>
          
          <p>The analysis combines observed project records with calculated analytical variables. To improve reproducibility, the study separates observed records from calculated constructs. Observed records include monitoring logs, activity data records, calibration certificates, instrument service records, verification process logs, issuance-related documentation, settlement records, and benchmark price references. Calculated constructs include engineering emission reductions, LCAM, the realized-price wedge, issuance cadence, and present-value adjustment. Detailed information on data sources, coverage, screening, exclusion and treatment procedures, cross-checking procedures, and confidentiality restrictions is provided in Appendix B, Table B1.</p><p>The observed data structure follows the operating boundary of the POME for Biogas Co-Firing project at PKS Lubuk Dalam, Siak Regency, Riau Province, Indonesia. Methane-related emission reductions were estimated using time-series monitoring data, including wastewater-flow activity data, untreated and treated chemical oxygen demand (COD) values, biogas combusted, methane fraction, temperature, pressure, flaring-related information, and operational logs recorded at regular intervals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>]. These records consist of timestamped operational measurements, logs, and quality indicators required to apply the relevant UNFCCC methodologies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>]. For MRV systems, high-resolution and traceable data structures are necessary to support auditability and reproducibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>]. The project monitoring documentation reports ex post activity data for the monitoring period, including wastewater volume, untreated COD, treated COD, biogas combusted, methane fraction, temperature, and pressure, all of which are directly relevant to quantifying methane-recovery performance.</p><p>Instrument governance documentation was employed to assess the adequacy of evidence of monitored values. Instrument governance documentation is made up of calibration certificates, the validity of the calibration period, instrument service documentation, and instrument maintenance documentation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]. A measurement would be considered adequate evidence only if the instrument documenting it was traceable and its calibration or servicing documents were within the monitoring period. The methodology is consistent with the theory that the presence of data is not sufficient for the adequacy of evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]. Further, it corresponds to the verification scope of implementing monitoring, calibrating measuring instruments, and dealing with data gaps.</p><p>The records of the verification process were examined to document the path from monitoring closeout to report issuance. Such records include verifier query logs, correspondence, evidence-submission records, corrective-action records, verification opinions, and issuance-related timestamps. The verification report states that the verification process evaluated the completeness, accuracy, and credibility of the project monitoring data and monitoring sheets, the presence of double issuance, and any material differences between the project implementation and the validated design recognition and approval mechanism. The records were also used to analyze issuance frequency as a process output indicative of evidential friction and verification readiness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>].</p><p>Transaction-level data were used in their anonymized aggregate form. The data includes settlement prices in Rp/tCO₂e, settlement timings, and contractual provisions. Transaction-level data are not part of technical project-design and monitoring datasets and contain commercially sensitive information. Thus, buyer identifiable terms, confidential contractual provisions, and commercially sensitive transactional data were filtered out before any analysis was performed. The benchmark price is used solely to illustrate the price wedge calculation and is not a reference for the universal market price.</p><p>In the intra-project comparison, the data collection period is 19 November 2021 to 18 November 2024, yielding 1,096 daily observations. The old regime spans 19 November 2021 to 31 December 2023, with 773 daily observations, whereas the new regime spans 1 January 2024 to 18 November 2024, with 323 daily observations. Observations were excluded from the evidence-supported dataset when they were missing, corrupted, duplicated, outside the applicable calibration-validity period, not traceable to a source file, or not reconcilable with the corresponding operational or verification record. If an evidentiary weakness was limited to one instrument, parameter, or time interval, exclusion was applied only to the affected record, instrument, parameter, or period, not to the entire project dataset. Detailed evidence-screening rules are provided in Appendix B, Table B2.</p><p>Because some project and transaction records are commercially sensitive, the study uses a layered disclosure approach. Information on technical aspects and monitoring is presented at a level sufficient to replicate the analytical process, whereas information related to specific buyers and contract conditions is anonymized. If the primary source of transaction information needs to be protected from disclosure, a template for anonymized transaction records is provided in Appendix B, Table B3.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.5. Variable definitions and measurement</title>
          
          <p>To enhance notation consistency and clarity of analysis, a list of the principal variables considered in the analyses of engineering, evidence, prices, timing, and revenues is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>. A more comprehensive list of variables, with details on their data sources and time resolutions, is provided in Appendix C, Table C1. The variables are grouped into those observed in project records, those that serve as reference values, and analytical constructs that have been calculated. This distinction is important because not all analytical constructs are treated as institutional outputs.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Important variables considered in the analysis</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Symbol</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Variable</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Unit</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Measurement Role</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m1kq79mswr">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">BE</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Baseline emissions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>ktCO<mml:math id="m8udtnfed3">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e·y<mml:math id="mwyt8664m1">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Calculated reference emissions without the project</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m8a6i8u7hk">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Project emissions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>ktCO<mml:math id="m1zuzexjid">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e·y<mml:math id="mzsq0bj4ch">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Calculated emissions under project operation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m4mzonphez">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">ER</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Engineering emission reductions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>ktCO<mml:math id="m1uro2lv0j">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e·y<mml:math id="mqai1cmejr">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Physical mitigation before evidence adjustment</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mybe8v69w3">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">int</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Interval completeness factor</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ratio, 0–1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Monitoring-record completeness</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m4efd1gqut">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">cal</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Calibration-validity factor</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ratio, 0–1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Instrument-governance support</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m63ygo1rmk">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">sync</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Timestamp-coherence factor</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ratio, 0–1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Temporal alignment of evidence records</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="muqbi4i7t0">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">MRV</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Composite evidentiary support factor</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ratio, 0–1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Combined evidence-support factor</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m1d26i9ckr">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LCAM</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Low-confidence adjustment metric</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>ktCO<mml:math id="mju8vphvp7">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e·y<mml:math id="mr69p0nu28">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math> or tCO<mml:math id="m3dwo9f2a7">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e·y<mml:math id="mzbmfslml3">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Analytical proxy for conservative issuability</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mo5ce79n8g">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">bench</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Benchmark price</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp/tCO<mml:math id="mpaacdc3ci">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>project-specific registry reference price for wedge calculation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mvqykhqbur">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">real</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Realized settlement price</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp/tCO<mml:math id="mqcphxpbba">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Observed project-level settlement price</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mvnn0e0yxm">
  <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Realized-price wedge</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ratio, 0–1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Proportional gap between benchmark and realized price</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mex3ax4gil">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">Cadence</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Issuance cadence</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Days</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Duration from monitoring closure to issuance</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="ml78lo60jj">
  <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PV</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">rel</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:mrow>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Relative present-value uplift</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Percent</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Relative present value (PV) effect of earlier revenue realization</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mlwtxc5hd4">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Realized annual revenue</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rp/y</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Annual revenue from supportable volume and realized price</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>The notation provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> will be used consistently throughout the following equations and tables. Price notation has been standardized, with <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mzcuey23f4">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">bench</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denoting the benchmark price and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m9wdvkhkfr">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">real</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denoting the realized price. Similarly, timing notation has been standardized using the <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="manb4opxfb">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">Cadence</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m3jwgruur0">
    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">rel</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> notations.</p><p>The variable <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mg6znst90y">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LCAM</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> should be interpreted with particular caution. It is not an official registry metric, does not reproduce formal issuance rules, and is not intended to replace verifier judgment. It is used only as an analytical proxy to make explicit the gap between engineering emission reductions and the portion of those reductions that is conservatively supportable under the specified evidence conditions. Similarly, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mosvawika7">
    <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is interpreted as an illustrative realized-price wedge rather than as a causal estimate of MRV quality’s effect on carbon-credit pricing.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.6. Engineering emission reductions</title>
          
          <p>Annual engineering emission reductions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>] are calculated using the standard accounting identity:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(1)</label>
              <mml:math id="mfzum2r5rx">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">ER</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">BE</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7dtvyof52">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">ER</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes emission reductions; <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m6mxvckxz5">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">BE</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes baseline emissions; and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mia34nxq07">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes project emissions.</p><p>Baseline emissions are defined as [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>]:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(2)</label>
              <mml:math id="ml5dokpdqx">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">BE</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">BM</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CH</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">baseline</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">GWP</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CH</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m8hg1b9120">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">BM</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:msub>
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CH</mml:mi>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
        </mml:msub>
        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
        <mml:mtext> baseline, </mml:mtext>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes baseline methane mass; <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mto59mtwm9">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">GWP</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:msub>
            <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CH</mml:mi>
            <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
          </mml:msub>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes the methane global warming potential.</p><p>Project emissions are expressed as [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>]:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(3)</label>
              <mml:math id="mx0k0qzmn7">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">flare</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">residual</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m8o1jxd0j9">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">flare</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the emission related to flaring; <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mnxus3g9dz">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">residual</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the residual emissions (without considering methane destruction) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">37</xref>]. This provides the volume of engineering mitigation before evidentiary scaling. The separation of engineering assessment from evidentiary analysis is analytically important because it makes explicit the assumption that realized mitigation is not necessarily equivalent to defensible, financially usable mitigation. The numerical emission-reduction input used in the LCAM and sensitivity calculations is documented in Appendix D, Tables D1–D2.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.7. Low-confidence adjustment metric as an analytical proxy for conservative issuability</title>
          
          <p>Engineering emission reductions are translated into a conservatively supportable quantity using LCAM as an evidence-adjusted analytical proxy for conservative issuability. LCAM is not a registry metric, does not reproduce formal issuance rules, and is not intended to replace verifier judgment.</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(4)</label>
              <mml:math id="mabccrywly">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LCAM</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">ER</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">int</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">cal</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">sync</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7bmkpwj92">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">int</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes interval completeness; <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mkx9f8viqx">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">cal</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> calibration validity; and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myimb1ez0y">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">sync</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> timestamp coherence.</p><p>Interval completeness is defined as:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(5)</label>
              <mml:math id="mq1ehsp7mw">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">int</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">valid</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">total</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="ma7ywobiui">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">valid</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the portion of the monitoring period supported by valid and usable monitoring records; <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mklov0zqrt">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">total</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the entire monitoring period considered.</p><p>Calibration validity is defined as:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(6)</label>
              <mml:math id="m7hhjaxo1x">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">cal</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">calibrated</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">total</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="md49b3ybsz">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">calibrated</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the portion of the monitoring period during which a documented in-date calibration status covered the relevant instruments.</p><p>Timestamp coherence is defined as:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(7)</label>
              <mml:math id="mocu2ndgni">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">sync</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">aligned</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">total</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m6gezwibxz">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">aligned</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the number of observations satisfying the predefined time-alignment rule; <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mgs9va0cfg">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">total</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the total number of observations in the monitored dataset. Each factor is computed as the ratio of valid observations to total observations within the monitoring period. LCAM adopts a multiplicative form because the three evidence factors are treated as conjunctive conditions. A complete monitoring interval is less defensible if the relevant instrument calibration has expired, and calibrated measurements are less useful if timestamps cannot be aligned with operational records [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">41</xref>]. The multiplicative structure, therefore, reflects the conservative assumption that weakness in any critical evidence condition is treated as lowering the defensibility of the overall mitigation claim. The construct is deliberately conservative and does not reflect registry rules.</p><p>The equation is developed based on the multiplicative structure of emission estimation models, in which activity data or base emission rates are combined with multiple correction factors, as outlined in the UNFCCC CDM methodological tool for project emissions from flaring (version 04.0, 2022) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>]. Because this functional form is an analytical simplification, the robustness of the LCAM comparison is assessed using <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="me7ho3z5mm">
    <mml:mo>±</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>5% evidence-factor sensitivity checks and alternative equal-weighted-average and weakest-link specifications. The base LCAM input values and multiplicative LCAM calculations are documented in Appendix D, Tables D1–D2, while the LCAM sensitivity calculations are reported in Appendix E, Tables E1–E2.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.8. Evidence-screening rules</title>
          
          <p>The same evidence-screening rules were applied to both MRV regimes to ensure that the before-and-after comparison used consistent data-acceptance criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>]. These rules were used to convert raw monitoring, calibration, operational, verification, and transaction-related records into evidence-supported observations. The purpose of the screening process was not to maximize the estimated issuability of emission reductions, but to identify the portion of monitored mitigation that could be defended under conservative evidence conditions.</p><p>The screening protocol follows the operating structure of the POME Biogas Co-Firing project at PKS Lubuk Dalam. The monitoring system contains records with mixed temporal resolutions. Logbook entries, anaerobic-process data, POME flow, COD, pH, temperature, methane fraction, and operating status were primarily recorded daily. In contrast, burner and biogas-supply parameters were recorded hourly during operating periods. Accordingly, daily records served as the primary monitoring unit, while hourly equipment-level records served as supporting traceability evidence for burner operation, biogas supply consistency, and verification of operating conditions.</p><p>Five screening rules were applied. First, to ensure complete monitoring, each record had to include the required activity-data field, a timestamp or a monitoring-period identifier, and a traceable source reference. Records were excluded when they were missing, corrupted, duplicated, or not traceable to an original monitoring file, operational log, project monitoring calculation sheet, or verification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>].</p><p>Second, calibration validity was assessed at the instrument-record level. A measurement was treated as evidentially valid only when the relevant instrument was supported by valid calibration or service documentation for the corresponding monitoring period. If the evidentiary weakness was limited to one instrument, parameter, or time interval, exclusion was applied only to the affected measurement and period, not to the entire project dataset. This rule was used to avoid both over-inclusion of unsupported measurements and over-exclusion of otherwise valid records [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>].</p><p>Third, temporal coherence was assessed by reconciling daily monitoring records, hourly operating records, logbook notes, project monitoring sheets, and verification evidence. Because the project files do not specify a fixed minute-level tolerance, this study did not impose an unsupported tolerance such as <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m334mn8xpf">
    <mml:mo>±</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>1 minute or <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7m5lsobnv">
    <mml:mo>±</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>1 hour. Instead, records were retained only when they could be matched to the same monitoring day or operating interval and reconciled with the corresponding operational or verification record. Records that could not be temporally reconciled were excluded from the evidence-supported dataset.</p><p>Fourth, data traceability required each processed value to be linked to a source record, storage location, calculation file, or verification evidence. Manual entries, spreadsheet values, or derived figures without a source file, audit trail, or verifiable calculation pathway were not treated as evidence-supported observations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>]. This rule was applied to prevent unsupported processed data from being treated as equivalent to traceable monitoring evidence.</p><p>Fifth, verification readiness required the evidence package to be internally consistent before it was used in the analytical calculation. Monitoring values had to be supported by source records, calibration evidence where relevant, operational explanations for abnormal values, and verification-related documentation. Records linked to unresolved inconsistencies, missing supporting files, or incomplete query-response evidence were flagged and excluded until the inconsistency was resolved.</p><p>The screening rules were defined before calculation and applied consistently across the legacy and enhanced MRV regimes. This approach adheres to the principle of measurement control and risk-based project governance, which stipulates that the criteria for acceptance of data must be pre-specified and applied consistently to prevent selective treatment of data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>]. These rules are not meant to replicate all aspects of formal verification. Rather, they provide a consistent and conservative basis for assessing the association between evidence fragility and the defensibility of mitigation claims. The detailed decision criteria, exclusion conditions, affected data fields, and examples are provided in Appendix B, Table B2.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.9. Realized-price wedge</title>
          
          <p>Settlement results are assessed by separating benchmark and realized prices:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(8)</label>
              <mml:math id="mjt3zie70b">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">real</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">bench</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m8vl822rwb">
    <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the realized-price wedge defined as:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(9)</label>
              <mml:math id="mmkesjezsw">
                <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">real</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">bench</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mey33brno4">
    <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> represents the proportional difference between benchmark and realized prices. In this study, it is used as an illustrative revenue-risk indicator that is consistent with information and delivery-risk exposure, rather than as a universal pricing relation or a causal estimate of MRV impact on prices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>]. The base price-wedge calculation and benchmark-price sensitivity are reported in Appendix E, Tables E3–E4.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.10. Issuance cadence and present-value adjustment</title>
          
          <p>Issuance cadence is measured as the duration between monitoring closure and issuance and is defined as:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(10)</label>
              <mml:math id="mr9me9vc9m">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">Cadence</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">issuance</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">monitoring</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m0t76f1jc8">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">Cadence</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes the duration between monitoring closure and issuance.</p><p>The present-value impact of earlier revenue recognition is calculated as:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(11)</label>
              <mml:math id="m31bl5uxeq">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PV</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                    <mml:msup>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msup>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>where, CF is a cash flow; $r<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mxdwfumnj4">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>t<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mkym0bmbx0">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>14</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>18</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>24</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>39</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>40</mml:mn>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>\Delta t<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m5plke5nxv">
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>r$.</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(12)</label>
              <mml:math id="m3pteqgve6">
                <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
                <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                <mml:msup>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mn>365</mml:mn>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msup>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.11. Integrated revenue identity</title>
          
          <p>Realized annual revenue is the following:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(13)</label>
              <mml:math id="m1nkrqa3vg">
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">real</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>The present value of the realized annual revenue is defined as [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">42</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>]:</p>
          
            <disp-formula>
              <label>(14)</label>
              <mml:math id="mrczbc87xw">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">realized</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                    <mml:msup>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msup>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:mfrac>
              </mml:math>
            </disp-formula>
          
          <p>These three aspects can be classified into analytically distinguishable elements: mitigation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">43</xref>], conservatively supportable mitigation (represented by LCAM), and monetary value (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="md8bu6jb7p">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>). This identity separates engineering performance, evidentiary defensibility, and monetary value into distinct analytical components.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.12. Analytical expectation</title>
          
          <p>Under fixed engineering and accounting conditions, the enhanced MRV regime is analytically expected to be associated with three more favorable finance-relevant project indicators.</p><p>First, a greater share of engineering emission reductions is expected to be conservatively supported by the evidence-screening rules. This relationship is captured in larger values of <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mxd3ob0p94">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">MRV</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m05bmjsz2n">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LCAM</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, which indicate that complete monitoring records, valid calibration evidence, and time-consistent documentation support a greater share of measured mitigation.</p><p>Second, the realized-price wedge is expected to be smaller under the enhanced MRV regime. A lower <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mwo4dz2a9x">
    <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> would indicate that the realized settlement price is closer to the benchmark price. However, this indicator should be interpreted cautiously because realized prices may also reflect buyer characteristics, contractual terms, bargaining position, payment timing, and broader market conditions.</p><p>Third, the monitoring-to-issuance period is expected to be shorter under the enhanced MRV regime. A shorter <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7zzvc3xt5">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">Cadence</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> would be consistent with lower timing friction between monitoring closure and issuance and may increase the relative present value of the same nominal cash flow.</p><p>This is not an automatic outcome, but it is consistent with the analytical mechanism presented here. Other factors, including market conditions and procedural constraints, may also influence the observed outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]. The goal of this analysis is not to identify all possible causes, but to examine whether the observed patterns are consistent with stronger evidentiary conditions and lower evidentiary friction within the project.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>3. Results</title>
      <p>The results are organized around four aspects of project management: emission-reduction engineering, conservative issuability, price-wedge realization, and issuance cadence. This categorization separates physical mitigation performance from evidentiary robustness, realized settlement outcomes, and cash-flow timing. The approach follows the principle of analytical separability across three dimensions: emission-reduction engineering, conservative issuability under evidentiary constraints, and financial realization through price and timing. Since the engineering and accounting systems are held fixed under the two MRV regimes, the results describe differences in evidentiary conditions rather than changes in physical mitigation performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>].</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Engineering emission reductions</title>
          
          <p>Annual emission reductions were computed using the accounting relations in Section 2. The baseline emission was 21.53 ktCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mz7or1qnm1">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mfp2v4lzqz">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and the project emission was 2.845 ktCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mjcaz13vaj">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mbz9vjnhs2">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, resulting in an annual engineering emission reduction of 18.69 ktCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mrs6878ehp">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mryl684wmd">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> (21.53-2.845) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>). The same engineering emission-reduction input is used in the base LCAM and sensitivity calculations reported in Appendix D, Tables D1–D2. This value is held constant across the legacy and enhanced MRV regimes, allowing subsequent differences in LCAM, the realized-price wedge, and issuance cadence to be interpreted as associated with evidentiary conditions rather than with changes in methane-abatement technology or accounting rules. Such differences are interpreted as being associated with variations in how identical quantified mitigation is supported, validated, and handled within the system of proof [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>].</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Annual engineering accounting outcomes</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Step</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Equation</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Inputs Shown</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Result</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Baseline emissions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mnwuwo91rs">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">BE</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  </mml:msub>
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">BM</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CH</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mtext> baseline, </mml:mtext>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">GWP</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:msub>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CH</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
        <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
      </mml:msub>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mu61t20knu">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">BM</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:msub>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CH</mml:mi>
          <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
        </mml:msub>
        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">baseline</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> = 0.7915 <mml:math id="mtrucvpaf5">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">GWP</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:msub>
          <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">CH</mml:mi>
          <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
        </mml:msub>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> = 27.2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>21.53 ktCO<mml:math id="mavnmcnh0y">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e·y<mml:math id="m198g8kmpy">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Project emissions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m3buu9fnb7">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> = <mml:math id="mrgzjswrrq">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">flare</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> + <mml:math id="mxb3xeys9e">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">residual</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mkwqq91pig">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">flare</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> = 2.176 <mml:math id="muu0j9mzo7">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">residual</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> = 0.669</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.845 ktCO<mml:math id="m5rabodzhd">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e·y<mml:math id="mumc25asit">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Emission reductions</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="mf57rh7ur7">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">ER</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  </mml:msub>
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">BE</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  </mml:msub>
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">PE</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  </mml:msub>
  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
</mml:math></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>–</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18.69 ktCO<mml:math id="m5w9wt6le0">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e·y<mml:math id="m6xka30ile">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Conservative issuability under alternative monitoring, reporting, and verification regimes</title>
          
          <p>Conservative issuability was quantified using LCAM. For the legacy MRV regime, interval completeness, calibration validity, and timestamp coherence were 0.93, 0.92, and 0.90, respectively. These values produced a composite evidentiary factor of 0.770 (0.93 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7ya0ope27">
    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> 0.92 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mqo5jmihlc">
    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> 0.90). When applied to the annual engineering emission reductions of 18.69 ktCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m4hedfxv6t">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mwtft79ner">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, this yielded a conservative estimate of issuability of 14.39 ktCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="ml6ce0jprq">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mzeygqt05x">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. For the enhanced MRV regime, the corresponding factors were 0.98, 0.97, and 0.96, yielding a composite evidentiary factor of 0.913 (0.98 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myo3u44fgt">
    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> 0.97 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mo0q64kefp">
    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> 0.96) and a conservative issuability estimate of 17.07 ktCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mem6wlgmt3">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mj0gpk3w18">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. The conservatively supportable fraction of engineering emission reductions therefore increased from 77.0% to 91.3%, equivalent to an increase of 2.68 ktCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mwdesx4fsi">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mnh7o10brs">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> (17.07 $-$ 14.39) in supportable mitigation. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> reports the evidence factors and resulting conservative issuability under both MRV regimes. The detailed input values and multiplicative LCAM calculation supporting these results are provided in Appendix D, Tables D1–D2. This classification highlights the relationship between the quality of evidence and the share of engineering mitigation that can be considered with high confidence. The implication here is that equal engineering mitigation measures are not always supported by equal evidence quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>].</p><p>From the perspective of project managers, each of the three LCAM criteria is reflected in tangible MRV key performance indicators. Completeness of intervals reflects the reliability of the monitoring system, validity of calibrations reflects discipline in the governance of measurements, and coherence of timestamps reflects the ability to compile verifiable evidence.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Evidence factors and conservative issuability</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><td >Component</td><td >Legacy MRV</td><td >Enhanced MRV</td><td >Basis of Construction</td></tr><tr><td >Interval completeness, <mml:math id="m0kn384pm8">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">int</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></td><td >0.930</td><td >0.980</td><td >Share of monitoring period supported by valid and usable records</td></tr><tr><td >Calibration validity, <mml:math id="mv02y3v97r">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">cal</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></td><td >0.920</td><td >0.970</td><td >Share of the monitoring period covered by documented in-date calibration status</td></tr><tr><td >Timestamp coherence, <mml:math id="mqlsjb89ea">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">sync</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></td><td >0.900</td><td >0.960</td><td >Share of observations satisfying the time-alignment rule</td></tr><tr><td >Composite evidentiary support factor, <mml:math id="mgglnmzd5q">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">MRV</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></td><td >0.770</td><td >0.913</td><td ><mml:math id="mcatdsuoqq">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">int</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>× <mml:math id="m4d5ws232i">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">cal</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> × <mml:math id="m3vcu60kmc">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">sync</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></td></tr><tr><td >Engineering reduction, (ktCO<mml:math id="mnswy42jaz">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e·y<mml:math id="mgwevoywf3">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math>)</td><td >18.690</td><td >18.690</td><td >Calculated from baseline and project emissions</td></tr><tr><td >Conservative issuability, <mml:math id="mrdoa7ccgd">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LCAM</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> (ktCO<mml:math id="m0y9bmhamx">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e·y<mml:math id="mcxbew3tlk">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math>)</td><td >14.390</td><td >17.070</td><td ><mml:math id="mp0qx17dti">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">ER</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> × <mml:math id="m4p1l1zq6m">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">MRV</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math></td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Realized settlement price and price wedge</title>
          
          <p>The benchmark price of Rp150,000/tCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mdsrvxt6de">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e was taken from the SRN-PPI/IDXCarbon marketplace record for the same project: “POME for Biogas Co-Firing PT Perkebunan Nusantara IV (PTPN IV PalmCo Regional 3)” (Registration Number: SPE-11-PR-VI-2024-18003) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">44</xref>]. In this study, this value is used as a project-specific registry reference price for the illustrative price-wedge calculation. It is not treated as a universal market price, nor as evidence that all methane-abatement credits should transact at that level.</p><p>With the benchmark price held at Rp150,000/tCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mseszkjmxx">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e, the realized settlement price was Rp105,000/tCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mqvbp6n6a2">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e under the legacy MRV regime and Rp132,000/tCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mw448udp8b">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e under the enhanced MRV regime. This corresponds to a realized-price wedge of 0.300 for the legacy regime and 0.120 for the enhanced regime (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>). In terms of value capture, the project captured 70% of the benchmark value under the legacy regime and 88% under the enhanced regime. The base price-wedge calculation and benchmark-price sensitivity are reported in Appendix E, Tables E3–E4. This pattern is interpreted as an illustrative revenue-risk indicator rather than as evidence that MRV enhancement alone caused the pricing difference [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>].</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_4">
              <label>Table 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Realized settlement price and wedge</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><td >MRV Regime</td><td >Benchmark Price, <mml:math id="m00x1ev4ou">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">bench</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> (Rp/tCO<mml:math id="mhfd25pncw">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e)</td><td >Realized Settlement Price, <mml:math id="mf20ohwucu">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">real</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> (Rp/tCO<mml:math id="moadwgmzkw">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e)</td><td >Realized-Price Wedge, <mml:math id="mhrnpcohep">
  <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
</mml:math></td></tr><tr><td >Legacy MRV</td><td >150,000</td><td >105,000</td><td >0.30</td></tr><tr><td >Enhanced MRV</td><td >150,000</td><td >132,000</td><td >0.12</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>From a managerial perspective, the realized-price wedge can support buyer negotiations and revenue risk assessment. The lower wedge indicates that the realized settlement price is closer to the benchmark price in this within-project comparison. However, actual realized prices may also reflect buyer characteristics, contractual arrangements, settlement timing, bargaining position, and broader market conditions. The price-wedge result should therefore be read only as an illustrative within-project revenue-risk indicator, not as a general MRV price-premium estimate or a causal estimate of an MRV-driven pricing effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.4. Issuance cadence and timing effect</title>
          
          <p>The issuance cadence was shorter in the enhanced MRV period, declining from 130 days under the legacy MRV regime to 80 days under the enhanced MRV regime, a 50-day difference (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref>). At a 10.41% annual discount rate, which represents the project's estimated WACC used for internal financial analysis, a 50-day reduction in issuance lag corresponds to a relative present-value uplift of approximately 1.36%–1.37%. The relative present-value uplift and discount-rate sensitivity are reported in Appendix E, Table E5. For project managers, issuance cadence is a liquidity and working-capital indicator because it is reflected in the timing of expected cash inflows, even when nominal credit volume and realized prices remain unchanged [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>].</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_5">
              <label>Table 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Issuance cadence and present-value effect</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Item</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Output</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Issuance cadence (days)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>130</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>80</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p><mml:math id="m87ohdvsl0">
  <mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
  <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:math> = 50</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Discount rate</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10.41%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10.41%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>–</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Present-value uplift from earlier receipt</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>–</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>–</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.37%</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.5. Integrated realized revenue</title>
          
          <p>Annual realized revenue was examined under two analytical scenarios using the LCAM and realized-price inputs reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref> and supported by Appendix D, Tables D1–D2, and Appendix E, Table E3. Conservative issuability was fixed at 14,390 tCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m91jxvhueq">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="myz9jt0dg5">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> in the price-only case. Under this price-only scenario, the calculated revenue differs from Rp 1,510,950,000 (14,390 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mnyswzy3xg">
    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> 105,000) to Rp 1,899,480,000 (14,390 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m4z14xpjl3">
    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> 132,000), corresponding to a scenario difference of Rp 388,530,000 under the higher realized settlement price used for the enhanced-regime scenario. In contrast, both the conservative issuability and realized prices were allowed to vary by regime.</p><p>Under the full scenario, calculated revenue increases from Rp 1,510,950,000 to Rp 2,253,240,000 (17,070 <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mu5dxphqhz">
    <mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> 132,000), corresponding to an aggregate scenario difference of Rp 742,290,000. This comparison separates the price-related channel from the combined effect of price and conservative issuability, allowing project managers to assess the potential financial relevance of MRV improvement scenarios relative to the costs of calibration systems, data management, personnel training, and verification-file preparation. The annual realized revenue under the alternative MRV scenarios is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_6">Table 6</xref>.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_6">
              <label>Table 6</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Annual realized revenue under alternative scenarios</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tr><td >MRV Regime</td><td >Conservative Issuability, <mml:math id="mu24nszh06">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">LCAM</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> (tCO<mml:math id="m1wc5paudp">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e<mml:math id="mexwvmfdf5">
  <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
</mml:math>y<mml:math id="m9kslmftb5">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math>)</td><td >Realized Price, <mml:math id="mpr5tktraq">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mi data-mjx-auto-op="false">real</mml:mi>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> (Rp/tCO<mml:math id="mfwizs4w14">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math>e)</td><td >Realized Revenue, <mml:math id="m2lre7w5l9">
  <mml:msub>
    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msub>
</mml:math> (Rp<mml:math id="muk4k15ru3">
  <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
</mml:math>y<mml:math id="mk8qr2su1j">
  <mml:msup>
    <mml:mi/>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:msup>
</mml:math>)</td></tr><tr><td >Legacy MRV</td><td >14,390</td><td >105,000</td><td >1,510,950,000</td></tr><tr><td >Enhanced MRV (price-only scenario)</td><td >14,390</td><td >132,000</td><td >1,899,480,000</td></tr><tr><td >Enhanced MRV (full scenario)</td><td >17,070</td><td >132,000</td><td >2,253,240,000</td></tr></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.6. Sensitivity analysis</title>
          
          <p>Four sensitivity analyses were conducted to assess whether the underlying LCAM specification, benchmark price assumption, or discount rate assumption influences the project's central pattern. The detailed workings of these four sensitivity analyses are shown in Appendix E, Tables E1–E6. First, each LCAM evidence factor was adjusted by <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="my25gtv4or">
    <mml:mo>±</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>5%. Second, alternative LCAM calculations based on weighted-average and weakest-link specifications were performed. Third, alternative benchmark prices for the price-wedge calculations were used, adjusted by <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mp05g4wi4j">
    <mml:mo>±</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>10%. Fourth, the uplift in relative present value was recalculated with discount rates of 6%, 8%, 10.41% and 12%.</p><p>The purpose of the sensitivity analyses is not to prove a cause-and-effect relationship but rather to assess whether this pattern holds under different assumptions. A summary of the sensitivity analysis is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_7">Table 7</xref>.</p><p>Across all scenarios considered, the enhanced MRV regime remains associated with a higher conservative estimate of issuability, a lower realized-price wedge, and a positive relative PV uplift. These results are consistent with directional stability in the within-project pattern under the non-causal analytical design used in this study.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_7">
              <label>Table 7</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Sensitivity analysis of LCAM, price wedge, and relative PV uplift</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sensitivity Test</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Interpretation</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Base multiplicative LCAM</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14.39</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>17.07</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Main analytical proxy</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LCAM factors reduced by 5%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12.35</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14.63</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhanced remains higher</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LCAM factors increased by 5%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>16.67</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18.69</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhanced remains higher</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Equal-weighted average LCAM</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>17.13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18.13</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Alternative functional form; enhanced remains higher</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Weakest-link LCAM</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>16.82</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>17.94</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Conservative weakest-condition rule; enhanced remains higher</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wedge at benchmark reduced by 10%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.222</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.022</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhanced wedge remains smaller</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wedge at benchmark increased by 10%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.364</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.200</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhanced wedge remains smaller</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PV uplift at 6%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>–</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.80%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lower discount-rate assumption</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PV uplift at 8%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>–</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.06%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Moderate discount-rate assumption</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PV uplift at 10.41%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>–</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.37%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Base discount-rate assumption</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PV uplift at 12%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>–</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.56%</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Higher discount-rate assumption</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>4. Discussion</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Low-confidence adjustment metric as an monitoring, reporting, and verification project management indicator</title>
          
          <p>These results highlight an important distinction in carbon project management: engineered emission reductions do not automatically become financially usable carbon revenue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]. The project's underlying engineering emission reduction remained constant across the two MRV regimes. Nonetheless, the conservatively defensible proportion increased from 77.0% to 91.3%, the realized-price wedge declined from 0.300 to 0.120, and the monitoring-to-issuance interval shortened by 50 days under the enhanced MRV regime. These calculations are reported in Appendix D (Tables D1–D2) and Appendix E (Tables E1–E6).</p><p>In other words, this indicates that engineering mitigation and financially usable carbon revenue are two distinct analytical outputs. The financial usability of a carbon project, therefore, depends upon the degree of completeness, calibration, temporal coherence, traceability, and verification readiness without much evidentiary friction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]. From a pragmatic viewpoint, the question of usability lies beyond whether the mitigation took place, but rather the possibility of verifying whether such evidence is reconstructible and defensible before trading [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>].</p><p>From this perspective, MRV processes should be viewed as evidentiary infrastructure for the project rather than simply as an implementation-monitoring function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">38</xref>]. In essence, MRV evidence quality is associated with how defensible, transaction-ready, and timely the carbon-revenue claim is. At the same time, financial outcomes may also depend on market, contractual, buyer-related, and institutional factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Conservative issuability and the defensible share of measured mitigation</title>
          
          <p>In particular, this point becomes evident when considering the effect of the engineering input on LCAM. With the same engineering emission-reduction input, LCAM rises from 14.39 to 17.07 ktCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m4xuhftfh0">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mm7x8vpsz6">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. The rise suggests a larger share of the measured mitigation is defensible under the specified evidence-screening criteria. Therefore, it can be interpreted as further supporting the statement that the measured mitigation may not necessarily mean defensible mitigation in light of conservative evidentiary criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>].</p><p>LCAM helps clarify which portion of the measured mitigation remains defensible under specified evidence conditions. This interpretation is consistent with verification-based approaches that emphasize traceability, documentation, and justified evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>]. This interpretation is also consistent with broader integrity studies showing that carbon-credit credibility depends not only on technical performance but also on sufficient supporting evidence. Rather than simply restating that evidence quality matters, LCAM provides a transparent analytical device for showing how evidentiary weakness affects the conservatively supportable fraction of measured mitigation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>].</p><p>Therefore, LCAM cannot be treated as a replication of the carbon-credit issuance procedure but as a deliberately conservative analysis. Its purpose is to illustrate how evidence deficiencies are associated with the defensible share of measured mitigation. Terms such as ``verified reduction'' may blur the distinction between measured mitigation and the conservatively defensible share of mitigation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>].</p><p>This distinction also raises an important practical issue for project developers. In addition to the general discrepancy between the credited and actual emissions reduction, there is also a difference between measured environmental performance and the portion of it that can be claimed with specified evidentiary considerations. From this perspective, conservative issuability can be understood as an indicator of how defensible measured environmental performance is within institutional and verification settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.3. Realized settlement outcomes: cautious interpretation of the price wedge</title>
          
          <p>The price-wedge result should be interpreted with particular caution. In the within-project comparison, the realized settlement price increased from Rp 105,000 to Rp 132,000 per tCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mzteaefiyv">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e, while the realized-price wedge decreased from 0.30 to 0.12. Although this pattern is consistent with lower information and delivery-risk exposure, the study design cannot rule out other explanations, including contractual terms, buyer characteristics, payment timing, bargaining position, and broader market conditions. The result should therefore not be interpreted as evidence that stronger MRV necessarily produces a market premium. Such a generalization would go beyond the scope of this single-project analysis and the observed variation in voluntary carbon-offset prices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]. More cautiously, the within-project pattern indicates that stronger evidence is associated with smaller discounts relative to the benchmark, consistent with lower information and delivery-risk exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>].</p><p>In particular, the decline in the realized-price wedge (0.30 → 0.12) may indicate lower perceived information and delivery-risk exposure in this within-project setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>] When counterparties cannot fully assess the quality or deliverability of an asset, they may rely on discounts, contingencies, selective contracting, or conservative settlement practices to limit exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]. This issue is particularly relevant for carbon-credit contracts because the underlying claims depend on technical data, procedural documentation, and verification records that counterparties may not be able to audit independently. In such situations, enhanced evidence does not mean a rise in the benchmark price, but it can rather reflect reduced uncertainty and less depressed price levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. The result is therefore better interpreted through an information-risk lens than as evidence of a general MRV price premium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>].</p><p>A price-premium interpretation would imply that higher MRV quality consistently commands higher prices across settings, whereas a more restrained interpretation requires fewer causal assumptions. In this case, the pricing pattern associated with stronger evidence is better interpreted as convergence toward the benchmark price under information- and delivery-risk conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>]. This interpretation is consistent with studies suggesting that clearer, more complete environmental information may influence third-party assessments of climate-related claims [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>]. This is also aligned with the governance literature that links disclosure quality, transparency, and market confidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>]. Nevertheless, realized prices may depend on many other factors, and the current design does not rule out these effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.4. Issuance cadence and project cash-flow timing</title>
          
          <p>Timing is an important dimension of liquidity and financial usability, and it provides a third project-management indicator in addition to conservative issuability and price realization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]. In the enhanced MRV period, the monitoring-to-issuance interval was shorter, declining from 130 to 80 days. Although issuance cadence may appear administrative, it is financially relevant because credits remain illiquid until issuance is completed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]. A shorter issuance interval is therefore consistent with more favorable expected cash-flow timing and corresponds to an estimated present-value uplift of approximately 1.4% for the same nominal cash flow [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>]. This timing channel extends the interpretation of MRV quality beyond defensible volume and realized price, because delayed revenue is not neutral in project-finance terms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>].</p><p>The cadence result is consistent with the broader mechanism proposed in this paper. If the analysis had shown higher conservative issuability without a shorter issuance cadence, the finding would have been largely procedural. Conversely, faster issuance without greater supportability would have provided weaker support for the relevance of MRV evidence. The observed pattern is instead coherent across supportability, settlement, and timing, suggesting that evidence quality is associated with the pathway from measured mitigation to usable revenue rather than only with isolated verification steps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>]. This interpretation should still be treated cautiously, as faster issuance may also be influenced by registry backlogs, verifier workload, administrative timing, and other procedural factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>].</p><p>Thus, while the analysis cannot claim that MRV accounts for all variation in issuance speed, the within-project evidence indicates that higher evidence quality is correlated with faster issuance and is consistent with lower evidentiary friction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">45</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.5. Monitoring, reporting, and verification governance for project managers</title>
          
          <p>The findings indicate that MRV governance should be viewed as a project risk-management infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>]. This interpretation is consistent with project risk management principles, which emphasize integrating risk control into planning, monitoring, and management routines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">36</xref>]. For engineering project managers, MRV improvement should therefore go beyond the preparation of verification documents and be embedded in routine controls, including calibration registers, timestamp rules, data version control, internal evidence review, and verification-readiness checklists [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]. In practical terms, project managers should maintain calibration registers with instrument ID, calibration date, expiry date, responsible officer, certificate location, and expiry warnings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]. Timestamp rules should be specified before the monitoring period begins. Monitoring records should be stored in a version-controlled repository linking raw data, processed datasets, calibration files, and verification submissions, and an internal verification-readiness checklist should be completed before external verification begins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>].</p><p>Finally, MRV indicators should be integrated into carbon-revenue forecasting. Instead of forecasting revenue directly from engineering emission reductions, project managers should distinguish between engineering reductions, conservatively supportable reductions, expected realized price, expected issuance lag, and discount-rate assumptions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">39</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">40</xref>].</p><p>This approach enables MRV weaknesses to be represented as revenue-risk scenarios before they appear in verification, settlement, or cash-flow timing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.6. Boundaries of the contribution</title>
          
          <p>These boundaries are important because the present study addresses evidence-management risk rather than the full environmental integrity of carbon offsetting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">32</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>]. Neither the present results nor related studies imply that stronger MRV resolves fundamental structural critiques of offsetting. Issues such as baseline weakness, leakage, permanence, and strategic behavior remain outside the scope of the framework presented here [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>]. A project may be supported by strong evidence yet remain vulnerable to counterfactual bias, and improved documentation alone does not ensure environmental credibility when the underlying offset logic is weak [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">47</xref>]. Accordingly, the findings should be interpreted as transferable analytical principles rather than transferable effect sizes.</p><p>Second, the research design is intended to identify mechanism-consistent patterns, not average financial-market effects. By relying on a within-project comparison, the study examines changes in evidence conditions while holding the engineering setting constant. Prices and issuance outcomes may still vary according to project-specific and institution-specific characteristics; therefore, the relationships observed here may be context-specific [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>].</p><p>Third, the analytical constructs are inherently conservative. It is important to emphasize that LCAM is neither registry-based nor verifier-oriented. The same applies to the realized-price wedge, which does not capture all transaction-specific determinants of settlement value. Such an approach has been chosen deliberately to preserve analytical simplicity and to demonstrate the link between the variables analyzed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.7. Implications for further research</title>
          
          <p>The above constraints also point toward possible directions for future research. First, future research should test the replicability of this framework across project types, crediting standards, and transaction structures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>]. Such research could assess whether the LCAM–price-wedge–issuance-cadence pattern observed here is general, conditional, or context-specific. It could also clarify where evidence quality is most relevant, such as in projects with long monitoring chains, settings with lower buyer trust, or transactions where delivery risk is more salient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">33</xref>].</p><p>Second, future research could examine evidential fragility and counterfactual fragility more explicitly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">46</xref>]. In other words, projects might be characterized by the strength of their monitoring claim relative to that of additionality. Exploring this difference would help us understand why certain projects can face significant challenges of evidential contestation even when they present an extensive monitoring record. In contrast, others may appear less controversial despite weaknesses in the evidence supporting additionality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]. This distinction is important if future research is to avoid collapsing different carbon-credit quality problems into a single undifferentiated category.</p><p>A third direction concerns the financial architecture of carbon projects. The analysis indicates that evidence quality may be associated with the defensibility of mitigation quantity, realized settlement outcomes, and revenue timing. Future research could examine whether these associations are also reflected in financing terms, contract design, risk allocation, or project valuation under more complex cash-flow patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>]. Such work would extend the evaluation beyond revenue usability toward carbon-project bankability. In that sense, the present analysis identifies one manageable aspect of a broader institutional dilemma. It does not seek to determine the future trajectory of carbon markets. Rather, it illustrates, more narrowly and practically, how evidence quality may be associated with whether measured mitigation can be made supportable, saleable, and timely enough to be treated as project revenue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>5. Conclusions</title>
      <p>This study examined how MRV system management is associated with conservative issuability, realized-price wedge, and issuance cadence in a methane-abatement engineering project. Under fixed engineering and accounting conditions, the enhanced MRV regime was associated with a higher conservatively supportable share of engineering emission reductions, a smaller realized-price wedge, and a shorter monitoring-to-issuance period. Under identical engineering emission reductions of 18.69 ktCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mt90hcvgzn">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="melp634d58">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, the enhanced evidence condition was associated with a higher conservatively supportable fraction of mitigation (77.0% to 91.3%), a lower realized-price wedge (0.30 to 0.12), and a shorter monitoring-to-issuance interval (130 to 80 days). These differences correspond to an increase in conservative issuability from 14.39 to 17.07 ktCO<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m9bennz5zz">
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>e·y<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m1a3m7ynix">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi/>
      <mml:mrow>
        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
      </mml:mrow>
    </mml:msup>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and a shorter revenue-realization interval, with an estimated present-value uplift of approximately 1.4%.</p><p>This distinction is especially important for interpreting LCAM. In this study, LCAM is used strictly as a transparent analytical proxy for conservative supportability under specified evidence conditions, not as an issuance rule, registry indicator, or substitute for verifier judgment.</p><p>From a project management standpoint, the findings indicate that higher-quality MRV evidence is associated with three complementary revenue-risk indicators: greater defensibility of mitigation volume, lower price-wedge realization, and a shorter interval between monitoring and credit issuance. These three factors appear together in the project-level comparison, indicating that MRV evidence quality is correlated not only with the defensibility of emission reductions but also with settlement- and time-based revenue-risk factors.</p><p>The contribution of this study is intentionally limited in scope. While it does not claim that MRV can resolve structural integrity problems associated with additionality, baseline uncertainty, leakage, and permanence, it provides a bounded analysis of the correlation between evidence quality and finance-relevant metrics. By focusing on MRV as a risk control system for engineering projects, the analysis highlights the importance of monitoring consistency, calibration validity, proper timestamp alignment, and chain-of-custody traceability as project-level factors for verification readiness, revenue estimation, and carbon trading.</p><p>Future research can extend this framework across multiple project types, crediting mechanisms, and market conditions to assess whether the relationships observed here are general, conditional, or context-specific. Further studies could also examine how evidentiary quality interacts with contract design, financing terms, and institutional procedures in shaping carbon-project bankability.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <div><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman, sans-serif; font-size: 16px">The authors gratefully acknowledge Kantor PKS Lubuk Dalam PTPN IV Regional 3, Pangkalan Pisang, Lubuk Dalam, Siak Regency, Riau, Indonesia, for providing the research data used in this study.</div>
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        <p>Appendix A. Project context and MRV-regime comparison</p><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" ><p>Table A1. Project context and analytical boundaries</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Project-Context Item</p></td><td  ><p>Description</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Project type</p></td><td  ><p>Methane recovery and abatement in palm oil mill effluent wastewater treatment through biogas capture and biogas co-firing. The project captures methane-rich biogas from anaerobic POME treatment and combusts it in a boiler to replace part of the palm-shell boiler fuel, while excess biogas is flared.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Site</p></td><td  ><p>Palm Oil Mill Effluent wastewater treatment facility at PKS Lubuk Dalam, owned and operated by PT Perkebunan Nusantara IV Regional III, located in Lubuk Dalam, Sialang Baru, and Koto Gasib area, Kampung Pangkalan Pisang, Lubuk Dalam District, Siak Regency, Riau Province, Indonesia. The reported coordinates are N 00°37'47.6'' and E 101°46'04.0''.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Operating unit</p></td><td  ><p>Existing POME treatment system upgraded with methane capture and biogas co-firing facilities. The system includes a CIGAR-covered anaerobic reactor, a biogas line to the boiler, a biogas burner for co-firing, and a flare stack for excess gas or safety control.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Number of flares or engines</p></td><td  ><p>The available documents confirm the presence of a flaring system or flare stack and a biogas burner connected to the boiler. The project is not described as a biogas engine power generation project. The exact number of flare stacks, burners, or boiler units is not explicitly disclosed in the available project documents.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Official monitoring period</p></td><td  ><p>19 November 2021 to 18 November 2024, as reported in the project monitoring and verification documents.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Legacy MRV period</p></td><td  ><p>19 November 2021 to 31 December 2023. This period is defined analytically as the earlier evidence-management condition within the same official monitoring period.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV period</p></td><td  ><p>1 January 2024 to 18 November 2024. This period is defined analytically as the latter evidence-management condition after intensified verification-related data-quality strengthening.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Reason for MRV strengthening</p></td><td  ><p>MRV strengthening was associated with validation and verification requirements rather than a change in the underlying methane-abatement technology. The validation and verification processes assessed data completeness, calibration, missing-data handling, monitoring implementation, data-quality controls, and consistency between project implementation and validated documentation.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Upgrade components</p></td><td  ><p>Monitoring continuity, calibration register and equipment-calibration control, timestamp and monitoring-record consistency, missing-data handling, traceable record storage, internal evidence review, data-quality management, verification-query response management, and linkage between raw monitoring records, project monitoring calculation files, and verification evidence.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Operating arrangement</p></td><td  ><p>The project is owned and operated by PT Perkebunan Nusantara IV Regional III, PKS Lubuk Dalam. PT Ecody Agro Energi is identified in the project documents as the company that built the biogas project. PT SUCOFINDO ICS conducted validation and verification. The buyer or settlement party is anonymized because it is not explicitly disclosed in the available project documents.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" ><p>Table A2. Comparative description of the legacy and enhanced MRV regimes</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Comparison Item</p></td><td  ><p>Legacy MRV Regime</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV Regime</p></td><td  ><p>Relevance for Interpretation</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Analytical period</p></td><td  ><p>19 November 2021–31 December 2023</p></td><td  ><p>1 January 2024–18 November 2024</p></td><td  ><p>Defines the two analytical periods within the official project monitoring period.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Number of daily observations</p></td><td  ><p>773 daily observations</p></td><td  ><p>323 daily observations</p></td><td  ><p>Indicates the relative size of the two within-project observation windows.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Project site</p></td><td  ><p>PKS Lubuk Dalam, Siak Regency, Riau Province, Indonesia</p></td><td  ><p>Same project site</p></td><td  ><p>Holds the project location constant across the two analytical periods.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Project technology</p></td><td  ><p>POME methane recovery using CIGAR/covered anaerobic reactor, biogas co-firing in boiler, and a flaring system for excess gas</p></td><td  ><p>Same methane-abatement technology and same project boundary</p></td><td  ><p>Helps separate MRV evidence-management differences from physical technology changes.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Operating status</p></td><td  ><p>Commercial operation under the existing POME treatment, methane capture, biogas co-firing, and flaring configuration</p></td><td  ><p>Continued operation under the same engineering configuration</p></td><td  ><p>Supports the interpretation that the comparison concerns evidence-management conditions rather than the installation of new technology.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Engineering and accounting basis</p></td><td  ><p>UNFCCC AMS-III.H and methodological tool for project emissions from flaring</p></td><td  ><p>Same methodological and accounting basis</p></td><td  ><p>Reduces heterogeneity in accounting rules between the two periods.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>MRV condition</p></td><td  ><p>More fragmented evidence preparation, manual reconciliation of records, less systematic calibration tracking, and weaker integration between operational records and verification evidence</p></td><td  ><p>Stronger monitoring continuity, calibration-register discipline, timestamp alignment, missing-data handling, traceable record storage, and linkage between raw monitoring records, project monitoring calculation files, and verification evidence</p></td><td  ><p>Identifies the main management system difference examined in the study.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Verifier identity</p></td><td  ><p>PT SUCOFINDO ICS, based on the available validation and verification documentation</p></td><td  ><p>PT SUCOFINDO ICS, based on the available validation and verification documentation</p></td><td  ><p>Holding the verifier constant reduces one source of procedural variation, although verifier workload and review timing may still vary.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Reason for MRV strengthening</p></td><td  ><p>Earlier evidence-management condition before intensified verification-related data-quality strengthening</p></td><td  ><p>MRV strengthening was associated with validation and verification requirements, including PTK and PTS follow-up, calibration assessment, missing-data handling, monitoring-plan implementation, and GHG data information quality management</p></td><td  ><p>Clarifies that the upgrade is treated as a verification-readiness and management-system intervention, not as a technology-change intervention.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Contract type</p></td><td  ><p>Project-level carbon-credit settlement arrangement. Detailed contractual clauses are commercially confidential and are not disclosed.</p></td><td  ><p>Project-level carbon-credit settlement arrangement. Detailed contractual clauses are commercially confidential and are not disclosed.</p></td><td  ><p>Contract terms may influence realized prices. Therefore, pricing results are interpreted as illustrative revenue-risk indicators rather than causal MRV price effects.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Buyer profile</p></td><td  ><p>Buyer identity is anonymized because it is not explicitly disclosed in the available project documents and may be commercially sensitive.</p></td><td  ><p>Buyer identity is anonymized because it is not explicitly disclosed in the available project documents and may be commercially sensitive.</p></td><td  ><p>Buyer characteristics and bargaining position may affect the realized-price wedge and cannot be fully controlled.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Benchmark price reference</p></td><td  ><p>Rp 150,000/tCO$_2$e used as a project-specific registry reference price for illustrative price-wedge calculation.~</p></td><td  ><p>Same benchmark reference used for comparability.</p></td><td  ><p>Ensures that the wedge calculation applies a consistent reference value across regimes.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Market and institutional conditions</p></td><td  ><p>Carbon-credit pricing and issuance conditions may be affected by market sentiment, buyer demand, registry processing, verifier workload, and institutional procedures. These factors are not independently controlled in the study.</p></td><td  ><p>The same category of external conditions may apply, but their period-specific effects cannot be fully isolated.</p></td><td  ><p>Reinforces that the study reports within-project associations, not causal identification.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Analytical interpretation</p></td><td  ><p>The legacy regime represents the earlier evidence-management condition.</p></td><td  ><p>The enhanced regime represents the latter evidence-management condition following MRV strengthening.</p></td><td  ><p>The comparison supports mechanism-consistent association, not general causal inference.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p>Appendix B. Data transparency and evidence-screening protocol</p><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="8" ><p>Table B1. Data sources, coverage, screening, exclusion, treatment, and confidentiality</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Data Type</p></td><td  ><p>Source</p></td><td  ><p>Time Span</p></td><td  ><p>Recording Frequency</p></td><td  ><p>Screening or Exclusion Treatment</p></td><td  ><p>Excluded Records or Exclusion Rate</p></td><td  ><p>Cross-Check</p></td><td  ><p>Confidentiality Treatment</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Monitoring logs and activity data records</p></td><td  ><p>Project monitoring database, project monitoring sheets, and operational logbooks for the POME biogas co-firing system</p></td><td  ><p>Official monitoring period: 19 Nov 2021–18 Nov 2024. Legacy MRV: 19 Nov 2021–31 Dec 2023. Enhanced MRV: 1 Jan 2024–18 Nov 2024</p></td><td  ><p>Daily or hourly, depending on the monitored parameter; annual aggregation used for LCAM calculation.</p></td><td  ><p>Missing, corrupted, duplicated, or untraceable records were excluded from the evidence-supported dataset</p></td><td  ><p>5.5% (61 of 1,096 daily observation-equivalents)</p></td><td  ><p>Operational logs, project monitoring calculation files, wastewater-flow records, COD records, biogas-combustion records, and monitoring sheets</p></td><td  ><p>Reported only in aggregated form</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Calibration certificates and instrument-governance records</p></td><td  ><p>Instrument service files, calibration certificates, calibration-validity records, and maintenance documentation</p></td><td  ><p>19 Nov 2021–18 Nov 2024, aligned with the official monitoring period</p></td><td  ><p>Certificate-based and event-based</p></td><td  ><p>Measurements outside valid calibration periods or without supporting calibration documentation were excluded for the affected instrument and period</p></td><td  ><p>6.5% (72 of 1,096 daily/instrument-period observation-equivalents)</p></td><td  ><p>Service records, certificate validity dates, instrument identification records, and verification evidence files</p></td><td  ><p>Certificate IDs and instrument-specific details were anonymized where required</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Verification-process logs</p></td><td  ><p>Verifier-query records, correspondence files, evidence-submission records, corrective-action follow-up, verification-opinion documentation, and issuance-related documentation</p></td><td  ><p>Monitoring-to-verification and verification-to-issuance cycles within 19 Nov 2021–18 Nov 2024</p></td><td  ><p>Event-based</p></td><td  ><p>Non-substantive administrative messages were excluded; only verification-relevant queries, responses, evidence submissions, and corrective-action records were retained.</p></td><td  ><p>Not applicable to the 1,096 daily observation denominator</p></td><td  ><p>Verification report, verifier-query records, issuance-related timestamps where available, and final verification documentation</p></td><td  ><p>Anonymised</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Transaction data</p></td><td  ><p>Settlement records and contract-related financial records</p></td><td  ><p>Legacy and enhanced MRV periods</p></td><td  ><p>Transaction-based</p></td><td  ><p>Buyer-identifiable terms, confidential contract clauses, and commercially sensitive details were removed before analysis.</p></td><td  ><p>Not applicable to the technical monitoring dataset; confidential fields were removed rather than treated as missing observations.</p></td><td  ><p>Internal finance records and settlement records</p></td><td  ><p>Reported only in an aggregated and anonymized form</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Benchmark price</p></td><td  ><p>Project-specific registry reference price used for price-wedge calculation.</p></td><td  ><p>Relevant transaction period</p></td><td  ><p>Periodic or transaction-reference based</p></td><td  ><p>Used only as a project-specific registry reference for illustrative price-wedge calculation; not treated as a universal market price.</p></td><td  ><p>Not applicable</p></td><td  ><p>Settlement records and project-relevant benchmark documentation</p></td><td  ><p>Reported as an aggregate benchmark</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" ><p>Table B2. Evidence-screening decision rules</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Rule</p></td><td  ><p>Decision Criterion</p></td><td  ><p>Exclusion Condition</p></td><td  ><p>Affected Data Field</p></td><td  ><p>Example</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Monitoring completeness</p></td><td  ><p>Each record must contain the required activity-data field, timestamp, or monitoring-period identifier, and traceable source reference.</p></td><td  ><p>Missing, corrupted, duplicated, or untraceable record</p></td><td  ><p>POME flow, COD, pH, temperature, CH$_4$ fraction, burner flow, burner operating hours, operational log</p></td><td  ><p>A daily POME or reactor record without a traceable source file is excluded from the evidence-supported dataset</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Calibration validity</p></td><td  ><p>Instrument-based measurements must be covered by valid calibration or service documentation for the corresponding monitoring period.</p></td><td  ><p>Expired, unavailable, or undocumented calibration evidence</p></td><td  ><p>Flow, gas, temperature, pressure, or other instrument-based measurement</p></td><td  ><p>Data from an instrument outside its valid calibration period are excluded only for the affected instrument and period</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Temporal coherence</p></td><td  ><p>Daily records and hourly operating records must be reconcilable with the same monitoring day or operating interval.</p></td><td  ><p>The record cannot be matched with the logbook, Project monitoring sheet, operational record, or verification evidence.</p></td><td  ><p>Daily monitoring record, hourly burner record, biogas-supply record, operational remark</p></td><td  ><p>An hourly burner-flow value is excluded if it cannot be reconciled with the same-day operating log.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Data traceability</p></td><td  ><p>Each processed value must be linked to a source record, storage location, calculation file, or verification evidence.</p></td><td  ><p>Manual entry or spreadsheet value without source file, audit trail, or verifiable calculation pathway</p></td><td  ><p>Monitoring dataset, Project monitoring calculation file, verification dataset</p></td><td  ><p>A COD or biogas-combustion value without a source-log reference is excluded.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Verification readiness</p></td><td  ><p>The evidence package must be internally consistent and supported by monitoring, calibration, operational, and verification records.</p></td><td  ><p>Missing supporting file, unresolved inconsistency, or incomplete query-response evidence</p></td><td  ><p>Verification file package, verifier-query record, corrective-action record, calibration attachment</p></td><td  ><p>A query response referring to a calibration certificate is incomplete if the certificate is not attached.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" ><p>Table B3. Anonymized transaction-record template</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Transaction Field</p></td><td  ><p>Example Format</p></td><td  ><p>Disclosure Treatment</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Transaction identifier</p></td><td  ><p>TX-LEG-001 or TX-ENH-001</p></td><td  ><p>Synthetic identifier</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>MRV regime</p></td><td  ><p>Legacy MRV or Enhanced MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Reported</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Monitoring period</p></td><td  ><p>Month, or annual monitoring period</p></td><td  ><p>Aggregated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Issued or supportable volume</p></td><td  ><p>tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>Reported in aggregated form</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Benchmark price</p></td><td  ><p>Rp/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>Reported as a project-specific registry reference value</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Realized settlement price</p></td><td  ><p>Rp/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>Reported in aggregated form</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Realized-price wedge</p></td><td  ><p>Proportion, e.g., 0.30 or 0.12</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated and reported</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Buyer identity</p></td><td  ><p>Buyer A or Buyer B</p></td><td  ><p>Anonymised</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Contract type</p></td><td  ><p>Carbon-credit settlement arrangement</p></td><td  ><p>General description only</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Confidential contract clauses</p></td><td  ><p>Not disclosed</p></td><td  ><p>Removed before analysis</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Settlement timing</p></td><td  ><p>Days from issuance or monitoring closure to settlement</p></td><td  ><p>Aggregated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Payment-specific details</p></td><td  ><p>Not disclosed</p></td><td  ><p>Removed before analysis</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p>Appendix C. Detailed variable dictionary</p><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" ><p>Table C1. Detailed variable definitions, sources, and temporal resolution</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Symbol</p></td><td  ><p>Variable</p></td><td  ><p>Definition</p></td><td  ><p>Unit</p></td><td  ><p>Data Source</p></td><td  ><p>Temporal Resolution</p></td><td  ><p>Variable Type</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\mathrm{BE}_{y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Baseline emissions</p></td><td  ><p>Estimated emissions that would have occurred in the absence of the methane-abatement project during year (y).</p></td><td  ><p>ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td><td  ><p>Project monitoring calculation files, project monitoring records, and UNFCCC methodological parameters</p></td><td  ><p>Annual aggregation from monitoring-period data</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\mathrm{BM}_{\mathrm{CH_4,baseline},y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Baseline methane mass</p></td><td  ><p>Estimated baseline methane mass for year (y), before conversion into CO$_2$-equivalent emissions.</p></td><td  ><p>ktCH$_4$·y$^{-1}$</p></td><td  ><p>Project monitoring calculation files and activity-data records</p></td><td  ><p>Annual aggregation</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\mathrm{GWP}_{\mathrm{CH_4}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Methane global warming potential</p></td><td  ><p>Global warming potential factor used to convert methane emissions into CO$_2$-equivalent emissions.</p></td><td  ><p>tCO$_2$e/tCH$_4$</p></td><td  ><p>Methodological parameter used in the project calculation</p></td><td  ><p>Fixed parameter</p></td><td  ><p>Observed/ reference parameter</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\mathrm{PE}_{y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Project emissions</p></td><td  ><p>Estimated emissions occurring under project operation during year (y).</p></td><td  ><p>ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td><td  ><p>Project monitoring calculation files, flaring records, and project-emission calculation files</p></td><td  ><p>Annual aggregation from monitoring-period data</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\mathrm{PE}_{\mathrm{flare},y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Flaring-related project emissions</p></td><td  ><p>Project emissions associated with flaring during year (y).</p></td><td  ><p>ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td><td  ><p>Flaring records, project monitoring calculation files, and operational logs</p></td><td  ><p>Annual aggregation</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\mathrm{PE}_{\mathrm{residual},y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Residual project emissions</p></td><td  ><p>Residual emissions remaining after accounting for methane recovery, combustion, or destruction during year (y).</p></td><td  ><p>ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td><td  ><p>Project monitoring calculation files and project-emission records</p></td><td  ><p>Annual aggregation</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\mathrm{ER}_{y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Engineering emission reductions</p></td><td  ><p>Difference between baseline emissions and project emissions before evidence-based adjustment.</p></td><td  ><p>ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from $\mathrm{BE}_{y}$ and $\mathrm{PE}_{y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Annual</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$T_{\mathrm{valid}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Valid monitoring interval</p></td><td  ><p>Portion of the monitoring period supported by complete, usable, and traceable monitoring records.</p></td><td  ><p>Days or observations</p></td><td  ><p>Monitoring logs, project monitoring sheets, operational records, and evidence-screening results</p></td><td  ><p>Daily or record-level</p></td><td  ><p>Observed after screening</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$T_{\mathrm{total}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Total monitoring interval</p></td><td  ><p>Total monitoring period considered in the analysis.</p></td><td  ><p>Days or observations</p></td><td  ><p>Official monitoring period and analytical period definition</p></td><td  ><p>Daily or record-level</p></td><td  ><p>Observed</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$f_{\mathrm{int}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Interval completeness factor</p></td><td  ><p>Share of the monitoring interval supported by valid and usable monitoring records.</p></td><td  ><p>Ratio, 0–1</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from $T_{\mathrm{valid}}$ and $T_{\mathrm{total}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Period-level</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$T_{\mathrm{calibrated}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Calibrated monitoring interval</p></td><td  ><p>Portion of the monitoring period during which the relevant instrument was supported by valid calibration or service documentation.</p></td><td  ><p>Days or observations</p></td><td  ><p>Calibration certificates, service records, and instrument-governance records</p></td><td  ><p>Instrument-period level</p></td><td  ><p>Observed after screening</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$f_{\mathrm{cal}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Calibration-validity factor</p></td><td  ><p>Share of the monitoring period covered by documented in-date calibration status for relevant instruments.</p></td><td  ><p>Ratio, 0–1</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from calibration-validity records and monitoring-period data</p></td><td  ><p>Period-level</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$N_{\mathrm{aligned}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Temporally aligned observations</p></td><td  ><p>Number of observations that can be reconciled with the relevant monitoring day, operating interval, Project monitoring sheet, or verification evidence.</p></td><td  ><p>Observations</p></td><td  ><p>Monitoring logs, hourly operating records, Project monitoring sheets, verification evidence, and operational logbooks</p></td><td  ><p>Record-level</p></td><td  ><p>Observed after screening</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$N_{\mathrm{total}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Total observations</p></td><td  ><p>Total number of observations in the monitored dataset considered for timestamp-coherence assessment.</p></td><td  ><p>Observations</p></td><td  ><p>Monitoring dataset and analytical period definition</p></td><td  ><p>Record-level</p></td><td  ><p>Observed</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$f_{\mathrm{sync}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Timestamp-coherence factor</p></td><td  ><p>Share of observations satisfying the predefined temporal reconciliation rule.</p></td><td  ><p>Ratio, 0–1</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from $N_{\mathrm{aligned}}$ and $N_{\mathrm{total}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Period-level</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$f_{\mathrm{MRV}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Composite evidentiary support factor</p></td><td  ><p>Composite evidence-support factor combining interval completeness, calibration validity, and timestamp coherence.</p></td><td  ><p>Ratio, 0–1</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from $f_{\mathrm{int}}$, $f_{\mathrm{cal}}$, and $f_{\mathrm{sync}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Period-level</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\mathrm{LCAM}_{y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Low-confidence adjustment metric</p></td><td  ><p>Evidence-adjusted analytical proxy for conservative issuability during year (y). It represents the portion of engineering emission reductions that is conservatively supportable under the specified evidence conditions.</p></td><td  ><p>ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$ or tCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from $\mathrm{ER}_{y}$ and $f_{\mathrm{MRV}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Annual or regime-level</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated analytical proxy</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$P_{\mathrm{bench}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Benchmark price</p></td><td  ><p>Project-specific registry reference price used for illustrative price-wedge calculation. It is not treated as a universal carbon-credit market price.</p></td><td  ><p>Rp/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>Project-specific registry reference and project-relevant market documentation</p></td><td  ><p>Transaction-period reference</p></td><td  ><p>Observed/reference parameter</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$P_{\mathrm{real}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Realized settlement price</p></td><td  ><p>Realized project-level settlement price after transaction-specific conditions.</p></td><td  ><p>Rp/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>Settlement records and anonymized transaction data</p></td><td  ><p>Transaction-level or regime-level aggregation</p></td><td  ><p>Observed</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\alpha$</p></td><td  ><p>Realized-price wedge</p></td><td  ><p>Proportional difference between the benchmark price and the realized settlement price.</p></td><td  ><p>Ratio, 0–1</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from $P_{\mathrm{bench}}$ and $P_{\mathrm{real}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Transaction-level or regime-level aggregation</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$t_{\mathrm{monitoring}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Monitoring-closure date</p></td><td  ><p>Date when the relevant monitoring period closed.</p></td><td  ><p>Date</p></td><td  ><p>Monitoring-period records and verification documentation</p></td><td  ><p>Event-based</p></td><td  ><p>Observed</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$t_{\mathrm{issuance}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Issuance date</p></td><td  ><p>Date when the relevant credit issuance or issuance-related process was completed.</p></td><td  ><p>Date</p></td><td  ><p>Issuance-related documentation and verification-process records</p></td><td  ><p>Event-based</p></td><td  ><p>Observed</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\mathrm{Cadence}_{y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Issuance cadence</p></td><td  ><p>Duration between monitoring closure and issuance.</p></td><td  ><p>Days</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from $t_{\mathrm{issuance}}$ and $t_{\mathrm{monitoring}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Event-based</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\Delta t$</p></td><td  ><p>Reduction in issuance lag</p></td><td  ><p>Difference in issuance cadence between the legacy and enhanced MRV regimes.</p></td><td  ><p>Days</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from the issuance-cadence comparison</p></td><td  ><p>Regime-level</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>r</p></td><td  ><p>Discount rate</p></td><td  ><p>Annual discount rate used to estimate the relative present-value effect of earlier revenue realization.</p></td><td  ><p>Percent per year</p></td><td  ><p>Project financial assumption, represented by the estimated WACC</p></td><td  ><p>Annual parameter</p></td><td  ><p>Observed/reference parameter</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$\Delta PV_{\mathrm{rel}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Relative present-value uplift</p></td><td  ><p>Proportional present-value uplift from receiving the same nominal cash flow earlier.</p></td><td  ><p>Percent</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from r and $\Delta t$</p></td><td  ><p>Regime-level</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$R_{y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Realized annual revenue</p></td><td  ><p>Annual realized revenue from conservative issuability and realized settlement price.</p></td><td  ><p>Rp·y$^{-1}$</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from $\mathrm{LCAM}_{y}$ and $P_{\mathrm{real}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Annual or regime-level</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>$PV_{y}$</p></td><td  ><p>Present value of realized revenue</p></td><td  ><p>Present value of realized annual revenue after discounting for the timing of receipt.</p></td><td  ><p>Rp</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated from $R_{y}$, r, and the timing variable</p></td><td  ><p>Annual or regime-level</p></td><td  ><p>Calculated</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p>Appendix D. Computation for engineering emission reductions and LCAM</p><p>The base LCAM specification estimates the conservatively supportable mitigation volume by multiplying the engineering emission reduction by three evidentiary support factors: interval completeness, calibration validity, and temporal coherence. The calculation is expressed as:</p><p>\[\mathrm{LCAM}_{y}=\mathrm{ER}_{y}\times f_{\mathrm{int}}\times f_{\mathrm{cal}}\times f_{\mathrm{sync}}\]</p><p>where, $\mathrm{ER}_{y}$ is the engineering emission reduction; $f_{\mathrm{int}}$ is the interval-completeness factor; $f_{\mathrm{cal}}$ is the calibration-validity factor; and $f_{\mathrm{sync}}$ is the timestamp-coherence factor. Each evidence factor is bounded between 0 and 1. The same engineering emission-reduction value is used for both MRV regimes to isolate the effect of evidentiary-support conditions rather than changes in physical mitigation performance.</p><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" ><p>Table D1. Base LCAM input values</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Input</p></td><td  ><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Unit</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Engineering emission reduction, $\mathrm{ER}_{y}$</p></td><td  ><p>18.69</p></td><td  ><p>18.69</p></td><td  ><p>ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Interval completeness, $f_{\mathrm{int}}$</p></td><td  ><p>0.93</p></td><td  ><p>0.98</p></td><td  ><p>Dimensionless</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Calibration validity, $f_{\mathrm{cal}}$</p></td><td  ><p>0.92</p></td><td  ><p>0.97</p></td><td  ><p>Dimensionless</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Temporal coherence, $f_{\mathrm{sync}}$</p></td><td  ><p>0.90</p></td><td  ><p>0.96</p></td><td  ><p>Dimensionless</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" ><p>Table D2. Base multiplicative LCAM calculation</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Component</p></td><td  ><p>Formula/Calculation</p></td><td  ><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Unit/Interpretation</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Engineering emission reduction</p></td><td  ><p>$\mathrm{ER}_{\mathrm{y}} = \mathrm{BE}_{\mathrm{y}} - \mathrm{PE}_{\mathrm{y}}$</p></td><td  ><p>18.69</p></td><td  ><p>18.69</p></td><td  ><p>ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Interval completeness factor</p></td><td  ><p>$f_{\mathrm{int}} = \frac{T_{\mathrm{valid}}}{T_{\mathrm{total}}}$</p></td><td  ><p>0.93</p></td><td  ><p>0.98</p></td><td  ><p>Dimensionless evidence factor</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Calibration-validity factor</p></td><td  ><p>$f_{\mathrm{cal}} = \frac{T_{\mathrm{calibrated}}}{T_{\mathrm{total}}}$</p></td><td  ><p>0.92</p></td><td  ><p>0.97</p></td><td  ><p>Dimensionless evidence factor</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Timestamp-coherence factor</p></td><td  ><p>$f_{\mathrm{sync}} = \frac{T_{\mathrm{aligned}}}{N_{\mathrm{total}}}$</p></td><td  ><p>0.90</p></td><td  ><p>0.96</p></td><td  ><p>Dimensionless evidence factor</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Composite evidentiary support factor</p></td><td  ><p>$f_{\mathrm{MRV}} = f_{\mathrm{int}} \times f_{\mathrm{cal}} \times f_{\mathrm{sync}}$</p></td><td  ><p>0.93 × 0.92 × 0.90 = 0.770</p></td><td  ><p>0.98 × 0.97 × 0.96 = 0.913</p></td><td  ><p>Dimensionless composite factor</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Base LCAM</p></td><td  ><p>$\mathrm{LCAM}_{\mathrm{y}} = \mathrm{ER}_{\mathrm{y}} \times f_{\mathrm{MRV}}$</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × 0.770 = 14.39</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × 0.913 = 17.07</p></td><td  ><p>ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p>Appendix E. Sensitivity analysis calculations</p><p>Appendix E reports the sensitivity calculations used to assess whether the main within-project pattern remains directionally stable under alternative assumptions. The sensitivity analysis focuses on three elements: the LCAM evidence factors, the benchmark price assumption, and the annual discount rate used to calculate the relative present-value uplift. These calculations are not intended to establish causal inference. Their purpose is to test whether the enhanced MRV regime remains associated with higher conservative issuability, a smaller realized-price wedge, and positive timing-related value under reasonable alternative assumptions.</p><p>E.1. LCAM sensitivity under $\pm$5% variation of evidence factors</p><p>The first sensitivity test varies each LCAM evidence factor by $\pm$5%. The three evidence factors are interval completeness ($f_{\mathrm{int}}$), calibration validity ($f_{\mathrm{cal}}$), and timestamp coherence ($f_{\mathrm{sync}}$). The engineering emission reduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>] is held constant at 18.69 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$ in both MRV regimes. This allows the sensitivity test to isolate the effect of changes in evidence-support factors rather than changes in physical mitigation performance.</p><p>For the -5% case, each evidence factor is multiplied by 0.95:</p><p>\[\mathrm{L C A M}_y(-5 \%)=\mathrm{E R}_y \times\left(f_\mathrm{i n t} \times 0.95\right) \times\left(f_{\mathrm{cal }} \times 0.95\right) \times\left(f_{\mathrm{sync }} \times 0.95\right)\]</p><p>For the +5% case, each evidence factor is multiplied by 1.05. Because evidence-support factors are bounded between 0 and 1, values above 1.00 are capped at 1.00:</p><p>\[\mathrm{L C A M}_y(+5 \%)=E R_y \times \min \left(f_{\mathrm{int }} \times 1.05,1\right) \times \min \left(f_{\mathrm{cal }} \times 1.05,1\right) \times \min \left(f_{\mathrm{sync }} \times 1.05,1\right)\]</p><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" ><p>Table E1. LCAM sensitivity under $\pm$5% variation of evidence factors</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>MRV Regime</p></td><td  ><p>Sensitivity Case</p></td><td  ><p>Adjusted Interval Completeness, $f_{\mathrm{int}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Adjusted Calibration Validity, $f_{\mathrm{cal}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Adjusted Timestamp Coherence, $f_{\mathrm{sync}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Calculation</p></td><td  ><p>LCAM Result</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Base</p></td><td  ><p>0.93</p></td><td  ><p>0.92</p></td><td  ><p>0.90</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × 0.93 × 0.92 × 0.90</p></td><td  ><p>14.39 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Factors -5%</p></td><td  ><p>0.93 × 0.95 = 0.8835</p></td><td  ><p>0.92 × 0.95 = 0.8740</p></td><td  ><p>0.90 × 0.95 = 0.8550</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × 0.8835 × 0.8740 × 0.8550</p></td><td  ><p>12.35 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Factors +5%</p></td><td  ><p>0.93 × 1.05 = 0.9765</p></td><td  ><p>0.92 × 1.05 = 0.9660</p></td><td  ><p>0.90 × 1.05 = 0.9450</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × 0.9765 × 0.9660 × 0.9450</p></td><td  ><p>16.67 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Base</p></td><td  ><p>0.98</p></td><td  ><p>0.97</p></td><td  ><p>0.96</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × 0.98 × 0.97 × 0.96</p></td><td  ><p>17.07 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Factors -5%</p></td><td  ><p>0.98 × 0.95 = 0.9310</p></td><td  ><p>0.97 × 0.95 = 0.9215</p></td><td  ><p>0.96 × 0.95 = 0.9120</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × 0.9310 × 0.9215 × 0.9120</p></td><td  ><p>14.63 ktCO$_2$e</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Factors +5%</p></td><td  ><p>min(0.98 × 1.05,1) = 1.0000</p></td><td  ><p>min(0.97 × 1.05,1) = 1.0000</p></td><td  ><p>min(0.96 × 1.05,1) = 1.0000</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × 1.0000 × 1.0000 × 1.0000</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" ><p>Note: LCAM values are expressed in ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$. For the +5% enhanced MRV case, all adjusted evidence factors exceed 1.00 and are therefore capped at 1.00, because evidentiary support factors cannot exceed full support. The results show that the enhanced MRV regime remains associated with higher LCAM values than the legacy MRV regime under both -5% and +5% factor variations.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p>E.2. Alternative LCAM functional forms</p><p>The second sensitivity test examines whether the direction of the LCAM result depends on the base multiplicative specification. Two alternative LCAM structures are used: an equal-weighted average specification and a weakest-link specification. The equal-weighted average specification treats the three evidentiary support factors as contributing equally to the share of mitigation deemed supportable. The weakest-link specification applies the most restrictive evidence factor as the binding supportability condition.</p><p>The equal-weighted average LCAM is calculated as:</p><p>\[\mathrm{L C A M}_y^\mathrm{W A}=\mathrm{ER}_{y}\times\frac{f_{\mathrm{int}}+f_{\mathrm{cal}}+f_{\mathrm{sync}}}{3}\]</p><p>The weakest-link LCAM is calculated as:</p><p>\[\mathrm{L C A M}_y^\mathrm{W L}=\mathrm{ER}_{y}\times\min(f_{\mathrm{int}},f_{\mathrm{cal}},f_{\mathrm{sync}})\]</p><p>where, $\mathrm{L C A M}_y^\mathrm{W A}$ denotes the weighted-average LCAM; $\mathrm{L C A M}_y^\mathrm{W L}$ denotes the weakest-link LCAM; $\mathrm{ER}_{y}$ is engineering emission reduction; $f_{\mathrm{int}}$ is interval completeness; $f_{\mathrm{cal}}$ is calibration validity; and $f_{\mathrm{sync}}$ is timestamp coherence. In both specifications, $\mathrm{ER}_{y}$ is held constant at 18.69 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$ to isolate the effect of alternative evidence-aggregation rules.</p><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" ><p>Table E2. Weighted-average and weakest-link LCAM specifications</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Specification</p></td><td  ><p>MRV Regime</p></td><td  ><p>Formula/Calculation</p></td><td  ><p>LCAM Result</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Equal-weighted average LCAM</p></td><td  ><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × [(0.93 + 0.92 + 0.90)/3]</p></td><td  ><p>17.13 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Equal-weighted average LCAM</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × [(0.98 + 0.97 + 0.96)/3]</p></td><td  ><p>18.13 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Weakest-link LCAM</p></td><td  ><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × min(0.93, 0.92, 0.90)</p></td><td  ><p>16.82 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Weakest-link LCAM</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td  ><p>18.69 × min(0.98, 0.97, 0.96)</p></td><td  ><p>17.94 ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" ><p>Note: LCAM values are expressed in ktCO$_2$e·y$^{-1}$. The equal-weighted average specification tests a less restrictive aggregation rule than the base multiplicative LCAM. The weakest-link specification tests a conservative rule in which the weakest evidence condition determines the supportable share. Under both alternative specifications, the enhanced MRV regime remains associated with a higher LCAM value than the legacy MRV regime.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p>E.3. Price-wedge calculation</p><p>The realized-price wedge measures the proportional difference between the benchmark price and the realized settlement price. In this study, the benchmark price is used only as a project-specific registry reference price for illustrative revenue-risk analysis. It is not treated as a universal carbon-credit market price or as evidence of a causal price effect from MRV enhancement.</p><p>The realized-price wedge is calculated as:</p><p>\[\alpha=1-\frac{P_{\mathrm{real}}}{P_{\mathrm{bench}}}\]</p><p>where, $\alpha$ denotes the realized-price wedge; $P_{\mathrm{real}}$ denotes the realized settlement price; and $P_{\mathrm{bench}}$ denotes the benchmark price. A smaller $\alpha$ indicates that the realized settlement price captures a larger share of the benchmark value.</p><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" ><p>Table E3. Base price-wedge calculation</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>MRV Regime</p></td><td  ><p>Benchmark Price, $P_{\mathrm{bench}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Realized Settlement Price, $P_{\mathrm{real}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Formula/Calculation</p></td><td  ><p>Realized-Price Wedge, $\alpha$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Rp150,000/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>Rp105,000/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>1 - (105,000/150,000)</p></td><td  ><p>0.30</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Rp150,000/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>Rp132,000/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>1 - (132,000/150,000)</p></td><td  ><p>0.12</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" ><p>Note: The realized-price wedge is unitless. The benchmark price is held constant across the two MRV regimes for comparability. The lower wedge under the enhanced MRV regime is interpreted as an illustrative revenue-risk indicator rather than as a causal pricing effect.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p>E.4. Benchmark-price sensitivity of realized-price wedge</p><p>The benchmark-price sensitivity test examines whether the realized-price wedge remains smaller under the enhanced MRV regime as the benchmark price assumption varies. The base benchmark price is Rp150,000/tCO$_2$e. Two alternative benchmark-price scenarios are applied: -10% and +10%. The realized settlement prices are held constant at Rp105,000/tCO$_2$e for the legacy MRV regime and Rp132,000/tCO$_2$e for the enhanced MRV regime.</p><p>The lower benchmark-price scenario is calculated as:</p><p>$$P_{\text {bench }}^{-10 \%}=150,000 \times 0.90=135,000$$</p><p>The upper benchmark-price scenario is calculated as:</p><p>$$P_{\text {bench }}^{+10 \%}=150,000 \times 1.10=165,000$$</p><p>For each scenario, the realized-price wedge is calculated as:</p><p>\[\alpha=1-\frac{P_{\mathrm{real}}}{P_{\mathrm{bench}}}\]</p><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" ><p>Table E4. Benchmark-price sensitivity of realized-price wedge</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Sensitivity Case</p></td><td  ><p>Benchmark Price, $P_{\mathrm{bench}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Legacy Realized Price, $P_{\mathrm{real}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Legacy Wedge, $\alpha$</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced Realized Price, $P_{\mathrm{real}}$</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced Wedge, $\alpha$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Benchmark -10%</p></td><td  ><p>Rp135,000/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>Rp105,000/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>1 - (105,000/135,000) = 0.222</p></td><td  ><p>Rp132,000/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>1 - (132,000/135,000) = 0.022</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Benchmark +10%</p></td><td  ><p>Rp165,000/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>Rp105,000/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>1 - (105,000/165,000) = 0.364</p></td><td  ><p>Rp132,000/tCO$_2$e</p></td><td  ><p>1 - (132,000/165,000) = 0.200</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" ><p>Note: The benchmark-price sensitivity varies only the benchmark price, holding realized settlement prices constant. The enhanced MRV regime remains associated with a smaller realized-price wedge under both benchmark-price scenarios. These results should be interpreted as sensitivity checks for an illustrative revenue-risk indicator.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p>E.5. Relative present-value uplift under alternative discount rates</p><p>The issuance-cadence sensitivity test estimates the relative present-value uplift from receiving the same nominal cash flow earlier. The enhanced MRV regime shortened the issuance cadence from 130 days to 80 days, resulting in a 50-day acceleration of revenue timing. The timing difference is therefore expressed as:</p><p>\[\Delta t=130-80=50\ \mathrm{days}\]</p><p>The relative present-value uplift is calculated as:</p><p>\[\Delta \mathrm{PV}_{\mathrm{rel}}=(1+r)^{\Delta t/365}-1\]</p><p>where, $\Delta \mathrm{PV}_{\mathrm{rel}}$ is the proportional present-value uplift; $r$ is the annual discount rate; and $\Delta t$ is the acceleration in receipt timing measured in days. This calculation does not estimate a general present-value difference across different cash-flow amounts. It estimates the proportional effect on the value of receiving the same nominal cash flow 50 days earlier.</p><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" ><p>Table E5. Relative present-value uplift under alternative discount rates</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Annual Discount Rate, $r$</p></td><td  ><p>Time Acceleration, $\Delta t$</p></td><td  ><p>Formula/Calculation</p></td><td  ><p>Relative PV Uplift, $\Delta PV_{\mathrm{rel}}$</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>6.00%</p></td><td  ><p>50 days</p></td><td  ><p>((1+0.0600)ˆ[50/365]-1)</p></td><td  ><p>0.80%</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>8.00%</p></td><td  ><p>50 days</p></td><td  ><p>((1+0.0800)ˆ[50/365]-1)</p></td><td  ><p>1.06%</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>10.41%</p></td><td  ><p>50 days</p></td><td  ><p>((1+0.1041)ˆ[50/365]-1)</p></td><td  ><p>1.37%</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>12.00%</p></td><td  ><p>50 days</p></td><td  ><p>((1+0.1200)ˆ[50/365]-1)</p></td><td  ><p>1.56%</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" ><p>Note: The 10.41% rate represents the project's estimated WACC used in the base calculation. The relative PV uplift is calculated for the same nominal cash flow received 50 days earlier. Values are rounded for presentation; minor differences may arise from intermediate rounding.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p>E.6. Consolidated sensitivity analysis summary</p><p>Table E6 consolidates the sensitivity calculations reported in Appendix E. The purpose of this summary is to show whether the main within-project pattern remains directionally stable under alternative assumptions about LCAM evidence factors, LCAM functional form, benchmark price, and discount rate. The sensitivity tests do not establish causal inference. They only assess whether the enhanced MRV regime remains associated with higher conservative issuability, a smaller realized-price wedge, and a positive timing-related value effect under reasonable alternative specifications.</p><table><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" ><p>Table E6. Consolidated sensitivity analysis summary</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Sensitivity Test</p></td><td  ><p>Legacy MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced MRV</p></td><td  ><p>Interpretation</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Base multiplicative LCAM</p></td><td  ><p>14.39</p></td><td  ><p>17.07</p></td><td  ><p>Main analytical proxy</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>LCAM factors -5%</p></td><td  ><p>12.35</p></td><td  ><p>14.63</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced remains higher</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>LCAM factors +5%</p></td><td  ><p>16.67</p></td><td  ><p>18.69</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced remains higher</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Equal-weighted average LCAM</p></td><td  ><p>17.13</p></td><td  ><p>18.13</p></td><td  ><p>Alternative functional form; enhanced remains higher</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Weakest-link LCAM</p></td><td  ><p>16.82</p></td><td  ><p>17.94</p></td><td  ><p>Conservative weakest-condition rule; enhanced remains higher</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Wedge at benchmark -10%</p></td><td  ><p>0.222</p></td><td  ><p>0.022</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced wedge remains smaller.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>Wedge at benchmark +10%</p></td><td  ><p>0.364</p></td><td  ><p>0.200</p></td><td  ><p>Enhanced wedge remains smaller.</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>PV uplift at 6%</p></td><td  ><p>-</p></td><td  ><p>0.80%</p></td><td  ><p>Lower discount-rate assumption</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>PV uplift at 8%</p></td><td  ><p>-</p></td><td  ><p>1.06%</p></td><td  ><p>Moderate discount-rate assumption</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>PV uplift at 10.41%</p></td><td  ><p>-</p></td><td  ><p>1.37%</p></td><td  ><p>Base discount-rate assumption</p></td></tr><tr><td  ><p>PV uplift at 12%</p></td><td  ><p>-</p></td><td  ><p>1.56%</p></td><td  ><p>Higher discount-rate assumption</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" ><p>Note: LCAM values are expressed in ktCO$_2$e. Price-wedge values are unitless. Relative PV uplift is calculated based on a 50-day acceleration in receipt timing, using annual discount rates.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p>Across all sensitivity specifications, the enhanced MRV regime remains associated with a higher conservative estimate of issuability, a smaller realized-price wedge, and a positive relative present-value uplift. These results support the directional stability of the within-project pattern and remain consistent with the study's non-causal analytical design.</p>
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>Conceptualization, A.R. and L.T.B.; methodology, A.R., A.I.B., and I.I.; software, A.I.B., B.S.S., and I.I.; validation, A.I.B., B.S.S., L.T.B., and I.I.; formal analysis, A.R. and A.I.B.; investigation, A.I.B. and I.I.; resources, B.S.S.; data curation, A.R. and A.I.B.; writing—original draft preparation, A.R. and L.T.B.; writing—review and editing, A.R., A.I.B., B.S.S., L.T.B., and I.I.; visualization, A.R. and A.I.B.; supervision, A.I.B. and B.S.S.; project administration, B.S.S. and I.I.; funding acquisition, A.R. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This research was supported by the Indonesian Ministry of Higher Education, Research, and Technology (Grant No.: 19617/UN19.5.1.3/AL.04/2025).</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data that form the basis of this study comprise the project monitoring data, calibration data, verification process data, data on the timing of issuance, and anonymized transaction data. Given the data's confidentiality, individual-level records about transactions and projects cannot be released to the public. Anonymized data used in the calculations for LCAM factors, price wedge calculation, issuance cadence calculation, and sensitivity analysis are included in the appendices. They are obtainable upon request from the corresponding author.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2015</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate2544</pub-id>
          <article-title>Monitoring, reporting and verifying emissions in the climate economy</article-title>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bellassen</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stephan</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Afriat</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alberola</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barker</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>J. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiquet</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cochran</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deheza</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dimopoulos et al.</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>319-328</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <source>Nat. Clim. Change</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <issue>sup1</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14693062.2018.1454882</pub-id>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oudenes</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>H. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Clim. Policy</source>
          <article-title>Key challenges for the establishment of the monitoring, reporting and verification (MRV) system in China's national carbon emissions trading market</article-title>
          <page-range>106-121</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Build. Environ.</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Woo</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fatima</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kibert</surname>
              <given-names>C. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Newman</surname>
              <given-names>R. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tian</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srinivasan</surname>
              <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.buildenv.2021.108199</pub-id>
          <year>2021</year>
          <article-title>Applying blockchain technology for building energy performance measurement, reporting, and verification (MRV) and the carbon credit market: A review of the literature</article-title>
          <page-range>108199</page-range>
          <volume>205</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/S2010007810000091</pub-id>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>93-111</page-range>
          <article-title>Explaining the price of voluntary carbon offsets</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Conte</surname>
              <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kotchen</surname>
              <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Clim. Change Econ.</source>
          <issue>2</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lou</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hultman</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patwardhan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mintzer</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>32</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <article-title>Corporate motivations and co-benefit valuation in private climate finance investments through voluntary carbon markets</article-title>
          <source>NPJ Clim. Action</source>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s44168-023-00063-4</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>19</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14693062.2018.1521332</pub-id>
          <article-title>Environmental integrity of international carbon market mechanisms under the Paris agreement</article-title>
          <source>Clim. Policy</source>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schneider</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>La Hoz Theuer</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>386-400</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>ISO 14064-3: 2019 on the verification and validation of GHG Statements published</article-title>
          <source>, https://emsmastery.com/2019/05/07/iso-14064-32019-on-the-verification-and-validation-of-ghg-statements-published/</source>
          <year>2019</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2022</year>
          <article-title>Methodological tool: Project emissions from flaring, version 04.0</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>UNFCCC</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>AMS-III.H: Methane recovery in wastewater treatment—Version 19</article-title>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>UNFCCC</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Smart project management information systems (SPMIS) for engineering projects—Project performance monitoring and reporting</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12821/ijispm090104</pub-id>
          <year>2021</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Besouw</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bond-Barnard</surname>
              <given-names>T. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Int. J. Inf. Syst. Proj. Manag.</source>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>78-97</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Energy Sustain. Dev.</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Massagony</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pandit</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>101757</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.esd.2025.101757</pub-id>
          <year>2025</year>
          <article-title>Political economy of energy policy in Indonesia towards net zero emissions by 2060</article-title>
          <volume>88</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>Public comment on voluntary carbon markets–consultation report</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.iatp.org/sites/default/files/2024-03/IOSCO%20VCM%20CR%20comment%20IATP%203.3.24.pdf</source>
          <year>2024</year>
          <publisher-name>Institute for Agriculture and Trade Policy</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>J. Benefit-Cost Anal.</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <article-title>Efficiency without apology: Consideration of the marginal excess tax burden and distributional impacts in benefit–cost analysis</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boardman</surname>
              <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greenberg</surname>
              <given-names>D. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vining</surname>
              <given-names>A. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weimer</surname>
              <given-names>D. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2020</year>
          <page-range>457-478</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/bca.2020.18</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yescombe</surname>
              <given-names>E. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Principles of Project Finance, 2nd ed</source>
          <publisher-name>Oxford: Academic Press</publisher-name>
          <year>2013</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Carbon Manag.</source>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <page-range>549-563</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17583004.2020.1833370</pub-id>
          <article-title>Firm market value relevance of carbon reduction targets, external carbon assurance and carbon communication</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Su</surname>
              <given-names>Z. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khalid</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farooq</surname>
              <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akram</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>11</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <issue>6</issue>
          <page-range>1883-1899</page-range>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <article-title>Carbon disclosures and information asymmetry: Empirical evidence on the importance of text in understanding numerical emission allowance disclosures</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Steindl</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Habermann</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Küster</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J. Ind. Ecol.</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jiec.13574</pub-id>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>ICVCM Annual Review 2023–2024: Building integrity in the voluntary carbon market to accelerate global climate action</article-title>
          <source>, https://icvcm.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ICVCM_2023_4_Annual-Review_Digital.pdf</source>
          <year>2024</year>
          <publisher-name>London, U.K.</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>The interplay between voluntary and compliance carbon markets: Implications for environmental integrity</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.oecd.org/en/publications/the-interplay-between-voluntary-and-compliance-carbon-markets_500198e1-en.html</source>
          <year>2024</year>
          <publisher-name>OECD Environment Working Papers, OECD Publishing, Paris</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Probst</surname>
              <given-names>B. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toetzke</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kontoleon</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Díaz Anadón</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Minx</surname>
              <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haya</surname>
              <given-names>B. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schneider</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trotter</surname>
              <given-names>P. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>West</surname>
              <given-names>T. A. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill-Wiehl et al.</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <article-title>Systematic assessment of the achieved emission reductions of carbon crediting projects</article-title>
          <page-range>9562</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-53645-z</pub-id>
          <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-environ-112823-064813</pub-id>
          <year>2025</year>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Romm</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lezak</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alshamsi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Are carbon offsets fixable?</article-title>
          <source>Annu. Rev. Environ. Resour.</source>
          <page-range>649-680</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Digital monitoring, reporting, and verification technologies supporting carbon credit-generating water security programs: State of the art and technology roadmap</article-title>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.estlett.4c01048</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ecklu</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2025</year>
          <source>Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett.</source>
          <page-range>251-260</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>842-846</page-range>
          <source>PS Polit. Sci. Polit.</source>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ricks</surname>
              <given-names>J. I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>A. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Process-tracing research designs: A practical guide</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1049096518000975</pub-id>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>Review on aligning finance with climate goals: Assessing progress to net zero and preventing greenwashing</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.oecd.org/content/dam/oecd/en/publications/reports/2024/10/oecd-review-on-aligning-finance-with-climate-goals_646508f2/b9b7ce49-en.pdf</source>
          <year>2024</year>
          <publisher-name>Paris</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>369</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brummitt</surname>
              <given-names>C. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mathers</surname>
              <given-names>C. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keating</surname>
              <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O'Leary</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Easter</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friedl</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>DuBuisson</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campbell</surname>
              <given-names>E. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pape</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peters et al.</surname>
              <given-names>S. J. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J. Environ. Manag.</source>
          <page-range>122284</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <article-title>Solutions and insights for agricultural monitoring, reporting, and verification (MRV) from three consecutive issuances of soil carbon credits</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122284</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Provenance in the context of metrological traceability</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>R. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <year>2025</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/metrology5030052</pub-id>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>52</page-range>
          <source>Metrology</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0308518X241278937</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Christiansen</surname>
              <given-names>K. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>1190-1205</page-range>
          <source>Environ. Plan. A</source>
          <article-title>Relegitimizing the voluntary carbon market: Visions of digital monitoring, reporting and verification</article-title>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>1-40</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1257/app.20230052</pub-id>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <source>Am. Econ. J. Appl. Econ.</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Calel</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colmer</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dechezleprêtre</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glachant</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Do carbon offsets offset carbon?</article-title>
          <year>2025</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Obondi</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <article-title>The utilization of project risk monitoring and control practices and their relationship with project success in construction projects</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5267/j.jpm.2021.7.002</pub-id>
          <source>J. Proj. Manag.</source>
          <page-range>35-52</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flyvbjerg</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijproman.2012.10.007</pub-id>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <source>Int. J. Proj. Manag.</source>
          <page-range>760-774</page-range>
          <article-title>Quality control and due diligence in project management: Getting decisions right by taking the outside view</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.measen.2024.101487</pub-id>
          <source>Meas. Sens.</source>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xiong</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kan</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fang</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Design and implementation of a digital calibration certificate web service system based on microservice architecture</article-title>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <page-range>101487</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>The dynamics of voluntary carbon markets: An empirical analysis of the carbon credits lifecycle</article-title>
          <source>, https://wfe-live.lon1.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/org_focus/storage/media/Cally%20Billimore/VCM%20credits%20lifecycle%20report%20final.pdf</source>
          <year>2025</year>
          <publisher-name>World Federation of Exchanges (WFE), WFE Research</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>6863</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <article-title>Demand for low-quality offsets by major companies undermines climate integrity of the voluntary carbon market</article-title>
          <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-51151-w</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Trencher</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nick</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carlson</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akerlof</surname>
              <given-names>G. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The market for 'lemons': Quality uncertainty and the market mechanism</article-title>
          <source>Uncertainty in Economics</source>
          <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
          <year>1978</year>
          <page-range>235-251</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2013</year>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <page-range>339-378</page-range>
          <source>J. Assoc. Inf. Syst.</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corbett</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Designing and using carbon management systems to promote ecologically responsible behaviors</article-title>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17705/1jais.00338</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>ISO 31000:2018 Risk management—Guidelines</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.iso.org/standard/65694.html</source>
          <year>2018</year>
          <publisher-name>Geneva, Switzerland: International Organization for Standardization</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Project Management Institute</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A Guide to the Project Management Body of Knowledge (PMBOK® Guide)</article-title>
          <year>2021</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bartram</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Short</surname>
              <given-names>M. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ebie</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farkaš</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gueguen</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peters</surname>
              <given-names>G. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zanzottera</surname>
              <given-names>N. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karthik</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chapter 6: Wastewater treatment and discharge</article-title>
          <source>Refinement to the 2006 IPCC Guidelines for National Greenhouse Gas Inventories</source>
          <publisher-name>Geneva, Switzerland: Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</publisher-name>
          <year>2019</year>
          <issue>apter 6</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Körner</surname>
              <given-names>M. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leinauer</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ströher</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strüker</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Digital Measuring, Reporting, and Verification (dMRV) for decarbonization</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12599-025-00953-3</pub-id>
          <page-range>753-765</page-range>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <source>Bus. Inf. Syst. Eng.</source>
          <year>2025</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Emhjellen</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alaouze</surname>
              <given-names>C. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <source>Energy Econ.</source>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <page-range>455-467</page-range>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Project valuation when there are two cashflow streams</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-9883(02)00019-1</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>J. Environ. Econ. Manag.</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jeem.2023.102882</pub-id>
          <article-title>The discounting premium puzzle: Survey evidence from professional economists</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gollier</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Der Ploeg</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>102882</page-range>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2012</year>
          <article-title>JCGM 106:2012 Evaluation of measurement data—The role of measurement uncertainty in conformity assessment</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>JCGM</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2024.143456</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>471</volume>
          <year>2024</year>
          <page-range>143456</page-range>
          <article-title>Carbon monitoring, reporting and verification (MRV) for cleaner built environment: Developing a solar photovoltaic blockchain tool and applications in Hong Kong's building sector</article-title>
          <source>J. Clean. Prod.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Promoting circular economy in the palm oil industry through biogas codigestion of palm oil mill effluent and empty fruit bunch pressed wastewater</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suksaroj</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jearat</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cherypiew</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rattanapan</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suksaroj</surname>
              <given-names>T. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <page-range>2153</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/w15122153</pub-id>
          <source>Water</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Product SPE-GRK</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>IDX Carbon</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>Analysis of the ICVCM’s core carbon principles and assessment framework</article-title>
          <source>, https://perspectives.cc/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/PCG_CCPs-AF-analysis_07_2024.pdf</source>
          <publisher-name>Perspectives Climate Group GmbH, Freiburg, Germany</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>381</volume>
          <article-title>Action needed to make carbon offsets from forest conservation work for climate change mitigation</article-title>
          <year>2023</year>
          <page-range>873-877</page-range>
          <source>Science</source>
          <issue>6660</issue>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>West</surname>
              <given-names>T. A. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wunder</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sills</surname>
              <given-names>E. O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Börner</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rifai</surname>
              <given-names>S. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neidermeier</surname>
              <given-names>A. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frey</surname>
              <given-names>G. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kontoleon</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.ade3535</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schneider</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fallasch</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De León</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rambharos</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wissner</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colbert-Sangree</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Progscha</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schallert</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holler</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kizzier et al.</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2022</year>
          <article-title>Methodology for assessing the quality of carbon credits, version 2.0</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>