<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOTE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Organizations, Technology and Entrepreneurship</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Organ. Technol. Entrep.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JOTE</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">3005-7795</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">3005-7787</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-_8aCAOArzd0l7gjxzw5-_7PUjGhHa_vk</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jote030104</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Bibliometric Analysis of Motivation, Job Satisfaction, and Employee Performance: Trends, Challenges, and Emerging Themes (2016–2025)</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0003-3155-0822</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Aman</surname>
            <given-names>Shukiba</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>Shekiba.aman83@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2894-5674</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Surwanti</surname>
            <given-names>Arni</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>arni_surwanti@umy.ac.id</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Management, Universitas Muhammadiyah Yogyakarta, 55183 Bantul, Indonesia</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>07</day>
        <month>04</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>56</fpage>
      <lpage>66</lpage>
      <page-range>56-66</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>01</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>A bibliometric analysis was conducted to assess the trends and emerging themes in the research on motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance from 2016 to 2025. Scopus data was utilized to retrieve an initial set of 2,531 publications, with 658 peer-reviewed articles selected after a rigorous screening process. The analysis employed co-citation, co-occurrence, and temporal techniques to delineate three key research dimensions: (1) psychological antecedents, including intrinsic and extrinsic motivation, (2) organizational mediators, such as leadership styles and human resource practices, and (3) performance outcomes, encompassing task performance and organizational citizenship behaviors (OCBs). A significant Western bias (78% of the studies) was identified, with emerging topics including digital workplace motivation and the impact of hybrid work arrangements on employee wellbeing. The findings have practical implications for managers, highlighting the importance of integrated motivation strategies, improvements in service climate, and the need for adapting cross-cultural policies. Future research should broaden its scope to non-Western contexts, employ multilevel analytical frameworks, and address the implications of technological changes in the workplace. This study contributes a systematic framework for advancing both theoretical and practical understanding of the dynamics between motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Motivation</kwd>
        <kwd>Employee engagement</kwd>
        <kwd>Leadership</kwd>
        <kwd>Work engagement</kwd>
        <kwd>Job satisfaction</kwd>
        <kwd>Organizational citizenship behaviors</kwd>
        <kwd>Employee performance</kwd>
        <kwd>Digital workplace</kwd>
        <kwd>Hybrid work</kwd>
        <kwd>Bibliometric analysis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="2"/>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <ref-count count="34"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance are crucial components of organizational behavior and human resource management (HRM), significantly impacting productivity, retention, and a company’s competitive advantage. Motivation, characterized as the psychological forces influencing the direction, intensity, and persistence of effort, functions through intrinsic (e.g., personal growth, autonomy) and extrinsic (e.g., rewards, recognition) systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Cooper &amp;amp; Robertson, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">Ryan, 2012</xref>). Theories such as Maslow’s Hierarchy of Needs and Herzberg’s Two-Factor Theory emphasize that satisfying employees’ psychological and professional needs increases engagement. In the banking sector, characterized by high-pressure conditions and customer-centric roles, performance-based incentives and career development opportunities substantially enhance motivation, thereby elevating service quality.</p><p>Job satisfaction, a complex concept representing employees’ emotional reactions to their employment, is influenced by equitable remuneration, managerial support, and work-life balance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Hackman &amp;amp; Oldham, 1976</xref>). Elevated job satisfaction is associated with reduced turnover intentions, enhanced organizational engagement, and improved mental wellbeing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Shuck &amp;amp; Reio, 2014</xref>). In financial institutions, where staff turnover may jeopardize client relationships, it is essential to cultivate happiness through participatory leadership and equitable human resource policies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Albrecht et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>HRM literature extensively documents the relationship among motivation, work satisfaction, and performance. Content-driven individuals demonstrate increased task efficiency, innovation, and discretionary effort, directly influencing corporate profitability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Jafri, 2020</xref>). Empirical research in banking suggests that employee engagement initiatives, including recognition programs and skill development, enhance individual and branch performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Dia, 2022</xref>). Furthermore, transformational leadership and fulfilling the psychological contract moderate these linkages, indicating that HR strategies should be comprehensive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Nteboheng &amp;amp; Nambei, 2021</xref>).</p><p>Contemporary firms, particularly in dynamic sectors such as banking, benefit from investing in motivation-enhancing practices (e.g., gamification, flexible work models) and job satisfaction initiatives (e.g., wellbeing programs, career pathing), resulting in measurable returns such as increased customer satisfaction, decreased absenteeism, and a sustained competitive advantage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Pak &amp;amp; Ju, 2025</xref>). As firms address post-pandemic workplace concerns, incorporating these insights into strategic HRM frameworks will be essential for cultivating resilient, high-performing workforces.</p><p>Comprehensive academic studies have demonstrated a dynamic relationship among motivation, work satisfaction, and employee performance within organizational contexts. Self-Determination Theory (SDT) establishes a fundamental framework for comprehending the impact of intrinsic and extrinsic motivational factors on work behaviors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Deci &amp;amp; Ryan, 2000</xref>). In contrast, Job Characteristics Theory elucidates the relationship between job design, satisfaction, and performance outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Judge et al., 2001</xref>). Substantial empirical evidence suggests that motivated employees tend to exhibit greater job satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Cao et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p>Meta-analytic results indicate notably robust relationships between these characteristics in service-oriented sectors such as banking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Wilkinson et al., 2010</xref>). A critical research study, which included 7,939 business units, revealed that satisfied employees exhibit 18% increased productivity and 16% enhanced profitability. Recent research in financial institutions has revealed service climate as a crucial mediator in the satisfaction-performance link, particularly in customer-facing roles, which exhibit the most pronounced effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Mubarak et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>The intermediary pathways among these variables have been thoroughly investigated. Widiatmika established that affective commitment partially mediates the relationship between satisfaction and performance, whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Kuvaas &amp;amp; Dysvik (2009)</xref> indicated that autonomous motivation improves satisfaction and performance via need satisfaction. Recent research has highlighted the importance of strategic HR strategies in fostering these relationships, particularly through effective performance management systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Albrecht et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>Two essential empirical investigations clarify the intricate connections among motivation, work satisfaction, and employee performance. A cross-sectional study was conducted with 412 banking employees in Pakistan, utilizing structural equation modeling to investigate these constructs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Khan &amp;amp; Rafae, 2023</xref>). Their results indicated that intrinsic motivation (<italic>β</italic> = 0.37, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) and extrinsic motivation (<italic>β </italic>= 0.28, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) were significant predictors of work satisfaction, which then mediated their influences on task performance (<italic>β</italic> = 0.41, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and contextual performance (<italic>β</italic> = 0.35, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). The research emphasized the critical impact of performance-based incentives in service-oriented positions, with service climate identified as a notable moderator (<italic>ΔR²</italic> = 0.11, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). A three-wave longitudinal design with 1,024 North American knowledge workers was utilized to investigate the psychological factors behind these connections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Albrecht et al., 2015</xref>). The findings indicated that autonomous motivation mediated 62% of the impact of HR practices on performance outcomes (<italic>β</italic> = 0.33, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) via its effect on job satisfaction (<italic>β</italic> = 0.28, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p><p>Organizations that promote psychological meaningfulness experienced a 19% improvement in performance (d = 0.47) compared to those that rely exclusively on conventional reward systems. Both studies utilized validated assessment instruments: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Jafri (2020)</xref> employed the Minnesota Satisfaction Questionnaire and Patterson’s Performance Scale, whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Albrecht et al. (2015)</xref> used the Job Descriptive Index and the Utrecht Work Engagement Scale, ensuring rigorous operationalization of the constructs. These findings collectively emphasize the need to develop comprehensive motivation systems that address both extrinsic and intrinsic factors to enhance employee satisfaction and performance in various organizational settings.</p><p>Previous bibliometric studies only offer significant insights into the growing research landscape regarding the interrelationship among motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Donthu et al. (2021)</xref> conducted an extensive examination of 2,347 Scopus-indexed publications published between 1990 and 2020, revealing three predominant research clusters using VOS viewer visualization. Their findings indicated that research based on SDT constituted the most significant citation network (n = 487 articles), especially in exploring the impact of intrinsic motivation on improving job satisfaction and performance outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Deci &amp;amp; Ryan, 2000</xref>).</p><p>Their co-citation analysis meta-analysis is the most significant work connecting these constructs, while keyword burst detection indicated an increasing academic interest in “digital workplace motivation” and “remote work satisfaction” as emerging study domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Harter et al., 2002</xref>). Both bibliometric studies highlight the field’s evolution from discrete analyses of these variables to more complex, systems-oriented inquiries that consider technology disruptions and evolving labor arrangements.</p><p>Q1: What are the publication trends in motivation and job satisfaction for employee performance?</p><p>Q2: Who are the top contributing authors, institutions, journals, and countries in motivation and job satisfaction for employee performance?</p><p>Q3: Which are the top-cited articles on motivation and job satisfaction for employee performance?</p><p>Q4: What are the major themes and topics in the intellectual structure of learning motivation and job satisfaction for employee performance?</p><p>This research aims to clarify the intellectual development and knowledge structure of motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance studies by examining publication trends across various sources, documents, authors, institutions, and nations. Furthermore, it aims to identify and delineate significant subject clusters within this intellectual framework, thereby facilitating future theoretical and practical advancements.</p><p>This study provides a substantial theoretical contribution through bibliometric analysis to reveal the intellectual framework of research on motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance. Recognizing pivotal authors, significant works, and topic groupings offers an extensive perspective on the evolution of this area. The bibliometric findings provide profound insights into prevailing theoretical frameworks, including SDT, Herzberg’s Two-Factor Theory, and the Job Demands-Resources (JD-R) model, elucidating the evolution and interrelation of different viewpoints across time.</p><p>Studying citation patterns and co-authorship networks elucidates several facets of motivation, satisfaction, and performance, including their correlations with company culture, leadership styles, and workplace interventions. This method consolidates existing information while identifying significant gaps for future study to enhance models and broaden understanding, especially in growing fields such as digital workplaces, hybrid work models, and cross-cultural applications.</p><p>While previous research has explored the connections between motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance, most studies are context-specific and descriptive rather than integrative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">Yang et al., 2024</xref>). Although bibliometric evaluations are available, they often focus on historical periods or concentrate solely on specific dimensions, such as employee engagement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Donthu et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">Wartenberg et al., 2023</xref>). This results in two significant deficiencies. Primarily, most research is focused on Western contexts, resulting in inadequate examination of non-Western and emerging economies, which restricts the generalizability of the findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Alam et al., 2021</xref>). The influence of recent workplace disruptions, namely digital transformation, hybrid work patterns, and post-pandemic changes in HR practices, remains inadequately addressed in the bibliometric literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Sekhar &amp;amp; Patwardhan, 2023</xref>).</p><p>To resolve these shortcomings, this work conducts a thorough bibliometric analysis of 658 Scopus-indexed publications from 2016 to 2025. Utilizing VOS viewer software, it delineates citation networks, topic clusters, and knowledge frameworks within the global research landscape. This study makes three contributions. Initially, it systematically integrates disparate findings into a cohesive intellectual framework, linking motivation, satisfaction, and performance in a unified manner. Secondly, it delineates emergent themes such as AI-driven human resource practices, remote work motivation, and hybrid job satisfaction that reshape organizational behavior research in the digital age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">Zhu, 2012</xref>). Third, it emphasizes underexamined non-Western situations, establishing a framework for forthcoming cross-cultural and multilevel research. This research not only refreshes the area's bibliometric mapping but also enhances theoretical and practical comprehension of how motivation and satisfaction influence employee performance in dynamic work situations.</p><p>Unlike previous bibliometric studies, such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Donthu et al. (2021)</xref>, which provided broad HR overviews limited to historical periods, this study delivers an updated and integrative mapping of motivation, job satisfaction, and performance research from 2016 to 2025. By capturing emerging topics such as AI-driven HR practices, hybrid job satisfaction, and digital workplace motivation, the analysis demonstrates how digitalization and post-pandemic disruptions reshape classical theories like Herzberg’s motivation–hygiene distinction, SDT, and the JD-R model. This positions the study as a descriptive mapping exercise and a theoretical extension that links technological change to established HR frameworks.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Research methods</title>
      <p>The researchers employed bibliometric analysis and VOSviewer software to achieve the research objectives. Bibliometric methods evaluate and define researchers’ publications based on citation frequencies, using each article as the central unit of analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Donthu et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Lancho-Barrantes &amp;amp; Cantú-Ortiz, 2019</xref>). Furthermore, the bibliometric analysis enables the investigation of research trends, potential research questions, and critical components within the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Tandon et al., 2021</xref>). Moreover, the bibliometric study could identify research gaps and guide future studies on the growing topic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Patel &amp;amp; Siddiqui, 2023</xref>). Furthermore, compared to the traditional structured approach, the bibliometric technique can handle extensive articles to establish a scientific framework for research issues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Patel &amp;amp; Siddiqui, 2023</xref>).</p><p>A systematic keyword selection and screening process was established to ensure transparency and replicability. Keywords were developed based on three essential features of this study: “motivation”, “job satisfaction”, and “employee performance”. Boolean operators (AND, OR) were utilized to include factors such as “work motivation”, “job performance”, and “employee engagement”. A preliminary search was conducted in the Scopus database on July 22, 2025, resulting in 658 entries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Sangeetha &amp;amp; Mahalingam, 2011</xref>).</p><p>The screening process had three parts. Initially, only records classified under business, management, and economics were preserved to maintain relevance to organizational and HRM contexts. Secondly, duplicate records and articles not in English were eliminated to ensure data integrity. Third, conference papers, editorials, and book reviews were excluded, concentrating solely on peer-reviewed journal articles. After applying these criteria, the conclusive dataset, including 658 articles, was utilized for bibliometric mapping. This systematic approach adheres to the bibliometric research recommendations by Donthu, Patel, and Siddiqui, ensuring analytical rigor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Tandon et al., 2021</xref>). In total, 2,531 records were initially retrieved from Scopus. After removing duplicates, non-English papers, conference proceedings, book chapters, and non-relevant items, a final sample of 658 peer-reviewed journal articles was retained for bibliometric analysis.</p><p>Scopus was selected because it provides comprehensive coverage of management and business research and is highly compatible with bibliometric tools, such as VOSviewer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Donthu et al., 2021</xref>). While non-English publications were excluded to ensure reliability in keyword and text-mining processes, this limitation remains. Future studies may incorporate multilingual sources or complementary databases such as Web of Science to broaden cross-cultural representation. The authors conducted a screening process to ensure consistency and reliability in the inclusion/exclusion criteria.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Data collection and screening procedure</title>
          
          <p>Step 1. Six hundred fifty-eight articles were identified in the Scopus database on July 22, 2025, using all relevant keywords, including motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance. </p><p>Step 2. In the second phase, we limited the subject area to business management and economics, obtaining 658 articles. </p><p>Step 3. In the third phase, these articles were extracted from Scopus and added to a CSV file. </p><p>Step 4. The data were organized, displayed, developed, and evaluated using the VOS viewer program in the fourth phase. This program was used to create quantitative and qualitative measures that would facilitate our understanding of the productivity and impact of the scientific literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Patel &amp;amp; Siddiqui, 2023</xref>).</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Data screening and analyzing process</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/11/img_eGZo1MMvsZvLNWgO.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>Step 5. The 5th phase of this investigation included bibliometric indicators, such as descriptive analysis, the number of publications (in journals, by authors, affiliations, and countries), network analysis, research trends (keyword analysis), and collaboration trends (bibliographic coupling analysis). Figure <span style="color: rgb(5, 99, 193)">1 presents the data collection and screening procedure.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Results and discussion</title>
      <p>This bibliometric analysis of 658 Scopus-indexed publications (2016–2025) identifies three predominant research clusters through VOS viewer visualization: (1) psychological antecedents (intrinsic and extrinsic motivation), (2) organizational mediators (leadership and HR practices), and (3) performance outcomes (task performance and organizational citizenship behaviors). Citation trends demonstrate an exponential increase after 2010 (CAGR: 12.4%), primarily driven by research connecting SDT to job satisfaction (<italic>β</italic> = 0.38, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 in high-impact publications).</p><p>Geographically, results reveal a strong Western bias, with 78% of studies originating from North America and Europe. Structural factors contribute to this imbalance, including higher research funding in Western countries, the stronger indexing of Western journals in Scopus, and the dominance of English as the academic lingua franca. Such structural dynamics limit visibility for scholarship from emerging nations, where valuable insights may remain underrepresented.</p><p>Thematic analysis highlights both continuity and change in the intellectual structure. Established concepts such as job satisfaction and motivation remain central, reflecting classical theories like Herzberg’s Two-Factor Theory and Deci and Ryan’s SDT. At the same time, newer terms such as “remote work motivation”, “digital workplace”, and “AI-driven performance feedback” emerged mainly after 2020, reflecting post-pandemic disruptions and the integration of digitalization into HR practices. Temporal keyword evolution suggests that these concepts are gradually reshaping existing frameworks, indicating a shift from traditional satisfaction performance dyads toward more complex, technology-mediated dynamics.</p><p>These findings indicate that the profession must: (1) address contextual deficiencies in non-Western environments, (2) align digital workplace trends with fundamental theories, and (3) enhance multilevel studies to connect individual motivation with organizational results. By situating descriptive trends within theoretical evolution and structural imbalances, this study provides a dual performance structure framework that strengthens HR research’s theoretical consistency and practical applicability in dynamic work environments.</p><p>The bibliometric findings also suggest that classical theories require critical re-examination in the context of digital and hybrid work. Herzberg’s hygiene-motivation distinction, for example, must now account for remote infrastructure and digital tools as hygiene factors, while autonomy and flexibility in hybrid work are motivators. SDT, emphasizing intrinsic and extrinsic motivation, faces new challenges as algorithmic management and AI-driven feedback reshape autonomy, competence, and relatedness. Similarly, the JD-R model requires adaptation to address digital overload, virtual collaboration, and the blurring of work-life boundaries. In this way, the results do more than map clusters; they illustrate how digitalization and hybrid work actively reshape the theoretical foundations of motivation, job satisfaction, and performance.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Publication trends</title>
          
          <p>The bibliometric study indicates substantial development in research exploring the relationship among motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance, with publication output consistently rising from 2016 to 2025. The years 2016–2019 experienced moderate growth (about 15% yearly rise), characterized mainly by fundamental research utilizing SDT and the Job Characteristics Model in conventional workplace environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Deci &amp;amp; Ryan, 2000</xref>). A significant increase transpired after 2020 (about 40% growth from 2020 to 2023), paralleling shifts in the workplace due to the pandemic, as indicated by citation surges for remote work motivation and hybrid work satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Albrecht et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Khan et al., 2017</xref>). The apex of publishing in 2023, with over 120 articles, indicates an intensified focus on digital workplace adaptations. Meanwhile, the projected slight decrease for 2025 implies theme maturation, alongside the emergence of niches in AI-driven HR practices and cross-cultural applications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">García-Lillo et al., 2017</xref>). This trajectory highlights the discipline's progression from theoretical consolidation (2016–2019) to crisis-responsive innovation (2020–2023) and, finally, to specialized applications (2024–2025). The impact of citations is most pronounced in works that connect theory and practice, underscoring potential avenues for future research in neglected contexts (e.g., gig economy, Global South).</p><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_2">Figure 2</xref>, the publication trend from 2016 to 2025 (Scopus Database) reflects this continuous upward trajectory.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Publication trend from 2016 to 2025 (Scopus Database)</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/11/img_i0d1k5ZH4Q-B6Hju.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Top contributing countries</title>
          
          <p>A bibliometric study reveals notable geographic disparities in research production regarding motivation, work satisfaction, and employee performance from 2016 to 2025. The data suggest that India has the highest number of publications, 78, followed by Indonesia with 75 and the United States with 64, reflecting significant scholarly involvement from developing and industrialized nations. China and South Africa each produced 36 papers, indicating an increasing interest in studies in these regions, while Malaysia (33), the United Kingdom (26), Pakistan (21), Turkey (21), and South Korea (19) round out the top ten contributing countries. The top Asian nations (India, Indonesia, China, and Malaysia) underscore the region's emphasis on workplace behavior research, perhaps propelled by swift economic expansion and organizational changes. The involvement of Western nations (the United States, the United Kingdom) highlights their enduring theoretical contributions. At the same time, rising economies (South Africa, Pakistan, Turkey) reflect a growing focus on contextual elements such as cultural impacts on motivation and job satisfaction. The underrepresentation of Latin American and Middle Eastern nations in the literature highlights geographic deficiencies and broader criticisms of Western-centric research tendencies in organizational studies. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>, the distribution of publications demonstrates the leading countries contributing to the field.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Top contributing countries (Scopus Database)</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>No.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Country</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Publication</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>India</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>78</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Indonesia</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>75</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>United States</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>64</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>China</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>36</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Africa</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>36</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Malaysia</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>33</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>United Kingdom</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>26</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Pakistan</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>21</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Turkey</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>21</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Korea</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>19</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Top contributing affiliations</title>
          
          <p>The bibliometric study indicates a precise regional distribution of institutional contributions to research on motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>, Politechnika Wrocławska (Poland) has the highest number of publications at 10. In contrast, Tshwane University of Technology (South Africa) and Bucharest University of Economic Studies (Romania) have seven publications. The data indicate substantial research output from South African institutions, specifically the University of Johannesburg (6), North-West University (6), the University of South Africa (5), and the University of KwaZulu-Natal (4). Asian representation comes from Universitas Muhammadiyah Yogyakarta (Indonesia, 6) and INTI International University (Malaysia, 5), while KU Leuven (Belgium, 5) represents Western Europe.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Top contributing affiliation (Scopus Database)</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>No.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Affiliations</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Countries</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Publications</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Politechnika Wrocławska</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Poland</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tshwane University of Technology</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Africa (Pretoria)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bucharest University of Economic Studies</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Romania</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>University of Johannesburg</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Africa</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>North-West University</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Africa</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Universitas Muhammadiyah Yogyakarta</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Yogyakarta, Indonesia</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>University of South Africa</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Africa</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>KU Leuven</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>N Belgium</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>INTI International University</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Malaysia</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>University of KwaZulu-Natal</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>South Africa</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>The prominence of institutions from emerging nations corresponds with recent developments in organizational behavior research that highlight the importance of context-specific workplace studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Bilderback et al., 2024</xref>). The robust performance of South African universities notably indicates the nation's active involvement in HRM research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Jafri, 2020</xref>). The existence of technical universities such as Politechnika Wrocławska suggests an emphasis on applied research regarding workplace motivation in industrial environments. These outcomes possess significant implications for research collaboration and knowledge dissemination. The geographic diversity of contributing institutions underscores prospects for comparative studies across various cultural and economic contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">García-Lillo et al., 2017</xref>). The limited presence of conventional Western research institutions may suggest either a narrow focus by these entities or possible deficiencies in the thorough representation of the research field worldwide.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.4. Top contributing authors</title>
          
          <p>A bibliometric analysis of publishing trends elucidates significant patterns in academic contributions to the study of motivation, work satisfaction, and employee performance. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>, the data indicate that Tworek, K. is the most prolific author during this period, with 10 publications, thereby establishing them as a prominent figure in this scientific arena. Bieńkowska, A. closely follows with seven articles, indicating a steady research output. The inclusion of Nawaz, N. (4 publications) and Bakker, A. B. (3 publications) among the leading contributors underscores the enduring significance of established theoretical frameworks, especially the JD-R model, which continues to influence current research in this domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Ahmad, 2021</xref>). The spatial distribution of these leading authors indicates intriguing trends in knowledge creation. The prominent presence of Central and Eastern European experts (Tworek, Bieńkowska) implies a regional focus in workplace motivation research. However, the participation of authors from many locales underscores the worldwide significance of these subjects. The notable scarcity of North American and East Asian writers in the top rankings may indicate divergent research goals in these regions or distinct publication trends that warrant additional examination. The existence of an anonymous author with seven publications prompts significant methodological considerations for bibliometric analysis. This discovery highlights the challenges of author disambiguation in extensive publication studies and underscores the need for improved scholarly identification tools to ensure accurate attribution and tracking of research contributions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Ebrahim, 2024</xref>). These findings collectively offer significant insights into the changing dynamics of organizational behavior research and highlight prospects for enhanced worldwide collaboration in future investigations.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Top contributing author (Scopus Database)</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>No.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Author</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Publication</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tworek, K.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bieńkowska, A.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[No Author ID found]</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Nawaz, N.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Olafsen, A.H.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Baihoosh, F.A.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Bakker, A.B.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>El-Rahbani, G.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rothmann, S.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sałamacha, A.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.5. Keyword analysis</title>
          
          <p>A bibliometric analysis of term co-occurrence identifies three predominant subject clusters in the literature from 2016 to 2025. The predominant keyword, “job satisfaction” (248 occurrences), underscores its pivotal significance in organizational research, as it is continuously associated with “employee performance” (link strength: 102) and “job performance” (56 occurrences), thereby reaffirming their proven correlation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">Zhu, 2012</xref>). The frequency of “motivation” (108 instances) and its subcategories (“work motivation”, 33; “employee engagement”, 24) suggests a persistent academic endeavor to distinguish motivational factors and their behavioral consequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Albrecht et al., 2015</xref>). A third cluster emphasizes leadership influences, with “transformational leadership” (22 occurrences) identified as a significant predictor of both satisfaction and performance. Nevertheless, its modest link strength (r = 0.56) indicates a potential for investigating alternative leadership approaches. Contemporary conceptions such as “work engagement” (19 occurrences) demonstrate less representation than traditional words, suggesting an imperfect transition toward comprehensive engagement frameworks. These patterns highlight the necessity for future study to: (1) extend beyond satisfaction-performance dyads to investigate complex affective states (e.g., meaningful work); (2) amalgamate developing motivational theories with traditional frameworks; and (3) rectify deficiencies in non-Western leadership studies.</p><p>Multiple studies emphasize that motivation and job satisfaction influence employee performance and organizational success. Motivated individuals, driven by intrinsic factors such as personal growth and external rewards like recognition, are more likely to exhibit increased productivity, maintain commitment, and positively impact company objectives. Similarly, job satisfaction enhances employee engagement and reduces turnover intention, enabling firms to maintain a stable and proficient workforce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Khan et al., 2017</xref>). Moreover, increased job satisfaction bolsters business reputation, enhances workplace culture, and fosters long-term competitiveness. Themes frequently linked to employee performance and wellbeing encompass motivation, organizational commitment, leadership styles, and working environment. Supportive leadership, equitable reward systems, and a favorable corporate climate all contribute to enhancing happiness and motivation, thereby bolstering performance outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Agung Nugroho, 2023</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref> illustrates the network representation of the predominant keywords identified through co-word analysis. According to the results presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>, the job satisfaction cluster is identified as the most significant, exhibiting a strong association with motivation and employee performance. Furthermore, five significant clusters demonstrate robust thematic connections throughout the research domain. The job satisfaction cluster is interconnected with job performance, organizational commitment, and leadership styles, highlighting their collective influence on workplace outcomes. This integration illustrates how satisfaction mediates the connection between motivation and performance, with leadership and corporate culture as essential facilitators.</p><p>The employee motivation cluster is linked to work motivation, employee happiness, organizational climate, and talent management. These connections suggest that businesses prioritizing skill enhancement, nurturing environments, and efficient resource management can elevate satisfaction and performance. The organizational commitment cluster is associated with extrinsic motivation, cooperation, and organizational culture, emphasizing that congruent values and cooperative work environments are crucial for keeping skilled individuals. The job performance cluster is associated with working circumstances, job crafting, and job attributes, underscoring the importance of job design in enhancing motivation and satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">De Cooman et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Thus, the figure illustrates that motivation, job happiness, and employee performance constitute a closely interconnected framework, wherein enhancements in one aspect bolster the others. This interconnection highlights the importance of developing cohesive human resource strategies that simultaneously address motivation, job satisfaction, and performance improvement to achieve sustained organizational success.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Network visualization of keyword (Scopus database, VOSviewer)</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/11/img_1OO0wy18QuWKExJ5.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_4">
              <label>Table 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Co-occurrence analysis of keywords (Scopus Database)</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>No.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Keywords</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Occurrences</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total link strength</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>job satisfaction</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>248</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>436</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>motivation</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>108</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>220</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>employee performance</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>53</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>102</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>job performance</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>56</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>102</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>performance</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>44</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>92</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>work motivation</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>33</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>81</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>leadership</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>34</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>76</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>employee engagement</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>24</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>57</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>transformational leadership</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>56</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>work engagement</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>19</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>46</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. Practical recommendations</title>
      <p>To the Managers: Employ evidence-based motivating techniques by incorporating both internal (e.g., autonomy, skill enhancement) and extrinsic (e.g., performance-related incentives) motivators, especially in customer-oriented positions. Implement adaptable work policies to enhance hybrid job happiness, as indicated by post-2020 trends, and utilize digital technologies for immediate performance feedback to conform to evolving AI-driven workplace practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">García-Lillo et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Khan et al., 2017</xref>). Employees are encouraged to actively participate in job crafting to align responsibilities with intrinsic motivators (e.g., mastery, meaning) and to leverage organizational support systems (e.g., mental health resources, upskilling programs) to improve job satisfaction and performance. To financial institutions: enhance service atmosphere by educating leaders in participatory management and acknowledging employee contributions, as these elements moderate the satisfaction-performance relationship. Invest in cross-cultural competency initiatives to bridge geographic disparities in motivating research, particularly in non-Western sectors. To the government: formulate labor policies that encourage organizations to implement sustainable HR practices (e.g., standardized wellbeing metrics, protections for gig workers) and allocate funding for research in underrepresented contexts (e.g., SMEs, informal sectors) to address knowledge deficiencies identified in bibliometric analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Donthu et al., 2021</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. Conclusion</title>
      <p>This study presents a comprehensive bibliometric analysis of research trends examining the interrelated dynamics of motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance. Employing Scopus data and VOSviewer visualization methods, we carefully delineated the intellectual framework and development path of this study domain from 1990 to 2023. Our analysis identified three primary research clusters: (1) psychological antecedents emphasizing intrinsic and extrinsic motivation; (2) organizational mediators comprising leadership styles and human resource practices; and (3) performance outcomes involving task performance and organizational citizenship behaviors. The results indicate substantial growth in publishing production, especially after 2020, signifying heightened academic interest in workplace changes prompted by the epidemic. Fundamental theoretical frameworks, such as SDT and the JD-R model, have emerged as essential for comprehending these linkages. Our study revealed significant deficiencies in the literature, notably a prevailing Western bias, with 78% of studies emanating from North America and Europe, and insufficient examination of cultural differences in motivational factors. These findings directly inform practice by demonstrating the need for organizations to design holistic HR strategies that integrate both intrinsic and extrinsic motivators, adapt to the realities of hybrid work, and prepare for AI-driven management systems. This research offers valuable insights for corporate executives seeking to enhance employee engagement and performance. The findings highlight the necessity of creating holistic motivation systems that consider both internal and extrinsic elements, especially in service-oriented sectors. Moreover, our findings underscore the need for future investigations to examine emerging issues, such as AI-driven performance management and hybrid work models, while addressing existing limitations in cross-cultural and multilevel analysis. By explicitly linking these gaps to practical directions, this study consolidates theoretical perspectives and charts actionable pathways for managers, policymakers, and researchers to strengthen motivation-performance systems in diverse contexts. This study synthesizes three decades of research, consolidating existing knowledge and offering a clear roadmap for enhancing theoretical understanding and practical applications in this vital domain of organizational studies. Recognized deficiencies and emerging trends inform forthcoming research initiatives aimed at enhancing employee motivation, satisfaction, and performance in dynamic work environments.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Limitations and future research directions</title>
      <p>This study possesses multiple shortcomings that warrant acknowledgment. The exclusive dependence on Scopus-indexed articles may have introduced selection bias by omitting pertinent studies from alternative databases, including Web of Science and Google Scholar. This method guaranteed the integration of high-quality, peer-reviewed materials; however, subsequent research should utilize numerous databases to facilitate a more thorough examination of motivation, job satisfaction, and employee performance. The limitation of English-language publications may have disregarded significant contributions from non-English-speaking areas, potentially constraining the worldwide relevance of the findings. Future studies should broaden their scope to incorporate multilingual sources, thereby more effectively encompassing cross-cultural perspectives. The omission of books, book chapters, and review articles limited the thoroughness of the analysis. Incorporating a wider range of academic and institutional sources in future study would provide deeper insights into these interrelated dimensions.</p><p>In addition, bibliometric analyses are subject to inherent biases. Citation bias and self-citation practices may inflate the influence of specific authors or regions, while the dominance of management journals compared to those in psychology or sociology may have skewed the intellectual landscape. Future research should therefore consider normalization techniques or complementary analyses across disciplines to mitigate these distortions.</p><p>Beyond generic calls for cross-cultural research, future directions should address specific theoretical questions that are relevant to the field. For instance, how might hybrid work arrangements reshape Herzberg’s hygiene–motivation distinction in practice? How can SDT be adapted for AI-driven performance management and algorithmic monitoring? In what ways might the JD-R model evolve in contexts of digital overload and remote collaboration? Addressing such targeted questions will move the field toward more nuanced, theory-building contributions.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The bibliometric data used in this study were obtained from the Scopus database. Processed datasets supporting the findings are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>1170–1186</page-range>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agung Nugroho</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.46799/jsa.v4i8.675</pub-id>
          <article-title>The effect of organizational learning on employee performance through organizational commitment</article-title>
          <source>Jurnal Syntax Admiration</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>104-112</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmad</surname>
              <given-names>P. S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.37391/ijbmr.090201</pub-id>
          <article-title>Motivation and performance: A psychological process</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Business and Management Research</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>7</volume>
          <page-range>1–19</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alam</surname>
              <given-names>S. M. Shamsul</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chowdhury</surname>
              <given-names>M. A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Razak</surname>
              <given-names>D. B. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s43093-021-00111-7</pub-id>
          <article-title>Research evolution in banking performance: A bibliometric analysis</article-title>
          <source>Future Business Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>2</volume>
          <page-range>7-35</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2015</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Albrecht</surname>
              <given-names>S. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bakker</surname>
              <given-names>A. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gruman</surname>
              <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macey</surname>
              <given-names>W. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saks</surname>
              <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/joepp-08-2014-0042</pub-id>
          <article-title>Employee engagement, human resource management practices, and competitive advantage: An integrated approach</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Organizational Effectiveness: People and Performance</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>48</volume>
          <page-range>591-608</page-range>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bilderback</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Movahed</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCarthy</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/EJTD-02-2024-0019</pub-id>
          <article-title>The role of virtual training in implementing Sustainable Development Goals globally</article-title>
          <source>European Journal of Training and Development</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>32</volume>
          <page-range>53-73</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cao</surname>
              <given-names>T. H. V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chai</surname>
              <given-names>D. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>L. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>H. T. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>C. S. -H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/TLO-09-2023-0177</pub-id>
          <article-title>Learning organization and employee performance: The mediating role of job satisfaction in the Vietnamese context</article-title>
          <source>The Learning Organization</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>C. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robertson</surname>
              <given-names>I. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>International Review of Industrial and Organizational Psychology 2003</source>
          <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
          <year>2003</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>43</volume>
          <page-range>1342-1352</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2013</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>De Cooman</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stynen</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van den Broeck</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sels</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Witte</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jasp.12143</pub-id>
          <article-title>How job characteristics relate to need satisfaction and autonomous motivation: Implications for work effort</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Applied Social Psychology</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>227-268</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2000</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deci</surname>
              <given-names>E. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ryan</surname>
              <given-names>R. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/S15327965PLI1104_01</pub-id>
          <article-title>The “what” and “why” of goal pursuits: Human needs and the self-determination of behavior</article-title>
          <source>Psychological Inquiry</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dia</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effect of training on employee engagement and employee retention</article-title>
          <source>, https://laur.lau.edu.lb:8443/xmlui/handle/10725/14150</source>
          <year>2022</year>
          <publisher-name>Lebanese American University</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>133</volume>
          <page-range>285-296</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Donthu</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mukherjee</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pandey</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lim</surname>
              <given-names>W. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2021.04.070</pub-id>
          <article-title>How to conduct a bibliometric analysis: An overview and guidelines</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ebrahim</surname>
              <given-names>N. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.10492304</pub-id>
          <article-title>Nader Ale Ebrahim’s academic impact and collaboration</article-title>
          <source>Zenodo</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>28</volume>
          <page-range>1786-1815</page-range>
          <issue>13</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>García-Lillo</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Úbeda-García</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marco-Lajara</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09585192.2015.1128461</pub-id>
          <article-title>The intellectual structure of human resource management research: A bibliometric study of the international journal of human resource management</article-title>
          <source>The International Journal of Human Resource Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>16</volume>
          <page-range>250-279</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1976</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hackman</surname>
              <given-names>J.Richard</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oldham</surname>
              <given-names>Greg R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0030-5073(76)90016-7</pub-id>
          <article-title>Motivation through the design of work: Test of a theory</article-title>
          <source>Organizational Behavior and Human Performance</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>87</volume>
          <page-range>268-279</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2002</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harter</surname>
              <given-names>J. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>F. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>T. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0021-9010.87.2.268</pub-id>
          <article-title>Business-unit-level relationship between employee satisfaction, employee engagement, and business outcomes: A meta-analysis</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jafri</surname>
              <given-names>S. M. I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysing the challenges for employee performance improvement—The case of commercial banks in Pakistan</article-title>
          <year>2020</year>
          <publisher-name>University of Wales Trinity Saint David</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>127</volume>
          <page-range>376-407</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2001</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Judge</surname>
              <given-names>Timothy A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thoresen</surname>
              <given-names>Carl J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bono</surname>
              <given-names>Joyce E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patton</surname>
              <given-names>Gregory K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.127.3.376</pub-id>
          <article-title>The job satisfaction–job performance relationship: A qualitative and quantitative review.</article-title>
          <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>191–199</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rafae</surname>
              <given-names>S. U. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.58859/bbe.2023.548</pub-id>
          <article-title>Effectiveness of training on employee motivation and job satisfaction with the mediating role of e-learning in branchless microfinance banking</article-title>
          <source>Bull. Bus. &amp; Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>8</volume>
          <page-range>2158</page-range>
          <year>2017</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>M. A. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jianguo</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Usman</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmad</surname>
              <given-names>Malik I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2017.02158</pub-id>
          <article-title>Moderated mediation model of interrelations between workplace romance, wellbeing, and employee performance</article-title>
          <source>Frontiers in Psychology</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>19</volume>
          <page-range>217-236</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kuvaas</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dysvik</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-8583.2009.00103.x</pub-id>
          <article-title>Perceived investment in employee development, intrinsic motivation and work performance</article-title>
          <source>Human Resource Management Journal</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>118</volume>
          <page-range>499-517</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lancho-Barrantes</surname>
              <given-names>Bárbara S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cantú-Ortiz</surname>
              <given-names>Francisco J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11192-018-2985-2</pub-id>
          <article-title>Science in Mexico: A bibliometric analysis</article-title>
          <source>Scientometrics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>31–40</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mubarak</surname>
              <given-names>R. Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Awang</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>N. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mubarak</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22555/ijelcs.v5i1.2725</pub-id>
          <article-title>Validating learning organization in the medical profession: A preliminary analysis</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Experient. Learn. Case Stud.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>27</volume>
          <page-range>1–16</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nteboheng</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nambei</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Theories of job satisfaction in the higher education context</article-title>
          <source>Acad. Entrep. J.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>33</volume>
          <page-range>1511-1525</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pak</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ju</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/IJOA-04-2024-4432</pub-id>
          <article-title>Shared high-performance work system perceptions as a competitive advantage: Mediating role of trust in management in the HPWS-performance link</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Organizational Analysis</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>732-756</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Patel</surname>
              <given-names>Ritesh J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siddiqui</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/QRFM-01-2022-0008.</pub-id>
          <article-title>Banking service quality literature: A bibliometric review and future research agenda</article-title>
          <source>Qualitative Research in Financial Markets</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ryan</surname>
              <given-names>R. M. (Ed.)</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The Oxford Handbook of Human Motivation</source>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
          <year>2012</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>4</volume>
          <page-range>83-103</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sangeetha</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahalingam</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/17538391111122221</pub-id>
          <article-title>Service quality models in banking: A review</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Islamic and Middle Eastern Finance and Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>72</volume>
          <page-range>1221-1238</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sekhar</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patwardhan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/IJPPM-07-2020-0396</pub-id>
          <article-title>Flexible working arrangement and job performance: The mediating role of supervisor support</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Productivity and Performance Management</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>21</volume>
          <page-range>43-58</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2014</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shuck</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reio</surname>
              <given-names>T. G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1548051813494240</pub-id>
          <article-title>Employee engagement and wellbeing: A moderation model and implications for practice</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Leadership &amp;amp; Organizational Studies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>136</volume>
          <page-range>186-197</page-range>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tandon</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhir</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Islam</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Talwar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mäntymäki</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2021.07.036</pub-id>
          <article-title>Psychological and behavioral outcomes of social media-induced fear of missing out at the workplace</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>35</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wartenberg</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aldrup</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grund</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klusmann</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10648-023-09831-4</pub-id>
          <article-title>Satisfied and high performing? A meta-analysis and systematic review of the correlates of teachers’ job satisfaction</article-title>
          <source>Educational Psychology Review</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wilkinson</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bacon</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Redman</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Snell</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The SAGE Handbook of Human Resource Management</source>
          <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
          <year>2010</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Obrenovic</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamotho</surname>
              <given-names>Daniel W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Godinic</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ostic</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/bs14080688</pub-id>
          <article-title>Enhancing job performance: The critical roles of wellbeing, satisfaction, and trust in supervisor</article-title>
          <source>Behavioral Sciences</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>293–298</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2012</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5539/ass.v9n1p293</pub-id>
          <article-title>A review of job satisfaction</article-title>
          <source>Asian Social Science</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>