<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOTE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Organizations, Technology and Entrepreneurship</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Organ. Technol. Entrep.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JOTE</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">3005-7795</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">3005-7787</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-IYFLMm9Rov2BAQ92-8aTifWLenujOOFv</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jote030105</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Managerial Profiles and Organizational Outcomes: Toward a Behavioral Governance Framework</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0003-5300-2659</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Amakhir</surname>
            <given-names>Hicham</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>h.amakhir@uhp.ac.ma</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-6982-5294</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Benghazala</surname>
            <given-names>Zakaria</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>z.benghazala@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Finance, Audit and Accounting, National School of Business and Management, Hassan 1st University, 26000 Settat, Morocco</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>03</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>67</fpage>
      <lpage>83</lpage>
      <page-range>67-83</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>02</day>
          <month>02</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Organizational outcomes are increasingly recognized as being shaped not only by formal governance structures and institutional arrangements, but also by the individual characteristics of those entrusted with managerial authority. Despite extensive research on leadership and decision-making, limited theoretical integration has been achieved regarding how multidimensional managerial attributes systematically influence organizational functioning within a governance context. To address this gap, a conceptual framework is developed in which managerial profiles are positioned as critical antecedents of organizational outcomes through the lens of behavioral governance. It is proposed that managerial profiles are constituted by four interrelated dimensions: sociological characteristics, professional competencies, psychological dispositions, and cultural orientations. Sociological attributes—including social background, age, gender, and value systems—are argued to shape cognitive schemas, interpersonal perceptions, and role expectations within organizational settings. Professional characteristics, such as educational attainment, occupational experience, domain expertise, and leadership capability, are considered essential in determining information processing capacity, strategic judgment, and adaptive managerial behavior. Psychological dimensions, including cognitive style, emotional regulation, risk perception, and motivational orientation, are further suggested to influence decision quality, conflict management, and behavioral consistency under conditions of uncertainty. In parallel, cultural orientations are expected to affect communication patterns, authority relationships, collective coordination, and the interpretation of organizational norms. Through the integration of these dimensions, managerial behavior is conceptualized as a central mechanism through which governance systems are enacted, interpreted, and transformed in practice. It is argued that a deeper understanding of managerial profiles can contribute to the design of more effective governance mechanisms, the mitigation of cognitive and behavioral biases, and the enhancement of organizational adaptability, strategic coherence, and long-term performance. A behavioral governance perspective is therefore advanced as a theoretically robust foundation for explaining the micro-level origins of macro-level organizational outcomes.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Managerial profiles</kwd>
        <kwd>Organizational behavior</kwd>
        <kwd>Sociological factors</kwd>
        <kwd>Psychological dimensions</kwd>
        <kwd>Decision-making</kwd>
        <kwd>Leadership style</kwd>
        <kwd>Organizational performance.</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="2"/>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <ref-count count="79"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Corporate governance has traditionally been shaped by agency theory, which portrays managers as potentially self-interested actors who may prioritize their own goals over those of shareholders, often due to differences in information and conflicting objectives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">Meckling &amp;amp; Jensen, 1976</xref>). This approach has led to the development of disciplinary mechanisms, such as board composition, the separation of executive and supervisory roles, and financial incentives, aimed at aligning the interests of managers and stakeholders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_71">Shleifer &amp;amp; Vishny, 1997</xref>). However, this perspective remains focused on a contractual and rationalist view, often overlooking the cognitive and behavioral dimensions of managerial decision-making.</p><p>In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Hambrick &amp;amp; Mason (1984)</xref>’s Upper Echelons Theory posits that executives’ personal and professional characteristics, such as age, education, experience, values, and psychological traits, play a decisive role in shaping strategic decisions and, ultimately, organizational performance. Leaders interpret and act upon organizational challenges through the lens of their experiences, beliefs, and competencies, thereby embedding a human and cognitive dimension at the heart of performance analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Carpenter et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>It is within this context that the notion of behavioral governance has gained prominence. This perspective seeks to incorporate cognitive, emotional, and cultural factors directly into governance mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">Bodolica &amp;amp; Spraggon, 2011</xref>). Instead of treating cognitive biases merely as sources of error, behavioral governance acknowledges that, when effectively managed, these biases can serve as catalysts for innovation, creativity, and strategic foresight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">Bosse &amp;amp; Phillips, 2016</xref>). In this context, the leader is not simply an agent to be monitored but a pivotal actor whose personal and professional attributes actively influence the organization’s ability to adapt, innovate, and generate sustainable value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">Finkelstein &amp;amp; Hambrick, 1996</xref>)</p><p>Despite these advances, the literature remains somewhat fragmented. Agency theory emphasizes control and discipline, Upper Echelons Theory stresses managerial discretion, and behavioral governance seeks to reconcile these perspectives. This underscores the need for an integrative conceptual framework that links leaders’ personal attributes, such as age, gender, values, and cognitive styles, with their professional characteristics, including education, experience, and skills, to behavioral governance mechanisms and organizational performance. Such a framework would provide deeper insight into how the cognitive and professional diversity of leaders shapes strategic decision-making, fosters innovation, and enhances organizational competitiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_62">Nielsen, 2014</xref>).</p><p>This study contributes to the literature on intelligent management decision-making by positioning managerial profiles as foundational antecedents of intelligent, data-informed, and human-centered decision processes. Beyond traditional governance mechanisms, the paper argues that sociological, professional, psychological, and cultural traits of managers shape how information is perceived, processed, and translated into strategic choices. From a behavioral governance perspective, these traits influence managers’ ability to mitigate cognitive biases, leverage decision-support systems, and balance analytical rationality with contextual judgment. By explicitly linking managerial profiles to intelligent decision-making processes, this study advances understanding of how governance effectiveness and decision quality emerge from the interaction between individual-level characteristics and organizational decision structures.</p><p>Methodologically, this paper adopts a conceptual and theory-building approach. Rather than testing hypotheses empirically, it develops an integrative conceptual framework that synthesizes contributions from behavioral governance, Upper Echelons Theory, and decision-making research. The proposed framework explains how managerial profiles influence governance mechanisms and, in turn, shape intelligent decision-making processes and organizational outcomes. By structuring and connecting fragmented theoretical perspectives, this study offers a coherent analytical model that can serve as a foundation for future empirical research and decision-support system design.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Literature review</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Agency theory</title>
          
          <p>Agency theory (<span style="font-size: 1rem"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">Fama &amp;amp; Jensen, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_56">Meckling &amp;amp; Jensen, 1976</xref>) has long served as the foundation of traditional corporate governance. It posits that managers (agents) may pursue their own interests at the expense of shareholders (principals), largely due to information asymmetries and conflicting objectives. To mitigate this potential for opportunistic behavior, the theory advocates for disciplinary mechanisms such as board oversight, financial transparency, and performance-based incentives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_71">Shleifer &amp;amp; Vishny, 1997</xref>). Nevertheless, this approach remains primarily centered on control, largely overlooking the individual traits of managers and their cognitive processes, which are treated as secondary factors in the creation of organizational value.</p><p>New empirical evidence has continued to indicate the application of agency theory in the study of governance, where, as shown through numerous investigations into working capital management and firm performance, agency theory has significant explanatory power through its relationship between the corporate governance mechanism and the financial performance outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_61">Naz et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>Recent syntheses of agency theory continue not only to develop the principal-agent relationship, but also to emphasize the ethical and professional implications of agency problems in the governance of organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_70">Shailer, 2023</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Upper echelons theory</title>
          
          <p>Introduced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Hambrick &amp;amp; Mason (1984)</xref>, the Upper Echelons Theory posits that organizations are, to a large extent, a reflection of their leaders’ personal and professional characteristics. Attributes such as age, gender, education, experience, values, and psychological traits shape how executives perceive their environment, interpret information, and make strategic decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">Carpenter et al., 2004</xref>). For instance, leaders with diverse educational backgrounds or international experience tend to foster innovation and strategic openness, whereas long tenure can sometimes contribute to greater risk aversion. This perspective places the leader at the heart of the organization, underscoring how their cognitive lenses and managerial choices directly influence organizational performance.</p><p>More recent upper echelons research expands from a focus solely on demographic proxies to identify CEO's complete psychological profiles and how they interact with firm context and gender and/or racial diversity. Data is being generated that provides insight into the impact of psychological characteristics and gender dynamics on executive decision-making and ultimately firm performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_55">McHugh &amp;amp; Duane, 2025</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Behavioral governance</title>
          
          <p>Behavioral governance refers to an approach to corporate governance that integrates the psychological, cognitive, and emotional aspects of managers, executives, and stakeholders into organizational decision-making. Unlike traditional governance approaches, which focus primarily on formal structures, legal rules, and institutional mechanisms, behavioral governance emphasizes how human behavior, cognitive biases, and perceptions influence the quality, transparency, and effectiveness of governance decisions.</p><p>Behavioral governance aims to bridge the gap between the control-oriented logic of agency theory and the managerial discretion emphasized by Upper Echelons Theory. Drawing on findings from cognitive and behavioral sciences, it views value creation as stemming not only from oversight, but also from managers’ capacity to learn, innovate, and leverage the organization’s cognitive and social resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">Charreaux &amp;amp; Wirtz, 2007</xref>). Cognitive biases, long regarded merely as sources of error, can, when properly managed within governance frameworks, serve as drivers of creativity and strategic differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">Busenitz &amp;amp; Barney, 1997</xref>). This perspective thus underscores the critical role of managers’ psychological and cultural characteristics in shaping organizational performance.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_75">Van Ees et al. (2009)</xref> develop a behavioral theory of corporate governance by shifting the focus from formal structures and agency assumptions to the actual behavior of boards of directors. They argue that board effectiveness is shaped by cognitive limitations, social interactions, group dynamics, trust, communication, and power relations among directors. Rather than viewing boards as purely rational decision-making bodies, the article shows that governance outcomes emerge from complex behavioral processes and contextual influences.</p><p>The work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_45">Kahneman &amp;amp; Tversky (2013)</xref> provided a fundamental behavioral framework for understanding decision-making under uncertainty by challenging the assumptions of expected utility theory. The authors show that individuals evaluate outcomes relative to a reference point rather than in absolute terms and exhibit loss aversion, whereby losses are perceived more strongly than equivalent gains. In addition, probabilities are subjectively weighted, with a tendency to overweight low probabilities and underweight high ones. These cognitive biases lead to systematic patterns such as risk aversion in gains and risk-seeking behavior in losses. In the context of behavioral governance, this theory helps explain why managers and board members may make suboptimal or irrational decisions, thereby emphasizing the importance of incorporating psychological factors into governance mechanisms to improve decision quality and organizational performance.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Resource-based view theory</title>
          
          <p>The   resource-based view (RBV) theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Barney, 1991</xref>) emphasized that strategic resources and organizational capabilities are fundamental sources of sustainable competitive advantage. Within this framework, the leader’s profile emerges as a critical strategic resource. Personal traits, such as values, cognitive characteristics, biases, and diversity, and professional attributes, such as education, experience, and managerial or technical skills, constitute distinctive human capital that directly shapes the organization’s ability to exploit its resources and pursue strategic opportunities. For example, a leader with international experience and strong analytical abilities can identify untapped markets or high-potential innovations, thereby generating sustainable competitive advantages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_48">Kor &amp;amp; Mahoney, 2005</xref>).</p><p>RBV further stresses that resources must be rare, valuable, difficult to imitate, and non-substitutable to contribute to lasting performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Barney, 1991</xref>). Applied to leadership, this suggests that executives with unique experiences, skills, or networks represent a major strategic asset, influencing not only economic outcomes but also the organization’s adaptability and capacity for innovation.</p><p>The RBV is used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_51">Lubis (2022)</xref> to explain how businesses use their internal resources and capabilities to improve their strategic performance. Because of the combination of the RBV and behavioral governance, the decisions made by managers impacted by cognitive biases or organizational culture were important for successfully utilizing the resources to improve the firm’s performance.</p><p>By integrating RBV with behavioral governance, the manager can be conceptualized as an internal strategic resource whose cognitive, emotional, and professional characteristics shape decision-making quality, innovation potential, and the creation of sustainable value. This perspective complements agency theory and Upper Echelons Theory by accentuating the leader’s active and creative role in mobilizing organizational resources to achieve competitive advantage.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>3. Managerial profiles and their influence on organizational decision-making</title>
      <p>Managers occupy a central position in corporate governance and organizational performance, not only because of their decision-making authority but also due to their personal and professional characteristics. Their behavior within the organization, leadership style, and capacity to mobilize resources are shaped as much by their experiences and skills as by the sociocultural factors that influence their worldview and attitudes toward risk. Accordingly, analyzing a manager’ s profile requires a multidimensional approach that encompasses sociological aspects – such as social background, gender, religion, and age – as well as professional factors, including education, experience, and specific competencies. This comprehensive perspective enhances our understanding of how leaders impact behavioral governance and, in turn, organizational performance, by considering the diversity of individual traits and contextual influences that guide their decision-making (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Finkelstein et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Hambrick &amp;amp; Mason, 1984</xref>).</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Definition of a manager</title>
          
          <p>A manager can be defined as an individual entrusted with the responsibility of making strategic and operational decisions within an organization and of mobilizing available resources to achieve the company’s objectives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Finkelstein et al., 2009</xref>). Managers occupy a central position in the organizational hierarchy and exert a decisive influence on the organization’s vision, culture, governance practices, and, ultimately, its performance.</p><p>In literature, the term “manager” covers several dimensions:</p><p>1. Functional dimension: The manager has decision-making power and legal responsibility for the organization, whether they are the CEO, president and CEO, executive director, or any member of senior management with strategic authority (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_57">Mintzberg, 1973</xref>).</p><p>2. Personal dimension: The manager is also an actor with individual characteristics, such as values, personality, cognitive and emotional traits, which influence their decision-making style and approach to governance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Hambrick &amp;amp; Mason, 1984</xref>).</p><p>3. Professional dimension: Their skills, experience, and training shape their ability to analyze the environment, assess risks, and effectively mobilize the company's resources to create value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">Barney, 1991</xref>).</p><p>Thus, managers are not limited to administrative or hierarchical functions; they are strategic actors whose personal and professional profiles determine how organizations function and adapt to the demands of the economic and social environment. In the context of behavioral governance, this definition takes on particular importance, as the behavior, cognition, and experiences of the leader become essential levers for guiding decision-making and influencing the overall performance of the company (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_64">Peni, 2014</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. The sociological aspects of a manager's profile</title>
          
          <p>The analysis of a manager's profile cannot be limited to their professional skills and experience alone, it must also take into account the sociological aspects that influence their perceptions, values, and behaviors within the organization. Factors such as social background, gender, religion, and age shape the way leaders interpret information, make decisions, and interact with their employees. These sociological dimensions influence not only leadership style, but also the way governance is exercised and organizational performance is achieved.</p><p>As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_54">Martinez (2023)</xref>, sociological factors influence managerial behavior through social norms, culture within organizations, and the relationships between various individuals who work for an organization when making decisions. Using this framework implies that managers' decisions are influenced by both formal rules and the dynamics of their social and/or cultural environments and, thus, can impact how well an organization performs overall.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.2.1 Origin</title>
              
              <p>A manager’s social origin plays a pivotal role in shaping their perceptions, values, and decision-making behaviors within the organization. It encompasses the family environment, socioeconomic status, cultural background, and social networks experienced during their education and socialization. These elements influence how managers assess risks, prioritize objectives, and mobilize organizational resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_37">Hofstede, 1987</xref>).</p><p>Family characteristics and the environment in which a child grows up play a decisive role in shaping a leader’s personality, skills, and outlook. The values transmitted by parents, early experiences within the family, and social interactions during childhood and adolescence all contribute to forming attitudes toward risk, problem-solving abilities, and decision-making style. For instance, a leader encouraged from an early age to act independently and take initiative is more likely to develop autonomous, solution-oriented leadership skills, which can positively impact governance and organizational performance.</p><p>Furthermore, social background affects a manager’s social capital, including relational networks and access to external strategic resources, thereby enhancing their capacity to identify opportunities and create sustainable competitive advantage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">Bournois &amp;amp; Roussillon, 1998</xref>).</p><p>As observed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">Fourot (2024)</xref>, the social origins and class habitus of top management team members influence their behaviors and decision-making processes. This study underscores the importance of behavioral governance by showing that managers’ social backgrounds shape strategic choices, risk preferences, and interactions within the corporate elite, ultimately affecting organizational performance and governance effectiveness.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.2.2 Religion</title>
              
              <p>Religion is a determining factor in shaping a leader's profile, influencing their values, beliefs, and, consequently, their strategic decisions within the company. These beliefs, derived from religious teachings, can shape their ethical perception, worldview, and priorities in decision-making. Indeed, religion can be a source of fundamental moral and ethical principles for a leader, prompting them to question certain company practices or decisions that conflict with these values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">Hofstede, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_74">Tribou, 1995</xref>).</p><p>In certain contexts, such as that of Muslim entrepreneurs, religion can guide economic and decision-making behavior by promoting principles such as integrity, fairness, prudence, and social responsibility. These religious values then become guidelines for governance style and managerial practices, promoting transparency, organizational cohesion, and stakeholder trust (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_74">Tribou, 1995</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_46">Kargarkamvar et al. (2023)</xref> emphasized that financial managers’ religious orientation can strongly shape their decision-making approaches. Their findings show that personal values and belief systems influence managerial judgments and risk assessments, illuminating the importance of behavioral governance in accounting for how individual and cultural factors affect organizational decisions and overall performance.</p><p>Commitment to work is considered a religious duty in Islam, and Muslim leaders are encouraged to be diligent, responsible, and committed in the performance of their professional duties. This can translate into exemplary leadership, effective resource management, and a commitment to excellence in achieving organizational goals.</p><p>Similarly, religion extends beyond being a personal attribute, serving as a socio-cultural factor that shapes organizational behavior. It influences how leaders perceive opportunities and constraints, make decisions, and engage with employees, thereby exerting a direct impact on corporate governance and organizational performance.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.2.3 Gender</title>
              
              <p>Gender is a significant sociological aspect of a manager’s profile, as it can influence leadership style, decision-making, and interactions with employees and stakeholders. While leadership style is not strictly determined by gender, research has identified certain tendencies. For example, female managers often adopt a more collaborative and participatory approach, emphasizing open communication and teamwork, whereas male managers may be more directive or hierarchical in their style (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">Eagly &amp;amp; Carli, 2007</xref>). These tendencies can affect organizational dynamics and the implementation of corporate strategies.</p><p>Gender can also influence risk-taking and strategic decision-making. Studies in behavioral finance and corporate governance suggest that female executives may approach investments and risk management more cautiously, which can impact the long-term performance and sustainability of organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">Adams &amp;amp; Funk, 2012</xref>). This cautiousness should not be seen as a limitation, but rather as a variation in strategic approach that can enrich decision-making within governing bodies.</p><p>The relationship between gender diversity and organizational performance is well documented. The presence of women in leadership positions or on boards of directors is often associated with stronger governance and more inclusive management practices, which enhance overall company performance. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_66">Piscopo (2020)</xref> noted that organizations with higher female representation in management teams generally exhibit better organizational culture and superior financial outcomes, largely due to a more balanced and thoughtful approach to decision-making.</p><p>Gender also shapes social perception and professional networks. Stereotypes can affect recognition, access to positions of power, and influence in decision-making processes, although these barriers are gradually diminishing as awareness of diversity and equal opportunities grows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">Claes, 1999</xref>). Therefore, gender should not be considered in isolation but as an interacting factor with other dimensions of a manager’s profile, such as experience, education, and cultural background, influencing their organizational behavior and leadership style.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">Heilman et al. (2024)</xref> showed that gender stereotypes can lead to bias and discrimination in the workplace, shaping managerial decisions and affecting interactions, opportunities, and career advancement. Their study illustrates the pathways through which social and cognitive perceptions influence organizational practices and outcomes.</p><p>Understanding the impact of gender helps identify potential differences in strategic decision-making and underscores how diversity can serve as a lever for innovation and enhanced organizational performance.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.2.4 Age</title>
              
              <p>Age is a key dimension of a manager’s profile. Older managers generally possess extensive professional experience, having accumulated knowledge in crisis management, organizational strategy, and interpersonal relations. This experience often fosters cautious and thoughtful decision-making grounded in a deep understanding of market dynamics and internal organizational processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Hambrick &amp;amp; Mason, 1984</xref>).</p><p>However, age can also pose challenges, particularly regarding openness to change. Older managers may prefer traditional approaches and be hesitant to adopt new technologies or management practices, which can sometimes impede innovation and the organization’s ability to adapt in a rapidly evolving business environment.</p><p>Conversely, younger managers can bring fresh energy and agility to the organization. They are often more willing to embrace change and experiment with new ideas, thereby stimulating innovation and growth. Their creative thinking and propensity for risk-taking can be valuable assets in dynamic business contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_43">Kahneman, 2011</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">Han &amp;amp; Jo (2024)</xref> examine the impact of CEO age on corporate performance in dynamic environments. Their findings indicate that younger CEOs tend to pursue more innovative and risk-taking strategies, which can enhance adaptability under rapidly changing conditions, whereas older CEOs often rely on experience and established routines to guide decision-making.</p><p>Age also shapes stakeholder perceptions and professional relationships. Older managers may enjoy greater credibility and legitimacy in certain cultural contexts, whereas younger managers may be seen as more dynamic and open to change. This interplay between age and social perception underscores the importance of considering age as a multidimensional factor when analyzing a manager’s profile.</p><p>These traits influence managers’ cognitive frames, openness to information, and interaction with governance mechanisms such as monitoring, transparency, and control. Consequently, sociological dimensions condition how managers interpret strategic signals and respond to organizational constraints, thereby affecting decision rationality and governance effectiveness. Understanding these implications allows governance systems to be better aligned with managerial profiles in order to enhance intelligent and context-sensitive decision-making.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. The professional aspects of a manager’s profile</title>
          
          <p>The professional dimensions of a manager’s profile encompass their education, experience, skills, and potential. These attributes directly shape their capacity to make strategic decisions, process and manage information effectively, and lead the organization toward achieving its objectives.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.1 Education and qualifications</title>
              
              <p>Education and qualifications are a fundamental component of a manager’s professional profile, directly shaping their ability to analyze information, make strategic decisions, and guide corporate governance. A manager’s academic level and area of specialization determine their theoretical knowledge, analytical skills, and credibility with stakeholders, which can translate into more informed strategic choices and improved organizational performance. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_76">Wang &amp;amp; Yin (2018)</xref> demonstrated that a CEO’s education and specialization directly influence the selection of acquisition targets, emphasizing the role of education in corporate strategy.</p><p>Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">Gottesman &amp;amp; Morey (2010)</xref> found a positive correlation between executives’ educational backgrounds and the financial performance of their companies, confirming the importance of training for organizational success. Moreover, the reputation and type of institution attended by a CEO significantly affect both their compensation and company performance, emphasizing the impact of the quality of education received (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_40">Jalbert et al., 2002</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_78">Yahaya (2025)</xref> investigated the relationship between CEO education and firm performance in Nigeria, finding that higher levels of formal education are positively associated with better organizational outcomes. The study shows that educated CEOs are more likely to adopt effective strategic practices, make informed decisions, and navigate complex business environments successfully.</p><p>Beyond formal qualifications, the relevance and specialization of training are crucial. Sector-specific education equips managers to better assess risks, identify opportunities, and integrate innovations into the company’s strategy. Additionally, continuous professional development throughout their careers enhances managers’ capacity to adapt to evolving economic and technological environments. Therefore, education and training extend beyond academic credentials, serving as a strategic lever that contributes to corporate performance, governance, and long-term sustainability.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.2 Professional experience</title>
              
              <p>Professional experience is a central element of a manager’s profile, as it shapes their capacity to oversee the organization, make strategic decisions, and anticipate potential risks. The knowledge and skills acquired over time enable managers to develop practical expertise, gain a deeper understanding of market dynamics, and enhance their organizational judgment. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Hambrick &amp;amp; Mason (1984)</xref> argued that executives’ professional characteristics, including experience, directly influence strategic choices and business performance, reflecting the interplay between their perceptions, values, and understanding of complex issues.</p><p>Diverse experience, including responsibilities in different sectors or functions, promotes cognitive flexibility and the ability to manage complex and uncertain situations. Managers with extensive experience in management or corporate leadership are better able to make balanced decisions and mobilize their networks and resources to support organizational strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Finkelstein et al., 2009</xref>). In addition, professional experience influences how leaders manage the company's intellectual capital and leverage talent within the organization, thereby enhancing innovation and overall performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_68">Quinn et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Furthermore, managers' previous experiences, particularly in international contexts or in foreign direct investment projects, have an impact on strategic choices such as the mode of entry into foreign markets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_36">Herrmann &amp;amp; Datta, 2006</xref>). Professional experience, therefore, plays a key role in the legitimacy and credibility of managers among employees and external partners, and determines the company's ability to achieve its strategic objectives.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_63">Peng &amp;amp; Chiu (2022)</xref> explored how CEOs’ international work experience, functional backgrounds, and career concerns influence their investment decisions. Their study finds that CEOs with international exposure and diverse functional experience are more likely to pursue innovative and growth-oriented investments, while career concerns can temper risk-taking.</p><p>Professional experience plays a crucial role in establishing a manager’s legitimacy and credibility with both employees and external stakeholders, while also shaping the organization’s capacity to achieve its strategic objectives.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>3.3.3 Skills and potential</title>
              
              <p>Skills and potential are fundamental components of a manager’s professional profile, as they determine their capacity to make strategic decisions, lead teams, and ensure the sustainable development of the organization. Skills include technical knowledge, mastery of management tools, analytical abilities, and interpersonal competencies, while potential reflects a manager’s capacity to grow, adapt to change, and guide the long-term evolution of the organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">Finkelstein et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>The combination of technical and managerial skills allows managers to process information efficiently and implement innovative strategies. Managers with high potential can mobilize their teams, foster creativity, and strengthen organizational culture, thereby enhancing overall company performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_68">Quinn et al., 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">Lee &amp;amp; Phan (2000)</xref> pointed out that in multinational corporations, managerial skills are critical for recruiting and evaluating executives, stressing the importance of strategic and decision-making abilities for global organizational success.</p><p>Moreover, skills and potential shape the relationship between a manager’s personal power and organizational performance. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">Amedu &amp;amp; Dulewicz (2018)</xref> demonstrated that managers with advanced skills, combined with legitimate authority, tend to achieve superior financial and operational outcomes. A manager’s potential also encompasses the ability to anticipate changes in the economic environment and adjust strategic decisions accordingly, which is essential for organizational sustainability.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_58">Mitan (2023)</xref> proposed strategies to enhance managers’ decision-making skills, emphasizing the importance of training, analytical tools, and structured frameworks. The study shows that strengthening managerial competencies improves the quality and consistency of decisions, enabling organizations to respond more effectively to complex and dynamic environments. These findings underscore the value of deliberate skill development in fostering better strategic and operational outcomes.</p><p>In sum, beyond individual capabilities, a manager’s skills and potential influence their ability to lead teams, drive innovation, and steer strategic decisions, making a decisive contribution to organizational performance and adaptability in a constantly changing environment.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>4. The psychological and cultural approach to the manager's profile</title>
      <p>The psychological and cultural approach to executive profiling focuses on the deeper factors that shape strategic behavior, management style, and ultimately organizational performance. From a psychological perspective, research points to the importance of personality traits such as locus of control, risk tolerance, self-confidence, and openness to change in influencing how managers perceive and interpret complex situations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_65">Peterson et al., 2012</xref>). For instance, managers with a high tolerance for ambiguity are often more willing to embrace bold, innovative strategies, whereas those with lower risk tolerance tend to favor caution, stability, and incremental change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_60">Nadkarni &amp;amp; Herrmann, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Beyond personality traits, emotions and cognitive biases also play a significant role in shaping managerial decision-making. Studies in behavioral governance indicate that biases such as overconfidence, excessive optimism, and anchoring can strongly influence strategic choices and risk management practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_44">Kahneman &amp;amp; Tversky, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_52">Malmendier &amp;amp; Tate, 2005</xref>). For instance, an overconfident manager may overestimate organizational capabilities, leading to overly ambitious or risky projects that could jeopardize long-term performance. In contrast, managers who recognize their own cognitive biases and regulate their emotional responses are better positioned to adopt a more balanced and rational approach to strategic decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">Bazerman &amp;amp; Moore, 2012</xref>).</p><p>The cultural dimension plays a crucial role in shaping the norms, values, and behaviors that are considered acceptable within organizations. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_38">Hofstede (2001)</xref> demonstrates, factors such as power distance, collectivism, and long-term orientation directly influence how managers exercise authority, interact with employees, and make decisions. For instance, in cultures characterized by low power distance, managers are more likely to adopt a participatory and collaborative approach to decision-making. In contrast, in cultures with high power distance, leadership tends to be more hierarchical and centralized, often resulting in a top-down decision-making style (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_39">House et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>The interplay between psychological traits and cultural dimensions is particularly important in shaping managerial effectiveness. A manager with strong emotional intelligence and high intercultural sensitivity is better equipped to adapt their leadership style to diverse cultural contexts, fostering cohesion, trust, and performance in multicultural teams (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">Dickson et al., 2003</xref>). This perspective underscores that organizational performance and governance depend not only on technical expertise or professional experience but also on personality traits, emotional regulation, cognitive biases, and cultural values that collectively shape strategic decisions and leadership approaches.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_47">Kitayama &amp;amp; Salvador (2024)</xref> examined how cultural contexts shape psychological processes, decision-making, and social behavior across diverse populations. Their study emphasizes that cognitive patterns, values, and social norms vary significantly across cultures, influencing individual and group choices.</p><p>Along with cognitive biases, motivating and self-determining processes have been shown to impact managers’ decisions by using causal agency theory to explain how individuals are involved in their intention by self-controlling how they act within an organizational context (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_72">Shogren &amp;amp; Raley, 2022</xref>).</p><p>Psychological traits, including cognitive biases, risk perception, and emotional regulation, play a critical role in shaping managerial decision-making under uncertainty. From a behavioral governance standpoint, these characteristics affect how managers process information, evaluate alternatives, and engage with decision-support systems. Governance mechanisms that acknowledge and mitigate such biases, through transparency, structured decision processes, and analytical tools, are more likely to foster intelligent decision-making. Thus, psychological dimensions represent a key explanatory link between individual cognition and the quality of governance-driven organizational decisions.</p><p>To provide a structured overview of the key dimensions shaping managerial profiles and their implications for behavioral governance, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref> summarizes the main sociological, professional, psychological, and cultural variables and their influence on decision-making processes. The sociological dimension emphasizes the role of demographic and social characteristics in shaping values and behaviors, while the professional dimension underscores the importance of education, experience, and skills in enhancing analytical and strategic capacities. The psychological dimension captures the effects of personality traits, cognitive biases, and emotions on judgment, whereas the cultural dimension reflects how shared values and norms influence perceptions and leadership styles.</p>
      
        <table-wrap id="table_1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Key dimensions of managerial profile</title>
          </caption>
          <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Dimension</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Variables</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Description</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Influence on Decision-Making</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Implications for Behavioral Governance</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sociological</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Age, gender, religion, social origin</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Reflects the social and demographic background shaping values, beliefs, and social identity of managers</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Influences risk perception, ethical orientation, leadership style, and interpersonal relations</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Requires adaptive governance mechanisms that consider diversity, social norms, and value systems</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Professional</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Education, experience, skills, managerial potential</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Represents the formal and experiential qualifications of managers</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Enhances analytical capacity, strategic thinking, and problem-solving abilities</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Supports the design of competence-based governance systems and informed decision processes</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Psychological</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Personality traits, cognitive biases (overconfidence, optimism), emotions, risk tolerance</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Captures internal cognitive and emotional processes influencing behavior</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Affects judgment quality, rationality, and susceptibility to biases in decision-making</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Necessitates governance tools to mitigate biases (e.g., monitoring, decision frameworks, behavioral controls)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cultural</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Values, norms, beliefs, cultural orientation (e.g., power distance, collectivism)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Reflects the broader cultural environment influencing managerial behavior</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Shapes interpretation of information, authority perception, and leadership approach</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Implies context-sensitive governance structures adapted to cultural environments</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
        </table-wrap>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>5. The manager’s profile as a determining factor in organizational behavior</title>
      <p>Organizational behavior within a company is shaped not only by its formal structures and governance mechanisms but also by the individual characteristics of its managers, who influence strategic vision, leadership style, and internal relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_32">Hambrick &amp;amp;amp; Mason, 1984</xref>). Drawing on Upper Echelons Theory, research suggests that strategic decisions and organizational dynamics are deeply rooted in the experiences, values, and personality traits of executives. Consequently, the manager’s profile emerges as a critical factor for understanding organizational behavior and, by extension, overall corporate performance.</p>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.1. The manager’s profile and relationships within the firm</title>
          
          <p>The manager’s profile plays a pivotal role in shaping the quality and dynamics of relationships within the organization. Individual attributes such as leadership style, communication skills, personality traits, and emotional intelligence largely determine how managers interact with employees, peers, and external stakeholders. Managers with strong emotional intelligence and an open communication style often foster a climate of trust and collaboration, enhancing organizational cohesion and facilitating the smooth flow of information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">Boyatzis et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>Emotional intelligence, in particular, is widely recognized as a critical asset for managing professional relationships effectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">Goleman, 1998</xref>). It enables managers to understand and regulate emotions, anticipate employee reactions, and address conflicts constructively. Recent research shows that managers with high emotional intelligence tend to strengthen organizational commitment, reduce turnover, and enhance employee satisfaction and motivation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">Abuzaid et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p>Moreover, the sociological and cultural background of managers shapes their values, attitudes, and social perceptions, influencing how they manage interpersonal dynamics. For instance, studies emphasize that cultural diversity and intercultural sensitivity among managers facilitate the effective management of heterogeneous teams and support conflict resolution in complex, multicultural environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">Groves &amp;amp; Feyerherm, 2011</xref>).</p><p>Professional experience and academic training also play a crucial role in shaping strategic interpersonal skills. Managers with diverse professional backgrounds are often better equipped to build constructive relationships with both internal and external stakeholders, enhancing the organization’s capacity for adaptation and innovation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_33">Hamori &amp;amp; Koyuncu, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_49">Lee &amp;amp; Phan, 2000</xref>).</p><p>Research further indicates that leadership style, whether transformational, transactional, or participative, directly affects the quality of interpersonal relationships within organizations. Transformational leadership, for instance, is typically associated with open, inclusive, and motivating interactions that foster collaboration and positively influence collective performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Bass &amp;amp; Riggio, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Moreover, the way managers exercise power has profound implications for organizational culture and the overall work climate. Authoritarian leadership marked by excessive control, favoritism, or abuse of authority often generates tension, conflict, and employee dissatisfaction, ultimately undermining motivation, productivity, and retention. In contrast, managers who delegate responsibilities, share decision-making power, and encourage employee participation tend to promote stronger commitment, greater accountability, and higher job satisfaction across the organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">Goetschy, 1981</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">Ghorbani (2023)</xref> reviewed the competencies and leadership profiles of successful construction project managers, focusing on key skills such as strategic planning, risk management, communication, and team coordination. The study shows that these managerial capabilities directly influence project outcomes, decision-making quality, and overall organizational effectiveness. It demonstrates the importance of developing a well-rounded skill set and leadership approach to achieve high performance in complex and dynamic project environments.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.2. The manager’s profile and the processing of information</title>
          
          <p>In today’s economic environment, marked by growing complexity and constant uncertainty, a manager’s ability to collect, process, and interpret information becomes a critical determinant of organizational performance. The decision-making process relies on two essential steps: Acquiring relevant information and interpreting it effectively. Both steps are influenced by the manager’s individual characteristics, including cognitive style, experience, and personal biases, meaning that information processing is never entirely neutral.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">Junge et al. (2023)</xref> investigated how organizational structure shapes senior managers’ selective information processing, with a particular focus on CEOs. They argue that organizational structure operates as an informational filter that influences how managers perceive, interpret, and prioritize environmental signals. A central contribution of their study is the concept of “perception gaps,” defined as the discrepancy between managers’ subjective perceptions and objective environmental conditions. Based on a sample of 281 CEOs from 216 firms, their findings show that functional organizational structures tend to amplify cognitive biases by increasing perception gaps, while divisional structures are associated with more accurate and integrated information processing. This difference is explained by variations in information flows within organizations: Functional structures often create siloed and fragmented information, whereas divisional structures facilitate more diversified and context-rich information exchange.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.2.1 Obtaining information</title>
              
              <p>A curious manager challenges the status quo, prompting the organization to reconsider existing approaches and adopt innovative solutions to emerging challenges. This mindset encourages the exploration of diverse information sources, including areas that may initially appear unrelated but can offer valuable insights for the business. By fostering an inclusive environment in which all employees are encouraged to contribute, curiosity and open-mindedness help cultivate a culture that supports creativity and innovation.</p><p>Diversifying information sources is a key aspect of an open-minded managerial approach. Managers who are receptive to new ideas actively seek insights from a wide range of disciplines, industries, and cultural contexts. This strategy not only broadens perspectives but also enhances the manager’s understanding of complex organizational challenges, enabling more informed and strategic decision-making.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_77">Wilson (1999)</xref> proposed a classification of information behavior models into three main categories:</p><p>• Models focusing on user interaction with information retrieval systems, which examine search strategies and tactics (information search behavior);</p><p>• Models addressing information access and utilization practices, exploring how individuals seek and use information in their decision-making processes (information search and use behavior);</p><p>• Models adopting a holistic perspective, which studies all aspects of information practices within a broader organizational or social context (information behavior).</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Albaum et al. (1995)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">Junge et al. (2023)</xref> jointly underlined that managerial information processing is shaped by both individual and organizational determinants. On the one hand, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">Albaum et al. (1995)</xref> emphasized the role of individual decision-making styles, showing that managers differ in how they value and use information, with some adopting a more analytical and systematic approach while others rely more on intuition and subjective judgment. On the other hand, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_41">Junge et al. (2023)</xref> focused on the organizational level, demonstrating that structural configurations influence senior managers’ selective information processing by shaping information flows and generating perception gaps. Taken together, these studies suggest that managerial cognition is not only a function of personal behavioral tendencies but is also structurally embedded within the organization.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.2.2 Interpretation of information</title>
              
              <p>The interpretation of information is heavily influenced by the context in which it is presented. Managers interpret data through their own frames of reference, shaped by past experiences, beliefs, values, and cultural background.</p><p>Filtering and processing information are critical skills for managers, who must navigate large volumes of data from both internal and external sources. The challenge lies in distinguishing relevant and meaningful insights from the surrounding noise, a task that can be highly complex. Skilled managers are able to identify key signals that point to important trends or potential risks, while filtering out less pertinent information. This ability allows them to concentrate on what is truly essential for effective strategic decision-making.</p><p>Information interpretation plays a central role in the decision-making process, directly affecting the quality and relevance of strategic choices. It is shaped not only by the quantity and complexity of available information but also by the individual characteristics of the manager, including knowledge, experience, values, and cognitive style (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_50">Lesca et al., 2012</xref>). Managers do not simply receive information; they actively filter, classify, and evaluate it using pre-existing mental models, beliefs, and prior experiences, which can sometimes introduce cognitive biases or subjective interpretations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_53">March &amp;amp; Simon, 1993</xref>). Therefore, a manager’s capacity to analyze, contextualize, and make sense of information is a key determinant in guiding strategy, managing risk, and seizing opportunities.</p><p>Furthermore, the organizational environment and corporate culture play a complementary role by shaping communication channels, promoting transparency, and influencing the flow of information, which in turn affects how managers interpret and use data in decision-making.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">Junghans (2017)</xref> emphasized the central role of managers in collecting, analyzing, and applying information to guide strategic decisions. His research emphasizes the interplay between information management, strategic thinking, decision-making, and leadership, demonstrating that a manager’s ability to process information effectively is a critical determinant of organizational performance, adaptability, and long-term success.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.3. The manager’s profile and decision-making</title>
          
          <p>The decisions made by a company’s managers have a profound impact on its performance, competitiveness, and long-term sustainability. Yet, the process through which these decisions are made is strongly shaped by the manager’s profile, a complex combination of personal characteristics and professional experiences.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_69">Sadler-Smith &amp;amp; Burke-Smalley (2015)</xref> critically examined how managers make important decisions and argue that existing knowledge remains incomplete regarding the actual cognitive processes involved. They emphasize that managerial decision-making is not purely rational or fully systematic, but rather a complex interplay between analytical reasoning and intuitive processes. The authors stress that intuition plays a significant and often underexplored role in managerial judgment, particularly in situations characterized by uncertainty, ambiguity, and time pressure. At the same time, they underline that analytical approaches remain essential for structuring problems and evaluating alternatives. Overall, the study calls for a more integrated understanding of decision-making that acknowledges the coexistence and interaction of both intuitive and analytical modes of thinking.</p>
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.3.1 Selecting decision priorities</title>
              
              <p>The process of setting decision-making priorities involves several interconnected steps, each of which is crucial for effective organizational governance. It begins with the identification of priorities, during which the manager determines the most critical strategic issues for the company, taking into account its mission, vision, and overall objectives.</p><p>The next step involves analyzing the factors that influence these priorities, including available resources, organizational context, external constraints, and potential risks. This analysis enables a careful assessment of the feasibility and potential impact of each priority, supporting informed decision-making.</p><p>The third step is the prioritization of actions, which establishes the order of importance and urgency for the initiatives to be undertaken. This prioritization is complemented by aligning priorities with the company’s overall strategic objectives, ensuring coherence and effectiveness in decision-making.</p><p>Once priorities are defined and aligned, the manager communicates and implements them with the relevant teams. This step is essential for ensuring coordinated, transparent, and shared execution, fostering employee engagement and effective resource mobilization.</p><p>Finally, the process includes continuous monitoring and adjustment of priorities based on results achieved and changes in the internal and external environment. This phase ensures agile and adaptive governance, enabling the organization to respond to evolving circumstances while maintaining the strategic relevance of its decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_42">Junghans, 2017</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.3.2 The rationality of decisions</title>
              
              <p>Rational decision-making is a fundamental pillar of governance and a core element of the managerial decision-making process. It refers to the ability to select the most appropriate options based on available information, strategic objectives, and organizational constraints (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_73">Simon, 1976</xref>). Within complex organizational contexts, rationality allows managers to structure their thinking, evaluate alternatives, and choose those that maximize benefits while minimizing risks.</p><p>However, managers’ rationality is often constrained by cognitive, emotional, and contextual factors, a concept <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_73">Simon (1976)</xref> describes as bounded rationality. In practice, this means that managers frequently make satisfactory rather than optimal decisions, relying on heuristics, past experiences, and subjective perceptions of the issues at hand. While this pragmatic approach helps manage uncertainty and complexity, it can also lead to biases or suboptimal choices if information is incomplete or misinterpreted.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_67">Pittenger et al. (2023)</xref> explored how bounded rationality affects managerial decision-making in the context of data usage. The study shows that managers face cognitive limitations when processing large volumes of information, which can lead to simplified or suboptimal decisions. Their findings indicate that effective data management and decision-support tools are essential to help managers make more informed and accurate choices, improving overall organizational performance.</p><p>Rational decision-making also entails anticipating both short- and long-term consequences, integrating diverse perspectives, and assessing the risks associated with each alternative. In practice, this translates into a structured approach that combines data analysis, strategic thinking, and stakeholder consultation, ensuring that decisions are coherent, justified, and aligned with the organization’s overall objectives.</p><p>Thus, rationality extends beyond mere logical calculation; it is closely linked to a manager’s ability to interpret information, prioritize effectively, and exercise power strategically to shape organizational outcomes.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>5.4. The manager’s profile and leadership style</title>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.4.1 The autocratic style</title>
              
              <p>This leadership style is characterized by centralized authority and decision-making that is tightly controlled by the manager. It relies on strict guidelines and close supervision of employees. Managers who adopt this style often have profiles oriented toward authority, discipline, and control. It can be effective in crisis situations, under high-pressure conditions, or when rapid decisions are required. However, over the long term, this approach can reduce employee motivation, stifle innovation, and lead to disengagement, as team members have limited opportunities to participate in decision-making (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">Bergeron, 1979</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">Ahmed &amp;amp; Simha (2023)</xref> examined the relationship between autocratic leadership and abusive behaviors in organizations. The study shows that highly centralized decision-making and lack of participative leadership can increase the risk of unethical conduct, employee dissatisfaction, and reduced organizational effectiveness.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.4.2 The democratic or participatory style</title>
              
              <p>This leadership style emphasizes consultation and the active involvement of teams in the decision-making process. Managers who adopt this approach prioritize communication, idea exchange, and collaboration, valuing the skills and perspectives of their employees. It is often associated with higher levels of employee satisfaction and engagement, stronger team cohesion, and more thoughtful decisions that are well-adapted to complex organizational contexts. This style is particularly effective among managers with profiles oriented toward empathy, sociability, and cognitive flexibility, enabling them to manage differences and build consensus effectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_79">Yukl et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">Damopolii et al. (2025)</xref> analyzed the participatory leadership style and its impact on organizational performance. The study shows that involving team members in decision-making enhances collaboration, trust, and commitment, leading to more effective outcomes. Their findings suggest that participatory approaches improve communication, foster innovation, and support better alignment between leadership decisions and organizational goals.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.4.3 The delegative style</title>
              
              <p>This leadership style is characterized by granting employees a high degree of autonomy, with minimal managerial intervention in daily operations, allowing teams to make decisions within established boundaries. It is particularly effective in environments where employees are highly skilled, motivated, and self-directed. By fostering independence, this approach encourages creativity, innovation, and the development of individual competencies. However, when teams lack experience or objectives are not clearly defined, it can result in poor coordination, errors, and a diffusion of responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">Bass &amp;amp; Riggio, 2006</xref>). Managers who adopt this style typically exhibit profiles marked by confidence, patience, and tolerance for uncertainty.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_59">Mujiono et al. (2024)</xref> examined how delegative leadership and the work environment influence employee performance through the mediation of job satisfaction. The study shows that allowing employees autonomy in decision-making, combined with a supportive work environment, enhances engagement, motivation, and overall performance. These findings indicate that leadership style and organizational conditions are key drivers of employee outcomes and effectiveness.</p>
            </sec>
          
          
            <sec>
              
                <title>5.4.4 The transformational style</title>
              
              <p>This leadership style is defined by the manager’s ability to inspire and motivate employees through the communication of a clear and ambitious vision. Managers who adopt a transformational approach focus on developing their teams’ skills, encouraging initiative, and fostering innovation. This style is linked to strong employee commitment to organizational objectives, higher engagement, and improved overall performance. Managers with visionary, charismatic, and human-development-oriented profiles are particularly suited to this style, as it requires high emotional intelligence and the ability to positively influence team behaviors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">Dussault et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">Agazu et al. (2025)</xref> reviewed the impact of transformational leadership on firm performance. Their study shows that leaders who inspire, motivate, and engage employees positively influence organizational outcomes, including innovation, productivity, and long-term growth.</p>
            </sec>
          
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>6. Managerial and decision-support implications</title>
      <p>The conceptual framework developed in this study offers several important implications for managerial practice and the design of decision-support systems. First, it emphasizes the strategic role of managerial profiles in shaping decision quality. Organizations can leverage this understanding by integrating behavioral and cognitive dimensions into leadership selection, evaluation, and development processes. Rather than focusing exclusively on technical competence or experience, decision-makers responsible for governance and human resource management may benefit from assessing how managerial sociological and psychological traits influence information interpretation, risk perception, and judgment under uncertainty.</p><p>Second, the findings suggest that governance mechanisms should be designed in alignment with managerial characteristics. Behavioral governance implies that transparency, monitoring, and control systems are not universally effective but depend on how managers perceive and respond to them. For instance, governance structures that incorporate clear information flows, accountability mechanisms, and feedback loops can help mitigate cognitive biases such as overconfidence or confirmation bias. By tailoring governance practices to managerial profiles, organizations can improve the consistency, rationality, and strategic coherence of managerial decisions.</p><p>Third, this study provides valuable contributions for the development of behavioral decision-support systems (BDSS). Traditional decision-support tools often assume fully rational users and emphasize analytical optimization. In contrast, the proposed framework accentuates the importance of designing decision-support systems that are sensitive to human cognitive limitations and behavioral tendencies. Such systems may incorporate features that enhance awareness of biases, structure complex information, and support reflective judgment rather than merely automate decision outcomes. In this sense, intelligent decision-support systems should complement managerial judgment by combining data analytics with behavioral considerations.</p><p>Fourth, the framework has implications for human-centered and AI-assisted decision-making environments. As organizations increasingly adopt data-driven and AI-enabled tools, the interaction between managerial profiles and intelligent technologies becomes critical. The study suggests that AI-based decision systems are most effective when they are integrated into governance structures that recognize the behavioral characteristics of managers. This includes ensuring transparency of algorithms, explainability of recommendations, and opportunities for managerial oversight and learning. Such alignment can enhance trust in decision-support systems and promote more informed and responsible managerial decisions.</p><p>From a broader organizational perspective, the proposed framework supports the development of sustainable and adaptive decision-making capabilities. By acknowledging the behavioral foundations of governance and decision-making, organizations can foster decision environments that are resilient to uncertainty and complexity. This approach encourages continuous learning, ethical awareness, and strategic adaptability, thereby strengthening long-term performance and organizational sustainability.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>7. Conclusion</title>
      <p>The manager’s profile is a central factor in understanding organizational dynamics and corporate governance. Sociological and professional dimensions provide insights into how a manager’s experiences, environment, and competencies shape their decision-making and leadership style. Sociological factors such as social background, religion, gender, and age influence a manager’s worldview, values, and priorities, directly affecting internal interactions, organizational culture, and the approach taken to both strategic and human challenges.</p><p>At the same time, professional aspects—including education, experience, technical skills, and managerial potential—serve as strategic levers for the organization. These attributes determine a manager’s ability to analyze information, anticipate risks, mobilize resources, and lead complex projects. The combination of professional expertise and lived experience also contributes to a manager’s legitimacy and credibility, enhancing their capacity to inspire teams and guide governance toward effective practices tailored to the organizational context.</p><p>The psychological and cultural dimensions further enrich this understanding by revealing the manager’s motivations, attitudes, personality traits, and values. These factors influence not only how situations are perceived and decisions are made but also how managers interact with employees and respond to change. Personal and organizational culture together play a critical role in setting priorities, managing conflicts, and fostering a climate of trust and collaboration.</p><p>The manager’s profile is closely linked to behavioral governance, as their traits, experiences, and values directly shape control mechanisms, transparency, and decision-making processes. By integrating sociological, professional, psychological, and cultural dimensions, behavioral governance helps explain how cognitive biases, individual preferences, and managerial attitudes influence organizational practices. Consequently, analyzing the manager’s profile is a key tool for anticipating organizational behavior, enhancing governance effectiveness, and improving overall performance by adapting control and decision-making mechanisms to the human and contextual realities of the organization.</p><p>Future research could extend this conceptual framework through empirical validation across different organizational and institutional contexts. Quantitative and qualitative studies may examine how specific managerial traits interact with governance mechanisms to influence decision quality and performance. Moreover, future work could explore the operationalization of behavioral governance principles within decision-support systems and data-driven governance tools, including AI-enabled decision technologies. Such research would contribute to a deeper understanding of how intelligent decision-making systems can be designed to complement, rather than replace, managerial judgment.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/admsci14090191</pub-id>
          <article-title>The effect of ethical leadership on innovative work behaviors: A mediating–moderating model of psychological empowerment, job crafting, proactive personality, and person–organization</article-title>
          <source>Administrative Sciences</source>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <page-range>191</page-range>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abuzaid</surname>
              <given-names>A. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghadi</surname>
              <given-names>M. Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madadha</surname>
              <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alateeq</surname>
              <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>58</volume>
          <year>2012</year>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1287/mnsc.1110.1452</pub-id>
          <source>Management Science</source>
          <page-range>219-235</page-range>
          <article-title>Beyond the glass ceiling: Does gender matter?</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adams</surname>
              <given-names>Renée B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Funk</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Transformational leadership and firm performance: A systematic literature review</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Innovation and Entrepreneurship</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13731-025-00476-x</pub-id>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2025</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agazu</surname>
              <given-names>B. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kero</surname>
              <given-names>C. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Debela</surname>
              <given-names>K. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simha</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Autocratic leadership and abuse</article-title>
          <source>Encyclopedia of Business and Professional Ethics</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <page-range>159-161</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-22767-8_1300</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>1-19</page-range>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Albaum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herche</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murphy</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Decision making dtyle influences on the valuation and use of information by managers</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10696679.1995.11501680</pub-id>
          <source>Journal of Marketing Theory and Practice</source>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1995</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <issue>4</issue>
          <source>Journal of General Management</source>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Amedu</surname>
              <given-names>Samson</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dulewicz</surname>
              <given-names>Victor</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The relationship between CEO personal power, CEO competencies, and company performance</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0306307018762699</pub-id>
          <page-range>188-198</page-range>
          <year>2018</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barney</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1991</year>
          <page-range>99-120</page-range>
          <article-title>Firm resources and sustained competitive advantage</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/01492063910170010</pub-id>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <source>J. Manag.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bass</surname>
              <given-names>Bernard M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riggio</surname>
              <given-names>Ronald E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Transformational Leadership</source>
          <publisher-name>Psychology Press</publisher-name>
          <year>2006</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bazerman</surname>
              <given-names>M. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Judgment in Managerial Decision Making</source>
          <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
          <year>2012</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>1979</year>
          <source>Relations industrielles</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bergeron</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <article-title>Les dimensions conceptuelles du leadership et les styles qui en découlent</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7202/028935ar</pub-id>
          <page-range>22-40</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>535-550</page-range>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10551-010-0695-7</pub-id>
          <source>Journal of Business Ethics</source>
          <article-title>Behavioral governance and self-conscious emotions: Unveiling governance implications of authentic and hubristic pride.</article-title>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bodolica</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spraggon</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Agency theory and bounded self-interest.</article-title>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5465/amr.2013.0420</pub-id>
          <year>2016</year>
          <page-range>276-297</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bosse</surname>
              <given-names>Douglas A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phillips</surname>
              <given-names>Robert A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Academy of Management Review</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bournois</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roussillon</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Préparer Les Dirigeants De Demain: Une Approche Internationale De La Gestion Des Cadres À Haut Potentiel</source>
          <publisher-name>Editions d’Organisation</publisher-name>
          <year>1998</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <issue>1</issue>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boyatzis</surname>
              <given-names>Richard E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goleman</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhar</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Osiri</surname>
              <given-names>J. Kalu</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>27</page-range>
          <article-title>Thrive and survive: Assessing personal sustainability.</article-title>
          <source>Consult. Psychol. J</source>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/cpb0000193</pub-id>
          <year>2021</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Busenitz</surname>
              <given-names>Lowell W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barney</surname>
              <given-names>Jay B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Journal of Business Venturing</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>9-30</page-range>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0883-9026(96)00003-1</pub-id>
          <article-title>Differences between entrepreneurs and managers in large organizations: Biases and heuristics in strategic decision-making</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Upper echelons research revisited: Antecedents, elements, and consequences of top management team composition.</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carpenter</surname>
              <given-names>Mason A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geletkanycz</surname>
              <given-names>Marta A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanders</surname>
              <given-names>Wm. Gerard</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>749-778</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jm.2004.06.001</pub-id>
          <source>Journal of Management</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2007</year>
          <page-range>211-215</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Charreaux</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wirtz</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <article-title>Discipline ou compétence? L’apport des perspectives cognitives et comportementales à la compréhension des mécanismes de gouvernance d’entreprise</article-title>
          <source>Revue française de gouvernance d’entreprise</source>
          <issue>1</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Women, men and management styles</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Claes</surname>
              <given-names>M. T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <page-range>431-446</page-range>
          <year>1999</year>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <source>International Labour Review</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1564-913x.1999.tb00396.x</pub-id>
          <volume>138</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Damopolii</surname>
              <given-names>I. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ibrahim</surname>
              <given-names>A. I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adam</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamid</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maku</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lo’o</surname>
              <given-names>M. J. D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>IJHESS</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56338/ijhess.v7i4.8228</pub-id>
          <article-title>Literature review: Analysis of participatory leadership style.</article-title>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <year>2025</year>
          <page-range>2098-2107</page-range>
          <issue>7</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.leaqua.2003.09.002</pub-id>
          <article-title>Research on leadership in a cross-cultural context: Making progress, and raising new questions</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dickson</surname>
              <given-names>Marcus W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Den Hartog</surname>
              <given-names>Deanne N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitchelson</surname>
              <given-names>Jacqueline K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <source>The Leadership Quarterly</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>729-768</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Leadership transformationnel et citoyenneté organisationnelle au sein d’une équipe</article-title>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dussault</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deschênes</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Émeriau-Farges</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1522/radm.no3.1108</pub-id>
          <source>Ad machina: l'avenir de l'humain au travail</source>
          <page-range>99-107</page-range>
          <year>2019</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eagly</surname>
              <given-names>A. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carli</surname>
              <given-names>L. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Through the Labyrinth: The Truth About How Women Become Leaders</source>
          <publisher-name>Boston, MA: Harvard Business School Press</publisher-name>
          <year>2007</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/467037</pub-id>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <source>The Journal of Law and Economics</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fama</surname>
              <given-names>Eugene F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>Michael C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Separation of ownership and control.</article-title>
          <year>1983</year>
          <page-range>301-325</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Finkelstein</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hambrick</surname>
              <given-names>D. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Strategic Leadership: Top Executives and Their Effects on Organizations.</source>
          <publisher-name>West Publishing Co.</publisher-name>
          <year>1996</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Finkelstein</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hambrick</surname>
              <given-names>D. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cannella</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Strategic Leadership: Theory and Research on Executives, Top Management Teams</source>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
          <year>2009</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fourot</surname>
              <given-names>Loïc</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Revue internationale de psychosociologie et de gestion des comportements organisationnels</source>
          <page-range>39-59</page-range>
          <volume>Vol. XXX</volume>
          <issue>81</issue>
          <article-title>Habitus de classe dans le comité de direction, le fonctionnement de l’élite dirigeante à l’épreuve des origines sociales</article-title>
          <year>2024</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3917/rips1.081.0039</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>76-95</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ghorbani</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J. Rehabil. Civ. Eng.</source>
          <article-title>A review of successful construction project managers’ competencies and leadership profile.</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <issue>4</issue>
          <article-title>Les théories du pouvoir.</article-title>
          <source>du Trav.</source>
          <page-range>447-467</page-range>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goetschy</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goleman</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Working With Emotional Intelligence</source>
          <publisher-name>NY: Bantam Books</publisher-name>
          <year>1998</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gottesman</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morey</surname>
              <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CEO educational background and firm financial performance.</article-title>
          <source>J. Appl. Finance.</source>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Group Organ. Manag.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <page-range>535-566</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Groves</surname>
              <given-names>Kevin S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feyerherm</surname>
              <given-names>Ann E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Leader cultural intelligence in context: Testing the moderating effects of team cultural diversity on leader and team performance.</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1059601111415664</pub-id>
          <volume>36</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Upper echelons: The organization as a reflection of its top managers.</article-title>
          <page-range>193</page-range>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <year>1984</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hambrick</surname>
              <given-names>Donald C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mason</surname>
              <given-names>Phyllis A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/258434</pub-id>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <source>Acad. Manag. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <issue>1</issue>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hamori</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koyuncu</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hrm.21617</pub-id>
          <article-title>Experience matters? The impact of prior CEO experience on firm performance.</article-title>
          <source>Hum. Resour. Manag.</source>
          <page-range>23-44</page-range>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <year>2015</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>How much does the CEO’s age impact corporate performance under a changing environment?</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jo</surname>
              <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2024</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/admsci14110304</pub-id>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <source>Adm. Sci.</source>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>304</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-orgpsych-110721-034105</pub-id>
          <year>2024</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>165-192</page-range>
          <source>Annual Review of Organizational Psychology and Organizational Behavior</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heilman</surname>
              <given-names>Madeline E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caleo</surname>
              <given-names>Suzette</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manzi</surname>
              <given-names>Francesca</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Women at Work: Pathways from Gender Stereotypes to Gender Bias and Discrimination</article-title>
          <issue>1</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>755-778</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Herrmann</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Datta</surname>
              <given-names>Deepak K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <article-title>CEO experiences: Effects on the choice of FDI entry mode.</article-title>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <source>J. Manag. Stud.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-6486.2006.00610.x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hofstede</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relativité culturelle des pratiques et théories de l’organisation.</article-title>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <source>Rev. Fr. Gest.</source>
          <page-range>10-21</page-range>
          <year>1987</year>
          <issue>4</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hofstede</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <source>Int. J. Cross Cult. Manag.</source>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <article-title>Culture's recent consequences: Using dimension scores in theory and research.</article-title>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>11-17</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/147059580111002</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>House</surname>
              <given-names>R. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanges</surname>
              <given-names>P. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Javidan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dorfman</surname>
              <given-names>P. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Culture, Leadership, and Organizations: The Globe Study of 62 Societies</source>
          <publisher-name>Sage publications</publisher-name>
          <year>2004</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2002</year>
          <page-range>83-98</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jalbert</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rao</surname>
              <given-names>R. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jalbert</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <article-title>Does school matter? An empirical analysis of CEO education, compensation, and firm performance</article-title>
          <source>Int. Bus. Econ. Res. J.</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>60</volume>
          <page-range>1178-1204</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joms.12918</pub-id>
          <year>2023</year>
          <source>J. Manag. Stud.</source>
          <article-title>The role of organizational structure in senior managers' selective information processing.</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Junge</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luger</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mammen</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>5</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Junghans</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Les dirigeants face à l’information : Traitement, appropriation, décision.</source>
          <publisher-name>De Boeck Supérieur.</publisher-name>
          <year>2017</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kahneman</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Fast And Slow Thinking</source>
          <publisher-name>Allen Lane and Penguin Books, New York.</publisher-name>
          <year>2011</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>39</volume>
          <article-title>Choices, values, and frames.</article-title>
          <source>American Psychologist</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0003-066x.39.4.341</pub-id>
          <page-range>341-350</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kahneman</surname>
              <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tversky</surname>
              <given-names>Amos</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>1984</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kahneman</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tversky</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prospect theory: An analysis of decision under risk.</article-title>
          <source>Handbook of the fundamentals of financial decision making: Part I</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <page-range>99-127</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/9789814417358_0006</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kargarkamvar</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khanmohammadi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yazdani</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moradi</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <article-title>Investigating the effect of religious orientation on decision making approach of financial managers.</article-title>
          <year>2023</year>
          <page-range>117-131</page-range>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <source>Int. J. Financ. Manag. Account.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Cultural psychology: Beyond east and west.</article-title>
          <source>Annu. Rev. Psychol.</source>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-psych-021723-063333</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kitayama</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salvador</surname>
              <given-names>Cristina E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <year>2024</year>
          <page-range>495-526</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/smj.459</pub-id>
          <source>Strategic Management Journal</source>
          <page-range>489-496</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kor</surname>
              <given-names>Yasemin Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahoney</surname>
              <given-names>Joseph T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>How dynamics, management, and governance of resource deployments influence firm‐level performance</article-title>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <year>2005</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Corporate Governance: An International Review</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phan</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <page-range>204-214</page-range>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Competencies of Directors in Global Firms: Requirements for recruitment and evaluation</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-8683.00199</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>49</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <source>Inf.  Manag.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <article-title>How managers interpret scanning information</article-title>
          <page-range>126-134</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.im.2012.01.004</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lesca</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caron-Fasan</surname>
              <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falcy</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <issue>6</issue>
          <article-title>Resource based view (RBV) in improving company strategic capacity</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.54518/rh.2.6.2022.587-596</pub-id>
          <source>Research Horizon</source>
          <page-range>587-596</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lubis</surname>
              <given-names>N. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <year>2022</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Malmendier</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tate</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <source>J. Finance</source>
          <article-title>CEO overconfidence and corporate investment.</article-title>
          <page-range>2661-2700</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1540-6261.2005.00813.x</pub-id>
          <issue>6</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>March</surname>
              <given-names>J. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simon</surname>
              <given-names>H. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Organizations.</source>
          <publisher-name>John wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
          <year>1993</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Martinez</surname>
              <given-names>Martha A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A sociological view of managerial behavior.</article-title>
          <source>The Employable Sociologist: A Guide for Undergraduates</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <page-range>155-168</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-41323-0_10</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McHugh</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duane</surname>
              <given-names>J. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Upper echelons theory: Research at the nexus of CEO psychological profiles, gender, and firm diversity</article-title>
          <source>J. Manag. Organ.</source>
          <year>2025</year>
          <page-range>714-735</page-range>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/jmo.2025.10041</pub-id>
          <issue>3</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_56">
        <label>56.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>1976</year>
          <source>J. Financ. Econ.</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Meckling</surname>
              <given-names>W. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>M. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Theory of the Firm. Managerial behavior, agency costs and ownership structure</article-title>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-405X(76)90026-X</pub-id>
          <page-range>305-360</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_57">
        <label>57.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Calif. Manage. Rev.</source>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <article-title>Strategy-making in three modes.</article-title>
          <page-range>44-53</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/41164</pub-id>
          <year>1973</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mintzberg</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_58">
        <label>58.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conference-proceedings">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21125/edulearn.2023.1295</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mitan</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>, http://dx.doi.org/10.21125/edulearn.2023.1295</source>
          <article-title>An approach to improve the manager's skills in the decision-making process</article-title>
          <year>2023</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_59">
        <label>59.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Int. J. Manag. Econ. Invent.</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.47191/ijmei/v10i9.06</pub-id>
          <year>2024</year>
          <page-range>3551–3562</page-range>
          <article-title>Mediation of job satisfaction: The role of delegative leadership style and work environment in improving employee performance</article-title>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mujiono</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nursaid</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanosra</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qomariah</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>9</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_60">
        <label>60.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>Acad. Manage. J.</source>
          <page-range>1050-1073</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5465/amj.2010.54533196</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nadkarni</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herrmann</surname>
              <given-names>P. O. L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>CEO personality, strategic flexibility, and firm performance: The case of the Indian business process outsourcing industry.</article-title>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_61">
        <label>61.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>1448-1461</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mde.3466</pub-id>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <source>Managerial and Decision Economics</source>
          <article-title>Corporate governance, working capital management, and firm performance: Some new insights from agency theory</article-title>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Naz</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rehman</surname>
              <given-names>R. U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ntim</surname>
              <given-names>Collins G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_62">
        <label>62.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>P. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2014</year>
          <page-range>431-458</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jopart/mut025</pub-id>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <article-title>Performance management, managerial authority, and public service performance.</article-title>
          <source>J. Public Adm. Res. Theory</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_63">
        <label>63.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <page-range>310-332</page-range>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/par-02-2021-0026</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peng</surname>
              <given-names>C. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiu</surname>
              <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The impact of international work experience, functional background and career concerns on CEO investment decisions</article-title>
          <source>Pacific Accounting Review</source>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_64">
        <label>64.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peni</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CEO and chairperson characteristics and firm performance</article-title>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10997-012-9224-7</pub-id>
          <year>2014</year>
          <source>J. Manag. Gov</source>
          <page-range>185-205</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_65">
        <label>65.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peterson</surname>
              <given-names>Suzanne J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galvin</surname>
              <given-names>Benjamin M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lange</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-6570.2012.01253.x</pub-id>
          <source>Pers. Psychol.</source>
          <page-range>565-596</page-range>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <article-title>CEO servant leadership: Exploring executive characteristics and firm performance.</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_66">
        <label>66.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Piscopo</surname>
              <given-names>Jennifer M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>951-959</page-range>
          <source>Polit. Gend.</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s1743923x20000525</pub-id>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <year>2020</year>
          <article-title>Women leaders and pandemic performance: A spurious correlation.</article-title>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_67">
        <label>67.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08874417.2022.2111380</pub-id>
          <year>2023</year>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <page-range>890-903</page-range>
          <source>J. Comput. Inf. Syst.</source>
          <article-title>Bounded rationality: Managerial decision-making and data.</article-title>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pittenger</surname>
              <given-names>Linda M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glassman</surname>
              <given-names>Aaron M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mumbower</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Merritt</surname>
              <given-names>Daisha M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bollenback</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_68">
        <label>68.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quinn</surname>
              <given-names>J. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Finkelstein</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Managing professional intellect: Making the most of the best.</article-title>
          <source>The strategic Management of Intellectual Capital</source>
          <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>
          <year>2009</year>
          <page-range>87-98</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-7506-9850-4.50009-9</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_69">
        <label>69.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>What do we really understand about how managers make important decisions?</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.orgdyn.2014.11.002</pub-id>
          <page-range>9-16</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sadler-Smith</surname>
              <given-names>Eugene</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burke-Smalley</surname>
              <given-names>Lisa A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <source>Organizational Dynamics</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_70">
        <label>70.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shailer</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Agency theory</article-title>
          <source>Encyclopedia of Business and Professional Ethics</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>
          <year>2023</year>
          <page-range>62-65</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-22767-8_151</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_71">
        <label>71.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>1997</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shleifer</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vishny</surname>
              <given-names>R. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <article-title>A survey of corporate governance.</article-title>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1540-6261.1997.tb04820.x</pub-id>
          <source>J. Finance</source>
          <page-range>737-783</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_72">
        <label>72.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shogren</surname>
              <given-names>Karrie A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raley</surname>
              <given-names>Sheida K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Self-Determination and Causal Agency Theory</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>
          <year>2022</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_73">
        <label>73.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Simon</surname>
              <given-names>Herbert A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>From substantive to procedural rationality</article-title>
          <source>25 Years of Economic Theory</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name>
          <year>1976</year>
          <page-range>65-86</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4613-4367-7_6</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_74">
        <label>74.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tribou</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>L'entrepreneur musulman: L'islam et la rationalité d'entreprise.</source>
          <publisher-name>L'Harmattan.</publisher-name>
          <year>1995</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_75">
        <label>75.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-8683.2009.00741.x</pub-id>
          <year>2009</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van Ees</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gabrielsson</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huse</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Corp. Gov. Int. Rev.</source>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <article-title>Toward a behavioral theory of boards and corporate governance.</article-title>
          <page-range>307-319</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_76">
        <label>76.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>J. Corp. Finance</source>
          <article-title>CEO educational background and acquisition targets selection</article-title>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcorpfin.2018.08.013</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yin</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2018</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <page-range>238-259</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_77">
        <label>77.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <source>J. Doc.</source>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <page-range>249-270</page-range>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>T.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Models in information behaviour research</article-title>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/eum0000000007145</pub-id>
          <year>1999</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_78">
        <label>78.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <year>2025</year>
          <article-title>CEO education and firm performance in Nigeria</article-title>
          <source>SSRN. 5230813</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.5230813</pub-id>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yahaya</surname>
              <given-names>O. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_79">
        <label>79.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yukl</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahsud</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hassan</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prussia</surname>
              <given-names>G. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <page-range>38-48</page-range>
          <article-title>An improved measure of ethical leadership</article-title>
          <source>J. Leadersh. Organ. Stud.</source>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1548051811429352</pub-id>
          <year>2013</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>