<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JGELCD</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.56578</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Green Economy and Low-Carbon Development</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="issn">J. Green Econ. Low-Carbon Dev.</abbrev-journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">JGELCD</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn publication-format="electronic">2957-9619</issn>
      <issn publication-format="print">2957-9600</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Acadlore</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AR-ELGkdctFDTEOLPaG-yysbI8Vi1xwS7Aw</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56578/jgelcd040203</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Factors Influencing Green Growth Practices and Avocado Yields: Insights from the Southern Agricultural Growth Corridor in Rungwe</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-9136-1342</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Kasongo</surname>
            <given-names>Diana Clemens</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>dianaclemens963@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_1">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4798-824X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Abdallah</surname>
            <given-names>Jumanne M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>abdallah@sua.ac.tz</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff_2">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0068-1152</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mutabazi</surname>
            <given-names>Khamaldin</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>kmutabazi@sua.ac.tz</email>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff_1">Department of Forest and Environmental Economics, Sokoine University of Agriculture, P.O. Box 3011 Morogoro, Tanzania</aff>
        <aff id="aff_2">Department of Trade and Investment (DTI), College of Economics and Business Studies (CoEBS), Sokoine University of Agriculture, P.O. Box 3007 Morogoro, Tanzania</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2025</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>91</fpage>
      <lpage>101</lpage>
      <page-range>91-101</page-range>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>04</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2025</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>©2025 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> Published by Acadlore Publishing Services Limited, Hong Kong. This article is available for free download and can be reused and cited, provided that the original published version is credited, under the CC BY 4.0 license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract><p>Green growth practices in avocado farming involve balancing economic productivity, environmental sustainability, and social inclusiveness. These practices could boost resource efficiency, conserve biodiversity, and minimize environmental degradation. While global demand for avocados is increasing, there is little understanding of the factors influencing farmers’ willingness to adopt green growth practices and the factors affecting avocado yields amid market pressures as well as insufficient information and inadequate resources. Therefore, this study investigated the current practices used by farmers and the factors influencing the adoption of green growth practices and avocado yields in the Southern Agricultural Growth Corridor of Tanzania (SAGCOT) region, specifically in Rungwe District. A cross-sectional research design and multistage sampling helped select targeted avocado farmers, from whom data was collected via questionnaires and surveys. Results of descriptive statistics showed that 82% of the interviewed farmers were male and 67% of them had primary education. Farmers identified mulching and the use of organic fertilizer as primary green growth practices. Regression analysis performed by SPSS version 27 was the main analytical method. Binary logistic regression indicated that larger avocado farm size, access to information, and perception of larger avocado demand significantly influenced the adoption of green growth practices; meanwhile, gender showed a marginally significant effect. Multiple linear regression further revealed that tree age significantly impacted avocado yields whereas chemical fertilizer decreased yields. The findings emphasized the importance of targeted interventions to improve knowledge dissemination and training of sustainable agricultural practices to enhance productivity in avocado farming.</p></abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Factors</kwd>
        <kwd>Green growth practices</kwd>
        <kwd>Avocados</kwd>
        <kwd>SAGCOT</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <count count-type="contributors" count="3"/>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="5"/>
        <ref-count count="35"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Green growth is increasingly endorsed by governments and development agencies worldwide as an all-encompassing strategy to combat critically environmental challenges, including climate change, biodiversity degradation, and overexploitation of natural resources, while fostering equitable socio-economic environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_1">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_2">2</xref>]. Green growth represents a development paradigm that seeks to harmonize economic advancement with inclusive social progress, while actively mitigating ecological degradation and pressure on the system of natural resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_3">3</xref>]. This integrated approach constitutes the agenda of global sustainable development, thus shaping policy directions and directing investments toward cleaner technologies and more sustainable production systems. Agriculture is central to these efforts, especially in developing countries where the majority of livelihoods depend directly on the natural resource base [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_4">4</xref>].</p><p>Green growth in agricultural systems seeks to enhance productivity, while preserving vital environmental functions such as maintaining soil fertility, conserving water, and protecting biodiversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_6">6</xref>]. In this context, the cultivation of perennial crops like avocados could potentially fulfill both economic and environmental goals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>]. Avocado farming in the Southern Agricultural Growth Corridor of Tanzania (SAGCOT), particularly in Rungwe District, is an emerging sustainable practice that strengthens soil structure, promotes the health of the ecosystem, and contributes to household income [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_8">8</xref>].</p><p>Amid rising constraints of natural resource and environmental degradation, Tanzania has adopted green growth as a key strategy to transform its agricultural sector toward sustainability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_9">9</xref>]. This strategic shift aligns with the country’s broader commitment to sustainable development and is especially important for regions that are heavily dependent on agriculture and are now vulnerable to climate change, land degradation, and biodiversity loss. The SAGCOT initiative, established under the Kilimo Kwanza (Agriculture First) policy, demonstrates this commitment by promoting agricultural productivity, boosting food security and rural incomes, and safeguarding natural ecosystems through climate-resilient and environmentally friendly farming practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>].</p><p>One of the producing areas in the SAGCOT region is Rungwe District [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_10">10</xref>], where avocado has evolved into a high-value commercial crop, contributing significantly to household livelihoods and national export revenues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_11">11</xref>]. According to the current data from the Tanzania Horticultural Association (TAHA), exports of avocados climbed from 15,432 tonnes to 26,826 tonnes, indicating a 74% rise between 2021 and 2023 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_12">12</xref>]. Although there is advancement in avocado farming in the region, farmers still encounter significant sustainability challenges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_13">13</xref>]. For instance, environmental issues such as soil erosion, declining soil fertility, and inadequate access to green technologies, along with economic uncertainties like market volatility, continue to limit the long-term productivity and resilience of the sector.</p><p>National programs and policies promote green growth practices, including organic composting, agroforestry, water harvesting, and conservation tillage. Previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_7">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_14">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_15">15</xref>] addressed higher-order issues related to agricultural sustainability in avocados, while adoption among smallholder farmers remained relatively low. Although there is an accelerating global demand for avocados and sustainable farming of this crop could provide significant economic benefits, little is known about the specific factors influencing the willingness of farmers to adopt green growth practices and the factors affecting avocado yields. To address these research gaps, this study aims to enrich the understanding of these crucial factors by answering the following questions: i) What green growth practices are currently adopted by avocado farmers? ii) What factors influence the adoption of these practices by avocado farmers? and iii) What are the key factors impacting avocado yields?</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="">
      <title>2. Methodology</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.1. Study area</title>
          
          <p>The study was conducted in Rungwe District, part of Tanzania's Southern Agricultural Corridor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_1">Figure 1</xref>). Rungwe is located in the Mbeya Region and covers 1,441 square kilometers. Situated in the Southern Highlands of Tanzania at $9^\circ 15^\prime<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mp7o4xyl0g">
    <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>33^\circ 40^\prime$E, this area is known for its moderate climate, with temperatures ranging from 15°C to 30°C. Its tropical, sub-humid environment receives about 1,200 mm of rainfall annually, making the fertile soils ideal for growing avocados.</p><p>Avocado, an emerging horticultural trade commodity among the several crops produced in Rungwe, demands well-drained soil as well as full and uninterrupted sunlight. The hilly terrain in the district could provide a suitable condition to cultivate avocados.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_1">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Map of the study area in Rungwe District</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_DWfiLXRQE2KAmiIV.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.2. Sampling design and determination of sample size</title>
          
          <p>A cross-sectional research design was employed to collect data at a single point in time in the field because it offers a snapshot of the current situation and is relatively efficient and cost-effective. The study population was selected by the multistage sampling technique. In both the first and second stages, purposive sampling was adopted; it helped select the study area, Rungwe District, which has a high concentration of avocado growers. Based on the concentration of these farmers and the accessibility of the locations, a total of four villages, namely Iponjora, Ilalabwe, Kyimo, and Kiwira, were chosen in the second stage. The final sample of active avocado farmers was randomly selected in the third stage to identify respondents, who constitute the sample size of 120 avocado farmers. Among them, 30 participants were interviewed in each of the four villages. According to Bailey [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_16">16</xref>], regardless of the population size, a sample of 30 respondents is the minimum requirement to be met for a study involving statistical analysis. </p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.3. Methods of data collection</title>
          
          <p>The study applied a mixed-method approach, combining both qualitative and quantitative methods to provide a thorough understanding of the current practices of avocado farmers, related sources of information, as well as factors influencing their willingness and avocado yields.</p><p>A structured questionnaire comprising open-ended and closed-ended questions was administered to the respondents. Quantitative data was retrieved by using pre-set questions on variables like demographic characteristics, current agricultural practices and factors affecting the adoption of green growth practices for direct statistical analysis. Meanwhile, open-ended questions allowed respondents to articulate their thoughts and experiences in their own words, yielding qualitative insights into the context and motivations behind their farming practices. This mixed-method approach allowed detailed investigation of factors affecting avocado farming, thus offering data about the statistical trends and individual opinions.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>2.4. Data analysis</title>
          
          <p>The collected data was analysed using Statistical Product and Service Solutions (SPSS) version 27 to assess the current green growth practices of avocado farmers. Binary logistic regression was used to determine factors influencing the willingness of farmers to adopt green growth practices whereas a multiple linear regression model was adopted to determine factors influencing the avocado yields.</p><p><italic>For question 1: What are the green growth practices currently implemented by avocado farmers?</italic></p><p>Descriptive analysis, including frequencies and percentages, was conducted to identify the specific green growth practices of avocado farmers. The variables included organic fertilizer, mulching, pruning, and agroforestry integration.</p><p><italic>For question 2: What are the key factors influencing the adoption of green growth practices by avocado farmers?</italic></p><p>A binary logistic regression model was employed to identify factors influencing the willingness of farmers to adopt green growth practices. The dependent variable for this study was whether the farmers were willing to adopt green growth practices, with a value of 1 assigned to indicate when a farmer was willing to adopt green growth practices and 0 assigned to indicate if the farmer was not willing to adopt green growth practices. The equation of the logistic regression model is given as follows:</p><p style="text-align: center"><inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mkmxcqig0q">
    <mml:mi>log</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>ln</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
      <mml:mfrac>
        <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
        <mml:mrow>
          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
          <mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
        </mml:mrow>
      </mml:mfrac>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
    <mml:msub>
      <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    </mml:msub>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula></p><p>where,</p><p>$P<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="ma4gwu3aer">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>B_0<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m48vzn1rxf">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>\beta_1, \beta_2, \beta_3 \ldots \ldots, \beta_{\mathrm{k}}<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mzy611ukx9">
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>X_1, X_2, X_3 \ldots \ldots, X_k<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mgutkbpjc2">
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>?</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>:&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>"</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
      <mml:mo>′</mml:mo>
    </mml:msup>
    <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>Y_i=\alpha+\beta_1 x_1+\beta_2 x_2+\beta_3 x_3+\cdots \beta_{10} x_{10}+\varepsilon<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mv4msizzkx">
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>Y_l<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m0iwdk32lv">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>\alpha<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mfa14qhmq6">
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>\beta_1, \beta_2, \ldots, \beta_{\mathrm{k}}<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7ayinaiau">
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>X_1, X_2, X_3 \ldots, X_{10}<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m283lqwsf5">
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>\mathcal{E}$ is the error term for the difference between observed and predicted values.</p><p>Independent variables were demographic factors, farm size, number of trees planted, age of trees, soil management techniques, use of fertilizer, participation in any farmer associations/groups, and access to information (This represents farmers’ access to agricultural knowledge and guidance acquired through avenues, such as extension services, radio broadcasts, television, conversations of farmer groups, mobile phones, and non-governmental organizations).</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>3. Results</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.1. Demographic characteristics of respondents</title>
          
          <p>The results of the 120 avocado farmers interviewed showed that 82% ($n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="me7d7ck9yb">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>99</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>17</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mb5q91qm3p">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>21</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>1.</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>18</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>47</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n$ = 57) falling into the age range of 41-55, and 23% falling into the age range of 56-65.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_1">
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Information on the number of avocado farmers interviewed in each village</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Villages</p></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>No. of Farmers</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Male</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Female</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kiwira</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>24</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Kyimo</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>26</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ilalabwe</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>25</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Iponjora</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>24</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>99</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>21</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          
            <table-wrap id="table_2">
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Demographic characteristics of avocado farmers</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>Variables</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Frequency (<italic>n </italic>= 120)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Percentage (%)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Gender</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Male</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>99</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>82.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Female</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>21</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>17.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="4"><p>Education level</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Non formal</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Primary</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>81</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>67.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Secondary</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>19</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15.8</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tertiary</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="7"><p>Marital status</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Never married</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Monogamous</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>81</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>67.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Polygamous</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11.7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cohabited</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Separated</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Divorced</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Widower</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.8</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="3"><p>Occupation</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Government employment</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>16</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13.3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Self-employment (farming)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>100</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>83.3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Retirement income</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="5"><p>Age (Years)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18-25</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>26-40</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>24</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>20</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>41-55</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>57</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>47.5</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>56-65</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>28</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>23.3</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Above 65</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7.5</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>According to the findings, the majority of farmers ($n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mgn6kbal87">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>81</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>10</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mmmwbvod2e">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>12</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>15</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mzqn1jstmf">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>19</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>7</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m02uo1iubg">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>8</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mi67wshfi0">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>83</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mmmsynd135">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>16</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>3.3</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mps88xpp31">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mttj3k9iww">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>?</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;gt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>95</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>1.</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>2.</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>40.8</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mibh9k0fbg">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>49</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>25</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mvnvhxido2">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>30</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>18.3</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mj509ix4go">
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>22</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>15.8</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>n$ = 19) cited using pruning on trees.</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_2">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Green growth practices used by avocado farmers</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_SQ9413NR9v1qe7vQ.png"/>
            </fig>
          
          <p>In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_3">Table 3</xref>, avocado farmers reported using soil management techniques to achieve green growth practices. 36.7% of the respondents ($n$ = 44) reported using organic fertilizers, 31.7% mentioned maintaining the right amount of moisture in their soil, 11.7% reported practising mixed cropping, another 11.7% practised soil testing, and only 8.3% practised weeding.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_3">
              <label>Table 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Soil management techniques used by avocado farmers</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Soil Management Techniques</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Frequency</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Percentage (%)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Adding organic matter</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>44</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>36.7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mulching</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>38</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>31.7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Mixed cropping</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11.7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Soil testing</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11.7</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Weeding</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8.3</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.2. Factors influencing the willingness of avocado farmers to adopt green growth practices</title>
          
          <p>A binary logistic regression model was performed to determine factors influencing the willingness of avocado farmers to adopt green growth practices. The model contained seven independent variables, i.e., gender, education, farmers’ perception of the demand for avocados, farm size, access to training, membership in any farmer associations, and occupation. The dependent variable was the number of farmers adopting green growth practices.</p><p>The full model containing all predictors was statistically significant <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m7i07jpdre">
    <mml:msup>
      <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
    </mml:msup>
    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>7</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>120</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>39.899</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>.000</mml:mn>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. The findings indicated that gender had a marginally significant effect (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mudscariz0">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.096</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>) on willingness to adopt green growth practices, while the negative coefficient indicated that being male decreased the likelihood of adopting green growth practices by 87% (1-0.133). Although the coefficient for avocado farm size was positive (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m2pc1viyv2">
    <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>1.775</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>), suggesting a potentially positive influence on the above adoption, the effect was not statistically significant (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mp4xx2p5xu">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.407</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>). Therefore, farm size could not be considered a reliable predictor of adopting the practices in this model. Compared to access to information and knowledge, the results showed that receiving information and knowledge about green growth practices significantly increased the likelihood of such adoption (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m93ryanti5">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.001</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>). Farmers who received information and training were 25 times more likely to adopt green growth practices than those who did not. Meanwhile, being a member of a cooperative society did not significantly influence the adoption of green growth practices (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mg9d2jk3nf">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.307</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>). However, membership tended to raise the likelihood of adoption (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m3662b95pg">
    <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>4.413</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>). The results of regression analysis showed that the variable, access to training, was slightly statistically significant at <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mu9mjvkn17">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.089</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and positively related to the dependent variable (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mb59nuut17">
    <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>2.932</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>), in terms of the demand for avocados significantly influencing (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mvjuut3ql4">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.023</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>) the adoption of green growth practices. Farmers perceived that a low demand for avocados were significantly less likely for them to adopt green growth practices (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="meuqlljdka">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.012</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>.123</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>). Furthermore, other variables indicated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref> were positively associated with the dependent variable but with lower significance.</p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_4">
              <label>Table 4</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Factors influencing the willingness to adopt green growth practices</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Variables (Assigned Value)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>S. E.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wald</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Sig.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Exp (B)</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Gender (1)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.212</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.774</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.096</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.133</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Occupation</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.940</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.230</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Occupation (1)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.300</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.877</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.090</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.110</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Occupation (2)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.208</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.699</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.192</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.056</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.616</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.656</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Education (1)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.017</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.019</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.891</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.870</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Education (2)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.362</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.096</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.757</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.656</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Education (3)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.168</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.362</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.243</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.080</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Avocado farm size</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.160</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.340</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Avocado farm size (1)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.819</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.687</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.407</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.972</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Avocado farm size (2)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.208</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.159</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.142</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.899</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Did you get any information and knowledge about green growth (1)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.881</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13.435</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>25.243</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Have you received training concerning sustainable avocado farming (1)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.713</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.928</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.087</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18.764</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Are you part of any farmer cooperatives or association societies (1)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.454</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.042</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.307</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.413</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Demand of avocados</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7.569</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.023</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Demand of avocados (1)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.053</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.297</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.586</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.564</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Demand of avocados (2)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.838</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.250</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.012</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.123</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Constant</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.937</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.787</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.375</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.179</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>3.3. Factors affecting avocado yields</title>
          
          <p>Multiple linear regression was used to identify factors affecting the avocado yields. The result demonstrated that some variables had a significant influence on the avocado yields, while others had a marginal or no impact. </p>
          
            <table-wrap id="table_5">
              <label>Table 5</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Factors affecting the avocado yields</title>
              </caption>
              <table><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p> </p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p><italic>B</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Std. Error</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p><italic>t</italic></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="2"><p>Sig.</p></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><p>95.0% Confidence Interval for <italic>B</italic></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lower Bound</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Upper Bound</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>(Constant)</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>37.924</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12.264</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.092</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.003</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13.601</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>62.247</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Age</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.527</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.308</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.403</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.688</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.121</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.066</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Occupation</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.862</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.084</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.894</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.374</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-5.995</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.270</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Education</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.640</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.546</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.414</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.680</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.706</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.427</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Marital status</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.523</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.700</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.747</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.457</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.865</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.911</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Avocado farm size</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.065</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.826</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.085</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.281</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-2.539</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8.668</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Trees planted</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.014</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.020</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.687</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.493</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.026</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.053</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Age of trees</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>26.258</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.648</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15.938</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.000</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22.991</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>29.526</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Soil management techniques</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.654</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.734</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.892</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.375</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-2.110</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.801</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Chemical fertilizer</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-4.340</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.123</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-2.045</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.043</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-8.551</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.130</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Herbicides</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-2.264</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.511</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-.902</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.369</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-7.245</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.716</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Pesticides</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.593</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.248</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.598</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.113</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-8.051</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.865</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Fungicides</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-3.208</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.367</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.355</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.178</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-7.902</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.487</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Irrigation system</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-2.115</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.376</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.537</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.127</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-4.843</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.614</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Did you get any information and knowledge about green growth</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-5.480</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.111</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-1.762</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.081</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-11.650</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.689</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Are you part of any farmer cooperatives or association societies</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.222</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.637</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.463</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>.644</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>-4.008</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.452</p></td></tr></tbody></table>
            </table-wrap>
          
          <p>The findings in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_5">Table 5</xref> revealed that the age of trees was a highly significant predictor of avocado yields, with a coefficient of <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mv3t8tn9yd">
    <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> 26.258 (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mfm3inl2tu">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>&amp;lt;</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.001</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>); the age of the avocado trees greatly increased production. Meanwhile, the application of chemical fertilizers decreased yields with <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m3dbyhfix2">
    <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>4.340</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, at <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mn4acjtirr">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.043</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, reflecting overreliance on or improper use of chemical fertilizers which would reduce avocado yields. Emphasizing the effects of applying chemical fertilizers, one of the avocado farmers said, “<italic>There was a time when I relied on chemical fertilizers, expecting higher yields, but the results were disappointing. After attending training sessions on improving yields through the use of organic fertilizers, I applied the knowledge I gained, and my yield performance improved significantly</italic>”.</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>4. Discussion</title>
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.1. Demographic characteristics of avocado farmers</title>
          
          <p>Avocado production is mainly male undertaking, comprising 82% ($n$ = 99) of the respondents, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_1">Table 1</xref>. Traditional gender roles significantly influence avocado farming as the vast majority of farmers are male. Malekela [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_17">17</xref>] noted that the type of crops produced affected gender involvement. A related observation by Rop et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_18">18</xref>] highlighted that most farmers were male, given that avocado farming was labour-intensive and some farm tasks were designated for men and young men only. The low participation of female farmers in avocado cultivation might hinder the adoption of green growth practices due to their limited access to resources and involvement in decision-making, which restricted their influence in this area. These findings suggested that greater gender equality could enhance productivity and promote sustainable farming practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_19">19</xref>]. Similarly, the SAGCOT aims to foster sustainable agriculture and create quality job opportunities for youth and women within its framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_20">20</xref>].</p><p>The education level of the avocado farmers shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref> indicate that the majority, 67%, of the respondents have attained primary education as basic educational attainment is prevalent among the farmers. A smaller percentage, 22%, had completed secondary and tertiary education, thus indicating potential areas for academic development and training. Fasha and Minde [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_21">21</xref>] stated that primary education was compulsory for every individual in Tanzania, as literacy enabled them to read and write. The results revealed a high percentage of those with merely primary education, implying that most farmers might lack the advanced agricultural knowledge and skills necessary for sustainable farming practices. This finding aligned with the argument of George et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_22">22</xref>], who advocated that farmers with higher education tend to adopt new farming methods more efficiently than their less-educated counterparts because they are better equipped to notice, understand, and respond to new information and advancement in agriculture.</p><p>The age distribution shows that most avocado farmers (47.5%) are between the age of 41 and 55, followed by those aged between 56 and 65 (23.3%). As indicated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_2">Table 2</xref>, avocado farming is pursued by middle-aged individuals; it is anticipated that a high level of farming experience is an asset for adopting sustainable practices. Usually, older farmers have a better understanding of local agricultural conditions, pest management, and crop rotation techniques for sustainable green growth practices. On the other hand, traditional practices may prevent the adoption of innovative green technologies, which younger farmers might indicate more interest to invest. Limited youth involvement (1.7% of the respondents) indicates a demand for incentives like funding, training, and market linkages to attract young people to partake in agriculture.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.2. Green growth practices currently implemented by avocado farmers</title>
          
          <p>The different growth practices of avocado farmers in the study showed their preferences and related implications for sustainable agriculture. The results indicated that most of the farmers, 40%, were using organic fertilizers, thus indicating the latest trends in farming towards sustainability and healthy soil, rather than dependence on synthetic chemicals. Tzatzani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_23">23</xref>] provided substantial input to improve sustainable avocado farming practices in subtropical regions by highlighting promising opportunities for using organic fertilizers, which can positively influence avocado tree growth and fruit quality under specific conditions. Mulching was applied by 25% of the farmers whereas in soil management, 3% focused on moisture management by mulching as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>a to conserve water and regulate soil temperature to retain soil moisture and control weeds. Farmers in Rungwe explained that to retain water and moisture, they placed leaves and other tree debris around the base of the tree. The qualitative data in this study reported farmers participating in community coping strategies against such constraints; as mentioned by one farmer, “<italic>Soil health here is good. We normally make a plate-like weep around the avocado tree to retain moisture</italic>”. As such, farmers could adapt to seasonal moisture stress through low-cost and environmentally friendly methods. It demonstrates sensitivity to local environmental conditions and grassroots innovation, thus indicating that green growth does not have to depend solely on foreign technology. This finding aligned with Iqbal et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_24">24</xref>], who stated that mulching could improve the microclimate of avocado trees by creating favorable conditions for growth. However, lower adoption rates of mulching compared to organic fertilizers suggested that farmers may need more education and support for this practice.</p><p>To diversify income at the farm level, 18% of the farmers reported implementing agroforestry practices as these practices could increase biodiversity and ecosystem services. Avocado farmers in Rungwe believed that agroforestry enhanced soil fertility, which could benefit avocado trees even with good shade conditions. Mixed cropping was practiced by 11% of the farmers for soil management, especially growing crops like coffee and beans as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_3">Figure 3</xref>b. Another study in Ethiopia explained how avocados could be integrated with coffee to help meet shade and other soil requirements for growing avocados [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_25">25</xref>]. A moderate adoption rate indicated that while some farmers recognize the benefits of agroforestry, barriers like a lack of knowledge or resources may hinder wider implementation. Pruning practiced by only 15% of the respondents was the least adopted, despite being the key to maintaining tree health, improving aeration, maximizing sunlight exposure, and ensuring optimal fruit production. Few farmers understand the importance of pruning; studies by Badrulhisham and Othman [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_26">26</xref>] reported that many farmers were unaware of proper pruning techniques. The limited knowledge about pruning may stem from a lack of information on its benefits or cultural preferences for less invasive farming methods.</p><p>Adding organic matter to soil is a crucial soil management technique that avocado farmers used to facilitate green growth practices. Avocado farmers in Rungwe mixed their soil with leaves and other debris during weeding; they also added banana leaves to the soil to enhance its nutrient content. This finding aligned with qualitative insights expressed by several farmers regarding the importance of organic fertilizers in adopting green practices. One farmer noted, “In contrast to artificial fertilizer, which decomposes quickly, we mostly employ organic manure in the soil since it lasts longer”. This practice is essential as organic amendments improve soil structure and enhance moisture retention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_27">27</xref>]. Avocado farmers in the SAGCOT are adopting practices such as cover cropping and organic fertilization to enhance soil structure and nutrition, in order to avoid soil erosion, promote biodiversity, and enable a healthier ecosystem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_28">28</xref>].</p>
          
            <fig id="fig_3">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <title>Photos of farming methods, (a) Mulching, and (b) Mixed cropping method</title>
              </caption>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_wGOj0wjgAqkzfkWi.png"/>
              <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://media.acadlore.com/assets/media/2025/10/img_MPBmFLvf0xgfVRQv.png"/>
            </fig>
          
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.3. Factors influencing avocado farmers to adopt green growth practices</title>
          
          <p>Access to information and knowledge is an important factor influencing the adoption of green growth practices by farmers. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table_4">Table 4</xref>, this relationship is statistically significant at <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mldaeipwbw">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.001</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, with a positive coefficient at <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m6kummu9x6">
    <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>3.229</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Farmers are more likely to adopt green practices when they are well informed of their benefits, as dissemination of information was one of the key determinants in promoting sustainable agricultural practices. This finding agreed to the existing literature, in which Liu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_29">29</xref>] attested that awareness and information influenced farmers' decisions. The impact of cooperative membership on adoption was insignificant at <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mb1irv15dc">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.307</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>; however, it tended to raise the likelihood of adoption as indicated by <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m8ccd3av4i">
    <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>4.413</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. This means that even though membership in a cooperative society may not necessarily be directly related to increased adoption rates. Access to resources, shared knowledge, and collective bargaining power might be useful to farmers in their pursuit of sustainability. Cooperatives can build capacities of farmers through training and support in adopting new technologies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_30">30</xref>]. The “access to training” variable presents slight statistical significance at <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mumeqra20u">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>0.089</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and a positive relationship as shown by <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mzst7ppovw">
    <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>2.932</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>. This suggested that access to training increased the likelihood of adopting green practices and the marginal significance suggested that efforts might be required to enhance this relationship. Shahir et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_31">31</xref>] reported that the knowledge and abilities of farmers about adopting green technologies could be achieved with training; such findings have been evidenced in other literature, where it has been realized that training is vital to sustainable practices.</p><p>On the other hand, farmers' perception of avocado demand significantly influenced the adoption of green growth practices (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="m0urilf9my">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.023</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>). Specifically, those who perceived the demand to be low were markedly less likely to adopt such practices (<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mycgckitje">
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>.012</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>0.123</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>). This finding underscored the critical role of perceived market dynamics in shaping agricultural decision-making. When farmers believe that consumer demand for their produce is unsatisfactory, even if this perception does not reflect actual market conditions, they may opt for short-term production strategies that compromise long-term sustainability. Therefore, addressing these perceptions through targeted consumer education and market development initiatives could help align the economic motivation of farmers with environmentally sustainable practices.</p>
        </sec>
      
      
        <sec>
          
            <title>4.4. Factors affecting the avocado yields</title>
          
          <p>The multiple regression analysis showed that avocado farm size positively and significantly affects avocado yields, with <inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mf8cm9hafq">
    <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mn>10.787</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula> and a $p<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mszyig95r2">
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mn>.000</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>32</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>B=26.258<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="msnyd4bcjq">
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>p<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mfx4ffw5fy">
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>z</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
    <mml:mn>.001</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>33</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>10</mml:mn>
    <mml:mn>20</mml:mn>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>B=-4.340<inline-formula>
  <mml:math id="mwi4v3cgs3">
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
    <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
  </mml:math>
</inline-formula>p$ value of .043. Past studies have raised similar concerns regarding excessive or improper use of chemical fertilizers, which adversely affects tree health and fruit quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_34">34</xref>], resulting in reduced avocado productivity and nutrient imbalances in the soil. Farmers should adopt balanced fertilization practices that support rather than hinder yields. Generally, observations indicated that farmers who applied merely chemical fertilizers experienced lower yields, compared to those who used organic fertilizers or a combination of organic and chemical fertilizers. As another farmer explained, “<italic>More education is needed in using the pesticides since most of us do not know how to apply pesticides well</italic>”. This indicated inadequate access to technical advice, which not only threatens crop quality but also threatens environmental sustainability through agrochemical misuse. The implementation of a green economy in the SAGCOT has also been contentious regarding the use of pesticide and its potential risks, thus emphasizing the need for improved regulation, training, and monitoring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref_35">35</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>5. Conclusions</title>
      <p>This study examined the adoption of green growth practices and its impact on avocado farming among smallholder farmers in the Southern Agricultural Growth Corridor of Rungwe. Findings showed that its adoption was influenced by farm size, access to information, and market perception but was not greatly influenced by gender. Mulching and organic manuring were the mostly employed sustainable practices, citing growing awareness of green strategies. Chemical fertilizers had, nevertheless, a negative impact on yields, while tree age substantially influenced productivity to a great degree. These findings reinforced the plea for intensified knowledge transfer and farmer training in order to promote sustainable practices that enhance environmental conservation and avocado productivity. Improved access to information and market-oriented incentives can be factors for wider green growth adoption and rural economic stability.</p><p>Developing inclusive training for farmers in respect of sustainable practices is a critical imperative for enhancing the avocado farming sector in Tanzania. The training program should involve various stakeholders, including government agencies, agricultural associations, non-governmental organizations, and the SAGCOT. Coordinating market incentives with environmental objectives will allow Tanzania to develop a truly sustainable avocado industry.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors would like to express special thanks to the farmers and local communities in Rungwe District for their cooperation and invaluable insights during data collection. They also appreciated the local agricultural officers and extension workers who provided guidance and support throughout the study.</p>
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <notes>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>Conceptualization, D.C.K., J.M.A., and K.M.; methodology, D.C.K. and J.M.A.; software, D.C.K.; validation, D.C.K., J.M.A., and nd K.M.; formal analysis, D.C.K.; investigation, D.C.K. and J.M.A.; data curation, D.C.K.; writing—original draft preparation, D.C.K. and J.M.A.; writing—review and editing, D.C.K. and J.M.A.; visualization, D.C.K. and J.M.A.; supervision, J.M.A.; project administration, K.M.; funding acquisition, K.M. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Funding</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      
    </notes>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
      <p>The data used to support the research findings are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref_1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>5901</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adamowicz</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su14105901</pub-id>
          <article-title>Green deal, green growth and green economy as a means of support for attaining the sustainable development goals</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>The World Bank</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Inclusive Green Growth: The Pathway to Sustainable Development</source>
          <publisher-name>World Bank Publications, Washington</publisher-name>
          <year>2012</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="conf-paper">
          <page-range>1376-1385</page-range>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khalid</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stecenko</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kadirova</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nurieva</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gazieva</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5220/0012967100003882</pub-id>
          <article-title>Sustainable development goals through the triad of green economy, growth, and deal</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 2nd Pamir Transboundary Conference for Sustainable Societies</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>45</volume>
          <page-range>178-191</page-range>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barbier</surname>
              <given-names>E. B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.reseneeco.2016.05.001</pub-id>
          <article-title>Is green growth relevant for poor economies?</article-title>
          <source>Resour. Energy Econ.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>61-75</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2011</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koohafkan</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Altieri</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gimenez</surname>
              <given-names>E. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14735903.2011.610206</pub-id>
          <article-title>Green Agriculture: Foundations for biodiverse, resilient and productive agricultural systems</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Agric. Sustain.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>OECD</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Food and Agriculture</source>
          <publisher-name>OECD Green Growth Studies, OECD Publishing</publisher-name>
          <year>2012</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bhore</surname>
              <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ochoa</surname>
              <given-names>D. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Houssari</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zelaya</surname>
              <given-names>A. L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deeya</surname>
              <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva Sens</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>al.</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20944/preprints202112.0523.v1</pub-id>
          <article-title>The Avocado (<i>Persea americana</i> Mill.): A review and sustainability perspectives</article-title>
          <source>Priprints</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>3343-3360</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boniphace</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kadigi</surname>
              <given-names>R. M. J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kangile</surname>
              <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/ojbm.2023.116182</pub-id>
          <article-title>Effects of avocado farming on livelihoods and biodiversity: Perspectives of smallholder farmers in Hai and Rungwe districts, Tanzania</article-title>
          <source>Open J. Soc. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>10398-10404</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nasania</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Exploring the interconnections of green financing, financial development, technological innovation, and agricultural production: Evidence from Tanzania</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Recent Adv. Multidiscip. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>129</volume>
          <page-range>104850</page-range>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bergius</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tor Benjaminsen</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maganga</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buhaug</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2019.104850</pub-id>
          <article-title>Green economy, degradation narratives, and land-use conflicts in Tanzania</article-title>
          <source>World Dev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>9</volume>
          <page-range>749</page-range>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Juma</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fors</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hovmalm</surname>
              <given-names>H. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nyomora</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Faith</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geleta</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carlsson</surname>
              <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ortiz</surname>
              <given-names>R. O.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agronomy9110749</pub-id>
          <article-title>Avocado production and local trade in the southern highlands of Tanzania: A case of an emerging trade commodity from horticulture</article-title>
          <source>Agronomy</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Tanzania advances avocado sector with support from FAO’s OCOP initiative</article-title>
          <source>, https://www.fao.org/africa/news-stories/news-detail/tanzania-advances-avocado-sector-with-support-from-fao-s-ocop-initiative/en</source>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>Challenges and opportunities for upgrading the avocado value chain in East Africa</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
          <year>2024</year>
          <publisher-name>Stockholm Environment Institute</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>5</volume>
          <page-range>1-26</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kathula</surname>
              <given-names>D. N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Avocado varieties and export markets for sustainable agriculture and afforestation in Kenya</article-title>
          <source>J. Agric. Environ. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>803</volume>
          <page-range>012067</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Muhlisin</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mulyatno</surname>
              <given-names>S. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Titik</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1755-1315/803/1/012067</pub-id>
          <article-title>The influence of socio-economic factors on sustainability avocado farming (<i>Persea americana</i>)</article-title>
          <source>IOP Conf. Ser.: Earth Environ. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bailey</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Methods of Social Research</source>
          <publisher-name>New York: Free Press</publisher-name>
          <year>2008</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>3</volume>
          <page-range>17-25</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Malekela</surname>
              <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.46606/eajess2022v03i02.0155</pub-id>
          <article-title>Value chain challenges: Experiences from avocado farmers and traders in Njombe Town, Tanzania</article-title>
          <source>East Afr. J. Educ. Soc. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>12</volume>
          <page-range>165-184</page-range>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rop</surname>
              <given-names>S. C. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inoti</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nkurumwa</surname>
              <given-names>A. O.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Factors influencing adoption of climate-smart practices by smallholder avocado farmers for integrated watershed conservation</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Dev. Sustain.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>34</volume>
          <page-range>2272-2304</page-range>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2021</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Muriithi</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kabubo-Mariara</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1057/s41287-021-00484-z</pub-id>
          <article-title>The dynamics and role of gender in high-value avocado farming in Kenya</article-title>
          <source>Eur. J. Dev. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Avocado Strategic Parshership</article-title>
          <source>, https://sagcot.co.tz/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/AvocadoValuechain.pdf</source>
          <year>2024</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>19</volume>
          <page-range>116-130</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fasha</surname>
              <given-names>G. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mind</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Livelihood assessments among small-holder farmers in the southern agricultural growth corridor in Tanzania: Lessons from households in Ihemi cluster</article-title>
          <source>Tanzania J. Agric. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>2048-2061</page-range>
          <issue>35</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>George</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Odhiambo</surname>
              <given-names>G. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagai</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwach</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/ajar2019.14153</pub-id>
          <article-title>An analysis of socioeconomic factors affecting avocado production in saline and flooded areas around Lake Victoria Basin of Western Kenya</article-title>
          <source>Afr. J. Agric. Res.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>14</volume>
          <page-range>12221</page-range>
          <issue>19</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tzatzani</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Psarras</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scuderi</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kokolakis</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Papadakis</surname>
              <given-names>I. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su141912221</pub-id>
          <article-title>Effect of organic fertilizers on avocado trees (Cvs. Fuerte, Hass, Lamb Hass) in western Crete, a cool subtropical region</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>44</volume>
          <page-range>1-16</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2020</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Iqbal</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raza</surname>
              <given-names>M. A. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valipour</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saleem</surname>
              <given-names>M. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zaheer</surname>
              <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmad</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toleikiene</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haider</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aslam</surname>
              <given-names>M. U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nazar</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s42269-020-00290-3</pub-id>
          <article-title>Potential agricultural and environmental benefits of mulches—A review</article-title>
          <source>Bull. Natl. Res. Cent.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>92</volume>
          <page-range>127-137</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Biazin</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haileslassie</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zewdie</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mekasha</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gebremedhin</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fekadu</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shewage</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10457-016-0020-2</pub-id>
          <article-title>Smallholders’ avocado production systems and tree productivity in the southern highlands of Ethiopia</article-title>
          <source>Agrofor. Syst.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>234</volume>
          <page-range>210-217</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2016</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Badrulhisham</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Othman</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sbspro.2016.10.236</pub-id>
          <article-title>Knowledge in tree pruning for sustainable practices in urban setting: Improving our quality of life</article-title>
          <source>Procedia – Soc. Behav. Sci.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Avocado soil health literature review</article-title>
          <source>, https://avocado.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Soil-health-literature-review_NOV-22.pdf</source>
          <year>2022</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Climate-Smart Agriculture in Tanzania</article-title>
          <source>, https://climateknowledgeportal.worldbank.org/sites/default/files/2019-06/CSA-in-Tanzania.pdf</source>
          <year>2017</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>10</volume>
          <page-range>432</page-range>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2018</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bruins</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heberling</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su10020432</pub-id>
          <article-title>Factors influencing farmers’ adoption of best management practices: A review and synthesis</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>11</volume>
          <page-range>361</page-range>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2022</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ram Ray</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hazem Kassem</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ihtisham</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siddiqui</surname>
              <given-names>B. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/land11030361</pub-id>
          <article-title>Can cooperative supports and adoption of improved technologies help increase agricultural income? Evidence from a recent study</article-title>
          <source>Land</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>48-66</page-range>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2023</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shahir</surname>
              <given-names>N. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Humaidi</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jailani</surname>
              <given-names>S. F. A. K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22610/imbr.v15i4(si)i.3576</pub-id>
          <article-title>Factors influencing green practice adoption and mediating role of green practice benefits</article-title>
          <source>Inf. Manage. Bus. Rev.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>1</volume>
          <page-range>100007</page-range>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2024</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ren</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reis</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Grinsven</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lam</surname>
              <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosa</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecz.2024.100007</pub-id>
          <article-title>Trade-offs in agricultural outcomes across farm sizes</article-title>
          <source>Earth Crit. Zone</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>93</volume>
          <page-range>51-71</page-range>
          <year>2010</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hofshi</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tapia</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M. L. Arpaia</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Stump and topwork–A technique for rejuvenating mature avocado trees</article-title>
          <source>Calif. Avocado Soc. Yearb.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <volume>15</volume>
          <page-range>1136-50</page-range>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2019</year>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ganeshamurthy</surname>
              <given-names>A. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>R. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shashidhar</surname>
              <given-names>K. S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rupa</surname>
              <given-names>T. R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fertilizer best management practices for perennial horticultural crops</article-title>
          <source>Indian J. Fertil.</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref_35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <article-title>Pesticides in the Southern Agricultural Growth Corridor of Tanzania (SAGCOT): A scoping study of current and future use, associated risks and identification of actions for risk mitigation</article-title>
          <source>, undefined</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <publisher-name>Wageningen Environmental Research</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>